<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="LastJudgment">
  <title>Last Judgment*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LAST JUDGMENT*</p>
<p class="fl">Time at the end of history when God will judge the deeds of all humankind. In their preaching concerning the Day of the Lord, various OT prophets anticipated the time when God would wage war against all wicked nations and establish his rule in the eternal city of Zion (<a href="?bref=Isa.4.2">Is 4:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.10">11:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.50.3-32">Jer 50:3-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.1-3">Jl 2:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.3.9-16">3:9-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.18-20">Am 5:18-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.9.11">9:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.7-18">Zep 1:7-18</a>). The NT writers continue this theme, restating it in the light of the words and work of Jesus. He has been appointed by God to be judge of the living and the dead (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.42">Acts 10:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.31">17:31</a>). Both believers and unbelievers must appear before the judgment seat of Christ, so that each one may receive good or evil, according to what they have done with their lives (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.10">2 Cor 5:10</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.14.10">Rom 14:10</a>).</p>
<p>The focus of God’s judgment is human behavior. Those faithful to the covenant will prosper, but those who are disloyal will perish. The prophet Habakkuk identifies the righteous person as the one who is faithful (<a href="?bref=Hab.2.4">Hb 2:4</a>). NT writers state that one will be judged according to whether or not his deeds are pleasing to God (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.10">2 Cor 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.20.12">Rv 20:12</a>). However, the NT also states that no one has met the perfect standards of God. All have sinned and therefore deserve to be punished (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.9,23">Rom 3:9, 23</a>). The issue to be determined at the time of judgment is not one’s guilt but rather whether or not one has been acquitted. The NT speaks of this acquittal as justification and reconciliation (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.21-28">3:21-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.1-21">5:1-21</a>). The means of acquittal is the death and resurrection of Christ, for Jesus’ act of righteousness leads to acquittal and life for all people (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.18">5:18</a>). The one who trusts in Christ is not condemned (<a href="?bref=John.3.16-18">Jn 3:16-18</a>) and can enter the Day of Judgment with confidence (<a href="?bref=1Jn.4.17">1 Jn 4:17</a>). His name is written in the Lamb’s Book of Life (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.27">Rv 21:27</a>). The unbeliever must face the Day of Judgment with no assistance. He will be judged by what is written in the books; that is, by what he has done (<a href="?bref=Rev.20.11-12">20:11-12</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DayoftheLord_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Day of the Lord</a>; <a href="?item=Eschatology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eschatology</a>; <a href="?item=Judgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judgment</a>; <a href="?item=JudgmentSeat_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judgment Seat</a>; <a href="?item=LastDays_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Last Days</a>; <a href="?item=WrathofGod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wrath of God</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>