<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Laughter">
  <title>Laughter</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LAUGHTER</p>
<p class="fl">Expression of a variey of emotions. Laughter can express overjoyed happiness when circumstances change for the better, as for the Jews in returning from exile (<a href="?bref=Ps.126.2">Ps 126:2</a>). Such joy is sincerely but facilely offered to Job by one of his comforters (<a href="?bref=Job.8.21">Jb 8:21</a>). Laughter can be good-humored and friendly, to encourage others (<a href="?bref=Job.29.24">29:24</a>). There is “a time to cry and a time to laugh” (<a href="?bref=Eccl.3.4">Eccl 3:4</a>), but the Preacher had his doubts: life is no laughing matter, and sorrow can be a better teacher (<a href="?bref=Eccl.2.2">2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.7.3">7:3</a>). Yet it is good to be able not to take certain things seriously. The well-prepared housewife “laughs with no fear of the future” (<a href="?bref=Pr.31.25">Prv 31:25</a>). Job is promised that war and famine would be nothing to worry about (<a href="?bref=Job.5.22">Jb 5:22</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Hab.1.9">Hb 1:9</a>).</p>
<p>Laughter can be a negative, derisive thing. We can laugh at people and laugh them to scorn. This element comes very much to the fore in the OT. Job and Jeremiah complain of being laughingstocks (<a href="?bref=Job.12.4">Jb 12:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.20.7">Jer 20:7</a>). The nation complains that their enemies laugh at their distress (<a href="?bref=Ps.80.6">Ps 80:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Chr.30.10">2 Chr 30:10</a>). Sometimes there is every justification. In <a href="?bref=Ps.52.6">Psalm 52:6</a> the righteous are promised the last laugh, at the expense of the wicked unbeliever who thinks that he can leave God out of his life. In <a href="?bref=Pr.1.26">Proverbs 1:26</a>, personified Wisdom warns that she will laugh at the calamity of those who refuse to take her advice: it will serve them right. In this sense laughter is ascribed to God three times in the Psalter. He laughs at the nations plotting against his anointed King (<a href="?bref=Ps.2.4">Ps 2:4</a>). He laughs at wicked people, knowing they are heading for disaster (<a href="?bref=Ps.37.13">37:13</a>). He is invited to laugh at the psalmist’s enemies (<a href="?bref=Ps.59.8">59:8</a>). This divine laughter is a way of expressing that the truth will eventually prevail.</p>
<p>Laughter has a special place in the Abraham narratives. It is used in connection with the name of his son Isaac, which means “He laughs” or “May [God] smile [upon him].” Hebrew stories like to bring out the meaning of words, and so the human reaction to the birth of Isaac, the channel of God’s patriarchal promises, is described in terms of laughter. It is theologically important because it tends to be contrasted with faith. In <a href="?bref=Gen.17.17">Genesis 17:17</a> laughter is Abraham’s incredulous response to God’s unrealistic promise of a son, in view of Sarah’s elderliness. In <a href="?bref=Gen.18.12">Genesis 18:12</a> Sarah cannot smother her laughter as she eavesdrops—it seems so absurd that she will become pregnant in her 90s. But finally in <a href="?bref=Gen.21.6">Genesis 21:6</a>, when the impossible becomes true, Sarah’s laughter is a mark of God-given joy.</p>
  </body>
</item>