<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="LeviticusBookof">
  <title>Leviticus, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LEVITICUS, Book of</p>
<p class="fl">Third book of the OT, largely concerned with the duties of the Levitical priests.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Date">Date</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurposeandTheology">Purpose and Theology</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">A traditional alternative title of Leviticus is the Third Book of Moses, which gives proper credit to the man who most deserves to be called its author. For though the book never says that Moses wrote down any of the material, it repeatedly states that God revealed the contents of Leviticus to Moses. It may be that Leviticus was not put into writing as soon as it was revealed, but there is little to commend the common critical view that it was composed nearly a thousand years after Moses. The spelling and grammar of Leviticus was, like other books of the OT, revised from time to time to make it understandable to later generations of Jewish readers, but that does not mean the essential content of the book was modified.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Date">Date</p>
<p class="fl">God revealed some of the laws in Leviticus by speaking to Moses from the tent of meeting, or tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.1">Lv 1:1</a>). Other laws were revealed on Mt Sinai (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.46">26:46</a>). Such statements show that Moses learned the contents of Leviticus after the tabernacle had been built but before the Israelites left Mt Sinai. This fits in with <a href="?bref=Exod.40.17">Exodus 40:17</a>, which says that the tabernacle was erected exactly a year after the Israelites left Egypt. They then spent another month at Sinai, during which time the laws in Leviticus were given to Moses. Then one month later (<a href="?bref=Num.1.1">Nm 1:1</a>) Moses was commanded to prepare the people to leave Sinai to conquer the Promised Land of Canaan.</p>
<p>It is difficult to give an exact date for the Israelite exodus from Egypt. Dates at the end of the 15th century <span class="era">BC</span> or early in the 13th century are put forward by different scholars. Whichever view is adopted, the origin of Leviticus must be one year later than the exodus. But certainty about the absolute date of Leviticus is unimportant so long as the religious setting of the book is understood.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">About 400 years before the exodus, God promised Abraham that his descendants would be very numerous and live in the land of Canaan. The family of Abraham multiplied, but as a result of famine they had to go and live in Egypt. Afraid of the Israelites, the rulers of Egypt turned them into slaves.</p>
<p>The book of Exodus tells how God, acting through Moses, brought the Israelites out of Egypt in a miraculous way. Moses led them to Mt Sinai, where God appeared in fire and smoke on the top of the mountain. Moses went up the mountain, and there God gave him the Ten Commandments and explained various laws. Through these acts God showed that he had chosen the nation of Israel to be his special holy people, different from all the other nations because they would show God’s character through their behavior (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.19.5-6">Ex 19:5-6</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientHebrewTextOfLeviticus"/>
<p>God’s revelation at Sinai was unique and unrepeatable. But he disclosed to Moses that he wanted to live among the people of Israel permanently. They were told to build a portable royal palace that would be suitable for the divine King of kings. The building of this portable palace, traditionally called the tabernacle, is described in <a href="?bref=Exod.35.1-40.38">Exodus 35–40</a>. When it was completed, the fire and cloud that had been seen on Mt Sinai appeared over the tabernacle as a sign that God was now dwelling in it (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.34-38">Ex 40:34-38</a>).</p>
<p>Exodus also tells how Moses was told to appoint his brother, Aaron, and Aaron’s sons to serve in the tabernacle as priests (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.1-29.46">Ex 28–29</a>). Unfortunately, before the Israelites even began to build the tabernacle, they made a golden calf under Aaron’s leadership and started to worship it instead. The people were spared only as a result of Moses’ prayers. The book of Exodus therefore leaves the reader in suspense. The tabernacle has been built, but no one knows how to worship God in it. Though Aaron and his family are alive, we are left wondering whether they will still be allowed to lead the worship of God after the idolatry of the golden calf. The book of Leviticus answers this question.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeandTheology">Purpose and Theology</p>
<p class="fl">The Ten Commandments explain briefly and simply how God expects his people to behave. The first four commandments explain our duty toward our neighbor. The book of Leviticus follows a similar scheme. Chapters <a href="?bref=Lev.1.1-17.16">1–17</a> show how God wanted Israel to worship him, while chapters <a href="?bref=Lev.18.1-27.21">18–27</a> are mainly concerned with how people should behave toward each other. Whereas the Ten Commandments are general and can be applied quite easily to every society, the book of Leviticus is much more detailed and specifically geared to the special circumstances of ancient Israel. If modern readers are to profit from reading Leviticus, they must look behind the specific regulations to the underlying religious principles that do not change—in other words, to the theology of Leviticus.</p>
<p>Four themes are very important in the theology of Leviticus: (1) the presence of God, (2) holiness, (3) sacrifice, and (4) the Sinai covenant.</p>
<p class="h3">The Presence of God</p>
<p class="fl">God is always present with Israel in a real way. Sometimes his presence becomes visible in fire and smoke. But even when there is no miraculous sign, God is present. He is especially near when people worship him and offer sacrifice. The many animal sacrifices mentioned in the book are all brought to the Lord. When the animals are burnt, God is pleased with the smell (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.9">1:9</a>). The priests who offer the sacrifices must be especially careful since they come closer to God than other people do. If they are careless in their duties and break God’s commands, they may die (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.1-2">10:1-2</a>).</p>
<p>God is present not just in worship but in all the ordinary duties of life. The recurring refrain of the later chapters, “I, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, am your God” (<a href="?bref=Lev.18.2">18:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.19.3">19:3</a>), reminds the Israelites that every aspect of their life—religion (chs <a href="?bref=Lev.21.1-24.18">21–24</a>), sex (chs <a href="?bref=Lev.18.1-30">18</a>, <a href="?bref=Lev.20.1-27">20</a>), and relations with neighbors (chs 19, 25)—matters to God. The behavior of every Israelite must mirror that of God himself (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.7">20:7</a>). The fear of God should prompt persons to help the blind, the deaf, the elderly, and the poor. Though such people may have no redress against unfair treatment, God cares about what happens to them (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.14,32">19:14, 32</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.25.17,36,43">25:17, 36, 43</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Holiness</p>
<p class="fl">“You must be holy because I am holy” (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.44-45">11:44-45</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.19.2">19:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.20.26">20:26</a>) could be termed the motto of Leviticus. “Holy,” “clean,” and “unclean” are common words in this book. God is the supremely holy person in the Bible, and holiness is the distinctive feature of his character. But earthly creatures can become holy too. To become holy, a person must be chosen by God and undergo the correct ceremony. Thus, at Sinai all Israel became a holy nation (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.6">Ex 19:6</a>). <a href="?bref=Lev.8.1-9.24">Leviticus 8–9</a> explains how Aaron and his sons were ordained priests. This made them more holy than ordinary Israelites and therefore able to approach God and offer sacrifice.</p>
<p>Before anyone could become holy, they had to be “clean.” Cleanness in Leviticus means more than just being free of dirt, though this idea is included. It means being free of any abnormality. Whenever a person appears to fall short of perfection, he is described as “unclean.” Thus, the worst uncleanness is death, the very opposite of perfect life. But bleeding and other discharges and patchy skin diseases can make someone unclean. Animals that move in peculiar ways or have strange habits are also called unclean (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.1-15.33">Lv 11–15</a>).</p>
<p>Holiness and its opposite, uncleanness, can describe behavior as well as outward appearance. To be holy means to obey God and to act like God. Chapters <a href="?bref=Lev.18.1-25.55">18–25</a> explain what holiness means in daily living. It means avoiding illicit sexual relations, caring for the poor, being honest, being fair, and loving your neighbor as yourself. This sort of behavior made Israel different from other peoples. Through their holiness the whole nation was supposed to demonstrate what God was like.</p>
<p class="h3">Sacrifice</p>
<p class="fl">In practice, unfortunately, the nation and the individuals within it rarely lived up to these ideals of holiness. Even if one did not commit a grievous sin, he or she was always liable to become unclean through contact with someone else, touching a dead animal, or in some other way. To maintain contact with a holy God, Israel’s sins and uncleanness had to be removed. This is what the sacrifices were for. They brought the forgiveness of sins and cleansing from uncleanness. Because sin affects relations between God and humans in various ways, Leviticus provides four different types of offerings to cover the different cases (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.1-6.30">Lv 1–6</a>), and explains which sacrifices must be offered on which occasions (chs <a href="?bref=Lev.7.1-17.16">7–17</a>). All these rituals served to underline the seriousness of sin and helped preserve peace and fellowship between God and humanity.</p>
<p class="h3">The Sinai Covenant</p>
<p class="fl">All the laws contained in Leviticus form part of the Sinai covenant. They fill out and apply the principles of the Ten Commandments to the specific circumstances of ancient Israel. But they are more than a set of detailed rules, because they were given as part of the covenant. Three things have to be remembered about this covenant. First, the covenant created a personal relationship. The Lord became Israel’s king, and Israel became his special treasure set apart from the other nations of the world. Second, the covenant was based on God’s grace. He had made a promise to Abraham and, in saving the people from Egyptian slavery, he demonstrated his faithfulness to his promise and his love for Israel. Israel, in turn, was to show its gratitude for salvation by keeping the law. In no way did keeping the law earn them salvation. The law was given to a redeemed people. Finally, there were promises and threats built into the covenant (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.1-46">Lv 26</a>). When the nation keeps the law, God promises they will enjoy good harvests, victory over their enemies, and God walking among them as he did in Eden. But if they reject God’s laws, terrible calamities will befall them: drought, famine, defeat, and even expulsion from the land God had promised to give them. These covenant curses form the background to the prophets’ warnings in later times.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Kinds of Sacrifices (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.1-7.38">1–7</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">These chapters explain how the different kinds of sacrifices were to be offered. Most of these sacrifices also formed part of the regular worship in the tabernacle and later in the temple. But these chapters are concerned with personal offerings made when someone had sinned or made a vow or recovered from an illness. They explain what the offerer must do and what the priest must do, which parts of the animal must be burned, which parts may be eaten by the priest, and what is to be done with the blood of the animal.</p>
<p>First, the offerer brought the animal into the outer court of the tabernacle. In the presence of the priest he put his hand on the head of the animal and explained why he was bringing the sacrifice. Then the worshiper killed the animal and chopped it up. The priest then took over. He caught the blood as it ran out of the dying animal and splashed it over the altar, and burned at least some of the animal on the great altar in the court of the tabernacle. These acts were performed with all the animal sacrifices.</p>
<p>The special feature of the burnt offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.1-17">Lv 1</a>) was that the whole animal, which had to be unblemished, was burned on the altar. All that the priest received was the skin. This was the most common sacrifice and was offered on many different occasions. In giving the whole animal to God in the sacrifice, the worshiper dedicated himself or herself totally to God’s service. “Lay your hand on its head so the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will accept it as your substitute, thus making atonement for you” (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.4">1:4</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.2.1-16">2</a> deals with the grain offering that always accompanied the burnt offering, but which could also be offered alone. Only part of this offering was burned; the rest was given to the priests to eat. The sacrifices formed an important part of their income.</p>
<p>The peace (fellowship) offering’s special feature was that it was the only sacrifice where the offerer was allowed to eat part of the meat (<a href="?bref=Lev.3.1-17">Lv 3</a>). Since in the earliest period Israelites were not permitted to kill animals except for sacrifice (ch <a href="?bref=Lev.17.1-16">17</a>), every meal that included meat had to be preceded by a peace offering. <a href="?bref=Lev.7.11-18">Leviticus 7:11-18</a> mentions three occasions that might prompt a peace-offering “thanksgiving”: when someone had something to praise God for or some sin to acknowledge; a vow promising a sacrifice if God would help one out of a difficulty; and a voluntary offering, made just because the person felt like it.</p>
<p>Despite its name, the sin offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.1-35">Lv 4</a>) was not the only offering dealing with sin. The other sacrifices also made the forgiveness of sin possible. The special significance of this sacrifice is emphasized by its unusual ritual. Instead of the blood being splashed over the altar, as in the other sacrifices, it was carefully smeared over the horns (corners) of the large altar in the courtyard (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.30">4:30</a>) or over the small altar inside the holy place (v <a href="?bref=Lev.4.18">18</a>); once a year the blood was sprinkled over the ark in the Holy of Holies (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.14">16:14</a>). Sin makes these different parts of the tabernacle unclean, unfit for the presence of God. And if God is not present in the tabernacle, worship has no point. The blood acts as a spiritual disinfectant, making the tabernacle clean and holy again. The sin offering was required whenever a person inadvertently broke one of the commandments or had suffered from a discharge or skin disease that made him or her unclean for a week or more (chs <a href="?bref=Lev.12.1-8">12</a>, <a href="?bref=Lev.15.1-33">15</a>).</p>
<p>The guilt offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.14-6.7">5:14–6:7</a>) was for more serious offenses, such as stealing holy property or deliberately using God’s name in a false oath. Such an offense was seen as robbing God. Therefore, a ram had to be offered as a sort of repayment. Whereas the poor person could offer just a bird for the other sacrifices, a ram was always required for a guilt offering.</p>
<p>Chapters <a href="?bref=Lev.6.8-7.38">6:8–7:38</a> contain various other regulations about sacrifice, mainly specifying how much of each sacrifice the priests may eat and how much must be burned. One important rule for those who weren’t priests was that they were not to eat any fat or blood or eat sacrificial meat when they were unclean. If they did, they could be cut off from Israel (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.21-27">7:21-27</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Beginnings of the Priesthood (<a href="?bref=Lev.8.1-10.20">8–10</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Though Leviticus looks like a law book, because it contains so many regulations, it is really a history book describing the events that occurred about a year after the exodus. These chapters remind us of the true character of the book, for they tell how Moses ordained Aaron and his sons to be priests and how they offered their first sacrifices.</p>
<p>Awed by the complexity of the ordination rituals, the modern reader may miss the marvel that Aaron should have been appointed high priest. For it was Aaron who had presided over the making of the golden calf and encouraged its worship (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.1-35">Ex 32</a>). Had not Moses interceded for Israel, the whole nation would have been destroyed in the wilderness. Here the gracious forgiveness of God is most clear. Aaron, the chief sinner, is appointed chief mediator between God and the people. In the NT the career of Peter parallels Aaron’s in some respect.</p>
<p>The greatness of the high priesthood is symbolized by the richly decorated robes Aaron wore. He and his sons were anointed with oil, and then Moses offered the three most common sacrifices on their behalf. They were confined to the court of the tabernacle for a week, and it seems likely that some of the rituals were repeated each day. By this means they were set apart from the rest of the people and entirely consecrated to their holy office.</p>
<p>By the eighth day the process was complete. Now Aaron and his sons could offer sacrifice. This time, Moses only told them what to do; he did not offer sacrifices himself. Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.9.1-24">9</a> concludes by telling that, after they had offered the sacrifices for themselves and the people, fire came out of the tabernacle to burn up the offerings, thereby displaying God’s approval of their actions.</p>
<p>After this, <a href="?bref=Lev.10.1-2">10:1-2</a> presents an unexpected turn of events: “Aaron’s sons Nadab and Abihu put coals of fire in their incense burners and sprinkled incense over it. In this way, they disobeyed the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> by burning before him a different kind of fire than he had commanded. So fire blazed forth from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>’s presence and burned them up, and they died there before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). We do not know exactly what is meant by unholy fire. What is important is that the priests did something that God had not commanded them. The priests were supposed to set an example of total obedience to God’s word: this is the essence of holiness. Instead, they decided to follow their own plans and the consequences were dire.</p>
<p>“Aaron was silent” (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.3">10:3</a>). He was warned not even to mourn his sons’ deaths, lest he be suspected of condoning their sin (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.10.6-7">6-7</a>). Yet, despite his sons’ actions, Aaron and his surviving sons were confirmed as priests. They were reminded that their job was “to distinguish between what is holy and what is ordinary, what is ceremonially unclean and what is clean. And you must teach the Israelites all the laws that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has given through Moses” (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.10.10-11">10-11</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The chapter closes on another note of grace. Although the priests made a mistake in offering one of the sin offerings, God would overlook it on this occasion.</p>
<p class="h3">Cleanness and Uncleanness (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.1-16.36">11–16</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Distinguishing between the unclean and the clean is the theme of chapters <a href="?bref=Lev.11.1-15.27">11–15</a>, which prepare for the great Day of Atonement ceremonies of chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.16.1-34">16</a>. These are designed to cleanse the tabernacle from the uncleannesses of the people of Israel, thereby ensuring that God would continue to dwell among them (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.16,19">16:16, 19</a>).</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.11.1-47">11</a> discusses unclean animals, that is, animals that may not be eaten. Land animals are dealt with first, then fish and birds, and finally various miscellaneous creatures such as locusts and reptiles. To be clean, a land animal must have cloven hooves and chew the cud; that covers sheep and cattle but excludes pigs and camels. Fish must have fins and scales to be edible; without them, they count as unclean. Birds are clean unless they are birds of prey or scavengers that eat carrion. Insects that resemble birds in having wings and two large legs to hop with—for example, locusts—are clean. Other flying insects are unclean. All squirming creatures that dart hither and thither, such as lizards, are unclean.</p>
<p>The reasons for declaring some animals clean and others unclean has long been a great puzzle. One suggestion is that the unclean animals were used in sacrifice by pagan worshipers or were thought to represent pagan deities. Certainly some unclean animals were used in pagan worship, but so were some clean ones, and that fact makes this explanation unsatisfactory. A second possibility is that the rules were hygienic: the clean animals were safe to eat whereas the unclean were not. There may be some truth in this explanation, but it is not completely adequate, for some clean animals can be harmful while some unclean ones are all right to eat.</p>
<p>Unclean animals could not be eaten, but there was no harm in touching them. Israelites could ride camels, for example. However, all dead animals, unless killed for sacrifice, were unclean. Anyone who touched the carcass of a dead creature became unclean himself and therefore could not enter the tabernacle that day (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.39-40">11:39-40</a>).</p>
<p>The following chapters deal with other conditions that make people unclean. Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.12.1-8">12</a> states that childbirth, or more precisely the bloody discharge that follows childbirth, makes a woman unclean. In OT theology death is the ultimate uncleanness, and conditions that are abnormal or threaten to lead to death are also unclean. When the discharge has ceased, after a fixed period the mother must bring a burnt offering and a sin offering to atone for any sin she may have committed, and to purify the tabernacle that may have been polluted through her uncleanness.</p>
<p>Chapters <a href="?bref=Lev.13.1-14.57">13–14</a> deal with the uncleanness caused by skin diseases. Detailed regulations are given to distinguish between different diseases so that the priests can decide whether people are unclean or not. If they are unclean, they must live outside the camp until their skin heals. Traditionally the unclean skin disease has been called leprosy. But this is unlikely to be correct, since leprosy was unknown in the Middle East in OT times. Rather, it was any disease that led to the skin peeling off in patches, such as psoriasis. This explains why the disease might spontaneously get better.</p>
<p>If the disease did retreat sufficiently, the sufferer could call the priest, and if the priest was satisfied with the cure, the sufferer could be readmitted to the community after following the rituals prescribed in chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.14.1-57">14</a>. This also explains what is to be done if patches of mold are found in pieces of cloth or house walls.</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.15.1-33">15</a> explains how men can become unclean through discharges from their sexual organs, due to gonorrhea or sexual intercourse, while women become unclean through menstruation or a long-term discharge. Part of the purpose of these regulations is to prevent the sacred prostitution that was common in the ancient world. Since sexual intercourse made people unclean, they could not go to worship immediately afterward. Further, the uncleanness of menstruation should have discouraged men from being overfamiliar with unmarried girls.</p>
<p>The broad scope of these uncleanness regulations meant that nearly every Israelite would be unclean at some time in his or her life. This uncleanness could contaminate God’s dwelling place, the tabernacle, making it impossible for God to continue to live there. To avert this catastrophe, a Day of Atonement was held once a year. This is the most solemn day in the Jewish calendar, and the ceremonies for it are described in detail in <a href="?bref=Lev.16.1-34">Leviticus 16</a>.</p>
<p>There are three acts on the Day of Atonement that are described in this chapter. There was first the special sin offering offered by the high priest, in the course of which the outer altar of burnt offering, the incense altar inside the Holy Place, and finally the ark itself in the Holy of Holies were sprinkled with blood to purify each part of the tabernacle. This was the one occasion in the year when the high priest entered the presence of God in the Holy of Holies, and elaborate precautions were taken to screen the high priest from God’s holiness (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.2-4,11-17">16:2-4, 11-17</a>). There was another public act that pictured the sins of Israel being taken away. A goat was chosen by lot. Then the high priest placed his hands on its head and recited over it the nation’s sin. This goat was then led away and driven into a solitary place; in later times it was pushed over a precipice. These actions pictured Israel’s sins being carried away, so that they could not disturb the peace between God and his people. The third important feature of the Day of Atonement was public prayer and fasting. This showed that sin could not be eliminated without effort, but only through a complete change of heart by every person in Israel.</p>
<p class="h3">Rules for Daily Life (<a href="?bref=Lev.17.1-25.55">17–25</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Whereas the opening chapters of Leviticus are entirely concerned with the Godward side of religion, the later chapters are more concerned with practical religious duties toward other persons. However, chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.17.1-16">17</a> repeats some of the rules about sacrifice and makes one new one: that all sacrifice must be offered in the tabernacle courtyard. This was to prevent people from secretly worshiping heathen gods.</p>
<p>Chapters <a href="?bref=Lev.18.1-30">18</a> and <a href="?bref=Lev.20.1-27">20</a> spell out the rules governing sexual relations in ancient Israel. Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.19.1-37">19</a> gives further examples of what holiness means in everyday life. Positively, it means helping the poor by leaving some grain behind in the fields at harvesttime (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.9-10">19:9-10</a>); paying people promptly (v <a href="?bref=Lev.19.13">13</a>); avoiding gossip (v <a href="?bref=Lev.19.16">16</a>); honoring the elderly, helping the immigrant, and being honest in business (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.19.32-36">32-36</a>). But holiness goes beyond deeds and words. It should transform thoughts: “Never seek revenge or bear a grudge against anyone, but love your neighbor as yourself” (v <a href="?bref=Lev.19.18">18</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Chapters <a href="?bref=Lev.21.1-24">21</a> and <a href="?bref=Lev.22.1-33">22</a> discuss how the holy men of Israel, the priests, are to demonstrate their holiness in their lives. First, they must avoid approaching dead bodies unless the dead are very close relatives. Second, they must marry women of known moral uprightness. Third, deformed priests—for example, a blind or lame priest—may never offer sacrifices. Here the principle is plain that men who represent God must reflect the perfection of God in normal, healthy bodies. However, those who are temporarily unclean, through skin disease or a discharge, may resume their duties as soon as their uncleanness is cured.</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.23.1-44">23</a> lists the main holy days and the sacrifices that had to be offered on each one. Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.24.1-23">24</a> deals with the lamp and special bread kept within the tabernacle. A case of blasphemy that occurred in the wilderness is mentioned. Because the man actually used the sacred name of God in a curse, he was sentenced to death.</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.25.1-55">25</a> deals with the jubilee year. In every society people fall into debt. Today the effects of debt are somewhat cushioned by state welfare payments and bank overdrafts, but ancient societies did not have such aid available. People in debt had to sell off their family land, on which they depended for their living, or in more serious situations, they could sell themselves into slavery. Once impoverished in this way, it was exceedingly difficult ever to recover one’s land or one’s freedom. But this law in Leviticus provided an escape. Every 50 years was a jubilee. In this year every slave was released from bondage, and everyone who had sold his land was given it back free. Thus, everyone who fell into debt was given a chance to make a fresh start. Though this law was primarily designed to help the poor, it also served to prevent the accumulation of too much wealth in the hands of a few rich men.</p>
<p class="h3">Blessings, Curses, and Vows (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.1-27.34">26–27</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.26.1-46">26</a> contains the blessings and curses that traditionally concluded a covenant. Israel is promised great material and spiritual prosperity if she keeps the law but is warned that tragedy will befall if she is disobedient.</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Lev.27.1-34">27</a> is an appendix dealing with vows and other gifts made to God. When a person promises to give something to God, it becomes holy and cannot be retracted unless a suitable payment is made instead. This chapter sets out the rules about such dedications.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Aaron_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Aaron</a>; <a href="?item=Moses_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Moses</a>; <a href="?item=OfferingsandSacrifices_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Offerings and Sacrifices</a>; <a href="?item=PriestsandLevites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Priests and Levites</a>; <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="LeviticusAndTheChristian"/>
  </body>
</item>