<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="LotsCastingof">
  <title>Lots, Casting of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LOTS, Casting of</p>
<p class="fl">Practice common in the OT, less common in the NT prior to Pentecost, and absent in the biblical narrative after Pentecost.</p>
<p>In the Bible the practice was used in a variety of circumstances, including (1) the selection of the scapegoat (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.8-10">Lv 16:8-10</a>); (2) the allocation of the tribal inheritance in the Promised Land (<a href="?bref=Num.26.55-56">Nm 26:55-56</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.14.2">Jos 14:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.1.3">Jgs 1:3</a>); (3) the determination of the families who had to relocate to give a proper distribution of the populace or of those warriors who had to go to war where only a percentage was required (<a href="?bref=Judg.20.9">Jgs 20:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.11.1">Neh 11:1</a>); (4) the order of the priests and their duties (<a href="?bref=1Chr.24.5-19">1 Chr 24:5-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.10.34">Neh 10:34</a>); (5) the determination of an offender (<a href="?bref=Josh.7.14-18">Jos 7:14-18</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Pr.18.18">Prv 18:18</a>).</p>
<p>According to biblical usage, lots seem to have been used only when the decision was important and where wisdom or biblical injunctions did not give sufficient guidance. One of the advantages of the casting of lots was the impartiality of the choice. It was held that the Lord directed the lots (<a href="?bref=Pr.16.33">Prv 16:33</a>). The method of casting lots is not specified or described and seems to have varied according to the need of the situation (cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.16.8">Lv 16:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.55-56">Nm 26:55-56</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.20.9">Jgs 20:9</a>).</p>
<p>The practice of casting lots was never condemned by God and on several occasions was sanctioned by him (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.8">Lv 16:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.18.18">Prv 18:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.17">Is 34:17</a>). The principle behind the procedure is set forth in <a href="?bref=Pr.16.33">Proverbs 16:33</a>, which affirms that the disposition or result of the lot is determined by God; therefore, the theory was that the lot pronounced the will of God.</p>
<p>In the NT the soldiers cast lots over Jesus’ garments (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.35">Mt 27:35</a>), and the disciples cast lots when they selected Matthias to the apostleship in place of Judas (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.26">Acts 1:26</a>). After the outpouring of the Holy Spirit upon the church, the practice of casting lots ceased. Some scholars think that there was no further need for the practice to continue, as the Holy Spirit guided the church in its decisions.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=UrimandThummim_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Urim and Thummim</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>