<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="KohathKohathites">
  <title>Kohath, Kohathites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">KOHATH, KOHATHITES</p>
<p class="fl">Son of Levi (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.11">Gn 46:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.6.16">Ex 6:16</a>), father of Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.18">Ex 6:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.19,27">Nm 3:19, 27</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.2">1 Chr 6:2</a>), and progenitor of the Kohathite branch of Levitical families who were responsible for the tabernacle service (<a href="?bref=Num.3.31-32">Nm 3:31-32</a>). Moses, Aaron, and Miriam were descendants of Kohath (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.18-20">Ex 6:18-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.59">Nm 26:59</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.3">1 Chr 6:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.13-17">23:13-17</a>).</p>
<p>The three main divisions of the tribe of Levi bore the names of Gershon, Kohath, and Merari, who were traditionally the original sons of Levi (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.11">Gn 46:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.6.16">Ex 6:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.17">Nm 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.1,16">1 Chr 6:1, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.6">23:6</a>). The Kohathites, therefore, were a prominent Levitical family. The order of their names in <a href="?bref=Num.4.1-49">Numbers 4</a>, <a href="?bref=Josh.21.1-45">Joshua 21</a>, <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.16">1 Chronicles 6:16</a>, and <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.12">2 Chronicles 29:12</a> indicates that they were assigned a more honorable office than either Gershon or Merari. Their position and responsibilities—whether referred to as “the Kohathites,” or “the sons of Kohath”—are noted throughout the early writings of the Hebrews (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.18">Ex 6:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.19,27-30">Nm 3:19, 27-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.4.2-4,15,18,34,37">4:2-4, 15, 18, 34, 37</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.7.9">7:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.10.21">10:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.57">26:57</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.4-5,10,20,26">Jos 21:4-5, 10, 20, 26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.2,18,22,33,54,61,66,70">1 Chr 6:2, 18, 22, 33, 54, 61, 66, 70</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.5">15:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.12">23:12</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.20.19">2 Chr 20:19</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.12">29:12</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.12">34:12</a>).</p>
<p>During the wandering of the Israelites in the desert following their exodus from Egypt, the Kohathites were assigned a position on the southern side of the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Num.3.29">Nm 3:29</a>). When the tabernacle was moved, they were to carry the ark and other sacred things on their shoulders (<a href="?bref=Num.7.9">7:9</a>). At the time of the building of the tabernacle, a census was taken to determine the number of male Kohathites who would be involved in the service of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Num.3.27-28">3:27-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.4.1-4,34-37">4:1-4, 34-37</a>).</p>
<p>After the settlement of the tribes in the land of Canaan, the service of the Kohathites appeared to have ended. God, however, specifically stated that they should be cared for in the same manner as the other Levitical families. The Kohathites were given numerous cities (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.4-5,20-26">Jos 21:4-5, 20-26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.66-70">1 Chr 6:66-70</a>).</p>
<p>When David became king, he organized the Levites into three divisions (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.6">1 Chr 23:6</a>). Heman, who represented the Kohathites, was charged with the musical service in the house of the Lord (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.31">6:31</a>), and another group of Kohathites was made responsible for the “bread of the presence” each Sabbath (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.32">9:32</a>). When David brought the ark of the covenant to Jerusalem, Uriel, a Kohathite, was commissioned to supervise its transportation (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.3-5">15:3-5</a>).</p>
<p>During the period of the divided kingdom, the combined forces of the Moabites and Ammonites attacked Judah. King Jehoshaphat admitted his inability to repulse the aggressors and sought the aid of the Lord. The Kohathites led the people in a song of praise and probably led the army when, the next morning, the king and the fighting men of Judah went out against the invaders (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.19-22">2 Chr 20:19-22</a>).</p>
<p>Two important reform movements characterized the declining years of the kingdom of Judah. The first took place during the reign of Hezekiah (715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.1-37">2 Kgs 18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.1-30.27">2 Chr 29–30</a>); the second in the reign of Josiah (640–609 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.1-23.37">2 Kgs 22–23</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.1-33">2 Chr 34</a>). The climax of Josiah’s reform came in 621 <span class="era">BC</span> with the discovery of the Book of the Law. In both these movements the Kohathites played an important role. In the reign of Hezekiah they were numbered among those who cleansed the house of the Lord (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.12-16">2 Chr 29:12-16</a>), and in Josiah’s time two notable Kohathites were among those appointed to supervise the work of the temple (<a href="?bref=2Chr.34.12">34:12</a>).</p>
<p>Following the exile, mention is again made of the Kohathites. The paucity of evidence precludes any judgment of the significance of their ministry. In all probability they were numbered among those who attempted to serve the Lord faithfully in the midst of general spiritual decline. The few whose names are forever enshrined in Scripture were appointed to humble offices. In the absence of evidence to the contrary, it may be assumed that they discharged their duties faithfully (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.19,31-32">1 Chr 9:19, 31-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.2.42">Ezr 2:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.12.25">Neh 12:25</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=LeviTribeof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Levi, Tribe of</a>; <a href="?item=PriestsandLevites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Priests and Levites</a>; <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>