<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Bacchides">
  <title>Bacchides</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BACCHIDES</p>
<p class="fl">Syrian general, governor of the Seleucid territories west of the Euphrates River. The area included Judea, which brought him into contact with five famous men of the intertestamental period: Demetrius I, ruler of the Seleucid kingdom (c. 160–150 <span class="era">BC</span>); Alcimus (Hellenized name of Jakim or Eliakim), puppet high priest (c. 162–158 <span class="era">BC</span>); and Judas, Jonathan, and Simon, the three brothers who ruled Judea in 165–160, 160–143, and 143–135 <span class="era">BC</span>, respectively. Their stories are told in 1 Maccabees.</p>
<p>Bacchides was supported by Demetrius, with whom the story begins. When Antiochus IV Epiphanes died in 163 <span class="era">BC</span>, Demetrius, a hostage in Rome at the time, asked the Roman Senate for permission to claim the throne. When permission was denied, Demetrius fled from Rome, and in a series of successful campaigns (161–160 <span class="era">BC</span>) secured the throne. He then tried to crush the Maccabean secessionists in Judea also. Victorious, he styled himself Demetrius I Soter, meaning “savior.”</p>
<p>Alcimus, a descendant of the OT priest Aaron, suggested to Demetrius that the Jews could be united in opposition to Judas Maccabeus if Alcimus were appointed high priest in Jerusalem. Demetrius I agreed and sent his friend Bacchides to install Alcimus in that important office.</p>
<p>Bacchides made three campaigns into Judea in his efforts to carry out his charge. The first campaign (162–161 <span class="era">BC</span>) met with partial success. Some pious Jews, known as the Hasidim, supported a legitimate Aaronic priest until Bacchides and Alcimus treacherously broke their word and slaughtered 60 Hasidim leaders (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.7.18-20">1 Macc 7:18-20</a>). That act united Judea behind Judas Maccabeus. Not realizing this, however, Bacchides left Alcimus and an army behind and returned to Syria.</p>
<p>Two months later (161 <span class="era">BC</span>) Bacchides returned with 20,000 infantry soldiers and 2,000 cavalrymen, meeting the courageous Judas (who had only 800 men left) in a desperate battle near Elasa (160 <span class="era">BC</span>). In that battle Judas was killed (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.9.18">1 Macc 9:18</a>), and Jonathan and Simon, his brothers, fled into the southern mountains. Bacchides pursued Jonathan, met him in an indecisive battle, and then retreated to Jerusalem. Again, he returned to Syria, leaving an army, the Jewish Hellenists, and Alcimus in charge (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.9.52-57">1 Macc 9:52-57</a>).</p>
<p>That arrangement lasted two years. Bacchides undertook one final Judean campaign (158 <span class="era">BC</span>). This time disaster dogged him. Alcimus died of a stroke, and Bacchides began to suspect that further support of the Jewish Hellenists was unwise. Sensing his indecision, Jonathan offered a truce and exchange of prisoners. Bacchides accepted that as the most dignified way to withdraw, and returned to Syria, leaving Jonathan in effective control of Judea (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.9.72">1 Macc 9:72</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=MaccabeanPeriod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Maccabean Period</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>