<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Bani">
  <title>Bani</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BANI</p>
<p class="list"> 1. Member of Gad’s tribe and warrior among David’s mighty men who were known as “the thirty” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.23.36">2 Sm 23:36</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Shemer’s son and ancestor of Ethan. Ethan was the Levite of Merari’s line in charge of the music in the tabernacle during King David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.46">1 Chr 6:46</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Member of Judah’s tribe and ancestor of Uthai (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.4">1 Chr 9:4</a>). Uthai was one of the first to settle again in Jerusalem after the exile. Possibly the same as #4 below.</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Ancestor of a family that returned to Judah with Zerubbabel after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.10">Ezr 2:10</a>), alternately spelled Binnui in <a href="?bref=Neh.7.15">Nehemiah 7:15</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Ancestor of a family that returned to Judah with Ezra after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.10">Ezr 8:10</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Esd.8.36">1 Esd 8:36</a>). Possibly the same as #4 above.</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Ancestor of some Israelites who were found guilty of marrying foreign women (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.29">Ezr 10:29</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Ancestor of another group of Israelites who were found guilty of marrying foreign women (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.34">Ezr 10:34</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Son (descendant) of Bani (#7 above). This Bani was among those found guilty of marrying foreign women (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.38">Ezr 10:38</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). Because Bani is spelled almost the same as “sons of” in Hebrew, most modern translations render verse <a href="?bref=Ezra.10.38">38</a> “of the sons of Binnui.”</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Rehum’s father and a Levite. Rehum repaired a section of the Jerusalem wall after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.17">Neh 3:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Levitical assistant of Ezra who explained to the people passages from the law read by Ezra (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.7">Neh 8:7</a>). He was among those who offered praises to God on the steps of the temple (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.4-5">Neh 9:4-5</a>). He is probably the same as Binnui (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.38">Ezr 10:38</a>) and Anniuth (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Esd.9.48">1 Esd 9:48</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Another Levitical assistant who explained passages from the law read by Ezra (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.4">Neh 9:4b</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. Levite who signed Ezra’s covenant of faithfulness to God after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.13">Neh 10:13</a>). He was a leader of the people representing the Bani family mentioned under #4 above.</p>
<p class="list">13. Uzzi’s father. Uzzi was the head of the Levites in Jerusalem after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.22">Neh 11:22</a>). Possibly the same as #9 or #10 above.</p>
<p class="sp">The popularity of this name and its similarity to other Jewish names (e.g., Binnui) has caused much confusion in the genealogical lists. The list above is one of several possible arrangements.</p>
  </body>
</item>