<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BanishBanishment">
  <title>Banish, Banishment</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BANISH, BANISHMENT</p>
<p class="fl">Exclusion of a person from a country or group as a form of punishment.</p>
<p>“Banishment” or a similar word is used in the Bible to describe God’s judgment on Adam and Eve (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.23-24">Gn 3:23-24</a>) and on Cain (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.9-14">4:9-14</a>), Absalom’s exile from his father David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.37-39">2 Sm 13:37-39</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.14.13-14">14:13-14</a>), and Israel’s exile from the Promised Land (<a href="?bref=Deut.30.1">Dt 30:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.12">Is 11:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.16.15">Jer 16:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.4.13">Ez 4:13</a>). During the exile, it was included in a list of punishments for those who disobeyed God or the Persian king Artaxerxes (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.26">Ezr 7:26</a>).</p>
<p>The Mosaic law specified that an Israelite should be “cut off” from the people of God for various offenses, such as failure to circumcise a male child (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.12,14">Gn 17:12, 14</a>), eating leavened bread during Passover (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.15">Ex 12:15</a>), making an unholy animal sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Lev.17.1-4">Lv 17:1-4</a>), eating blood (v <a href="?bref=Lev.17.10">10</a>), sinning deliberately (<a href="?bref=Num.15.30-31">Nm 15:30-31</a>), or failing to undergo ceremonial cleansing after contact with a dead body (<a href="?bref=Num.19.11-20">19:11-20</a>). The term “cut off” probably meant exclusion from the social and religious life of the community (cf. <a href="?bref=John.9.18-23,34">Jn 9:18-23, 34</a>). After the exile, when the whole nation of Israel had been “banished,” disinheritance and permanent excommunication from God’s people were made official punishments (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.7-8">Ezr 10:7-8</a>). The Romans, like other conquerors before them, practiced deportation in various forms. Controversy among the Jews led to the banishment of Jews from Rome under Emperor Claudius (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.2">Acts 18:2</a>). The author of Revelation was banished to the island of Patmos during Roman persecution (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.9">Rv 1:9</a>). More severe forms of banishment included permanent exclusion from an area, loss of citizenship, and confiscation of all goods and property.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>