<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BankerBanking">
  <title>Banker, Banking</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BANKER, BANKING</p>
<p class="fl">A person who engages in loaning, exchanging, and issuing money. The development of interstate and international trade made it imperative to devise a method of banking to facilitate the transfer of funds. The appearance of coinage in the seventh century <span class="era">BC</span> brought the money changer into being. The royal monopoly in commerce (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.11">2 Sm 5:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.14-29">1 Kgs 10:14-29</a>) gave place to a system that resembled modern banking.</p>
<p>In NT times money changers represented one aspect of the banking system. They spent their time converting Roman money into orthodox coinage for the temple half-shekel (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.24">Mt 17:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.21.12">21:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.25.27">25:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.11.15">Mk 11:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.19.23">Lk 19:23</a>; <a href="?bref=John.2.14-15">Jn 2:14-15</a>).</p>
<p>Those who lent money (lenders) and those who gave credit in financial transactions (creditors) were protected by a system of guarantees such as pieces of movable property or a pledge of some kind. Interest was theoretically forbidden by Israelite law (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.25">Ex 22:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.15.1-18">Dt 15:1-18</a>), although the law was not always observed and exorbitant rates of interest were sometimes charged. Prophets and some national leaders deplored the practice (<a href="?bref=Neh.5.6-13">Neh 5:6-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.18.8,13,17">Ez 18:8, 13, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.22.12">22:12</a>). Often, the people of Israel were afraid of their creditors (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.1">2 Kgs 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.109.11">Ps 109:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.24.2">Is 24:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.50.1">50:1</a>), who might invade their homes to recover a debt, even carrying off children as slaves (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.1">2 Kgs 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.50.1">Is 50:1</a>). The parable of the creditor and the two debtors in <a href="?bref=Luke.7.41-42">Luke 7:41-42</a> represents a kindly creditor (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.25.14-30">Mt 25:14-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.19.11-27">Lk 19:11-27</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Money_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Money</a>; <a href="?item=MoneyChanger_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Money Changer</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>