<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BaptismofFire">
  <title>Baptism of Fire*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BAPTISM OF FIRE*</p>
<p class="fl">Metaphor coined by John the Baptist. John was looking for the coming of One who would “baptize in Spirit and fire” (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.11">Mt 3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.16">Lk 3:16</a>). The context makes clear that fire in that phrase denotes judgment, a judgment that would presumably purify the penitent (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.4.4">Is 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.3.2-3">Mal 3:2-3</a>) as well as destroy the impenitent (<a href="?bref=Mal.4.1">Mal 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.3.10">Mt 3:10</a>,12).</p>
<p>The prophets and apocalyptic writers frequently spoke of a period of tribulation and suffering necessary before the new age could come: “the messianic woes,” “the birth pangs of the Messiah,” “a river of fire.” Parallels to John’s phraseology are found in <a href="?bref=Isa.30.27-28">Isaiah 30:27-28</a> and in the pseudepigraphal <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Esd.13.10-11">2 Esdras 13:10-11</a>. John the Baptist probably adopted that usage and reexpressed it through a metaphor drawn from his own most characteristic act (baptism). His “baptize in fire” thus probably denoted the purifying judgment that would bring in the new age as well as bring individuals into the new age.</p>
<p>There is no further biblical reference specifically to baptism of fire. Mark and John abbreviate the Baptist’s preaching by omitting all mention of judgment. With Pentecost and beyond, John’s baptism in water is seen as fulfilled in baptism in the Spirit. But Jesus seemed to echo the Baptist’s conviction that a fiery purification was necessary (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.49">Mk 9:49</a>). And he clearly picked up the Baptist’s prediction, but referred the baptism and presumably the fire to his own death (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.49-50">Lk 12:49-50</a>). His death is understood as suffering the fiery baptism for others. That thought is matched by the apostle Paul in his understanding of baptism into Christ as a baptism into Christ’s death (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.3">Rom 6:3</a>). So it can be said that John’s expectation of a purgative baptism of fire for the penitent is most nearly fulfilled in the believer’s being united with Christ in his death and sharing in his sufferings; only in that way does one come to share fully in Christ’s risen glory (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.5">Rom 6:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.8.17-23">8:17-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.3.10-11">Phil 3:10-11</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Baptism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Baptism</a>; <a href="?item=BaptismoftheSpirit_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Baptism of the Spirit</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>