<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Beauty">
  <title>Beauty</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BEAUTY</p>
<p class="fl">Harmonious combination of qualities pleasant to see. Archaeological materials indicate that the ancient Hebrews were concerned more with usefulness than with beauty. Hebrew pottery, for example, was generally more bulky than Canaanite pottery. Yet such artifacts do not mean that the Hebrews had no aesthetic appreciation.</p>
<p>The OT speaks of God’s creation as beautiful (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.9">Gn 2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.26.13">Jb 26:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.19.1-6">Ps 19:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.6.10">Sg 6:10</a>). The land of Canaan is a “pleasant land” (<a href="?bref=Jer.3.19">Jer 3:19</a>). Jerusalem is called “beautiful” (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.1">Is 52:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.2.15">Lam 2:15</a>), as is one of its temple gates (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.2,10">Acts 3:2, 10</a>). The Hebrews admired the wild grandeur of the Lebanon mountain range (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.16">Ps 104:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.60.13">Is 60:13</a>). The Canaanite city of Tirzah (“beauty”), King Baasha’s capital in the northern kingdom (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.33">1 Kgs 15:33</a>), was so named for its attractive location.</p>
<p>Although the Hebrews did not exalt the human form as did the ancient Greeks, the OT does idealize physical attractiveness. A bride’s beauty is described eloquently by her bridegroom in love lyrics in <a href="?bref=Song.4.1-15">Song of Songs 4:1-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.6.4">6:4</a>. Such praise of the bride may have been a traditional feature of Israelite weddings. Several women prominent in the OT are described as beautiful (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.17">Gn 29:17</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.11.2">2 Sm 11:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.2.7">Est 2:7</a>). But sensual beauty was secondary to industry, resourcefulness, and traditional piety in a woman (<a href="?bref=Pr.31.10-31">Prv 31:10-31</a>). A number of men also were known for their physical attractiveness—for example, David (<a href="?bref=1Sam.16.12">1 Sm 16:12</a>) and Absalom (<a href="?bref=2Sam.14.25">2 Sm 14:25</a>). Cosmetics, jewelry, and other accessories were used as female beauty aids in OT times. The prophet Isaiah listed such items (<a href="?bref=Isa.3.18-24">Is 3:18-24</a>), and Ezekiel mentioned cosmetic practices current in his day (<a href="?bref=Ezek.16.10-13">Ez 16:10-13</a>). Israelite worship was beautiful, too, with the high priest’s elaborate ceremonial robes designed for glory and beauty (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.2,40">Ex 28:2, 40</a>).</p>
<p>The concept of beauty is applied also to God in the OT. The Lord’s favor is called his “beauty” (<a href="?bref=Ps.90.17">Ps 90:17</a>). Isaiah recorded God’s promise to give his people “beauty for ashes” (<a href="?bref=Isa.61.3">Is 61:3</a>). The psalmist expressed a desire to spend time in the temple enjoying the Lord’s beauty, his “incomparable perfections” (<a href="?bref=Ps.27.4">Ps 27:4</a>). Isaiah described God as a “diadem of beauty” to the faithful Israelite remnant (<a href="?bref=Isa.28.5">Is 28:5</a>), and the Messiah was spoken of as a beautiful king (<a href="?bref=Isa.33.17">33:17</a>). Thus in the OT the concept of beauty had a deeper meaning than simply physical attractiveness. It became a theological concept affirming God’s essential glory.</p>
<p>The NT urges Christ’s followers to live lives that will “adorn” the teaching of the Savior, making it attractive to nonbelievers (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.10">Ti 2:10</a>). Those who preach the gospel of Christ are spoken of as beautiful (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.15">Rom 10:15</a>). The apostles Paul and Peter warned women against being satisfied with outward beauty (<a href="?bref=1Tim.2.9-10">1 Tm 2:9-10</a>), reminding them that beautiful character is the true adornment of godliness (<a href="?bref=1Pet.3.3-5">1 Pt 3:3-5</a>). The beauty of the believer’s final home in heaven is reflected in the description of the “new Jerusalem” as a bride and in the symbolism of treasured precious stones of antiquity (see <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-22.21">Rv 21–22</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>