<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BenHadad">
  <title>Ben-Hadad</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BEN-HADAD</p>
<p class="fl">Title of two or possibly three kings of Syria, meaning “son of Hadad.” Hadad was the Syrian storm god probably identical with Rimmon (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.5.18">2 Kgs 5:18</a>).</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Ben-hadad I, son of Tabrimmon and grandson of Hezion. In spite of a history of Syrian hostility to Israel, Ben-hadad I entered into an alliance with King Baasha (908–886 <span class="era">BC</span>) of the northern kingdom of Israel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.18-20">1 Kgs 15:18-20</a>). The pact was broken, however, when continuing hostilities between Israel and the southern kingdom of Judah erupted into a major encounter. Baasha conducted a major campaign against King Asa (910–869 <span class="era">BC</span>) of Judah. In order to cut off infiltration into his kingdom and defection to the southern kingdom, Baasha fortified the city of Ramah, situated north of Jerusalem but uncomfortably close to it. His action extended Israel’s territory into Judah.</p>
<p class="list-text">In the face of that threat, Asa sent his remaining wealth to Ben-hadad I, asking him to break his pact with Baasha (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.18-19">18-19</a>). The Syrian king took advantage of the offer and sent his armies against Israel. He conquered the cities of Ijon, Dan, and Abel-beth-maacah plus the territory of Naphtali (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.20">20</a>), thus ensuring Syrian control of the main caravan routes through Galilee. Baasha was forced to abandon Ramah and move to Tirzah. Asa then conscripted the population of Judah to dismantle and carry off the fortifications erected by Baasha. Materials taken from Ramah were used to help build Geba in the territory of Benjamin. Asa’s victory became the subject of a prophetic protest by Hanani, who berated Asa for his reliance on the king of Syria (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.7">16:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Ben-hadad II. The biblical accounts in 1 Kings and 2 Chronicles do not make a clear differentiation between Ben-hadad I and II. Some scholars have therefore identified them as a single person. This view finds apparent support in the “Melqart Stele,” which mentions Ben-hadad and to which a date of about 850 <span class="era">BC</span> has been assigned. It seems better, however, to posit a Ben-hadad II who was the son of Ben-hadad I. If one does not distinguish between the two, Ben-hadad’s activity must overlap both the reign of Ahab (874–853 <span class="era">BC</span>) and that of Baasha. In each, a military encounter with Ben-hadad was recorded; one must posit an interval of up to four decades between the encounters if no distinction is made.</p>
<p class="list-text">Ben-hadad II led a coalition of armies against Samaria during the reign of King Ahab of Israel. In the course of the siege, Ben-hadad demanded that Ahab surrender his wealth, wives, and children to him. Ahab agreed to that demand, but when Ben-hadad added the condition that he be given anything that his aides laid their hands on, Ahab refused on advice of his counselors. His refusal enraged Ben-hadad.</p>
<p class="list-text">An anonymous prophet predicted that Ahab would defeat the armies of Ben-hadad (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.13">1 Kgs 20:13</a>). Ahab’s victory came when aides of the district governors killed the soldiers who had come out of the Syrian camp to take them captive. The Syrian forces fled. Ben-hadad was again defeated by the Israelites the next year when he attempted to engage them in battle on the plain rather than in the hill country. His reason was his belief that the “gods” of the Israelites were gods of the hills (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.23">23</a>). That Syrian defeat was also predicted by a prophet, who declared its cause to be Ben-hadad’s misconception of the nature of Israel’s God (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.28">28</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Ben-hadad pleaded for his life, promising to restore all the cities his father had taken from Israel. Ahab agreed, but his action met with prophetic protest (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.35-43">35-43</a>). The pact established by the two kings brought about a cessation of hostilities that lasted only three years. The peace was broken by Ahab, who, at the instigation of King Jehoshaphat of Judah, sought to regain the city of Ramoth-gilead. Guidance was first sought from a group of prophets who predicted victory. Micaiah, however, a true prophet, predicted defeat (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.5-28">22:5-28</a>). Ahab’s forces were defeated, and Ahab died in battle (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.29-36">29-36</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Ben-hadad also figured in the life of the prophet Elisha, whom he sought to capture (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.11-19">2 Kgs 6:11-19</a>). The attempt was thwarted when the Syrian army was stricken with blindness.</p>
<p class="list">3. Ben-hadad III, son of King Hazael of Syria. This Ben-hadad was not related to Ben-hadad I or II but adopted the name. Because Jehoahaz (814–798 <span class="era">BC</span>), king of Israel, did not follow the Lord, God allowed Israel to come under the control of Ben-hadad III. Release from the oppression of Ben-hadad III was accomplished by a “savior” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.5">2 Kgs 13:5</a>), probably a reference to Assyrian incursions into Syria.</p>
<p class="sp"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=SyriaSyrians_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Syria, Syrians</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>