<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Bethsaida">
  <title>Bethsaida</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BETHSAIDA</p>
<p class="list">1. Town northeast of the Sea of Galilee. Bethsaida was the home of three of Jesus’ disciples: Andrew, Peter, and Philip (<a href="?bref=John.1.44">Jn 1:44</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.21">12:21</a>). Jesus announced that calamity would come upon Bethsaida because of its unbelief in spite of the mighty works he had done there (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.21-22">Mt 11:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.13">Lk 10:13</a>). A blind man was healed in Bethsaida (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.22-26">Mk 8:22-26</a>), and nearby over 5,000 people were fed by the miracle of the loaves and fish (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.34-45">Mk 6:34-45</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.10-17">Lk 9:10-17</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Bethsaida is mentioned in several ancient sources, chiefly the writings of Josephus, a first-century <span class="era">AD</span> Jewish historian. Two Bethsaidas, one on each side of the Sea of Galilee, were once postulated because the reference in Mark mentions the feeding of the 5,000 as happening across the lake from Bethsaida, whereas in Luke it seems to have taken place near Bethsaida. One solution is that the miracle occurred in the district surrounding Bethsaida, but that the quickest way to reach the city itself was to cross part of the lake. Such an interpretation questions the traditional location of the miracle (et-Tabgha on the west shore, nearer to Capernaum) but is preferable to the proposal of two Bethsaidas so close to each other.</p>
<p class="list-text">Bethsaida was merely a fishing village until it was enlarged and beautified by Philip the tetrarch (4 <span class="era">BC</span>–<span class="era">AD</span> 34), son of Herod the Great, after the death of Caesar Augustus. Philip was later buried there, according to Josephus. Bethsaida’s name was changed to Julias in honor of Julia, daughter of Augustus. That city was defended by Josephus when he was its military commander during the first Jewish revolt against Rome (<span class="era">AD</span> 66–70).</p>
<p class="list-text">Josephus wrote that Bethsaida was “at the lake of Gennesareth” but “near to the Jordan River.” He also said that it was in lower Gaulanitis, a district that touched the northeast quarter of the Sea of Galilee. There is, however, no ancient “tell” or ruin fitting the size or description of the city near either the lake or the river. A suggestion that the small harbor of el-’Araj is the site of Bethsaida has little archaeological support, but et-Tell, located about two miles (3.2 kilometers) from the lake, shows evidence of extensive Roman occupation and building activity. At present, et-Tell seems to be the most satisfactory candidate for identification of Bethsaida.</p>
<p class="list">2. A variant name for the pool at Jerusalem, otherwise called Bethesda or Beth-zatha. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Bethesda_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bethesda</a>; <a href="?item=BethZatha_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Beth-zatha</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>