<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BibleQuotationsoftheOldTestamentintheNewTestament">
  <title>Bible*, Quotations of the Old Testament in the New Testament</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BIBLE*, Q<span class="lc">uotations of the Old Testament in the New Testament</span></p>
<p class="fl">OT passages cited or alluded to in the NT writings.</p>
<p>One of the most complex problems in interpreting the Bible is in understanding how NT writers quoted the OT. Obviously nothing is so formative and authoritative for the NT writers as Scripture. However, the way that they used OT passages often seems strange to modern readers.</p>
<p>The OT has provided the words and ideas for much of the NT. Unless one has a Bible that prints OT quotations in distinctive print, this may not be easily seen, for the NT writers often weave the OT words into their own without indicating they are borrowing from the OT. There are over 400 passages of the OT that are explicitly cited in the NT. Almost half of these are introduced by a statement like “Scripture says” to draw attention to the fact that the authority and thought of the OT is being implemented. For the others, however, the OT words are woven into the fabric of the author’s own statement.</p>
<p>In addition to the over 400 passages cited explicitly, there are well over 1,000 places where there is an allusion to an OT text, event, or person. The difference between a quotation and an allusion is sometimes debated for particular texts, but usually the distinction is that in a quotation the author consciously uses the words of an OT passage, whereas with an allusion he has the texts in mind but is not consciously trying to use the words.</p>
<p>Quotations are easy to identify if there is an introductory formula such as “the Scripture says” (as in <a href="?bref=Rom.10.11">Rom 10:11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.28.16">Is 28:16</a>). Where there is no introductory formula, it is easy to overlook explicit quotations (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.13">Rom 10:13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Joel.2.32">Jl 2:32</a>). The allusions are, of course, harder still to recognize, but they often provide the key to interpretation. For example, <a href="?bref=John.1.14-18">John 1:14-18</a>—with its mention of glory, grace and truth, Moses, and the fact that no one has seen God—is much more easily and profoundly understood when read in connection with <a href="?bref=Exod.33.17-34.8">Exodus 33:17–34:8</a>. In the Exodus passage the glory of God and his grace and truth are revealed to Moses. The author was showing that a much more complete revelation of God was given in Jesus than was given Moses in the account recorded in Exodus.</p>
<p>In addition, significant light is shed on many NT passages from OT passages with similar ideas and words even where the NT author may not have been consciously alluding to those texts (e.g. <a href="?bref=Matt.16.19">Mt 16:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.22.22">Is 22:22</a>). What was behind the author’s thinking is not certain, but in such cases the NT reflects the thinking, the culture, and language of the OT period.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DistributionofOldTestamentQuotations">Distribution of Old Testament Quotations</p>
<p class="fl">The books of the NT that show the most dependence on the OT are Matthew, John, Romans, Hebrews, 1 Peter, and Revelation. Such a statement can be misleading, however, because the writers have different methods.</p>
<p>Matthew quotes or consciously reflects the wording of OT passages about 62 times, almost half of which have an introductory formula. The book of Revelation, on the other hand, never quotes the OT and never has an introductory formula but is probably more dependent on the OT than any other NT book. The book of Hebrews quotes or consciously reflects the OT about 59 times, again half of which have an introductory formula, but the Gospel of John does so only 18 times, nearly always with an introductory formula. However, the allusions to the OT are present on virtually every page of John’s Gospel, so much so that some scholars have argued that he has modeled his account on the exodus narrative, the Jewish feasts, or OT persons and images. Paul’s Letter to the Romans uses the OT 54 times (about three-fourths of which have introductory formulas), but nowhere else so frequently (e.g., 1 Cor 16 times, Gal 11 times, Phil one time, 1 Thes one time).</p>
<p>In addition to the indication that Philippians and 1 Thessalonians use the OT only once each, some other books make explicit use of the OT rarely or never. Colossians, Titus, Philemon, and the Johannine letters do not use the OT at all; 2 Timothy and Jude use the OT only once; while 2 Peter and 1 Timothy make use of it twice.</p>
<p>The important point is to realize that the OT is used most frequently in circumstances where the audience is familiar with the OT or where the OT is essential for describing the events relating to Christ and the church. The books using the OT most frequently (Mt, Jn, Rom, Heb, 1 Pt, Rv) either stem from or are addressed to a Jewish context or, as in the case of Romans and John, deal specifically with the relation of Jews and Christians. The Gospels make rather extensive use of the OT because the language of the OT is necessary to convey the identity and importance of Jesus in the purposes of God. Similarly 1 Peter uses the OT frequently because the author is trying to convey to his persecuted audience that they are the people of God and the inheritors of the promises of God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DifficultiesinInterpretation">Difficulties in Interpretation</p>
<p class="fl">Often when people think of quotations of the OT in the NT they think only in terms of prophecy. Some have been guilty of counting up the OT statements that the NT applies to Christ and the church and then claiming these OT texts as predictions that prove Jesus is the Messiah. Such a procedure is filled with problems because it is too simplistic and does not do justice to either the OT or to the way the NT uses it. Of course, the early church used the OT to show that Jesus fulfilled the promises of God and did God’s work, but the use the church made of the OT was quite varied and much of it cannot be classified as predictive prophecy. Prophecy itself is too complex to be limited to predictive thinking.</p>
<p>Some of the most obvious examples of the difficulties appear in Matthew’s Gospel, although they are by no means confined there. <a href="?bref=Matt.2.15">Matthew 2:15</a>—“Out of Egypt I called my son”—is a quotation of <a href="?bref=Hos.11.1">Hosea 11:1</a>, but in Hosea these words do not refer to the Messiah. They refer to the nation of Israel. Similarly <a href="?bref=Matt.2.18">Matthew 2:18</a> quotes <a href="?bref=Jer.31.15">Jeremiah 31:15</a> (“A voice is heard in Ramah, weeping and great mourning, Rachel weeping for her children and refusing to be comforted, because they are no more,” <span class="sc">niv</span>) as fulfilled in the slaughter of the innocent babies in Bethlehem, but in Jeremiah the weeping is over the destruction of Jerusalem. <a href="?bref=John.12.40">John 12:40</a> views <a href="?bref=Isa.6.10">Isaiah 6:10</a> as fulfilled in Jesus’ ministry, but this verse deals with the call of Isaiah and is not a prediction concerning the ministry of the Messiah. The examples could be multiplied but these should be sufficient to illustrate the problem. For this reason the NT writers have often been accused of twisting the Scriptures, but this charge is as simplistic as the thought that all prophecy is predictive and in fact springs from the same error. Therefore, any attempt to understand the use of the OT in the NT will have to deal with the variety of ways in which the OT is used and with the methods employed by the NT writers.</p>
<p>There are other difficulties that are encountered as well. Sometimes the NT writer will indicate that some fact related to Christ is a fulfillment of the OT but the explicit text that he had in mind cannot be identified. For example, <a href="?bref=John.7.38">John 7:38</a> introduces the words “Out of his heart shall flow rivers of living water” with the statement “as Scripture has said.” No OT text reads this way. Possibly the allusion is to the rock that provided water in the wilderness (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.1">Ex 17:1</a>), or to the waters that flowed from the new temple (<a href="?bref=Zech.14.8">Zec 14:8</a>) or, more generally, it may be a reference to <a href="?bref=Isa.58.11">Isaiah 58:11</a>. Similarly, the difficulty in determining the OT text behind the prophecy that Christ will be called a Nazarene (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.23">Mt 2:23</a>) is notorious. Probably the reference is to <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1">Isaiah 11:1</a> and the Hebrew word there translated as “branch,” but the connection is not easily made and is not certain. A third example of this kind of difficulty is in <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.34">1 Corinthians 14:34</a>, where Paul indicates that women should be in submission just as the Law says, but there is no OT text expressing this idea. His statement in probably to be understood as a summary rather than a quotation or allusion. Similarly on a few occasions an OT text is seemingly attributed to the wrong OT book. In <a href="?bref=Mark.1.2-3">Mark 1:2-3</a> an OT quotation is attributed to Isaiah but the quotation is really a conflation (or mixing) of <a href="?bref=Exod.23.20">Exodus 23:20</a>, <a href="?bref=Mal.3.1">Malachi 3:1</a>, and <a href="?bref=Isa.40.3">Isaiah 40:3</a>. <a href="?bref=Matt.27.9-10">Matthew 27:9-10</a> quotes a passage that is said to be from Jeremiah, when really it is dependent on <a href="?bref=Zech.11.13">Zechariah 11:13</a> and might best be described as a summary of <a href="?bref=Zech.11.12-13">Zechariah 11:12-13</a>, with certain words included from <a href="?bref=Jer.32.6-9">Jeremiah 32:6-9</a>. These two examples do not create a major problem, however, for the determination of the origin of the words may be due to their use in collections of quotations from various prophets, in which case the more prominent prophets would be used to designate origin.</p>
<p>The wording of the quotations of the OT text does not always conform to the modern form of the OT. Just as today there are numerous translations of the Bible, when the NT was being written there were various forms of the OT text. With regard to the Hebrew text (for the OT was written mostly in Hebrew), there were different traditions. Such differences in the Hebrew traditions would have been relatively small. Because of the increasing importance of Aramaic after the Babylonian captivity and of Greek after the conquests of Alexander the Great, the OT was also known and used in both these languages when the NT was being written. In fact, the Jews found it necessary in their synagogue services after reading the Hebrew OT to paraphrase the reading in Aramaic so that all could understand. These paraphrases were later written down and are known as Targums. The Greek translation of the OT that stems from the third century <span class="era">BC</span> is known as the Septuagint, but there were also other Greek translations in use. This being the case, the wording of a NT quotation is not identical in every detail to the text of the Hebrew OT.</p>
<p>Added to the fact that there were various forms of the text known in first-century <span class="era">AD</span> Palestine is the complicating factor that NT writers often did not intend to quote the OT exactly. The use of formal quotation marks is a modern device, and ancient writers were not so taken by technical precision. They were more concerned with the intention of a text and consequently might copy or quote it verbatim, quote it from memory, use or adapt part of a verse, or even change certain words as they borrowed the verse to express their points. (The NT writers often use the OT words describing God’s actions in the past to explain what he has done in their time.) The importance of any differences between the NT quotation and the OT depends on the use to which the quotation is put and the degree to which the use is dependent on textual differences.</p>
<p>Some examples should illustrate the nature of these difficulties. <a href="?bref=Eph.4.8">Ephesians 4:8</a> quotes <a href="?bref=Ps.68.18">Psalm 68:18</a>. Whereas the Hebrew and Septuagint read, “You ascended to the heights, you lead captivity captive, you received gifts among mankind,” Ephesians records the verse as “After he ascended into the heights, <span class="ital">he</span> led captivity captive; he <span class="ital">gave</span> gifts to men.” Paul is stressing that Christ has given grace to people for ministry. He has either adapted the wording of the OT to make his point or he quoted a variant reading, <span class="ital">“he gave</span> gifts.” Some versions do have this reading. In fact, the Targum understands this verse as Moses giving the words of the law to the children of men, and Paul may well be adapting this understanding to the new revelation that has come in Christ.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Matt.1.23">Matthew 1:23</a> quotes <a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">Isaiah 7:14</a>, but there are distinct differences between the Hebrew text and the wording in Matthew. The Hebrew reads, “Behold the young woman will become pregnant and will bear a son and you will call his name Immanuel,” whereas Matthew’s text records “Behold, the <span class="ital">virgin</span> will become pregnant and will bear a son, and <span class="ital">they</span> will call his name Immanuel.” The Septuagint does have the specific word “virgin,” like Matthew, but is not the source of Matthew’s quotation since other differences exist. Some have argued that the change from “you will call” to “they will call” was made by Matthew when he applied the words to Jesus. However, there are several traditions known for this part of the quotation and partial support for the reading in Matthew is provided by the text of Isaiah found among the Dead Sea Scrolls.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Rom.11.26-27">Romans 11:26-27</a> is a conflation of <a href="?bref=Isa.59.20-21">Isaiah 59:20-21</a> and part of <a href="?bref=Isa.27.9">Isaiah 27:9</a>, but there are important differences. One of these is that the OT has “the redeemer will come to Zion,” whereas Romans has “the deliverer will come <span class="ital">from</span> Zion.” The change to “from Zion” could indicate that Paul had a different textual tradition, could be the result of an intentional change by Paul, or more probably, could reflect the wording of <a href="?bref=Ps.14.7">Psalm 14:7</a>.</p>
<p>An awareness of the difficulties involved in the quotations of the OT by the NT writers will prohibit a simplistic approach and will prevent hasty conclusions. Care to ask not only which text was used but also which form of the text was used and how is obviously essential in any serious study. In addition it is necessary to allow for the possibility that the NT writers knew forms of a text that are now lost.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheMethodsoftheNewTestamentWriters">The Methods of the New Testament Writers</p>
<p class="fl">The methods used by the NT writers were not unique to them. Many of these methods were also employed in first-century Judaism. In fact, both the technique used in quoting and the understanding of the OT text itself in many cases are paralleled in Judaism. For example, from the standpoint of technique used in quoting, the same kinds of formula introductions are used in the Dead Sea Scrolls, the rabbinic writings, and elsewhere. The rabbinic technique of “pearl stringing,” that is, of applying verses from various parts of the OT (the Law, the Prophets, the Writings) to a subject, can be seen especially in Paul’s writings (note <a href="?bref=Rom.9.12-19">Rom 9:12-19</a> or <a href="?bref=Rom.11.8-10">11:8-10</a>). Somewhat related is the practice of using quotations that all contain a key word or key words (note <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.6-8">1 Pt 2:6-8</a>, which draws together quotations using the word “stone,” or <a href="?bref=Rom.15.9-12">Rom 15:9-12</a>, which joins OT verses referring to the “nations”).</p>
<p>The methods used in the NT to interpret an OT text are also displayed in Judaism. Some passages interpret the OT “literally,” such as Jesus’ replies during temptation (see the quotations of <a href="?bref=Deut.8.3">Dt 8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.6.16">6:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.6.13">6:13</a>; in <a href="?bref=Matt.4.3-10">Mt 4:3-10</a>), his teachings on marriage based on <a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Genesis 2:24</a> (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.5">Mt 19:5</a>), or Paul’s use of <a href="?bref=Hab.2.4">Habakkuk 2:4</a> (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.17">Rom 1:17</a>) or <a href="?bref=Gen.15.6">Genesis 15:6</a> (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.3-9">Rom 4:3-9</a>). Many such examples could be given. With regard to prophecy, some of these statements are fulfilled in a “literal” or “direct” way in keeping with the intention of the OT (e.g., <a href="?bref=Mic.5.2">Mi 5:2</a>, Bethlehem as the birthplace of the Messiah; <a href="?bref=Matt.2.4-6">Mt 2:4-6</a>). <a href="?bref=Jer.31.31-34">Jeremiah 31:31-34</a>, the promise of the new covenant, is viewed as directly fulfilled in Christ (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.7-13">Heb 8:7-13</a>). The prophecy of <a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-32">Joel 2:28-32</a> concerning the pouring out of the Spirit of the Lord is directly fulfilled in the Pentecost event (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.17-21">Acts 2:17-21</a>), but the changing of the sun to darkness and the moon to blood are certainly not understood literally in connection with this event.</p>
<p>A different method of interpretation is based on the concept of <span class="ital">corporate solidarity.</span> This technical expression is an attempt to convey the idea that the individuals among God’s people are not merely individuals; they are part of a larger whole. Consequently, what is said about the individual can apply to the whole and vice versa. This is the reason the Servant of the Lord in Isaiah is seen both as the nation (<a href="?bref=Isa.44.1">44:1</a>) and as an individual (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.13-53.12">52:13–53:12</a>). Also the king is sometimes viewed as representative of the nation. The easiest places to see the concept of corporate solidarity are in the effect of the sin of Achan on all the people (<a href="?bref=Josh.7.1-26">Jos 7</a>) or the sin of David in numbering the people (<a href="?bref=1Chr.21.3-8">1 Chr 21:3-8</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">Correspondence in history</span> is not so much a method of interpretation as it is a way of thinking about God. It assumes that the things that happen to God’s people are the things that have happened to previous generations and that God is faithful and operates in the present as he has in the past. Consequently, the trials and deliverance of God’s people are often expressed with words borrowed from the previous accounts of God’s people. Isaiah describes the anticipated deliverance in terms of a second exodus (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.15-16">11:15-16</a>). Ezekiel describes the king set up over the people in terms of a second David (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.25">Ez 37:25</a>). In the NT, <a href="?bref=Rev.22.1-21">Revelation 22</a> describes the new heavens and the new earth in terms of the Garden of Eden (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.1-3.24">Gn 2–3</a>). Sometimes this technique is described as “typology,” but this term has been used for so many questionable interpretations that it is misleading. The most important thing about this concept is that it is a view of God and his working among his people.</p>
<p>With these two concepts, the way that the OT is quoted in the NT can be understood. The conviction that Jesus was the promised deliverer and that the last days had dawned in his ministry are evident everywhere. The quotation of <a href="?bref=Hos.11.1">Hosea 11:1</a> can be used in <a href="?bref=Matt.2.15">Matthew 2:15</a> because of corporate solidarity and correspondence in history. What was said of the nation is true of the one who is its representative, and there is correspondence in their respective histories. <a href="?bref=Jer.31.15">Jeremiah 31:15</a> can be used in <a href="?bref=Matt.2.18">Matthew 2:18</a> because of correspondence in history and especially because Jeremiah looked forward to God’s intention for Israel and prophesied a new covenant (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.17,31-34">31:17, 31-34</a>). Matthew saw not only the correspondence in history but believed that in Jesus this promised salvation had been granted. <a href="?bref=John.12.40">John 12:40</a> can quote <a href="?bref=Isa.6.10">Isaiah 6:10</a> of Jesus’ ministry, not because he twists the meaning of the OT text, but because he saw that what had happened with God’s messenger before happened again and even <span class="ital">ultimately</span> in Jesus’ ministry. The instances of such correspondences in history are numerous.</p>
<p>There are other texts where there seems to be an <span class="ital">actualization</span> of the OT text. Some quotations seem to be “lived out” in the ministry of Jesus. Because of their conviction about Jesus and his kingdom, the NT writers often saw certain OT texts as appropriated and made alive by Jesus. <a href="?bref=Ps.118.22">Psalm 118:22</a> was not intended as a prophecy of the Messiah, but Jesus saw it as descriptive of his ministry (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.42">Mt 21:42</a>), and the early church saw this verse as actualized in his death and resurrection (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.11">Acts 4:11</a>). <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">Isaiah 53</a> is another text that the NT views as actualized in Jesus’ ministry (see <a href="?bref=Acts.8.32-35">Acts 8:32-35</a> and <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.22-25">1 Pt 2:22-25</a>). Some Christians would view <a href="?bref=Ps.22.1-31">Psalm 22</a> as a prophecy of the crucifixion of Jesus, but it seems instead to be the lament of a righteous OT sufferer. Through correspondence in history, and because Christians saw so much of the psalmist’s plight actualized in Jesus’ crucifixion, the psalm became the easiest way to describe what once again had happened to God’s righteous sufferer. The words of <a href="?bref=Isa.40.3">Isaiah 40:3</a> describe the ministry of John the Baptist (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.3">Mt 3:3</a>). Jews had come to see this verse as a prophecy of God’s end-time salvation, and the early church saw John the Baptist fulfilling this forerunner’s task. Luke made this identification (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.4-6">Lk 3:4-6</a>), but he applied the same role to Jesus’ disciples (<a href="?bref=Luke.9.52">9:52</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.1">10:1</a>). This seems to be a further example of actualization and correspondence in history. In other places the church has applied to Christians ideas that were previously understood of Christ (e.g., the stone in <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.4-5">1 Pt 2:4-5</a>; the ministry of the Suffering Servant in <a href="?bref=Acts.13.46-47">Acts 13:46-47</a>).</p>
<p>The most convenient term to describe the way the OT is “fulfilled” in Christ is to say that the OT finds its climax in Jesus. Even where actual quotations are not involved, the OT ideas such as prophet, priest, or king are climaxed in him as the ideal and embodiment of all the OT models. He could tell religious authorities that “one greater than Solomon is here” (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.42">Mt 12:42</a>) or “one greater than the temple is here” (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.6">Mt 12:6</a>). Those passages involving correspondence in history or actualization also lead to the conviction that he is the climax of the OT Scriptures.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ThePurposesoftheUseoftheOldTestament">The Purposes of the Use of the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The variety of methods of interpretation and application of the OT parallels the fact that the OT was used for a variety of purposes. People tend to think only in terms of the use of the OT to show that Jesus was the Messiah, but there are a number of other uses with a variety of goals. Many OT texts are used to show Jesus is the Messiah, the fulfillment of the OT promises (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.16-21">Lk 4:16-21</a>). Without lessening the fulfillment emphasis, however, other verses are applied to Jesus for other purposes: to evangelize (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.32-25">Acts 8:32-25</a>); to demonstrate or convince (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.33-35">Acts 13:33-35</a>); to rebuke (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.6-7">Mk 7:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.11.7-10">Rom 11:7-10</a>); and to describe (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.12-15">Rv 1:12-15</a>). On the other hand, many quotations of the OT in the NT are not directly related to the Messiah. OT passages are adapted to provide a word from God on some aspect of life or ethics. For example, Jesus used <a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Genesis 2:24</a> to substantiate his teaching on divorce as he attempted to deal with the issues raised by the civil regulation of divorce (<a href="?bref=Deut.24.1">Dt 24:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.19.1-12">Mt 19:1-12</a>). The stress on the OT commandments shows their importance for Christians (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.16-22">Mt 19:16-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.13.8-10">Rom 13:8-10</a>). Often OT statements deal with specific problems. The problem of pride at Corinth is solved by the quotation of <a href="?bref=Jer.9.24">Jeremiah 9:24</a> (“Let the one boasting, boast in the Lord,” <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.31">1 Cor 1:31</a>). <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.10-12">First Peter 3:10-12</a> incorporates <a href="?bref=Ps.34.12-16">Psalm 34:12-16</a> as ethical instructions, and <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.14-15">3:14-15</a> borrows from <a href="?bref=Isa.8.12-13">Isaiah 8:12-13</a> to address the fear of suffering. The spiritual armor in <a href="?bref=Eph.6.14-17">Ephesians 6:14-17</a> is derived largely from OT passages. Such examples are so numerous that there can be no doubt that the OT is used to describe Christian existence. In fact, nearly every subject discussed in the NT is presented somewhere via OT terms and quotations. Frequently OT passages are used to describe the church as God’s end-time community. <a href="?bref=Hos.2.23">Hosea 2:23</a> is used to show that those who formerly were not God’s people now are (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.25-26">Rom 9:25-26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.10">1 Pt 2:10</a>). Several OT texts contribute to the description of the church in <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Peter 2:9</a>. OT texts that speak of the word of God describe the apostles’ preaching (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.8">Rom 10:8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.24-25">1 Pt 1:24-25</a>). OT quotations describe the sinful condition of humanity (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.10-20">Rom 3:10-20</a>). Salvation is explained through OT concepts and symbols and is based on OT statements (<a href="?bref=John.6.31-33">Jn 6:31-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.6-13">Gal 3:6-13</a>). The words of Daniel describe the Second Coming (<a href="?bref=Dan.7.13-14">7:13-14</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.24.30">Mt 24:30</a>). Even the worship of early Christians was expressed through use of the OT (see <a href="?bref=Acts.4.24">Acts 4:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.11.34-35">Rom 11:34-35</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="HowToUnderstandTheUseOfTheOldTestamentInTheNewTestament"/>
  </body>
</item>