<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BindingandLoosing">
  <title>Binding and Loosing*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BINDING AND LOOSING*</p>
<p class="fl">Biblical concept much discussed and debated throughout Christian history. Jesus referred to binding and loosing on two different occasions. After Peter’s confession that Jesus was the Messiah, Jesus said to him: “I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatever you bind on earth shall be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven” (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.19">Mt 16:19</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Later, Jesus gave the same authority to bind and loose to all of the disciples (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.18">18:18</a>).</p>
<p>Matthew is the only Gospel writer to record those specific words of Jesus. According to the Gospel of John, Jesus addressed similar but not identical words to the disciples after the resurrection: “If you forgive the sins of any, they are forgiven; if you retain the sins of any, they are retained” (<a href="?bref=John.20.23">Jn 20:23</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). A problem arises in identifying both the nature and the extent of the authority Jesus gave.</p>
<p>“Bind” and “loose” translate two Greek words, themselves translations of words in Aramaic, the language spoken by Jesus. Among Jesus’ Jewish contemporaries, the two Aramaic words were often used as technical rabbinic terms. They referred to the verdict of a teacher of the Law who, on the basis of his authority as an expert in the interpretation of the Mosaic law, could declare some action “bound” (forbidden) or “loosed” (permitted). (Compare <a href="?bref=Matt.23.2-3">Mt 23:2-3</a>, where Jesus said: “The scribes and Pharisees sit on Moses’ seat; so practice and observe whatever they tell you,” <span class="sc">rsv</span>.) Among the greatest Jewish rabbis, Shammai “bound” many actions that the more liberal teacher Hillel “loosed.”</p>
<p>Alongside that scribal use of the terms was their use in judicial contexts. They referred to the imposition or the removal of a ban or judgment. In that context the words meant “to condemn; imprison” and “to absolve; set free.” Both sets of meanings have been used to interpret the two texts in Matthew.</p>
<p>The precise meaning of the words in Matthew must be understood on the basis of their use in specific situations and in the light of the general NT understanding of apostolic authority. In <a href="?bref=Matt.16.19">Matthew 16:19</a> Peter’s authority to bind and loose is connected with his receiving “the keys of the kingdom of heaven.” In the Gospels the “kingdom of heaven” (that is, kingdom of God) is the sphere of God’s rule, the “community” of people whom he rules as Lord. In a figurative sense, Peter was entrusted with the keys to that kingdom, that “building.” (See <a href="?bref=1Cor.3.9,16-17">1 Cor 3:9, 16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.2.20-22">Eph 2:20-22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.4-5">1 Pt 2:4-5</a> for the idea of the people of God as his building.) The keys symbolize the authority entrusted to Peter as the one who confessed Jesus as Lord (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.16">Mt 16:16</a>), and as the one who represents all those disciples who utter the same confession.</p>
<p>According to <a href="?bref=Matt.23.13">Matthew 23:13</a>, the scribes were understood as guardians of the kingdom, since the knowledge of God had been entrusted to them (<a href="?bref=Luke.11.52">Lk 11:52</a>). But they did not fulfill their trust; they shut the doors of the kingdom. Therefore, their task was transferred to Peter, spokesman for the 12 disciples, who were representatives of a new Israel (see <a href="?bref=Matt.21.43">Mt 21:43</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=KeysoftheKingdom_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Keys of the Kingdom</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="InterpretationsOnBindingAndLoosing"/>
  </body>
</item>