<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Birds">
  <title>Birds</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BIRDS</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="Birds"/>
<p class="fl">Feathered vertebrates of the class Aves. Over 8,000 species of birds are known. Approximately 400 species are found in the Holy Land and about 40 are mentioned in Scripture.</p>
<p>Modern scientists classify organisms on the basis of internal and external structure, but the biblical writers generally classified organisms according to habitat. Thus, in the Bible, bats are listed with birds as creatures of the air (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.19">Lv 11:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.18">Dt 14:18</a>).</p>
<p>Precise identification of biblical birds is often difficult or impossible. The biblical languages were not highly specialized scientific languages. People in biblical times generally knew the difference between similar animals now categorized as separate species. For birds, however, they frequently used poetic, descriptive terms. Biblical scholars attempt to overcome the difficulties in identification by comparing the Hebrew words with similar words in related languages and by attention to the habitat, habits, and characteristics attributed to the birds in Scripture. Nevertheless, different scholars sometimes arrive at different identifications.</p>
<p class="h2" id="BiblicalReferencestoBirds">Biblical References to Birds</p>
<p class="fl">The Bible refers to birds both in literal and figurative senses. The biblical writers were keen observers of nature, their awareness of birds and bird life being reflected in many passages. They asserted that God knows all the birds (<a href="?bref=Ps.50.11">Ps 50:11</a>) and cares for them (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.29">Mt 10:29</a>). They saw God’s covenant with Noah after the flood, his promise never to destroy life again by flood, as extending even to the birds and animals (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.10">Gn 9:10</a>).</p>
<p>The Mosaic law declared many birds “unclean,” mostly species that were scavengers or predators, or inhabited waste places. Centuries later the early Christians came to regard unclean species as clean by God’s decree, revealed in the apostle Peter’s vision (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.12">Acts 10:12</a>). Other birds, like quail, sustained the Israelites in their wanderings (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.13">Ex 16:13</a>). The Law prescribed birds as sacrifices for a firstborn child (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.24">Lk 2:24</a>), for a Nazirite vow (<a href="?bref=Num.6.10">Nm 6:10</a>), for cleansing a leper (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.22">Lv 14:22</a>), and as a burnt offering and sin offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.12.8">12:8</a>).</p>
<p>Birds are easily subject to extinction, especially through human activity. God required the Israelites to practice conservation to prevent any birds from becoming extinct in the Holy Land, both for the birds’ sake and so the Israelites would have a continuous source of food. The Law allowed foraging Israelites to take eggs or the young from a bird’s nest, but they were not permitted to kill both a mother bird and her young (<a href="?bref=Deut.22.6">Dt 22:6</a>).</p>
<p>Biblical writers turned to nature frequently for illustrations of divine principles or human characteristics. Comparisons of humans to birds sometimes carry a sense of lowness, as when King Nebuchadnezzar developed claws like a bird in his madness (<a href="?bref=Dan.4.33">Dn 4:33</a>), or when Job remarked that birds did not know the source of wisdom (<a href="?bref=Job.28.21">Jb 28:21</a>). In Jesus’ parable of the sower, the birds that ate the seed scattered by the wayside may represent indifference and a lack of spiritual understanding (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.4">Mt 13:4</a>).</p>
<p>Scripture also contains sympathetic images of the plight of birds. A lonely man praying was likened to a lonely bird on a housetop (<a href="?bref=Ps.102.7">Ps 102:7</a>). If someone was unjustly hunted by his enemies, he would understand a hunted bird’s plight (<a href="?bref=Lam.3.52">Lam 3:52</a>). Birds were said to be affected by curses on evildoers as they fled from Jerusalem or from the face of the earth (<a href="?bref=Jer.9.10">Jer 9:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.3">Zep 1:3</a>).</p>
<p>In spite of such misfortune visited upon birds, Scripture affirms that, like other creatures, they are cared for and delighted in by God (<a href="?bref=Ps.50.11">Ps 50:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.6.26">Mt 6:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.10.29">10:29</a>). Both Pharaoh and Nebuchadnezzar were compared to a tree that gives shelter to the birds (<a href="?bref=Ezek.31.6">Ez 31:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.4.12">Dn 4:12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Dan.2.38">2:38</a>). Human power, however, fails eventually as when the tree representing Nebuchadnezzar was cut down, forcing the birds to flee (<a href="?bref=Dan.4.14">Dn 4:14</a>). God’s protection, by contrast, is unfailing. Jesus likened the kingdom of God to a mustard seed, growing to become a shelter for birds (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.32">Mt 13:32</a>). God provides a habitation for birds (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.12">Ps 104:12</a>), although Jesus, the Son of Man, had nowhere to rest his head (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.20">Mt 8:20</a>).</p>
<p>Birds were considered evidence of God’s handiwork (<a href="?bref=Job.12.7">Jb 12:7</a>). Bird lore provided examples of good sense in learning from a mistake (<a href="?bref=Pr.1.17">Prv 1:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.6.5">6:5</a>) and of bad judgment in failing to avoid the snares of immorality (<a href="?bref=Pr.7.23">7:23</a>). Birds and other creatures could be tamed, unlike the wicked human tongue (<a href="?bref=Jas.3.7">Jas 3:7</a>). Birds flying without alighting were an image of an undeserved curse (<a href="?bref=Pr.26.2">Prv 26:2</a>). Without trust in God, people might be forced by evil to flee like a bird to the mountains (<a href="?bref=Ps.11.1">Ps 11:1</a>). Birdsong was said to bring joy (<a href="?bref=Song.2.12">Sg 2:12</a>). The return of God’s people to the Promised Land would be like birds returning (<a href="?bref=Hos.11.11">Hos 11:11</a>). Jesus expressed his love for Jerusalem by saying that he longed to gather his people to himself as a hen gathers her brood under her wing (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.37">Mt 23:37</a>).</p>
<p>Finally, birds were occasionally regarded as ominous signs. For example, Pharaoh’s baker learned of impending death because in a dream birds ate the food from a basket on his head (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.17">Gn 40:17</a>). Solomon warned against cursing the king, even in private, because “a little bird may tell them what you said” (<a href="?bref=Eccl.10.20">Eccl 10:20</a>). A vivid biblical image is that of scavenging, carrion-eating birds consuming the bodies of evildoers. To the Israelites, such a desecration of humanity was an image of ultimate horror (<a href="?bref=Deut.28.26">Dt 28:26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.17.44">1 Sm 17:44</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.46.11">Is 46:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.7.33">Jer 7:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.12.9">12:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.29.5">Ez 29:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.4">39:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.17,21">Rv 19:17, 21</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IndividualSpecies">Individual Species</p>
<p class="h3" id="Bittern">Bittern</p>
<p class="fl">Long-legged wading bird <span class="ital">(Botaurus stellaris)</span> similar to the heron, but with shorter legs and a smaller, more compact body. Bitterns inhabit marshes, where it is easy for them to hide with their natural camouflage. A bittern’s mottled plumage of barred brown and black so duplicates the color and shape of swamp vegetation that at times the bird seems to disappear before the observer’s eyes. The neck is covered with long, soft feathers, making it appear disproportionately heavy. Bitterns are wary and solitary. During mating season the bittern’s larynx is modified to produce a mysterious-sounding cry. The body twists in an unusual manner in harmony with the notes. Bitterns nest alone in grassy marshes. Because they are shy, they have become symbols of places of desolation and loneliness.</p>
<p>There is some question as to whether the bittern is actually mentioned in the Bible. The <span class="sc">kjv</span> has “bittern” in three places (<a href="?bref=Isa.14.23">Is 14:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.11">34:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.14">Zep 2:14</a>). Many biblical scholars believe the Hebrew word in those verses refers not to the bittern but to the hedgehog (<a href="?bref=Isa.14.23">Is 14:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.14">Zep 2:14</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) or porcupine (<a href="?bref=Isa.34.11">Is 34:11</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The Hebrew word is similar to an Arabic word meaning “porcupine.” Other scholars point out that the references suggest a bird rather than a mammal, especially <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.14">Zephaniah 2:14</a>, which speaks of the creature making its “lodge in her capitals” (i.e., above Nineveh’s doorposts). Bitterns are particularly abundant in the swamps of the Tigris River (near Nineveh). The bittern’s characteristics may fit the references in the three passages better than do the hedgehog’s.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Hedgehog_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hedgehog</a>; <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals (Porcupine)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Buzzard">Buzzard</p>
<p class="fl">Hawklike soaring bird <span class="ital">(Buteo vulgaris</span> or <span class="ital">Buteo ferox).</span> It resembles the kite, though its tail is straight and not cleft. It is mentioned in the list of unclean birds (<a href="?bref=Deut.14.13">Dt 14:13</a>). But other translations render the word as “glede” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) or “kite” (<span class="sc">nasb</span>, <span class="sc">neb</span>). The parallel list in <a href="?bref=Lev.11.1-47">Leviticus 11</a>, however, substitutes “kite” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>, <span class="sc">neb</span>) or “vulture” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) for “buzzard.” Thus, it is difficult to determine whether the buzzard is actually mentioned in the Bible, even though it is a common resident of Israel.</p>
<p>Like other great soaring birds, the buzzard is noted for its sharp eyesight, and may be the bird mentioned for that quality in <a href="?bref=Job.28.7">Job 28:7</a> (variously translated “falcon,” “eagle,” or “vulture”). It will trail its prey for hours, and has a remarkable ability to see a carcass on which it descends to feed. Somewhat larger than the common buzzard is the long-legged buzzard, found in Israel, western Asia, and Syria.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#KestrelorFalcon">Kestrel</a>; <a href="#KiteorGlede">Kite</a>; <a href="#Vulture">Vulture (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Cormorant">Cormorant</p>
<p class="fl">Large, black gooselike bird <span class="ital">(Phalacrocorax carbo),</span> repeatedly depicted in art from Egypt and the Holy Land. Its length varies from 19 to 40 inches (48.3 to 101.6 centimeters). Its feet have webs between all four toes. The feet, attached far back on the body, serve as propellers when the cormorant dives to catch its meal of fish, crustacea, or amphibia. The long bill is curved at the tip, and under the bill is a sac in which the cormorant keeps the captured fish.</p>
<p>Cormorants live in large companies, making nests of sticks and other vegetation that they carry to trees or to rocky shelves near coasts. Up to four eggs are incubated, and the young are fed by both parents.</p>
<p>The cormorant frequents swamps around the Sea of Galilee, Lake Huleh (the waters of Merom), and the Mediterranean coast. Its Hebrew name originally denoted the “hurling down” of the bird at its prey. Cormorants dive into deep water and sometimes seem to zoom beneath the surface in their hunt for fish. The cormorant’s greed is proverbial. It was ceremonially unclean for the Israelites (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.17">Lv 11:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.17">Dt 14:17</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Pelican">Pelican (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Crane">Crane</p>
<p class="fl">Tall wading birds <span class="ital">(Grus grus)</span> resembling storks and herons but with shorter talons. The plumage has a silvery gloss and the tail feathers are wavy. Large flocks of cranes flying in wedge-shaped formations pass over the Holy Land during the daylight hours each fall on their way to Africa from the northern countries of Europe and again in the spring when they return north to breed. Migratory flocks may number as many as 2,000 birds. <a href="?bref=Jer.8.7">Jeremiah 8:7</a> refers to the crane’s migratory habits.</p>
<p>The usual call of the crane is best described as a bellow, but during migratory flight they emit a chattering sound that may be referred to in <a href="?bref=Isa.38.14">Isaiah 38:14</a>. Cranes have remarkably powerful voices, their calls seeming to carry for miles. Migrating flocks usually have a flock leader who does the calling.</p>
<p>A crane’s height may reach 40 to 60 inches (101.6 to 152.4 centimeters). Except for the ostrich, the crane is the tallest bird ever to inhabit the Holy Land. A crane’s wingspread may exceed 90 inches (228.6 centimeters). The overall color is steel gray; the head and neck are black with a longitudinal white stripe. The crane feeds on land rather than in shallow water. It feeds primarily on grass and grain yet may devour insects, snakes, small alligators, frogs, and worms, using its long, powerful bill as a sharp hammer for killing such creatures.</p>
<p>The crane usually nests in solitary places, often in shallow water or nearby. Its nest is a mass of vegetation, holding two or three eggs that are light-colored with darker spots.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Cuckoo">Cuckoo</p>
<p class="fl">Small, drab brown bird known for its parasitic habits. The term the <span class="sc">kjv</span> used in <a href="?bref=Lev.11.16">Leviticus 11:16</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.14.15">Deuteronomy 14:15</a> may refer either to the common cuckoo <span class="ital">(Cuculus canorus)</span> or to the great spotted cuckoo <span class="ital">(Clamator glandarius).</span> The bird acts as a brood parasite, laying its eggs in the nest of another species after pushing out one of the eggs of the host species. The young cuckoo hatches before the young of the host species and evicts the other young. The foster parents raise it as their own.</p>
<p>The cuckoo, an insect eater, is considered ritually unclean in Scripture, which might imply that it is a predator or carrion-eater. For that reason some believe the Hebrew word actually refers to the seagull or sea mew rather than the cuckoo. Gulls, terns, and petrels are all common on the seashore and lakes of the Holy Land.</p>
<p>Other scholars believe that the Hebrew word refers not to the cuckoo but to one of the owls, possibly the long-eared owl.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Owl">Owl</a>; <a href="#Seagull">Seagull (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Eagle">Eagle</p>
<p class="fl">Large bird of prey, genus <span class="ital">Aquila.</span> Vultures were often confused with eagles, making identification of the biblical birds difficult. Eagles’ heads are not bald as are the heads of vultures, but from a distance they appear similar. It is possible that the Hebrew word translated “eagle” (which literally means “to tear with the beak”) may have referred to all large birds of prey, eagles and vultures alike. A number of references to the eagle in Scripture are actually references to the griffon vulture (e.g., <a href="?bref=Hos.8.1">Hos 8:1</a>; perhaps <a href="?bref=Matt.24.28">Mt 24:28</a>). In certain passages, however, the true eagle may be meant.</p>
<p>The Holy Land has several varieties of eagle, including the imperial eagle <span class="ital">(Aquila heliaca)</span> and the less common golden eagle <span class="ital">(Aquila chrysaetos).</span> These birds are powerfully built with strong wings; their movements reveal suppleness and strength. A distinctive hooked beak, which enhances the eagle’s dignified and somewhat ferocious appearance, provides it with an effective instrument for tearing and killing prey. Short, powerful legs and prehensile claws enable an eagle to apply an almost unbreakable grip on a struggling victim. The strong talons have sharp points and edges. The eagle hunts by day.</p>
<p>For Jeremiah and other prophets, the eagle was the epitome of swiftness. The golden eagle, which can fly three or four miles (5–7 kilometers) in ten minutes, may have evoked the comparisons in <a href="?bref=2Sam.1.23">2 Samuel 1:23</a>;<a href="?bref=Jer.4.13">Jeremiah 4:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.49.22">49:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.4.19">Lamentations 4:19</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>), and <a href="?bref=Hab.1.8">Habakkuk 1:8</a>. Moses used a similar comparison to emphasize the sudden striking power of a hostile enemy (<a href="?bref=Deut.28.49">Dt 28:49</a>). The author of Proverbs, observing the high altitude to which the eagle soars, applied that image to the human situation (<a href="?bref=Pr.23.4-5">Prv 23:4-5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.12.14">Rv 12:14</a>).</p>
<p>The eagle’s strength and invincibility were mentioned often with reference to powerful nations attacking Israel. The prophet Ezekiel described Nebuchadnezzar as an eagle (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.3">Ez 17:3</a>). Both the Babylonians and Assyrians frequently depicted the eagle in their art, especially as a deity with a man’s body and an eagle’s head. Nebuchadnezzar even had an experience of temporary insanity in which “his hair grew as long as eagles’ feathers, and his nails were like birds’ claws” (<a href="?bref=Dan.4.33">Dn 4:33</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>The eagle builds its nest on inaccessible mountain peaks or at the top of the tallest trees, a fact noted by Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.49.16">Jer 49:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Job.39.27-28">Jb 39:27-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Obad.1.4">Ob 1:4</a>). The brood consists of two or occasionally three eggs. Only the female sits on the nest, but the young eaglets are fed by both parents. Eagles are devoted to their offspring and train them with great care in the art of flying. Some commentators interpret <a href="?bref=Exod.19.4">Exodus 19:4</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.32.11">Deuteronomy 32:11</a> as evidence of the eagle’s practice of catching its young on its wings. There is virtually no evidence from observation, however, that any eagle can perform such a feat. In some versions the wording avoids a direct statement that eagles bear their young on their wings.</p>
<p>Some eagles in captivity have lived to an age of over 100 years. This remarkable longevity caused the psalmist to speak of the eagle whose youth is renewed (<a href="?bref=Ps.103.5">Ps 103:5</a>). Confronted by its impressive qualities, biblical authors observed the eagle with awe and wonder (<a href="?bref=Job.39.27-30">Jb 39:27-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.30.18-19">Prv 30:18-19</a>). Those awesome qualities also contributed to several prophetic visions, including Ezekiel’s vision of a creature with an eagle’s face (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.10">Ez 1:10</a>) and the apostle John’s vision of a holy beast like a flying eagle (<a href="?bref=Rev.4.7">Rv 4:7</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Vulture">Vulture (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="FowlDomestic">Fowl, Domestic</p>
<p class="fl">Domesticated poultry <span class="ital">(Gallus gallus domesticus),</span> probably derived from the red jungle fowl of India. They seem to have been known already in OT times (<a href="?bref=Pr.30.31">Prv 30:31</a>). A seal of Jaazaniah (see <a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.23">2 Kgs 25:23</a>), dating from about 600 <span class="era">BC</span>, bears the image of a fighting cock. A reference to fowls or poultry for Nehemiah’s table, however, may be to wild game rather than domestic fowl (<a href="?bref=Neh.5.18">Neh 5:18</a>).</p>
<p>Poultry symbolized fertility, and the Jews carried a cock and hen in front of bridal couples at weddings. The motherly concern of hens gathering their broods was familiar to Jesus’ hearers (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.37">Mt 23:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.34">Lk 13:34</a>).</p>
<p>Since roosters habitually crow an hour or two before dawn, the third watch of the night, from midnight to 3:00 <span class="sc">am</span>, was known as the cockcrow. According to the Talmud (a commentary on Jewish law), keeping chickens was prohibited in Jerusalem in NT times to prevent the insects and larvae that breed in chicken droppings from contaminating sacrificial flesh. For that reason the cock that Peter heard (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.34,74">Mt 26:34, 74</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.22.34,60-61">Lk 22:34, 60-61</a>) probably belonged to Romans living there or to Jews who did not follow Jewish regulations.</p>
<p class="h3" id="GoatsuckerorNightHawk">Goatsucker or Night Hawk</p>
<p class="fl">Migratory bird, dark in color and short-legged, similar to the American whippoorwill. The goatsucker (genus <span class="ital">Caprimulgus</span>) resembles an owl with a flat head, large eyes, soft plumage, and a noiseless flight. It hunts insects at night, catches them on the wing, and during the day rests on branches. Goatsuckers were so named because they were thought by the ancients to milk goats. According to <a href="?bref=Lev.11.16">Leviticus 11:16</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.14.15">Deuteronomy 14:15</a>, they were ritually unclean. Although some scholars believe that an owl is intended, there seems to be good reason to accept the “night hawk” translation.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Goose">Goose</p>
<p class="fl">Long-necked, web-footed water birds with waterproof feathers (genus <span class="ital">Anser</span>). Domestic geese were known to the Greeks of Homer’s day, since they are mentioned in the <span class="ital">Odyssey.</span> They were domesticated in Egypt perhaps as early as the Old Kingdom (c. 2500 <span class="era">BC</span>) and certainly by the time of the New Kingdom (c. 1500– 1100 <span class="era">BC</span>). They were used for food and sacrifice. The breeding of geese was widespread in Canaan in biblical times; ivory carvings of the 13th or 12th century <span class="era">BC</span> showing geese have been found in excavations at Megiddo in Israel.</p>
<p>Many species of geese spend most of their lives on land even though they are waterfowl; some even build their nests in trees. Wild geese tend to inhabit flatlands and prairies rather than mountainous terrain.</p>
<p>Geese may have graced the table of King Solomon. In <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.23">1 Kings 4:23</a> they are referred to as “fatted fowl,” a term that may also refer to ducks, swans, guineas, pigeons, or other domestic edible birds.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Hawk">Hawk</p>
<p class="fl">Small birds of prey found in the Holy Land. Most references are probably to the sparrow hawk <span class="ital">(Accipter nisus).</span> This bird is slightly larger than the kestrel, has a grayish-brown back and a white belly with black and brown bars. It has short feathers, long, curved talons, and broad wings, rounded at the outer ends, which enable it to soar on updrafts. The long tail, acting as a rudder, helps the bird change its course swiftly in flight. It is hence very maneuverable in the air when chasing warblers or other small birds. It does not seize its prey on the ground, as does the kestrel, but hunts and attacks small birds in flight. Hawks hunt in the daytime, unlike owls that are adapted for nighttime hunting. With their eyes located on the side of the head, hawks are very keen-sighted. They usually nest in tall trees and their nests are often occupied by the same pair year after year.</p>
<p>The Egyptians embalmed sparrow hawks and regarded all hawks highly. The god Horus was depicted with the head of a hawk hawk was ceremonially unclean to the Israelites (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.16">Lv 11:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.15">Dt 14:15</a>). It was not a permanent resident of Israel but stopped off as it migrated from north to south. Its southward migration is mentioned in <a href="?bref=Job.39.26">Job 39:26</a>. A reference in <a href="?bref=Isa.34.11">Isaiah 34:11</a> to “hawk” (“cormorant,” <span class="sc">kjv</span>) is uncertain. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="#KestrelorFalcon">Kestrel or Falcon</a>; <a href="#KiteorGlede">Kite (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Heron">Heron</p>
<p class="fl">Wading bird (genus <span class="ital">Ardea</span>) with a long, thin neck and long legs. It has a characteristic comblike growth on the inner side of the third toe.</p>
<p>Herons are generally white, blue, green, or gray. They nest together in rookeries, and both parents bring in food for the young. Herons feed on fish, small reptiles, and insects, gulping them down in one swallow. Adults and young migrate in the late fall to warm southern climates. The white heron attains a length of more than 3 feet (.9 meter), whereas the dwarf heron is only about 22 inches (55.9 centimeters) long.</p>
<p>At least seven varieties of heron are reported in the Holy Land. The white ibis, or buff-backed heron (<span class="ital">Buphus russatus</span>), was probably the most common species. The purple heron <span class="ital">(Ardea purpureus)</span> is a summer breeder found in all parts of the Holy Land where there is standing water.</p>
<p>The blue-gray heron (<span class="ital">Ardea cinerea</span>) winters in southern Europe and North Africa, migrating to northern Europe in the early spring. In Israel it builds its winter nest near water, in swamps and along riverbanks, where it feeds on fish and frogs. It will stand patiently in the water for hours, and then suddenly its long, pointed beak darts down with lightning speed to catch its prey. Often the blue-gray heron builds its nest in a tall tree to which it may return year after year.</p>
<p>According to <a href="?bref=Lev.11.19">Leviticus 11:19</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.14.18">Deuteronomy 14:18</a>, the heron was ceremonially unclean to the Israelites. Some scholars believe those references are to the cormorant, but most scholars think they refer to one of the herons.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Cormorant">Cormorant (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Hoopoe">Hoopoe</p>
<p class="fl">One of the Holy Land’s most beautiful birds (<span class="ital">Upupa epops</span>). It has vividly colored plumage, a lovely crown-shaped crest that becomes erect when the bird is alarmed, and a long, slender curved bill. The pinkish-brown hoopoe is about 11 inches (27.9 centimeters) long, with black and white bands on its back, tail, and wings. Hoopoes are basically desert-dwelling birds.</p>
<p>The name “hoopoe” is derived from the sound of the bird’s call. To emit the sound, the neck feathers are puffed up and the head snapped in the air. When on the ground, the bird hammers its beak into the earth.</p>
<p>The hoopoe arrives in the Holy Land in February, breeds in the summer, and leaves in September. It was held in religious reverence by the Egyptians. It was listed as ritually unclean (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.19">Lv 11:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.18">Dt 14:18</a>), probably because it searches for grubs and small insects in such unsanitary places as dunghills.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Ibis">Ibis</p>
<p class="fl">Wading bird (<span class="ital">Threskiornis aethiopica</span>) presently unknown in the Holy Land but possibly known there in biblical times. It was well known in ancient Egypt, where it was sacred to the god Thoth. Today it has practically vanished with the disappearance of swamps along the Nile.</p>
<p>There is some question as to whether the ibis is meant in <a href="?bref=Lev.11.17">Leviticus 11:17</a>, where it is classified as ceremonially unclean. The same Hebrew word in <a href="?bref=Deut.14.16">Deuteronomy 14:16</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.34.11">Isaiah 34:11</a> is translated “great owl,” a translation preferred by most scholars.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#OwlGreat">Owl, Great (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="KestrelorFalcon">Kestrel or Falcon</p>
<p class="fl">Small hawk (<span class="ital">Falco tinnunculus</span>) about a foot (30.5 centimeters) long with brown, black, and yellow feathers on its breast. It was abundant in the Holy Land in villages and in the countryside, nesting on rooftops and among rocks. Like most hawks, the kestrel is able to hover and float in midair and then swoop down on its prey, seizing it with sharp, hooklike talons. It feeds largely on mice, small reptiles, and insects.</p>
<p>Embalmed kestrels have been found in ancient Egyptian tombs. The Egyptians also embalmed the hunting kestrel <span class="ital">(Falco cherug),</span> which can be tamed and trained to hunt rabbits and other small game. Falconry (hunting with hawks of various species) was well known among the ancients and is still practiced today. That the Assyrians were familiar with falconry is seen in the records of Ashurbanipal. Because the kestrel is a predator, it was ceremonially unclean (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.14">Lv 11:14</a>). Some translations render the word as “kite” (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.14">Lv 11:14</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.13">Dt 14:13</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), an illustration of the difficulty of identifying biblical birds precisely.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#KiteorGlede">Kite or Glede (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="KiteorGlede">Kite or Glede</p>
<p class="fl">Large bird of prey <span class="ital">(Milvus milvus).</span> The average length of the kite is about 19 inches (48.3 centimeters). The upper part is generally dark, but the belly is white. Kites nest high in trees and build nests of vegetation, including sticks. They rarely have more than two or three young, which they feed on snakes, grasshoppers, and so on. Sometimes kites are called snake hawks.</p>
<p>The kite is a migratory bird that stays in Israel during the summer, especially in the mountains of southern Judea, in the trackless wastes west of the Dead Sea, and in the wilderness of Beersheba.</p>
<p>The red kite or glede is a medium-sized bird of prey. The edges of the upper part of the bill overlap with the lower one, forming sharp scissors. The tail is forked or cleft like that of a fish. Its loud cry often includes sharp whistling notes. Other Holy Land species include the black kite <span class="ital">(Milvus migrans)</span> and the black-winged kite <span class="ital">(Elanus caeruleus).</span></p>
<p>The kite is listed among the unclean birds in Mosaic law (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.14">Lv 11:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.13">Dt 14:13</a>), but the precise identification of the birds mentioned there is disputed by some scholars and translators.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="Buzzard">Buzzard</a>; <a href="#KestrelorFalcon">Kestrel or Falcon (above)</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="Kite"/>
<p class="h3" id="Lammergeier">Lammergeier</p>
<p class="fl">Largest of the vultures and less common than the other members of the family. It is grayish brown with white streaks and has a black tuft of stiff hairs in the facial area that gives it the name “bearded vulture.” Another name for it is “lamb vulture.”</p>
<p>The lammergeier <span class="ital">(Gypaetus barbatus)</span> has a unique way of killing its prey; since its beak is not particularly powerful it carries its victim high in the air and then drops it on rocks.</p>
<p>The lammergeier is especially partial to tortoises and to marrow bone. After jackals and smaller vultures have reduced a carcass to bone, the lammergeier crushes the bones to obtain the marrow, or swallows the pieces intact. Hence it is also known as the ossifrage, from a Latin word meaning “bone crusher.” The lammergeier was unclean in Mosaic law (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.13">Lv 11:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.13">Dt 14:13</a>; both translated “vulture” in <span class="sc">nlt</span> and “ossifrage” in <span class="sc">kjv</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Vulture">Vulture (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Ostrich">Ostrich</p>
<p class="fl">Two-toed, swift-running, flightless bird (<span class="ital">Struthio camelus</span>) that lives in deserts or in areas covered with stunted bushes.</p>
<p>In biblical times ostriches ranged as far north as Syria and were found over the entire wasteland of the Negev Desert, but they have since become extinct there. Its Hebrew name means “daughter of the desert.” It is the largest of all living birds, attaining a height of about 10 feet (3 meters) and a weight of 175 pounds (79.5 kilograms), though some males may weigh as much as 300 pounds (136.4 kilograms). The female is considerably smaller. Powerful thighs and long legs give the ostrich great speed, reported to be as high as 40 <span class="sc">mph</span> (64 <span class="sc">kph</span>).</p>
<p>The ostrich is omnivorous. It eats grass, fruits, small mammals, birds, snakes, and lizards, as well as large pebbles that assist in the breakdown of food in its gizzard. The ostrich is hunted, but its eggs are generally more sought after than the bird itself. The empty shells are traded throughout the Mediterranean area for use as utensils, or when broken up as raw material for beads. The eggs—as many as 25 in one clutch—are laid in a shallow nest of sand, with some left uncovered. They may appear to be neglected by day, but only because they are ordinarily incubated at night. The cock does most of the incubating; the female participates only during cold days. The strong, thick eggshell protects the embryo from the heat of the desert.</p>
<p>Occasionally the ostrich is used for riding or even for pulling small carts. Ostrich feathers are in great demand. Ostrich plumes graced ancient royal courts as fans. An ivory-handled fan of Pharaoh Tutankhamen (King Tut) had lovely ostrich plumes. The plumes are white in the male and brownish gray in the female. The reputation of the ostrich for stupidity comes from its behavior when hunted and cornered; it fails to take evasive action even when doing so would save it. In open country, however, it is very wary and runs at great speed to escape. In contrast to the partridge, an ostrich will run away from its eggs and chicks when pursued.</p>
<p>Most biblical references to ostriches emphasize their negative characteristics. They were regarded as unclean in Jewish law (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.16">Lv 11:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.15">Dt 14:15</a>). Several references associate ostriches with images of wilderness and desolation (<a href="?bref=Job.30.29">Jb 30:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.13.21">Is 13:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.13">34:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.43.20">43:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.50.39">Jer 50:39</a>). Their night cry, which has been compared to an ox’s lowing in pain, is referred to in <a href="?bref=Mic.1.8">Micah 1:8</a>. Biblical writers also noted the apparent indifference of the ostrich to its brood (<a href="?bref=Job.39.13-18">Jb 39:13-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.4.3">Lam 4:3</a>).</p>
<p class="h3" id="Owl">Owl</p>
<p class="fl">Nocturnal birds (order Strigiformes) with large heads and large, forward-looking eyes. Their wing and tail feathers are soft as velvet, helping to make their flight noiseless. The owl’s body is small and slender, about the size of a pigeon, but it appears bulky because of the thick covering of feathers. Owls have been considered bearers of misfortune and omens of disaster. In the Near East, owls now live in temple ruins and pyramids in Egypt, and in rock-hewn graves, ruins, and caves on both sides of the Jordan River in Israel. They seldom come near inhabited dwellings.</p>
<p>Owls have excellent night vision, which they use to capture rodents or other animals. Although unusually large, the owl’s eyes are almost useless in the daylight because the light dazzles them. The owl is able to swallow its prey whole because of its elastic esophagus. Indigestible hair and bones are regurgitated as pellets. The bill is short but sharply hooked.</p>
<p>Owls may lay up to ten eggs. The young are cared for on the nest by both parents. Both adults and young tend to remain in the area in which they were hatched. Eight species of owls are found in the Holy Land, of which five are plentiful. It is difficult, however, to identify a particular species with any of the four Hebrew words translated “owl” in Scripture. A fifth word translated “owl” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) is more appropriately identified with the ostrich (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). Owls appear in the lists of unclean birds (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.17">Lv 11:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.16">Dt 14:16</a>), and although translations differ, they concur that all species of owls, being predators, are unclean.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Ostrich">Ostrich (above)</a>; <a href="#OwlBarnorWhite">Owl, Barn or White</a>; <a href="#OwlGreat">Owl, Great</a>; <a href="#OwlLittle">Owl, Little</a>; <a href="#OwlScops">Owl, Scops (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="OwlBarnorWhite">Owl, Barn or White</p>
<p class="fl">Large owl <span class="ital">(Tyto alloa)</span> with a distinct heart-shaped face. It may get its Hebrew name from a snoring sound it makes when breathing in the nest. In flight it emits a frightening screech, and thus is sometimes referred to as the screech owl. Its somewhat sinister features—a large head and wide pop eyes—have led some people to consider it demonic, but they have also inspired another name, the monkey-faced owl. It is a useful bird, however, devouring rodents that raid fields and damage stored grain. Like other owls, it sleeps during the day and hunts at night with a well-developed sense of hearing and sight. Its color is light brownish yellow with a white mask around the eyes and cheeks. The whole leg is covered with feathers that protect it against the bites of struggling victims in its talons.</p>
<p>Some modern translations mention the barn or white owl by name (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.17">Lv 11:17</a>, <span class="sc">njb</span>; <a href="?bref=Lev.11.18">11:18</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.16">Dt 14:16</a>, <span class="sc">njb</span>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Owl">Owl (above)</a>, <a href="#OwlScops">Owl, Scops (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="OwlGreat">Owl, Great</p>
<p class="fl">Large owl, standing nearly two feet (60.9 centimeters) tall <span class="ital">(Asio otus).</span> The color is mouse gray with gray-brown spots and black stripes. As one of its names indicates, it has tufted “ears” and is sometimes called the great horned owl. It feeds on rodents, such as rats and mice. It winters in Israel among ruins and in groves.</p>
<p>The great owl may be the owl mentioned in the Bible among the birds of desolation that will inhabit devastated Edom (<a href="?bref=Isa.34.11">Is 34:11</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span> mg). It is also mentioned by name in some translations of the lists of ritually unclean birds (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.17">Lv 11:17</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.16">Dt 14:16</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p class="h3" id="OwlLittle">Owl, Little</p>
<p class="fl">Smallest of all nocturnal birds of prey. Chiefly insectivorous, the little owl <span class="ital">(Athene noctua glaux)</span> also feeds at times on tiny birds. It is the most common owl in the Holy Land, dwelling among ruins, tombstones, rocks, and thickets (perhaps the owl of <a href="?bref=Ps.102.6">Ps 102:6</a>). Its voice sounds like that of a dying person. On occasion it may be observed perched on a rock with its large eyes gazing off into the distance, a pose that the ancients considered a sign of wisdom. The Greeks associated the little owl with the goddess Athena. It is mentioned by name in several translations (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.17">Lv 11:17</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.16">Dt 14:16</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Owl">Owl (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="OwlScops">Owl, Scops</p>
<p class="fl">Small owl <span class="ital">(Otus scops)</span> distinguished by two horn-shaped crests of hairlike feathers on its head. It perches in an inclined posture and hops and dances like a goat. During the hatching period, the male’s hooting sounds like a moan. The scops owl feeds on insects, rodents, and birds. During invasions of mice or locusts, these owls have appeared in large flocks and helped to destroy the pests. They have been known to attack humans who intrude on their nests. They are well-known inhabitants of Eurasia and Africa.</p>
<p>Some scholars suggest that the scops is the true screech owl, because of its whistling calls that resound through the night. The screech owl is mentioned only once in Scripture (<a href="?bref=Isa.34.14">Is 34:14</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>), but that translation is the subject of scholarly debate. Following traditional Jewish mythology, some translations use the Hebrew word <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">lilith</span><span class="ital">)</span> as a proper name. In Jewish tradition Lilith was a witch-demon who, before Eve’s creation, was Adam’s wife. She became the mother of demons and was thought to attack children during the night; thus the name “Lilith” is translated “night hag” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>) or “night monster” (<span class="sc">nasb</span>). Most scholars favoring the mythical interpretation, however, suggest that Isaiah was using a popular legend to evoke a sense of desolation and did not himself believe in the existence of Lilith. There is little support for “screech owl” as an appropriate translation of the name.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Owl">Owl</a>; <a href="#OwlBarnorWhite">Owl, Barn or White (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Partridge">Partridge</p>
<p class="fl">Most common game bird in the Holy Land. The partridge resembles a chicken in its basic anatomy but has a less chunky body and a longer tail. Two species of partridge inhabit the Holy Land: the sand partridge <span class="ital">(Ammoperdix heyi),</span> found near the Dead Sea, in the Jordan River valley, and in the Sinai Desert; and the chukar partridge <span class="ital">(Alectoris graeca).</span> The sand partridge is a medium-sized bird with yellow feet. The male has sandy-buff plumage, upper tail feathers penciled and barred with brown, and a chestnut and white undersurface. The female is a grayish buff. The chukar partridge resembles the common French partridge of Europe, having a body about 16 inches (40.6 centimeters) long. It is covered with beautiful and radiantly colored feathers.</p>
<p>The biblical reference (<a href="?bref=1Sam.26.20">1 Sm 26:20</a>; probably the sand partridge because of the geographical context) alludes to the common method of catching it by chasing. It was also hunted with snares (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.91.3">Ps 91:3</a>) or by hunters hiding in a blind. The fast-running partridge soon becomes exhausted, which enables hunters to run it to the ground and kill it. Nevertheless, by running and jumping, it can ascend very steep cliffs. The bird finds refuge among bushes into which its brownish-green feathers blend protectively. If it were not such a prolific breeder, it would probably have become extinct by being hunted for food.</p>
<p>The biblical description of the partridge gathering a brood she did not hatch (<a href="?bref=Jer.17.11">Jer 17:11</a>) seems to be based on the fact that the hen lays at least two clutches of eggs, one for herself and one for the cock to incubate.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="Partridge"/>
<p class="h3" id="Peacock">Peacock</p>
<p class="fl">Member of the quail, partridge, and pheasant family, the peacock <span class="ital">(Pavo cristatus)</span> is actually the male peafowl. Its mate is properly known as the peahen. The male attracts attention because of a stately, luxurious appearance enhanced by magnificent feathers. The breast is a brilliant metallic blue, and each tail feather has a brilliant eye near the tip. When lowered, the unusually long tail feathers form a train behind the peacock on the ground, giving it an overall length of up to six feet (1.8 meters). The train can also be raised to form a huge fan adorned with the multicolored eyes. During courtship the feathers are raised and vibrated to make a distinct rustling noise. The rather drab peahen lacks the long train.</p>
<p>Because it is not native to the Holy Land, the peacocks referred to in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.22">1 Kings 10:22</a> and <a href="?bref=2Chr.9.21">2 Chronicles 9:21</a> are thought by some scholars to be Old World monkeys or baboons brought from east Africa, or guinea hens from the upper Nile River region. There is evidence, however, that the Phoenicians introduced peacocks to the Egyptian pharaoh, perhaps as early as the time of King Solomon. It is possible that Solomon’s trade expeditions ranged as far as India, where the peacock is native. The peacock was also well known to the Greeks and Romans. Alexander the Great prized its beauty and forbade his soldiers to kill the bird.</p>
<p>In the early Christian church the peacock became a symbol of the immortality promised in the resurrection of Christ. In addition, the eyes of its tail came to represent the all-seeing eye of God.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Pelican">Pelican</p>
<p class="fl">Largest of all aquatic birds, considerably larger even than the swan. The pelican <span class="ital">(Pelecanus onocrotalus)</span> is generally about 50 inches (127 centimeters) long with a 16-inch (40.6-centimeters) beak, the upper part of which is hooked downward at the end, facilitating fish catching. The lower part of the bill supports a yellow pouch extending down the throat. The pouch may hold up to three gallons (11.4 liters) of food (small fish) and water. The pelican’s webbed feet are peculiar in having webs between all four toes. Pelicans are expert swimmers as well as efficient fliers. The pelican’s massive body, long neck, and comparatively small head give it proportions that make rising from the water difficult. To take off, a pelican must first flap awkwardly along the surface, pounding at the water with its legs.</p>
<p>Pelicans fly and nest in groups. Both sexes care for the young that hatch from the one to four eggs. Whereas most birds feed their young by placing food into their mouths, the pelican reverses the process; the young pelican sticks its head and most of its body into its mother’s throat and plucks partially digested food from the mother’s crop. The deep penetration of the young’s beak into the mother’s gullet led ancients to believe that the young were feeding on the blood of the mother’s breast, thus giving rise to wide usage of the pelican as a symbol of Christ’s atonement, and of charity in general.</p>
<p>The roseate pelican is white, at times with a faint rose tinge, and has black feathers growing from the wing joint farthest from the body. The legs, pouch, and skin around the eyes are yellow; the hook of the beak is red. This species may grow up to six feet (1.8 meters) long with a wingspread of up to eight feet (2.4 meters). During the breeding season, the coloration of the exposed areas of the roseate pelican’s legs and face changes from gray to bright orange or red. At the same time the white feathers acquire a beautiful pink tint originating from an oil-gland secretion. The oil is spread throughout the plumage by the bird as it preens.</p>
<p>Some scholars question whether “pelican” is an appropriate translation of the Hebrew in several verses, believing rather that the word refers to one of the owls, hawks, or vultures. Most translations include the pelican in the lists of ritually unclean birds (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.18">Lv 11:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.17">Dt 14:17</a>). Opinion on the other references is more sharply divided. Some scholars maintain that the desert context of the verses eliminates the possibility of a water bird like the pelican (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.102.6">Ps 102:6</a>, “vulture,” <span class="sc">rsv</span>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.11">Is 34:11</a>, “cormorant,” <span class="sc">kjv</span>; “hawk,” <span class="sc">rsv</span>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.14">Zep 2:14</a>, “cormorant,” <span class="sc">kjv</span>; “vulture,” <span class="sc">rsv</span>). On the other hand, the roseate pelican frequents the rivers, lakes, and marshes of the Holy Land. After flying out to sea as far as 20 miles (32.2 kilometers) to swoop down on fish near the surface, the pelican often returns inland to a deserted place to digest its enormous meal. Thus, the pelican may be the lonely wilderness bird of those passages.</p>
<p class="h3" id="PigeonorDove">Pigeon or Dove</p>
<p class="fl">Species of the pigeon family (Columbidae). In common usage the names “pigeon” and “dove” are virtually interchangeable. The common domestic pigeon familiar to city dwellers the world over, for example, is actually a descendant of the wild rock dove. Both names are used in English translations of the Bible to translate the same Hebrew word. A second Hebrew word is usually translated “turtledove.” Nevertheless, it seems clear that the ancient Hebrews recognized differences among dove species.</p>
<p>At least six species of pigeon or dove reside in modern Israel: the rock, ring, and stock doves (genus <span class="ital">Columba</span>), and the turtle, collared, and palm doves (genus <span class="ital">Streptopelia</span>). Of the six, the rock dove <span class="ital">(Columba livia)</span> and the turtledove <span class="ital">(Streptopelia turtur)</span> seem to be the two most often referred to in Scripture.</p>
<p>Pigeons vary in size from 6 to over 12 inches (15 to 30 centimeters). The most colorful Israeli species is the rock dove, which can be a beautiful silvery gray with grayish-green iridescent plumage on the wings (noted by David, <a href="?bref=Ps.68.13">Ps 68:13</a>). The smaller doves <span class="ital">(Streptopelia)</span> are less colorful, mostly gray or buff with a blackish or checkered half collar on the back of the neck. Pigeons have short necks and small heads, plump bodies, and short wings controlled by strong muscles that enable them to fly considerable distances. The smaller doves have longer tails.</p>
<p>At present, the wild rock dove is found primarily in the area around the Sea of Galilee and farther to the south in the many ravines leading down to the Dead Sea. Wild rock doves prefer to build their nests on rocks and cliff faces, a fact precisely described in Scripture (<a href="?bref=Song.2.14">Sg 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.48.28">Jer 48:28</a>). All Israeli doves build fragile nests of scraps of vegetation. Eggs are hatched twice a year. Doves seldom lay more than two eggs. The young are cared for in the nest by both parents, who rove over the fields eating seeds and weeds. The adult’s crop contains digested food in a milky condition, called pigeon’s milk, which can be regurgitated and fed to the young.</p>
<p>During courtship there is a great deal of rivalry among the male doves. The turtledove’s courtship dance is an awesome aerial display. The attention to courtship, the joint care of young, and the solicitude of the parents for each other, noted from earliest times, have made the dove one of the most popular symbols of love and peace (<a href="?bref=Song.1.15">Sg 1:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.2.14">2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.1">4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.5.2">5:2</a>).</p>
<p>A major distinction between pigeons (ring doves) and turtledoves seems to have been recognized by ancient writers. Pigeons are year-round residents and easily tamed, whereas turtledoves are migratory. Turtledoves were confined in cages singly or in pairs as pets or for sacrifices. Pigeons were probably the first birds to be domesticated, perhaps as early as Noah’s time (<a href="?bref=Gen.8.8-12">Gn 8:8-12</a>). They were depicted on the earliest Egyptian monuments, and their edibility was mentioned in early Egyptian texts. Before long, domestic pigeons were regarded as evidence of a household’s prosperity. In the more prosperous households they nested in dovecotes of molded pottery clay fashioned in latticelike structures (hence the “windows” of <a href="?bref=Isa.60.8">Is 60:8</a>).</p>
<p>In NT times there were many dovecotes in the parks around Herod the Great’s palace in Jerusalem. The dove’s popularity was due not only to its docility but also to its desirability as food and as an acceptable and relatively inexpensive sacrifice. The turtledove may have been regarded more highly as a sacrifice because of its wildness and consequent lesser availability. The two biblical references to turtledoves not in a sacrificial context refer to their migratory habits and to their arrival in Israel in the spring (<a href="?bref=Song.2.12">Sg 2:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.8.7">Jer 8:7</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Hos.11.11">Hos 11:11</a>).</p>
<p>Most of the references to doves and pigeons in the Bible are in statements about sacrificial procedures (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.7-10">Gn 15:7-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.1.14">Lv 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.5.7">5:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.12.6">12:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.6.10">Nm 6:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.24">Lk 2:24</a>). Other references, however, include a range of observations and symbolic usages of the dove. Its throaty moaning was often observed (<a href="?bref=Isa.38.14">Is 38:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.59.11">59:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.7.16">Ez 7:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Nah.2.7">Na 2:7</a>). Its power of flight was well known (<a href="?bref=Ps.55.6">Ps 55:6</a>), as were its beauty (<a href="?bref=Song.1.15">Sg 1:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.1">4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.5.12">5:12</a>), its gentleness and loyalty to its mate (<a href="?bref=Song.2.14">Sg 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.5.2">5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.6.9">6:9</a>), its affection (<a href="?bref=Ps.74.19">Ps 74:19</a>), and its innocence (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.16">Mt 10:16</a>). The one negative reference to doves is in <a href="?bref=Hos.7.11">Hosea 7:11</a>, where they are said to be senseless and foolish, perhaps in reference to their overly trusting nature.</p>
<p>Of NT references, perhaps the most significant is the description of the Holy Spirit at Christ’s baptism as a descending dove (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.16">Mt 3:16</a>). The dove’s loving nature made it natural for early Christians to connect the dove image with the concept of the Comforter. Since then the dove has remained the most popular symbol of the Holy Spirit.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="RockDove"/>
<p class="h3" id="Quail">Quail</p>
<p class="fl">Short, stocky birds with bills and feet similar to those of chickens; hence they are adapted to eating seeds or insects. Quail <span class="ital">(Coturnix coturnix)</span> are the smallest of the subfamily of poultry that also includes pheasants and partridges. Quail (or “quails,” another plural form) are about ten inches (25.4 centimeters) long and have small, rounded wings. They burst from their hiding places in the grass or bushes with a whirring sound. The belly of the quail is white. Up to 18 eggs are laid, and if the mother dies, the male has been known to assume the care of the young. Quail of the Mediterranean region winter in the Sudan and migrate northward in vast flocks in the spring. Quail cannot maintain a long sustained flight but make use of wind currents to keep them aloft.</p>
<p>Enormous flocks of quail twice served as food for the Israelites in the wilderness of Sinai, when the birds were driven down in the desert miraculously by winds (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.13">Ex 16:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.11.31-32">Nm 11:31-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.105.40">Ps 105:40</a>). The second time they were probably flying along the Gulf of Aqaba and were blown off course by the east wind (<a href="?bref=Num.11.31">Nm 11:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.26-28">Ps 78:26-28</a>). Their inability to sustain long flight may account for their low flying level—two cubits, or about 40 inches (101.6 centimeters). When exhausted, they were easily caught by hand (<a href="?bref=Num.11.31-32">Nm 11:31-32</a>). Quail were considered clean and the most delicate eating of all game birds, and they were preserved by drying in the sun.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Raven">Raven</p>
<p class="fl">Member of the crow family (Corvidae). The Hebrew word for “raven” means “black one.” The raven (<span class="ital">Corvus corax</span>) weighs about three pounds (1.36 kilograms) and varies from 22 to 26 inches (56 to 66 centimeters) in length. Its tail is broader in the middle than at either end. Eight species are found in Israel: three ravens, two jackdaws, one crow, one rook, and one chough. The crow, about 20 inches (50.8 centimeters) long, is smaller than a raven, and its tail is uniform in width. The raven’s most conspicuous feature is its glossy black iridescent plumage.</p>
<p>Ravens and crows have survived in spite of the dislike many humans have for them. Excellent fliers, they migrate by day and congregate in great flocks of up to several hundred thousand. During the nesting season, they make nests of sticks in which two to seven eggs are laid. Ravens mate for life. Equipped with strong wings, a strong bill, and strong feet, ravens can live in isolated places from which they range widely for food. That it did not return to the ark was a good sign to Noah, indicating that the raven could find food and possibly a place to rest on dry mountaintops (<a href="?bref=Gen.8.7">Gn 8:7</a>).</p>
<p>The raven, essentially a scavenger, was ceremonially unclean (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.15">Lv 11:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.14">Dt 14:14</a>). Yet ravens fed Elijah at God’s command (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.17.4-6">1 Kgs 17:4-6</a>). Job was told that God gave the raven its food (<a href="?bref=Job.38.41">Jb 38:41</a>), as the psalmist and Jesus repeated (<a href="?bref=Ps.147.9">Ps 147:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.24">Lk 12:24</a>). The raven’s glistening black plumage inspired the bride’s comparison of her beloved’s hair (<a href="?bref=Song.5.11">Sg 5:11</a>). They prefer desolate, uninhabited areas as their home territory (<a href="?bref=Isa.34.11">Is 34:11</a>). Ravens are crafty, active birds. Some are capable of speaking, solving puzzles, and performing feats of memory. Bold and curious, they sometimes use their talents for theft.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Seagull">Seagull</p>
<p class="fl">Robust seabirds, primarily scavengers (family Laridae). Several species of gulls live along the seacoast of the Holy Land. They are usually gray-backed with white heads and underparts and black wing tips. The slender bill ends in a downward curve.</p>
<p>Seagulls may be 8 to 30 inches (20 to 76 centimeters) long. Many species migrate, traveling long distances with their superb flying ability. Gulls can also swim easily because of their webbed feet. Their voice is like a harsh scream or squawk. In nesting season many nest together in any available place, such as a cliff or tree. Both male and female incubate and care for the young.</p>
<p>Because gulls will eat almost anything, they are listed as ritually unclean birds (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.16">Lv 11:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.15">Dt 14:15</a>, <span class="sc">asv</span> has “sea mew,” a common European gull). Some commentators believe that those passages refer to an owl or to the cuckoo and not to the seagull.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Cuckoo">Cuckoo (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Sparrow">Sparrow</p>
<p class="fl">Small bird of the finch family (Fringillidae) or the weaver finch family (Ploceidae), considered to be of little worth. The Hebrew word is a general term for “bird” and refers to any small bird such as a sparrow, finch, thrush, or starling. In translation, however, the word sometimes refers to the common English or house sparrow (<span class="ital">Passer domestica;</span> <a href="?bref=Ps.84.3">Ps 84:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.26.2">Prv 26:2</a>).</p>
<p>Dull in color with a black throat, the male house sparrow is a noisy and energetic creature. The nest, when built in open places, has an opening on the side and is made of almost anything available. Sparrows also nest in sheltered places, in dwellings, boxes, or holes in trees. They lay four to seven eggs.</p>
<p>The common or house sparrow was known in ancient Greece and Egypt. There it had a reputation for invading fields in large swarms and picking the seeds from them. It is a permanent resident of the Holy Land.</p>
<p>The sparrow is prolific and lives in close association with humans. It was considered ritually clean. Sparrows brought low prices in countries where they were sold (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.29">Mt 10:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.6">Lk 12:6</a>). Today in Near Eastern marketplaces, boys offer live sparrows for sale. Tied together in groups of four to six by strings attached to one leg, the birds fly about over the boys’ heads. Evidently such a sight was common in NT times.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Stork">Stork</p>
<p class="fl">Long-legged, white wading bird (genus <span class="ital">Ciconia</span>) having large, powerful wings with glossy black primary and secondary feathers. The flapping of its wings produces a loud rushing sound. Connecting membranes between the toes prevent the bird from sinking into the mud. Its red bill is sharp and long, serving to seize and lift its prey out of the water. Storks are mute, lacking a voice box.</p>
<p>Flocks of storks pass through the Holy Land during their September migration on the way to central and southern Africa and likewise in the spring on their return flight to their homes in northern Israel, Syria, and Europe. Storks travel in vast flocks during the day, spreading out against the sky.</p>
<p>The stork’s faithful tending of the young is proverbial, as is its habit of returning annually to the same nesting place. Storks have the habit of adding to their nests each year, and it is possible to find nests that are 100 years old and have a height of more than three feet (.9 meter).</p>
<p>Two species of storks frequent the Holy Land. The white stork <span class="ital">(Ciconia alba)</span> is 40 inches (101.6 centimeters) tall, and its wingspread is six feet (1.8 meters), enabling it to move with a slow, sustained flight or to soar. In folklore the white stork is sometimes considered to be a harbinger of good fortune.</p>
<p>The black stork <span class="ital">(Ciconia nigra),</span> common around the Dead Sea valley, nests in trees; hence it may be the tree-dwelling species referred to in <a href="?bref=Ps.104.17">Psalm 104:17</a>. The Hebrew name for “stork” means literally the “kingly one,” or the “loyal one,” a reference to the care of the bird for its young. Like the heron, the stork was ceremonially unclean because of its diet of aquatic organisms, refuse, small animals, birds, and reptiles (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.19">Lv 11:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.18">Dt 14:18</a>). Jeremiah mentioned the stork’s uncanny and instinctive knowledge of the time of its migration (<a href="?bref=Jer.8.7">Jer 8:7</a>). Its impressive wings figured in one of Zechariah’s visions (<a href="?bref=Zech.5.9">Zec 5:9</a>).</p>
<p class="h3" id="Swallow">Swallow</p>
<p class="fl">Small, nearly black, forked-tailed bird with long, tapering wings, noted for its graceful flight <span class="ital">(hirundo rustica).</span> The small, weak feet are poorly adapted for walking. Swallows resemble swifts in shape and life habits but are somewhat smaller.</p>
<p>The swallow’s large mouth enables it to catch insects while in flight. Colors vary from brown and blue to white. Swallows often nest in buildings, a feature noticed by the psalmist, who reported a swallow’s home at the temple (<a href="?bref=Ps.84.3">Ps 84:3</a>).</p>
<p>Swallows are basically resident in Israel, whereas the swift is a migratory bird noted for the regularity of its migratory schedule. The “swallow” of <a href="?bref=Isa.38.14">Isaiah 38:14</a> probably refers to a swift, as does <a href="?bref=Jer.8.7">Jeremiah 8:7</a>, where the dependability of the bird is contrasted with the irregularity of God’s people. <a href="?bref=Pr.26.2">Proverbs 26:2</a> may be a reference to either the swallow or the swift.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Swift">Swift (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Swan">Swan</p>
<p class="fl">Large, graceful water birds. Two species of swan (genus <span class="ital">Cygnus</span>) are found in the Middle East as passing migrants <span class="ital">(Cygnus olor</span> and <span class="ital">Cygnus musicus).</span> Swans are known as the best musicians among the birds and were considered sacred to the god Apollo by the Greeks. Their voices sound like flutes and harps.</p>
<p>The references in <a href="?bref=Lev.11.18">Leviticus 11:18</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.14.16">Deuteronomy 14:16</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) are probably not to the swan but to the water hen or the barn owl, since there seems little reason to declare the vegetarian swan an unclean animal. <span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Owl">Owl, Barn or White (above)</a>; <a href="#WaterHen">Water Hen (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Swift">Swift</p>
<p class="fl">Small, strong flyers (genus <span class="ital">Apus</span>). Like the swallow, the swift has long, bent wings and a cleft tail, enabling it to obtain great speed as it skims the ground and sweeps through the air. A swift devours a great many harmful insects, catching them in its mouth in flight. Many swifts make their nests in rooftops and in nooks and crannies of city walls. Their nests are built with strong feathers cemented together with saliva. Other swifts live in caves and clefts of rocks.</p>
<p>Common swifts are native to Israel, and in the Jordan Valley they occur in large flocks. <a href="?bref=Isa.38.14">Isaiah 38:14</a> (<span class="sc">niv</span>) seems to be clear reference to the swift’s plaintive call, since the swallow’s sharp chirp is not a striking simile for a distraught king’s cry. The swift has a soft, delicate voice, and its cry could be easily interpreted as melodious wailing.</p>
<p>The migratory swifts arrive on a precise schedule in the Holy Land in late winter, and immense flocks fill the cities with their cries. Thus the reference in <a href="?bref=Jer.8.7">Jeremiah 8:7</a> to swallows, which are largely permanent residents, is probably to swifts.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Swallow">Swallow (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Vulture">Vulture</p>
<p class="fl">Subfamily (Aegypiinae) of the hawk family (Accipitridae). Each of the four species of Old World vultures is found in the Holy Land: the Egyptian, griffon, black, and bearded vulture (the bearded vulture is also known as the lammergeier). These birds range in size from the 24-inch (61-centimeters) Egyptian vulture to the huge bearded vulture, largest of all flying birds in the Holy Land.</p>
<p>Most vultures are brown or black, having a short neck and a short, hooked bill with which they tear the dead animal flesh of which they are fond. All vultures, except the bearded, have bare or down-covered heads and necks, enabling these scavengers to penetrate deep into a carcass without spoiling the plumage. Excellent eyesight enables a vulture to locate a carcass from a lofty soaring position. Considering the decayed condition of most of its food, a vulture’s poor sense of smell may be a fortunate limitation. Vultures nest in any convenient place; both parents care for the young.</p>
<p>The Hebrew word usually translated “eagle” in the OT may have been a general term for all large birds of prey, including vultures. Thus many of the passages about eagles may refer to either the eagle or the vulture (cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.11.13">Lv 11:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.12">Dt 14:12</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span> mg). Such passages include references to nesting habits (<a href="?bref=Job.39.27-28">Jb 39:27-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.49.16">Jer 49:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Obad.1.4">Ob 1:4</a>), care for fledglings (<a href="?bref=Deut.32.11">Dt 32:11</a>), powers of flight (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.4">Ex 19:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.28.49">Dt 28:49</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.9.26">Jb 9:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.4.19">Lam 4:19</a>), and extremely high soaring altitude (<a href="?bref=Pr.23.5">Prv 23:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.30.19">30:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.31">Is 40:31</a>). Despite variations among translations, the vulture clearly belongs in the list of unclean birds because of its foul diet (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.13,18">Lv 11:13, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.12,17">Dt 14:12, 17</a>).</p>
<p>Several references to the eagle in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> have been changed to “vulture” in modern translations. The change seems appropriate in the references to the vulture as a sign of present or impending doom (<a href="?bref=Lam.4.19">Lam 4:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.8.1">Hos 8:1</a>). Likewise the eye-plucking bird of <a href="?bref=Pr.30.17">Proverbs 30:17</a> is probably a vulture. The phrase “bald as the eagle” (<a href="?bref=Mic.1.16">Mi 1:16</a>) clearly should read “bald as the vulture,” since there are no bald eagles in Israel and most vultures are bald. Since the vulture, like the eagle, was a symbol of sovereignty and domination in the ancient Near East, some gods were represented as vultures. Thus Ezekiel’s comparison of the kings of Babylon and Egypt to eagles may be conceived alternatively as comparisons to vultures (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.3,7">Ez 17:3, 7</a>). Jesus’ reference to the eagles congregating around corpses at the end times (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.28">Mt 24:28</a>) should also be revised to vultures, since eagles are usually solitary eaters, whereas vultures generally flock together around carrion.</p>
<p>Several <span class="sc">kjv</span> references to vultures are usually translated “kite” or “falcon” in modern translations (cf. various versions of <a href="?bref=Lev.11.14">Lv 11:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.13">Dt 14:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.28.7">Jb 28:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.15">Is 34:15</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Eagle">Eagle</a>; <a href="#KestrelorFalcon">Kestrel</a>; <a href="#KiteorGlede">Kite</a>; <a href="#Lammergeier">Lammergeier</a>; <a href="#VultureBlackorOsprey">Vulture, Black, or Osprey</a>; <a href="#VultureEgyptian">Vulture, Egyptian</a>; <a href="#VultureGriffon">Vulture, Griffon</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="VultureBlackorOsprey">Vulture, Black, or Osprey</p>
<p class="fl">Diurnal flesh eater, a little over three feet (.9 meter) long with a wingspread of over three yards (2.7 meters). The feathers of the black or osprey vulture (<span class="ital">Aegypius monachus</span>) are black and the head and upper part of the neck are bald like those of other carrion eaters. It nests in the Jordan River valley and seems to have been abundant in biblical times. Today it is quite rare. The black vulture is probably the osprey of <a href="?bref=Lev.11.13">Leviticus 11:13</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.14.12">Deuteronomy 14:12</a>.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Vulture">Vulture (above)</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="OspreyOrFishhawk"/>
<p class="h3" id="VultureEgyptian">Vulture, Egyptian</p>
<p class="fl">Also known as the gier eagle or as pharaoh’s hen. The plumage of the Egyptian vulture (<span class="ital">Neophron percnopterus</span>) is basically white with a naked head and yellow neck. The Egyptian vulture breaks bones left by other vultures. Its flight is slow and easy, and its voice is a croak. Measuring about 24 inches (61 centimeters) in length, it is the smallest of all the carrion-eating birds found in the Holy Land. It may be referred to in the list of unclean birds (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.18">Lv 11:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.17">Dt 14:17</a>, “gier eagle,” <span class="sc">kjv</span>; “carrion vulture,” <span class="sc">rsv</span>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Vulture_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Vulture (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="VultureGriffon">Vulture, Griffon</p>
<p class="fl">One of the largest flying birds in the Holy Land <span class="ital">(Gyps fulvus).</span> Until a generation ago, the griffon vulture was one of the most common birds in the Holy Land. Today it is on the verge of extinction. Many have been killed by eating poisonous bait meant for foxes and jackals. In addition, its reproduction is limited; the female lays only one or two eggs a year.</p>
<p>The griffon vulture measures about four feet (121.9 centimeters) in length and up to ten feet (3 meters) between wing tips. Its beak is extremely strong, and its short toes are fitted with blunt talons. It is a light-brown bird with a pale yellow head and neck that are almost bare, being covered only with a very fine down.</p>
<p>The griffon vulture feeds mostly on carrion, but also on locusts and small tortoises. It is able to go without food for several days with no ill effects, but when it does break its fast, it gorges itself. It is found especially in the region of the Sea of Galilee. Most biblical references to the vulture are likely to be to the griffon vulture.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Eagle">Eagle</a>; <a href="#Vulture">Vulture (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h3" id="WaterHen">Water Hen</p>
<p class="fl">Small water bird of the rail family. The water hen listed among unclean birds (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.18">Lv 11:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.16">Dt 14:16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span> only) may be the biblical bird most difficult to identify. Several alternatives have been suggested, including the swan (<span class="sc">kjv</span>), one of the owls (<span class="sc">nasb</span>, <span class="sc">neb</span>), or the marsh hen (<span class="sc">tlb</span>). Most scholars rule out the swan, since it is a vegetarian bird and thus should not be considered unclean. An owl remains a possibility.</p>
<p>The marsh hen is a rail, several species of which inhabit Israel. One of those species is the purple gallinule <span class="ital">(Porphyrio porphyrio).</span> Rails are very thin birds varying from 6 to 20 inches (15 to 51 centimeters) in length. They live in marshes, where they eat a great variety of animal and vegetable matter, thus making them a candidate for inclusion in the Mosaic lists of unclean animals.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>