<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Blindness">
  <title>Blindness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BLINDNESS</p>
<p class="fl">Condition of lacking the ability to see. Physical blindness was common in the ancient Near East and is still prevalent among the poor and tribal peoples lacking the benefits of modern medicine.</p>
<p>Medical causes of blindness are not specified in the Bible, but poor personal hygiene and unsanitary living conditions were undoubtedly contributing factors. Newborn babies were especially susceptible. Much blindness from birth (<a href="?bref=John.9.1-3">Jn 9:1-3</a>) was probably gonorrhea of the eyes. In the birth process germs from the mother passed to the eyes of the infant, where they found an ideal medium for growth. Within three days inflammation, pus and swelling would be evident. In such cases, primitive treatment could not prevent some permanent or even total damage to the eye. Modern medical practice treats all newborn babies with antiseptic eyedrops; but such treatment is not always available to the poor, or is rejected by them in parts of the Middle East today. Babies and young children have also been threatened by infectious ophthalmia. Carried by flies, that disease causes heavy crusting, droopy eyelids, loss of eyelashes, and eventually clouding of the cornea, often leading to total blindness. In parts of the world one may still see a mother (because of folk superstition) permitting flies to swarm continuously on her baby’s face even as she holds the infant in her lap. Blindness among adults might be due to side effects from illnesses such as malaria, long exposure to sandstorms and sun glare in the desert, accidents, punishment (as with Samson, <a href="?bref=Judg.16.21">Jgs 16:21</a>), or old age (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.1">Gn 27:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.4.15">1 Sm 4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.4">1 Kgs 14:4</a>).</p>
<p>The OT demanded special consideration for the blind (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.14">Lv 19:14</a>) and imposed punishment for misleading a blind person (<a href="?bref=Deut.27.18">Dt 27:18</a>). A blind man, considered defective, was not permitted to serve as a priest (<a href="?bref=Lev.21.18">Lv 21:18</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus’ healing ministry brought sight to the blind in fulfillment of prophecy (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.18">Lk 4:18</a>). His ability to restore vision was one of the proofs given to John the Baptist that Jesus was the Messiah (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.5">Mt 11:5</a>). Jesus healed two blind men in Galilee (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.27-30">9:27-30</a>), one blind man in Bethsaida (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.22-26">Mk 8:22-26</a>), a man blind from birth in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=John.9.1-41">Jn 9</a>), and a blind beggar named Bartimaeus and his friend at Jericho (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.46-52">Mk 10:46-52</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.20.30-34">Mt 20:30-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.18.35-43">Lk 18:35-43</a>). At times Jesus commanded immediate restoration (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.52">Mk 10:52</a>). On other occasions he used “means” such as clay and water (<a href="?bref=John.9.6-11">Jn 9:6-11</a>) or his own saliva (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.23">Mk 8:23</a>). The apostle Paul was blinded at his conversion and received a miraculous cure in the presence of Ananias (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.1-9,18">Acts 9:1-9, 18</a>). Paul later afflicted a sorcerer, Elymas, with temporary blindness for opposing his ministry on the island of Cyprus (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.11">13:11</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=MedicineandMedicalPractice_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Medicine and Medical Practice</a>; <a href="?item=Disease_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Disease</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="SpiritualBlindness"/>
  </body>
</item>