<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Bloodguilt">
  <title>Bloodguilt*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BLOODGUILT*</p>
<p class="fl">Term used in some English Bibles to translate a Hebrew word meaning “blood” or “bloods” (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.2-3">Ex 22:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.17.4">Lv 17:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.25.26,33">1 Sm 25:26, 33</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.12.14">Hos 12:14</a>). The translation “bloodguiltiness” occurs only in <a href="?bref=Ps.51.14">Psalm 51:14</a>. The plural form almost invariably means the shedding of blood, but the singular can mean blood itself, bloodshed, or the guilt incurred by bloodshed (i.e., by killing). The idea that killing was punishable by death pervades the Bible; killing was generally done by literally shedding another’s blood.</p>
<p>The first category of bloodshed resulting in bloodguilt was deliberate homicide, murder “in cold blood,” as moderns say, or of “innocent blood,” as the OT says (<a href="?bref=Jon.1.14">Jon 1:14</a>). Several passages define the shedding of innocent blood and its punishment (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.6">Gn 9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.19.11-13">Dt 19:11-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.4">2 Kgs 24:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.6">Ez 33:6</a>). The Bible prohibits any ransom for a murderer (<a href="?bref=Num.35.31">Nm 35:31</a>).</p>
<p>Another category was accidental homicide (<a href="?bref=Num.35.9-28">Nm 35:9-28</a>, <a href="?bref=Deut.19.4-10">Dt 19:4-10</a>). After an accidental killing, the “avenger of blood” might retaliate if he caught the offender outside a city of refuge. If the murderer was unknown, the town nearest the discovered corpse assumed the guilt; <a href="?bref=Deut.21.1-9">Deuteronomy 21:1-9</a> prescribes a ceremony for removing such guilt.</p>
<p>In ancient Israel it was possible to shed the blood of an animal and incur bloodguilt (<a href="?bref=Lev.17.3-4,10-11">Lv 17:3-4, 10-11</a>). An animal that was legally guilty of bloodshed was to be stoned (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.28-29">Ex 21:28-29</a>). Exceptions to bloodguilt were made in the case of self-defense (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.2">22:2</a>), capital punishment (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.9-16">Lv 20:9-16</a>), and war (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.5-6">1 Kgs 2:5-6</a>). Frequently the prophets would use the Hebrew word for “bloods” or “blood” to speak of the whole nation’s guilt (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.15">Is 1:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.4.4">4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.7.23">Ez 7:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.9.9">9:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.1.4">Hos 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.4.2">4:2</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>; <a href="?bref=Mic.3.10">Mi 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.2.8,12,17">Hb 2:8, 12, 17</a>; and many others). Other crimes beside bloodshed could bring on a death sentence (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.9-16">Lv 20:9-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.18.10-13">Ez 18:10-13</a>). Such crimes included honoring pagan deities, worshiping idols, adultery, robbery, oppressing the poor, breach of promise, and usury.</p>
<p>From the beginning (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.10-12">Gn 4:10-12</a>), through the Prophets (<a href="?bref=Isa.26.21">Is 26:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.24.6-9">Ez 24:6-9</a>), and into the NT (<a href="?bref=Rev.6.10">Rv 6:10</a>), the Bible supports the idea that God will avenge wrongs and punish those guilty of bloodshed.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CitiesofRefuge_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cities of Refuge</a>; <a href="?item=CriminalLawandPunishment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Criminal Law and Punishment</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>