<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Body">
  <title>Body</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BODY</p>
<p class="fl">Term used biblically in several different ways, including certain metaphorical or theological expressions. Many of the biblical references illustrate special features of Hebrew thought about human life.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The OT writers used a number of Hebrew words translated “body” in English versions, mostly with reference to physical life. The body suffers; it is plagued with illness or is injured. Sometimes it is dead, that is, a corpse or carcass. Reference is even made to the “bodies” of spiritual beings—of the cherubim in Ezekiel’s vision (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.11">Ez 1:11</a>) and of an angel (<a href="?bref=Dan.10.6">Dn 10:6</a>). Jeremiah spoke of the bodies of pagan gods, referring to their images in the form of idols (<a href="?bref=Jer.10.1-16">Jer 10:1-16</a>). Such usages indicate that the Hebrews thought of all beings, whether heavenly or earthly, as embodied.</p>
<p>At times, the word “body” is close to the meaning of “flesh,” and frequently the same Hebrew word lies behind both terms. “Body” is man in his total physical experience. “Flesh” is generally used to refer to the sinfulness or creatureliness of man.</p>
<p>Human beings have bodies and a bodily existence; each person also has a spirit and a spiritual dimension in life. But in Scripture the two are not set over against each other or viewed as separate “parts” of man. The body is not seen as a hindrance to the soul (as in much Greek thought). Not until the intertestamental period did Jewish writers begin to speak of the body as evil or as something set over against the soul.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Though “body” is used in the NT in the same ways as in the OT, the concept is given new significance. The body of Jesus (i.e., his corpse) was taken down from the cross (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.43">Mk 15:43</a>). A body could experience illness and healing (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.29">5:29</a>) and needed to be clothed (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.16">Jas 2:16</a>); yet the body (i.e., physical life) is more than clothing (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.25">Mt 6:25</a>). Jesus said not to fear those who kill the body but cannot kill the soul; rather, fear those who can destroy both soul and body in hell (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.28">10:28</a>).</p>
<p>At the Lord’s Supper Jesus said with reference to the bread, “This is my body,” and then added—with the cup in his hand—“This is my blood” (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.22,24">Mk 14:22, 24</a>). Those terms from the OT sacrificial system were intended to underscore the sacrificial significance of Jesus’ death. Under both the old and new covenants, a real, physical life was offered in death for the sake of the “covenant people.”</p>
<p>The apostle Paul made the term “body” a fundamental reference in the understanding of Christian experience. Most of the NT references to “body” are in his letters.</p>
<p class="h3">The Sinful Body</p>
<p class="fl">In <a href="?bref=Rom.6.6">Romans 6:6</a> Paul spoke of the destruction of the “sinful body.” The phrase did not mean that the body itself is sinful, as though sin is in some way tied to physical matter. Neither did it refer to some entity, sin, thought to dwell within human nature. Nor did it personify sin. Rather, the phrase referred to the physical life of human beings—life on earth—which is dominated by sin’s influence. In Christian conversion Paul saw that familiar pattern of human experience being destroyed. To link sin with the body is only to recognize that human beings in their earthly life (“life in the body”) are pervasively sinful. After describing the awful conflict in human experience, Paul cried out, “Who will deliver me from this body of death?” (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.24">Rom 7:24</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Human life, “spoiled” by sin and its consequences at every point, requires Christ’s redemption (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.25-8.4">7:25–8:4</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Body of the Believer</p>
<p class="fl">In conversion, believers are said by Paul to experience not only the “saving of the soul” but also the transformation of present life. They have died to sin and have been freed from sin’s bondage. Paul therefore called for holiness of life “in the flesh.” “Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal bodies, to make you obey their passions” (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.12">Rom 6:12</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Righteousness, not sin, is to govern a Christian’s physical experience. The social and personal lives of believers are to be characterized by holiness. Believers are in the world (<a href="?bref=John.17.11">Jn 17:11</a>) and are to live for God in the world (i.e., in their bodily existence); they are not to be indifferent to the world.</p>
<p>Physical, earthly life thus takes on new significance. Paul told Christians to present their bodies as a living sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.1">Rom 12:1</a>). Each individual human life is to be a “living sacrifice” to God. Far from deprecating earthly existence, Paul saw that in Christ it had new potential. The reason is that the Holy Spirit is found there. “Your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit within you, which you have from God” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.19">1 Cor 6:19</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). That affirmation is not to be read materialistically, as though the Spirit takes up residence in certain tissues; “body” means one’s whole physical, earthly existence.</p>
<p>Paul also anticipated an ultimate transformation of life in the body through Christ. He spoke of the “redemption of our bodies” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.23">Rom 8:23</a>) and of the transformation of “our lowly bodies to be like his glorious body” (<a href="?bref=Phil.3.21">Phil 3:21</a>). The Bible, although it has a realistic view of human sin and physical deterioration, does not share the pessimism of worldviews that seek escape from the world.</p>
<p class="h3">The Resurrection Body</p>
<p class="fl">The possible separation of body and soul did not occur to the Hebrew mind. Biblically, life beyond death is not bodiless but an existence for which a “new body” is prepared. Though Paul raised many questions in <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.35-57">1 Corinthians 15:35-57</a>, it is clear that he saw continuity between the earthly body and the resurrection body. “It is sown a physical body, it is raised a spiritual body” (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.44">44</a>). That expression may be derived in large part from the experience of Jesus, whose dead body was not only brought to life but also transformed so that it was not bound by earth. His resurrection body was derived from the earthly. But Paul was sure that in the promised resurrection, life would return to the body without its present limitations and with new manifestations. Death, said Paul, is thereby “swallowed up in victory” (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.54">54</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Resurrection_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Resurrection</a>; <a href="?item=BodyofChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Body of Christ</a>; <a href="?item=Church_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Church</a>; <a href="?item=Man_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Man</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>