<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BookoftheCovenant">
  <title>Book of the Covenant</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BOOK OF THE COVENANT</p>
<p class="fl">Term occurring in two OT contexts. It describes, first, a document read by Moses to the people of Israel at Mt Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.7">Ex 24:7</a>), and second, a document discovered in the temple by Hilkiah the priest at the time of King Josiah’s program of repairing the temple (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.2,21">2 Kgs 23:2, 21</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.30">2 Chr 34:30</a>). The term “covenant” refers to the covenant laws that God made with his people Israel in the time of Moses. The Hebrew term “book” means any written document, whether written on clay or stone tablets or on parchment scrolls. Ancient covenants were often in written form. The main problem in understanding the two references to “book of the covenant” is in trying to determine the concepts of those particular documents.</p>
<p>The book read at Mt Sinai has been taken to refer either to the Ten Commandments or to the whole section of <a href="?bref=Exod.20.1-23.32">Exodus 20 to 23</a>, minus the narrative parts. Since the people responded, “All that the Lord has spoken we will do,” it was evidently legal in its thrust, but it seems impossible to define its contents more precisely than that. The fact that Moses wrote the book (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.4">Ex 24:4</a>) need not exclude the Ten Commandments, which are explicitly stated to have been written by God (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.15-16">32:15-16</a>). Moses could also have written them down, perhaps in a preliminary stage (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.25">19:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.20.1">20:1</a>).</p>
<p>The content of the “book of the covenant” read by King Josiah to the people of Judah is uncertain. Some scholars have tried to reconstruct its contents on the basis of Josiah’s reforms, concluding that those reforms were similar to principles taught in the book of Deuteronomy. That approach has several weaknesses. First, some of the reforms are nowhere mentioned in the Law (e.g., burning the chariots of the sun—<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.11">2 Kgs 23:11</a>) and would have to represent inferences Josiah derived from the Law. It becomes unclear how much of his reform was based on explicit passages in the Book of the Covenant and how much on inferences. Second, the account in <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.30-33">2 Chronicles 34:30-33</a> indicates that much of the reform took place <span class="ital">before</span> discovery of the Book of the Covenant.</p>
<p>On the other hand, explicit statements in 2 Kings indicate that some of the reforms were based on the Book of the Covenant. Thus the book must have contained instructions on the Passover (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.21">2 Kgs 23:21</a>). It probably dealt with mediums, wizards, and other idolatrous practices, unless that reform was an inference suggested by the wording. In addition, the book evidently contained warnings of the destruction God would bring if his words were not followed (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.16-19">22:16-19</a>). Those expressions probably indicate that Josiah’s Book of the Covenant was larger than <a href="?bref=Exod.21.1-23.33">Exodus 21–23</a>. In the older book, the Passover is mentioned only as the Feast of Unleavened Bread (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.15">Ex 23:15</a>). <a href="?bref=Exod.22.18">Exodus 22:18</a> might possibly give a basis for Josiah’s action against wizards. But in <a href="?bref=Exod.21.1-23.33">Exodus 21–23</a> no statement of judgment for disobedience is sufficient to explain the wording of <a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.16-19">2 Kings 22:16-19</a>; the closest thing to it is <a href="?bref=Exod.23.33">Exodus 23:33</a>.</p>
<p>Finally, the fact that Josiah’s Book of the Covenant is also called the Book of the Law (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.8">2 Kgs 22:8</a>) suggests that numerous references to the Book of the Law in the OT should also be understood as referring to the Book of the Covenant.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ExodusBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Exodus, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=LawBiblicalConceptof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Law, Biblical Concept of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>