<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BookofLife">
  <title>Book of Life</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BOOK OF LIFE</p>
<p class="fl">Term used to refer to a heavenly record. The phrase appears seven times in the NT: <a href="?bref=Phil.4.3">Philippians 4:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.3.5">Revelation 3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.13.8">13:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.8">17:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.20.12,15">20:12, 15</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.27">21:27</a>. The Christian understanding of the phrase, however, is rooted in the OT. Passages such as <a href="?bref=Exod.32.32">Exodus 32:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.87.6">Psalm 87:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.7.10">Daniel 7:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.12.1">12:1</a>; and <a href="?bref=Mal.3.16">Malachi 3:16</a> imply or affirm a record kept by God. God is seen as keeping account of his people’s faithfulness and disobedience—and possibly that of other nations as well (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.87.6">Ps 87:6</a>). <a href="?bref=Ps.69.28">Psalm 69:28</a> uses the phrase “book of the living”; parallel poetic lines refer to physical living.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Dan.7.10">Daniel 7:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.12.1">12:1</a>; and <a href="?bref=Mal.3.16">Malachi 3:16</a> references are linked with descriptions of final judgment and events of the end times. Names and deeds from the divine records are evidence set before a judge. <a href="?bref=Luke.10.20">Luke 10:20</a> and <a href="?bref=Heb.12.23">Hebrews 12:23</a> reflect similar thought; no concrete mention of a “book” is made but a heavenly record is assumed. In <a href="?bref=Phil.4.3">Philippians 4:3</a> Paul uses “Book of Life” to encourage his fellow workers in a lively hope for the future.</p>
<p>“Book of Life” in the book of Revelation refers to a heavenly record with the names of persecuted Christians who remain faithful. It is used first in the letter to Sardis (<a href="?bref=Rev.3.5">3:5</a>) where the risen Lord, identified as “the Lamb” is keeper of the book (<a href="?bref=Rev.13.8">13:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.7">21:7</a>). If a person’s name is found in the book, admittance is granted to new Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Rev.20.15">20:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.27">21:27</a>). If one’s name is not written there, the judgment is final destruction. Absolute confidence in God’s care for his own is affirmed by the words “written before the foundation of the world” (<a href="?bref=Rev.13.8">13:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.8">17:8</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BookofRemembrance_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Book of Remembrance</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>