<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Branch">
  <title>Branch</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BRANCH</p>
<p class="fl">Literally, a shoot or sprout from a tree or bush; figuratively, a messianic or other spiritual metaphor. It is used for the three sets of arms that come off the main shaft of the golden lampstand in the tabernacle (e.g., <a href="?bref=Exod.25.31-36">Ex 25:31-36</a>) and for the palm fronds from which booths were constructed for the ancient Jewish Feast of Tabernacles (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.40-43">Lv 23:40-43</a>).</p>
<p>Metaphorically, the expression is found in passages where Israel is described as an olive tree (<a href="?bref=Hos.14.6">Hos 14:6</a>), a cedar (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.23">Ez 17:23</a>), and a vine (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.6">Ez 17:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.80.8-11">Ps 80:8-11</a>). “Branch,” with its implication of new growth, can signify prosperity (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.22">Gn 49:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.8.16">Jb 8:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.80.8-11">Ps 80:8-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.36.8">Ez 36:8</a>). Branches can be cut or broken off; hence, the word may depict judgment (<a href="?bref=Job.18.16">Jb 18:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.9.14">Is 9:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.11.16">Jer 11:16</a>). Such passages speak of withering, being cut, or being burned; Jesus combined all three ideas into one metaphor (<a href="?bref=John.15.6">Jn 15:6</a>). In a similar way, the apostle Paul wrote that the Jews who didn’t believe would be broken off (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.19-21">Rom 11:19-21</a>).</p>
<p>The major use of such symbolism refers to the Davidic Messiah. Although that use of “branch” actually stems from the prophetic period, its roots go much farther back. The concept was used with reference to an influential figure, such as a king’s personal servant (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.9-13">Gn 40:9-13</a>), the patriarch Joseph (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.22">49:22</a>), Job (<a href="?bref=Job.29.19">Jb 29:19</a>), or the Assyrian king Nebuchadnezzar (<a href="?bref=Dan.4.12">Dn 4:12</a>). Passages such as <a href="?bref=2Sam.23.4">2 Samuel 23:4</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.132.17">Psalm 132:17</a> speak of the Davidic line as “growing” or “sprouting forth” (the literal meaning of the Hebrew verbs). Finally, images of agricultural prosperity were used as promised blessings of the messianic age (cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.26.1-46">Lv 26</a> with the prophetic passages on previous page). It is understandable how the term “branch” could become a technical designation for the Messiah, as is described above.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="TheBranchASymbolForTheMessiah"/>
  </body>
</item>