<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BrideofChrist">
  <title>Bride of Christ*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BRIDE OF CHRIST*</p>
<p class="fl">One of the NT metaphors for the church. In it Christ is pictured as a husband, and the church as his bride.</p>
<p>Addressing the church at Corinth, the apostle Paul referred to himself as the one who gave the church to Christ, presenting her as a pure bride to her one husband (<a href="?bref=2Cor.11.2-3">2 Cor 11:2-3</a>). In ancient Near Eastern culture the father gave his daughter in marriage to the bridegroom, assuring him of her purity. To Paul, understanding himself as the church’s spiritual father (<a href="?bref=1Cor.4.15">1 Cor 4:15</a>), the thought of the church as his daughter sprang readily to mind. To be Christ’s pure bride requires the church to have pure and simple devotion. Like a concerned father, Paul was worried that the young bride (the church) might commit adultery by her willingness to accept “another Jesus,” “another Spirit,” or “a different gospel” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.11.4">2 Cor 11:4</a>). As between marriage partners, the relation between the church and Christ is governed by a covenant of mutual faithfulness. Disloyalty shatters the covenant.</p>
<p>The OT furnished Paul a rich background for that image of the church. God’s covenant with Israel was commonly pictured as a marriage pledge, with Israel as God’s bride. Through the prophet Jeremiah, the Lord said to Israel: “I remember the devotion of your youth, your love as a bride” (<a href="?bref=Jer.2.2">Jer 2:2</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). He went on to lament the fact that Israel had been faithless; by going after other gods, she had actually prostituted herself and become an adulteress (<a href="?bref=Jer.3.6-9,20">Jer 3:6-9, 20</a>).</p>
<p>The theme of Israel’s desertion of her lover (God) was explicitly treated in <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.1-63">Ezekiel 16</a> and in Hosea. The terms “harlotry” and “whoredom” were used to connote disloyalty to Yahweh and allegiance to other gods. Thus, adultery and idolatry became synonymous. Through his own struggles with a faithless wife, the prophet Hosea experienced God’s agony over his bride Israel and his longing for her to return. Hosea was given a vision of a future day in which God would betroth his people to him forever in steadfast love and faithfulness (<a href="?bref=Hos.2.19-20">Hos 2:19-20</a>). That vision may have enabled Paul to transfer the image of Israel as God’s bride to the church as the bride of Christ.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Eph.5.22-33">Ephesians 5:22-33</a>, the relationship between Christ and his church is compared to the relationship between a husband and wife. The image is taken from the common understanding of the husband-wife relationship in that part of the world. The church’s submission to Christ is compared with the wife’s submission to the husband, but the stress of the passage is on the role of the husband: he is to love her as Christ loved the church and gave himself up for her. Christ relates to the whole church on the basis of self-sacrificial love. Just as a husband is joined to his wife, with a mutual interdependence so intimate that they become one, so Christ and his church become one body. As the man’s love for his wife intends her wholeness, so Christ’s love of the church intends her completeness.</p>
<p>A variation on the theme is found in John the Baptist’s testimony to Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.3.29">Jn 3:29</a>). John saw himself as “the Bridegroom’s friend” who, according to Jewish custom, takes care of the wedding arrangements. The Messiah is identified with the bridegroom to whom the bride (his messianic community) belongs and who comes to claim that bride.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Rev.19.1-21">Revelation 19</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-27">21</a> the metaphor of the church as the Messiah’s bride is further developed. The vision in <a href="?bref=Rev.19.7-8">Revelation 19:7-8</a> announces the marriage of the Lamb (Christ) to the bride (church). In <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-27">Revelation 21</a> the vision depicts the new Jerusalem coming down from heaven, “prepared as a bride adorned for her husband” (v <a href="?bref=Rev.21.2">2</a>). Then the seer is invited to behold “the Bride, the wife of the Lamb” (v <a href="?bref=Rev.21.9">9</a>) and to see the Holy City “coming down out of heaven from God” (v <a href="?bref=Rev.21.10">10</a>). The new Jerusalem is identified as the people of God, the bride of Christ, among whom and with whom God will be present forever.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Church_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Church</a>; <a href="?item=JerusalemNew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jerusalem, New</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>