<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BrothersofJesus">
  <title>Brothers of Jesus*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BROTHERS OF JESUS*</p>
<p class="fl">James, Joses (or Joseph), Simon, and Judas, identified in the NT as members of Jesus’ own family (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.55">Mt 13:55</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>). They are described as visiting Jesus with Mary, his mother (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.47-50">Mt 12:47-50</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.34-35">Mk 3:34-35</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.19-21">Lk 8:19-21</a>), and hearing Jesus’ statement that all who did the will of God were brother, sister, and mother to him.</p>
<p>They were well enough known in Nazareth that when Jesus returned to preach there, the people said, “Is not this the carpenter, the son of Mary and brother of James and Joses and Judas and Simon, and are not his sisters here with us?” (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). In Matthew’s Gospel the order of the names of the last two brothers is reversed (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.55">Mt 13:55</a>). When Jesus and his disciples went to Capernaum, they were accompanied by Mary and his brothers (<a href="?bref=John.2.12">Jn 2:12</a>). Just before the Feast of Tabernacles the brothers visited Jesus to persuade him to go to Jerusalem for the festival. Although they were skeptical about his miracles, they said he should perform his feats in public to gain recognition (<a href="?bref=John.7.4">Jn 7:4</a>). Jesus acknowledged opposition from within his family when he said, “A prophet is honored everywhere except in his own hometown and among his own family” (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.57">Mt 13:57</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). His brothers or other friends from home thought him to be losing touch with reality when crowds were first attracted to him (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.21">Mk 3:21</a>).</p>
<p>In spite of their earlier skepticism, however, the brothers became active members of the Jerusalem church during its earliest days. They are mentioned as being frequently at prayer in an upper room with Mary, showing a sharp reversal from their earlier lack of faith (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.14">Acts 1:14</a>). One of the resurrection appearances was made to James (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.7">1 Cor 15:7</a>). On Paul’s return to Jerusalem after his conversion, he met Peter and James, “the Lord’s brother,” but not the other apostles (<a href="?bref=Gal.1.19">Gal 1:19</a>). When the apostle Peter was released from prison, he went to the home of Mary the mother of John Mark, and despite the excitement of the occasion, he immediately asked the group to “tell this to James and to the brethren” (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.17">Acts 12:17</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). A number of references in Acts show James as a strong, respected leader of the Jerusalem church (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.13-21">Acts 15:13-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.21.18">21:18</a>). In the council at Jerusalem, he expressed a strong opinion on the acceptance of Gentiles into the church; he was later visited by Paul, who told him about his ministry and the many conversions among the Gentiles. Although James is mentioned more often by name, all the brothers seem to have been well respected at that time. Thus, their actions were used as an example by Paul when he argued that it would be appropriate for him also to have a wife accompany him on his journeys, as Jesus’ brothers did (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.5">1 Cor 9:5</a>).</p>
<p>The author of the Epistle of James is generally assumed to be the Lord’s brother, although he does not identify himself specifically that way (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.1">1:1</a>). It seems clear, though, that the author wrote as a recognized leader in the church; hence, to identify him as the Lord’s brother seems logical. The author of the Epistle of Jude identifies himself as the brother of James. The reference would most logically be to James, the leader mentioned in Acts and probably the author of the other epistle. The author thus seems to be the Judas named as the brother of the Lord in the Gospels (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.55">Mt 13:55</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>).</p>
<p>Throughout the NT the group of the 12 apostles is consistently distinguished from the brothers of the Lord. Luke named the apostles and then said, “All these with one accord devoted themselves to prayer, together with the women and Mary the mother of Jesus, and with his brothers” (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.13-14">Acts 1:13-14</a>). The apostle Paul pointed to the brothers of the Lord as a group separate from the apostles (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.5">1 Cor 9:5</a>); each mention of them in the Gospels describes them as family members and distinct from the disciples.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=JamesPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">James (Person) #1</a>; <a href="?item=Joseph_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Joseph #7</a>; <a href="?item=JudePerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jude (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=Mary_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mary #1</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="BrothersStepbrothersOrCousins"/>
  </body>
</item>