<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BrothersandSisters">
  <title>Brothers (and Sisters)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BROTHERS (<span class="lc">and Sisters</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Designation of those in the household of God. Good evidence exists that Jews at the time of Jesus frequently referred to themselves as brothers (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.29,37">Acts 2:29, 37</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.2">7:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.22.5">22:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.28.21">28:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.9.3">Rom 9:3</a>). From the beginning it seemed natural for Jewish Christians to call each other “brothers” (that is, “siblings”—the term included both male and female; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.15-16">Acts 1:15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.30">9:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.1">11:1</a>). Members of gentile religious communities also called each other brothers, so the name found a home in the gentile churches as well (<a href="?bref=Acts.17.14">Acts 17:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.13">Rom 1:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.1,10">1 Cor 1:1, 10</a>; plus dozens of other places in Paul’s letters to gentile churches). In fact, along with “disciple” (in Acts) and “saint” (always plural in the writings of Paul and the book of Revelation), it was one of the most popular names for Christians and the only one used in James and 1 John.</p>
<p>Each Christian was called “brother,” and the Christians collectively were “the brothers.” The name stressed the intimacy of the Christian community. That is, the relationship of believers to one another was as close as that of blood kin (closer, in fact—<a href="?bref=Mark.10.23-31">Mk 10:23-31</a>). In 1 John and James the name underlines the claim that poorer Christians have upon those better off (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.15">Jas 2:15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.10-18">1 Jn 3:10-18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.20-21">4:20-21</a>). It also points to equality among members of the Christian community.</p>
  </body>
</item>