<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hand">
  <title>Hand</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HAND</p>
<p class="fl">The terminal part of the forelimb that has the ability to grasp. “Hand” is used hundreds of times in the Bible to describe a physical part of one’s body. It is also used frequently in metaphors or figurative language.</p>
<p>Figuratively, the hand meant power (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.15">Dt 2:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.31.5">Ps 31:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.62">Mk 14:62</a>). Indeed, in <a href="?bref=Josh.8.20">Joshua 8:20</a> “hand to flee” is translated “power to flee” (see <a href="?bref=Ps.76.5">Ps 76:5</a>). Contrarily, limp hands symbolized indecision and weakness (<a href="?bref=Isa.35.3">Is 35:3</a>). Clasping the hands signified friendship (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.15">2 Kgs 10:15</a>). To seat someone on one’s right hand denoted favor (<a href="?bref=Ps.16.11">Pss 16:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.77.10">77:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.110.1">110:1</a>). Clean hands symbolized innocence (<a href="?bref=Ps.26.6">Ps 26:6</a>), while striking hands sealed a bargain (<a href="?bref=Pr.6.1">Prv 6:1</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). Lifting the hand symbolized violence (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.26">1 Kgs 11:26</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The hands were used in supplicatory prayer (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.11">Ex 17:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.9.22">Lv 9:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.15">Is 1:15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.2.8">1 Tm 2:8</a>) and in making vows (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.22">Gn 14:22</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>; <a href="?bref=Gen.24.2">24:2</a>).</p>
<p>Other idiomatic uses of the hands expressed jeopardizing one’s life (<a href="?bref=Judg.12.3">Jgs 12:3</a>), gladness (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.12">2 Kgs 11:12</a>), generosity (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.11">Dt 15:11</a>), grief (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.19">2 Sm 13:19</a>), humility (<a href="?bref=Pr.30.32">Prv 30:32</a>), and undertaking a duty (<a href="?bref=Luke.9.62">Lk 9:62</a>). Manual labor is an expression of man’s dignity and duty (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.28">Eph 4:28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.11">1 Thes 4:11</a>), the marks of which Paul was not ashamed to display (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.34">Acts 20:34</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.12">1 Cor 4:12</a>). Ritual hand washing was obligatory for the priests before fulfilling their office (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.19-21">Ex 30:19-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.40.30-32">40:30-32</a>). The scribes and Pharisees so misapplied this that Jesus ignored ceremonial hand washing (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.1-20">Mt 15:1-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.38">Lk 11:38</a>). Pilate’s hand washing (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.24">Mt 27:24</a>) disclaimed responsibility for, or professed innocence concerning, a wrong that, however, could not be done without his consent.</p>
<p>When Israel went out of Egypt “with an high hand” (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.8">Ex 14:8</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>), the reference is to the hand or help of the Lord. The hand of the Lord represented God’s unstoppable power (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.15">Dt 2:15</a>), judgment (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.11">Acts 13:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.31">Heb 10:31</a>), divine inspiration (<a href="?bref=Ezek.8.1">Ez 8:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.1">37:1</a>), and providential care (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.6">Ezr 7:6</a>; <a href="?bref=John.10.28-29">Jn 10:28-29</a>).</p>
<p>The laying on of hands had a profound significance and occurs frequently in the Bible. Before making a blood sacrifice, the person making the offering, not the priest, laid hands on the victim. The act signified the transference of guilt to, or self-identification with, the victim (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.4">Lv 1:4</a>). Laying on of hands signified appointment to an office, as when Moses commissioned Joshua (<a href="?bref=Num.27.12-23">Nm 27:12-23</a>), the apostles made seven disciples their associates or deputies in the ministry (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.5-6">Acts 6:5-6</a>), and Paul and Barnabas were appointed missionaries and representatives of the church in Antioch (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.3">13:3</a>). By laying on of hands, a person was made an associate with the holder of an office and was admitted to the status of that office (<a href="?bref=1Tim.4.14">1 Tm 4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.1.6">2 Tm 1:6</a>). The act was accompanied by prayer and was, in itself, a form of prayer. As Augustine remarks: “What else is the laying on of hands but a prayer over one?”</p>
<p>The laying on of hands accompanied healing in the ministry of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.5">Mk 6:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.40">Lk 4:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.11-13">13:11-13</a>) and of the disciples (<a href="?bref=Mark.16.18">Mk 16:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.12,17">Acts 9:12, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.28.8">28:8</a>). This expressed the self-identification and sympathy of the healer with and for the sufferer, as well as reinforced the patient’s faith and God’s imparting health to him in answer to prayer.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=RightHand_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Right Hand</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>