<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Head">
  <title>Head</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HEAD</p>
<p class="fl">The uppermost portion of the body, containing the brain, major sense organs, and the mouth. It appears many times in the Bible as a physical description. The Hebrew term for <span class="ital">head</span> is also used figuratively in the Old Testament. Frequently, it designates prominence or authority.</p>
<p>To raise one’s head was considered an act of pride (<a href="?bref=Ps.140.9">Ps 140:9</a>) or honor (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.20">Gn 40:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.3.3">Pss 3:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.27.6">27:6</a>). Bowing the head signified humility (<a href="?bref=Isa.58.5">Is 58:5</a>) or sadness (<a href="?bref=Lam.2.10">Lam 2:10</a>). The Hebrew word is used metaphorically of mountain peaks (<a href="?bref=Gen.8.5">Gn 8:5</a>), the tops of buildings (<a href="?bref=Gen.11.4">Gn 11:4</a>) or trees (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.24">2 Sm 5:24</a>), and river sources (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.10">Gn 2:10</a>). The term was commonly used to designate positions of political, military, or familiar authority. In this sense the “head” exercised control over all those subjected to him (<a href="?bref=Judg.10.18">Jgs 10:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.15.17">1 Sm 15:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.18.43">Ps 18:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.7.8-9">Is 7:8-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.31.7">Jer 31:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.1.11">Hos 1:11</a>). David was called the “keeper of mine head” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) when he served as the bodyguard of Achish (<a href="?bref=1Sam.28.2">1 Sm 28:2</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.9.53">Jgs 9:53</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.68.21">Ps 68:21</a>).</p>
<p>Greek philosophers used the image of the body to represent the universe. The head of this body—called Zeus or Reason—was considered responsible for the creation and sustenance of the remaining members (celestial beings, humans, animals, plants, and inanimate objects). The universe, or “body,” owed its existence to the “head.”</p>
<p>Between 460 <span class="era">BC</span> (the date usually ascribed to the first writings of Hippocrates) and <span class="era">AD</span> 200 (the death of Galen, who developed Hippocrates’ findings), Greek medical science came to understand the head as the seat of intelligence. The body was able to operate efficiently only because the brain was capable of interpreting data received from the body (eyes, ears, skin, and so on), and because it was able to send out appropriate impulses to the various members of the body, based upon the data received. The ability of the brain to interpret and direct made the existence of the body completely dependent upon it.</p>
<p>In the NT, the term refers to the actual human head (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.36">Mt 5:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.6.17">6:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.14.8">14:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.26.7">26:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.27">Mk 6:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.3">14:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.46">Lk 7:46</a>; <a href="?bref=John.13.9">Jn 13:9</a>; <a href="?bref=John.20.7">20:7</a>), to apocalyptic beings (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.14">Rv 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.4.4">4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.12.1">12:1</a>), and to animals (<a href="?bref=Rev.9.7,17,19">Rv 9:7, 17, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.12.3">12:3</a>). Furthermore, it appears in such expressions as “to heap coals of fire upon the head,” meaning to return good for evil (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.20">Rom 12:20</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.5.44">Mt 5:44</a>); to “shear” or “anoint the head” expressing a vow (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.24">Acts 21:24</a>); and “to lay down the head,” meaning to sleep (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.20">Mt 8:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.58">Lk 9:58</a>).</p>
<p>The apostle Paul drew from the OT metaphorical understanding of the term to express the headship of God over Christ, Christ over man, and man over woman (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.3-16">1 Cor 11:3-16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Eph.5.23">Eph 5:23</a>). In the light of these relationships, Paul encouraged women at Corinth to wear veils in worship. The veil gave a woman the authority to worship as an equal with men before God. The term is used again with the meaning “authority” to express the lordship of Christ over the universe (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.21-22">Eph 1:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.2.10">Col 2:10</a>).</p>
<p>Paul used the image of the head and body to express the relationship between Christ and his church (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.15">Eph 4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.23">5:23</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.12-27">1 Cor 12:12-27</a>). In addition to the OT sense, the contributions of medical science in Paul’s day may provide insight into this image, for Christ is not only the dominant ruler over the church but also the dynamic force that provides its direction and unity. The ability of the church to exist and the focal point of its activity are rooted in the work of its “head,” Jesus Christ. In this light, various modern interpreters have argued that headship does not mean “authority” as much as it means “source,” as in the term “fountainhead.” Thus, he who is the head is the source, the supplier. These interpreters see God as being Christ’s supplier, and Christ being the church’s supplier, and man being woman’s supplier.</p>
  </body>
</item>