<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Heaven">
  <title>Heaven</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HEAVEN</p>
<p class="fl">Realm (or realms) designated by a Hebrew term used to represent the sky and air and also heaven. The form of the word in Hebrew is dual (implying two of something). Although this dual form may only represent an ancient device for expressing the plural, it is supposed by some to imply the existence of a lower and an upper heaven—a physical and a spiritual heaven.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The OT writers viewed the physical heavens as a “firmament” appearing as a great arch supported on foundations and pillars (<a href="?bref=2Sam.22.8">2 Sm 22:8</a>) and spread out above the earth, with rain descending through its doors (<a href="?bref=Ps.78.23">Ps 78:23</a>). The keynote of the OT revelation about the physical heavens is set forth in <a href="?bref=Ps.8.1-9">Psalms 8</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.19.1-6">19:1-6</a>. Elsewhere the OT speaks of the atmospheric heavens as the region of the clouds (<a href="?bref=Ps.147.8">Ps 147:8</a>), winds (<a href="?bref=Zech.2.6">Zec 2:6</a>), rain (<a href="?bref=Deut.11.11">Dt 11:11</a>), thunder (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.10">1 Sm 2:10</a>), dew (<a href="?bref=Deut.33.13">Dt 33:13</a>), frost (<a href="?bref=Job.38.29">Jb 38:29</a>), and the abode of birds (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.26,30">Gn 1:26, 30</a>). It is also the place of such destructive forces as hail (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.11">Jos 10:11</a>), fire, and brimstone (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.24">Gn 19:24</a>). The NT continues the idea that the sky is the space where the elements, clouds, and tempests gather (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.2">Mt 16:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.25">Lk 4:25</a>) and birds fly (<a href="?bref=Luke.9.58">Lk 9:58</a>).</p>
<p>In addition to the atmospheric regions, the Hebrew idea of the physical heavens includes stellar space, which ultimately embraces the universe. The heavenly bodies of the stellar heavens were viewed by the Hebrews as inexpressibly glorious manifestations of God’s handiwork without having any power or vitality of their own. These include the sun, moon, planets, and stars, which were but lights in the firmament of the heavens (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.14">Gn 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.15.5">15:5</a>). As such, they were regarded as unworthy of worship because God had, by his own will and grace, made humans superior to them. In fact, the Hebrews were expressly forbidden to worship the stellar bodies (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.4">Ex 20:4</a>), the gods and goddesses who represented them (<a href="?bref=Jer.44.17-25">Jer 44:17-25</a>), or to participate in astrological speculation (<a href="?bref=Isa.47.13">Is 47:13</a>). Hence, this unique theological law differentiated the Hebrews, who viewed the heavenly bodies as made and moved by the will of God, from the superstitious pagans, who worshiped them.</p>
<p>The term “heaven of heavens” (<a href="?bref=Deut.10.14">Dt 10:14</a>; see also <span class="sc">kjv</span> <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.27">1 Kgs 8:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.68.33">Pss 68:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.148.4">148:4</a>) is the literal English rendition of the Hebrew idiom for the superlative “the highest heaven.” Some have thought this the counterpart to Paul’s expression “the third heaven” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.12.2">2 Cor 12:2</a>), which matches the classical Greek conception of three heavens. This notion was then adopted by the Roman Catholic medieval church and in the Latin form of <span class="ital">Coelum Aqueum, Coelum Sidereum,</span> and <span class="ital">Coelum Empyreum.</span> The basic concept followed the Greek view, and it coincides with the OT view of the physical and spiritual heavens as indicated earlier. Those who follow this approach tend to regard this third heaven as the place reached by the souls of the blessed as they pass through the two lower regions of the atmosphere and outer space containing the celestial bodies, and enter into the uttermost reaches of the universe.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The Lord Jesus indicated that heaven is the dwelling place of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.9">Mt 6:9</a>). Jesus, during his earthly ministry, repeatedly claimed that he had come from heaven (<a href="?bref=John.3.13">Jn 3:13</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.33-51">6:33-51</a>); and on at least three occasions utterances from heaven confirmed these claims (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.16-17">Mt 3:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.17.5">17:5</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.28">Jn 12:28</a>). There is where the true tabernacle stands, of which the earthly tabernacle was merely a shadow (cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.8.1-5">Heb 8:1-5</a>). That abode of God was in view when the apostle Paul wrote of “the third heaven” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.12.2">2 Cor 12:2</a>). As such, it is often seen as a synonym for God himself (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.23.22">Mt 23:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.15.18">Lk 15:18</a>).</p>
<p>After Jesus’ ascension, recorded in <a href="?bref=Acts.1.6-11">Acts 1:6-11</a>, two angels reminded the disciples that Jesus would return again from heaven. This was later confirmed by the apostle Paul (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-11">1 Cor 15:1-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.7-16">Eph 4:7-16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.3.16">1 Tm 3:16</a>) and reiterated in the summary of the teachings of the NT known as the Apostles’ Creed. In all, the relationship of Jesus Christ to the heavenly abode of God is inextricably connected in the NT and is inseparable from the gospel message itself. Indeed, it is from the “right hand of God” that Christ forever lives to make intercession for those who have come to him by faith (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.25">Heb 7:25</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.14.62">Mk 14:62</a>).</p>
<p>Paul asserts that the believer’s body will be made conformable to the glorious body of Jesus Christ when Christ returns from heaven (<a href="?bref=Phil.3.20-21">Phil 3:20-21</a>). The believers need such a heavenly body to match their heavenly citizenship. The term “citizenship” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) or “commonwealth” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>) implies a colony of individuals who live in a foreign country while observing the laws of their homeland instead of the land in which they reside (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.22.28">Acts 22:28</a>). The implication for believers is quite clear: They are to live according to the moral and ethical principles of God as revealed from heaven regardless of the standards proclaimed by the world. They have been raised together with Christ and have been instructed to “seek the things that are above, where Christ is, seated at the right hand of God” (<a href="?bref=Col.3.1">Col 3:1</a>). From there Christ has blessed his followers “with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly places” (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.3">Eph 1:3</a>). The expression “in the heavenly places” is unique to the book of Ephesians (see <a href="?bref=Eph.1.3,20">1:3, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.2.6">2:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.3.10">3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.6.12">6:12</a>), suggesting that the blessings of the spiritual world are not relegated to some remote future time or place but can be perceived by faith here and now. That is why believers are said to have been made partakers already in the heavenly calling (<a href="?bref=Heb.3.1">Heb 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.6.4">6:4</a>).</p>
<p>In the meanwhile, believers look forward to a new heaven and a new earth with the new Jerusalem. There will be no tears, sorrow, pain, death, and night there because the Son of God will be there (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-4,27">Rv 21:1-4, 27</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.22.1-5">22:1-5</a>), and in the resurrected state there will be no marrying or giving in marriage (<a href="?bref=Luke.20.27-38">Lk 20:27-38</a>). At least two OT saints, Enoch (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.22-24">Gn 5:22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.5">Heb 11:5</a>) and Elijah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.11">2 Kgs 2:11</a>), were translated directly into the presence of God—into heaven. In addition to Paul’s statement about the third heaven, John was called into heaven (<a href="?bref=Rev.4.1">Rv 4:1</a>), a heaven that is intended to be populated (cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.19.1">19:1</a>). All believers will ultimately dwell in heaven in their resurrection bodies, which they will receive when the Lord comes for them from heaven (<a href="?bref=1Thes.4.16-17">1 Thes 4:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.1-4">Rv 19:1-4</a>). The Lord will also give treasures and rewards at that time (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.12">Mt 5:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.9.25">1 Cor 9:25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.1">2 Cor 5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.4.8">2 Tm 4:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.1.12">Jas 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.4">1 Pt 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.4">5:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.2.10">Rv 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.4.10">4:10</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=AbrahamsBosom_Textbox_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">“Abraham’s Bosom”</a>; <a href="?item=NewHeavensandNewEarth_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New Heavens and New Earth</a>; <a href="?item=Paradise_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paradise</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>