<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HighPlace">
  <title>High Place</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HIGH PLACE</p>
<p class="fl">Phrase commonly translated from the Hebrew bamah, which apparently derived from a word originally meaning “the back (or ridge) of an animal.” Thus it came to refer to a height or hill or a stone burial cairn. Usually it was an elevated worship center, such as the ones referred to in <a href="?bref=Num.33.51-52">Numbers 33:51-52</a>, <a href="?bref=1Sam.9.13-14">1 Samuel 9:13-14</a>, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.3">2 Kings 12:3</a>, <a href="?bref=2Chr.21.11">2 Chronicles 21:11</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ezek.36.1-2">Ezekiel 36:1-2</a>. But sometimes (as in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.8">2 Kgs 23:8</a>) it was a <span class="hebrew">bamah</span> of the gate, a sanctuary with no special reference to height, located at the city gate as in Dan and Beersheba. It might even have been placed in a declivity (<a href="?bref=Jer.7.31">Jer 7:31</a>).</p>
<p>That a <span class="hebrew">bamah</span> might simply be a burial place with commemorative stelae or memorial stones is clear from such a passage as <a href="?bref=Ezek.43.7">Ezekiel 43:7</a>. An illustration of such a <span class="hebrew">bamah</span> is the so-called Gezer high place. This Bronze Age center with its 10 huge pillars is now interpreted as a mortuary shrine instead of a sanctuary in the strict sense of the term.</p>
<p>A second word translated “high place” is <span class="hebrew">ramah</span> (elevation), from the Hebrew meaning “to be high.” Ezekiel used this term to refer to illicit worship centers (<a href="?bref=Ezek.16.24-25,31-39">16:24-25, 31-39</a>) that evidently had no necessary connection with height.</p>
<p>One of the best-known and best-preserved of all high places in the vicinity of Palestine is the great high place at Petra, discovered by George L. Robinson in 1900. Located on a ridge west of the Khazneh, or treasury, it consists of a large rectangular court and adjacent altars. The court is about 47 feet (14.3 meters) long and 21 feet (6.4 meters) wide and is cut into the rock platform to a depth of 18 inches (45.7 centimeters). West of the court stand a square and a round altar, each hewn from the solid rock. South of the court is a pool measuring about eight and a half by nine and a half feet (2.6 by 2.9 meters) and cut four feet (1.2 meters) into the rock. South of the pool stand two sacred obelisks or pillars, also cut out of the solid rock. This whole complex is reached from a lower terrace by two flights of stairs. At this center the ancient Nabatean inhabitants of Petra evidently engaged in feasts and sacrifices to honor their gods. Though the worship center in its present form does not date before the first century <span class="era">BC</span>, it preserves an ancient tradition of Transjordan and illustrates the pagan and Israelite high places of OT times.</p>
<p>The pagan high place was usually located on a physical height, where one could feel closer to the god. Its first essential was an altar, which might be a heap of earth, unhewn stones, or a unit cut out of the solid rock. Second, there was a stone pillar (<a href="?bref=Deut.12.3">Dt 12:3</a>) or obelisk <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">matsebah</span><span class="ital">)</span> representing the male deity and having phallic associations; third, a tree or pole <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">asherah</span><span class="ital">)</span> representing the female deity (a fertility goddess); and fourth, a laver for ceremonial washings. A sanctuary with an image of the deity also required a building of some sort to protect it (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.29">2 Kgs 17:29</a>).</p>
<p>At these pagan high places sacrifices of animals and sometimes of human beings took place, and religious prostitution or homosexual acts were common. It is natural that such practices should develop in a context of sympathetic magic, where promiscuity and breeding among human beings was supposed to influence animals and crops.</p>
<p>The Hebrews had legitimate high places between the time of the destruction of the tabernacle at Shiloh and construction of the temple, though there was little similarity to pagan accoutrements or practices, apart from the presence of an altar and the offering of sacrifices. At one high place the people ate a sacrificial meal before Samuel anointed Saul king (<a href="?bref=1Sam.9.12-10.1">1 Sm 9:12–10:1</a>). The tabernacle was located at the high place of Gibeon during the reign of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.16.39">1 Chr 16:39</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.21.29">21:29</a>). Solomon offered sacrifices at several high places (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.3.2-3">1 Kgs 3:2-3</a>), and at the high place of Gibeon he met God and was granted the gift of wisdom for his administration (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.3.4-15">4-15</a>). Once Solomon’s temple was completed, high places were eliminated and were off-limits for the Hebrews.</p>
<p>When the Hebrews entered Canaan, they encountered pagan peoples who had long worshiped at high places. God commanded the Israelites to destroy those sanctuaries (<a href="?bref=Num.33.51-52">Nm 33:51-52</a>) to avoid contamination by them, but the warning went largely unheeded. At the height of the Hebrew kingdom, after Solomon had completed the temple, he built high places for the god Chemosh of Moab, Molech of Ammon, and other gods of his pagan wives. For this sin God determined to split the Hebrew kingdom (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.7-11">1 Kgs 11:7-11</a>).</p>
<p>After the division of the kingdom, Jeroboam established high places at Dan and Bethel, and Ahab and others proliferated their construction. Judgment was prophesied (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.13.2-3">1 Kgs 13:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.7-18">2 Kgs 17:7-18</a>), and ultimately the kingdom of Israel went into captivity to Assyria for her idolatry.</p>
<p>Rehoboam, the first king of the southern kingdom, spread high places all over his domain (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.23-24">1 Kgs 14:23-24</a>). Though King Asa launched a revival of true religion, he did not remove the high places (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.12-14">15:12-14</a>). Jehoshaphat also initiated revival, but again the high places remained (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.43">22:43</a>). On the other hand, his son Jehoram and his wife, Athaliah, encouraged their construction (<a href="?bref=2Chr.21.11">2 Chr 21:11</a>). Joash, during his revival, did not eliminate the high places (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.3">2 Kgs 12:3</a>), nor did the good king Uzziah in similar efforts (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.3-4">15:3-4</a>). Ahaz made no pretense of faithfulness to God, and actively encouraged the idolatry of the pagan sanctuaries (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.3-4">16:3-4</a>). Finally, Hezekiah launched a campaign against the high places (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.1">2 Chr 31:1</a>), but his policies were reversed during the reign of his wicked son Manasseh (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.2-9">2 Kgs 21:2-9</a>). Josiah led the last Judean revival and again attacked the high places (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.5,8">23:5, 8</a>).</p>
<p>The prophets Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.15.2">Is 15:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.16.12">16:12</a>), Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.48.35">Jer 48:35</a>), Ezekiel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.6.3">Ez 6:3</a>), Hosea (<a href="?bref=Hos.10.8">Hos 10:8</a>), and Amos (<a href="?bref=Amos.7.9">Am 7:9</a>) roundly condemned these centers of idolatry. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=CanaaniteDeitiesandReligion_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Canaanite Deities and Religion</a>; <a href="?item=GodsandGoddesses_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Gods and Goddesses</a>; <a href="?item=Grove_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Grove</a>; <a href="?item=IdolsIdolatry_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Idols, Idolatry</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>