<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="World">
  <title>World</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WORLD</p>
<p class="fl">An important NT term from the Greek word <span class="greek">kosmos</span> (meaning that which is ordered or arranged), having five different meanings:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. The universe created by God with design and order (e.g., <a href="?bref=Matt.13.35">Mt 13:35</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.24">Jn 17:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.24">Acts 17:24</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. The planet earth (e.g., <a href="?bref=John.11.9">Jn 11:9</a>). This includes the idea of earth as the dwelling place of human beings (<a href="?bref=John.16.21">16:21</a>) and of earth as contrasted with heaven (<a href="?bref=John.6.14">6:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.46">12:46</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. The total of humanity (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.14">Mt 5:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.3.16">Jn 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.13">1 Cor 4:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. The total of human existence in this present life, with all of its experience and possessions (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.26">Mt 16:26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.33">1 Cor 7:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. The world order as alienated from God, in rebellion against him, and condemned for its godlessness. It is “this world” (<a href="?bref=John.8.23">Jn 8:23</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.25">12:25</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.3.19">1 Cor 3:19</a>), as opposed to “that which is to come.” The ruler of this world is the devil (<a href="?bref=John.12.31">Jn 12:31</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.30">14:30</a>; <a href="?bref=John.16.11">16:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.10">1 Cor 5:10</a>)—as John said it, “The whole world is under the control of the evil one” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.5.19">1 Jn 5:19</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Christians are not of this world (<a href="?bref=John.15.19">Jn 15:19</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.16">17:16</a>), even though they live in the world and participate in its activities (<a href="?bref=John.17.11">17:11</a>). The believer is regarded as dead to the world (<a href="?bref=Gal.6.14">Gal 6:14</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Col.3.2-3">Col 3:2-3</a>). The Christian is to be separated from the world (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.27">Jas 1:27</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">One’s relationship with the world is an indicator of one’s relationship with God. Those who love the world don't love God the Father (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.15">1 Jn 2:15</a>). The Scripture points out that “all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh and the lust of the eyes and the pride of life, is not of the Father but is of the world” (v <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.16">16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The world and its desires or lusts are transient, passing away, but the doer of God’s word abides forever (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.17">1 Jn 2:17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.4.18">2 Cor 4:18</a>). Friendship with the world is enmity toward God (<a href="?bref=Jas.4.4">Jas 4:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The discourse of Jesus on the night before his crucifixion contains much teaching about the world. The world cannot receive the Spirit of truth (<a href="?bref=John.14.17">Jn 14:17</a>). Christ gives a peace that the world cannot give (v <a href="?bref=John.14.27">27</a>). Jesus offers love, while the world gives hatred and persecution (<a href="?bref=John.15.19-20">15:19-20</a>). The world’s hatred of God is also directed against the followers of Christ (vv <a href="?bref=John.15.18-21">18-21</a>). Although the disciples of Jesus have tribulation “in this world,” they are to be of good cheer, for Jesus has overcome the world (<a href="?bref=John.16.33">16:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Another Greek word sometimes translated “world” is <span class="greek">aion</span><span class="ital">,</span> which emphasizes the temporal aspect of the world. It is used of time without end, eternity (e.g., <a href="?bref=Rom.1.25">Rom 1:25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.31">2 Cor 11:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.4.20">Phil 4:20</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Age_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Age</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>