<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Abiathar">
  <title>Abiathar</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ABIATHAR</p>
<p class="fl">One of two high priests during the reign of King David. The other high priest was Zadok, who evidently was appointed by David after his conquest of Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Only Abiathar escaped when the priestly families at Nob were massacred at the instigation of King Saul. The priests of Nob had given food and Goliath’s sword to David during his escape from the wrath of Saul, thus earning Saul’s hatred (<a href="?bref=1Sam.21.1-22.23">1 Sm 21–22</a>). When Abiathar joined David he brought the ephod, which David then used in determining the will of God (<a href="?bref=1Sam.23.6,9-11">1 Sm 23:6, 9-11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.30.7-8">30:7-8</a>). Abiathar was one of the first persons from Saul’s administration to support David. His support was formidable because he represented the priesthood of the old tribal league of the line of Eli.</p>
<p>During the last days of David’s kingship, his sons struggled for the throne. The two major rivals were Adonijah and Solomon. Abiathar the high priest supported Adonijah’s claim to the throne, probably because Adonijah was David’s oldest living heir and because David’s general Joab, one of the strongest men in the kingdom, supported Adonijah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.5-7">1 Kgs 1:5-7</a>). Zadok supported Solomon, who actually succeeded David on the throne. Having fallen out of favor with the new king, Abiathar was banished to his estate in Anathoth (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.26-27">1 Kgs 2:26-27</a>), a village about four miles (6.4 kilometers) northeast of Jerusalem. </p>
<p>The relationship of Abiathar to Ahimelech is confusing. Ahimelech could have been the name of both Abiathar’s father (<a href="?bref=1Sam.22.20">1 Sm 22:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.23.6">23:6</a>) and son (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.17">2 Sm 8:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.16">1 Chr 18:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.24.6">24:6</a>). If each of the references was to the same Ahimelech, then the names were reversed in the later passages. In the NT, Abiathar is mentioned as the high priest when David came to Nob needing food and weapons (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.26">Mk 2:26</a>). The OT account says that Ahimelech was the priest at that time (<a href="?bref=1Sam.21.1-2">1 Sm 21:1-2</a>). The apparent discrepancy may have resulted from a copyist’s error or from the fact that Abiathar as high priest was more prominent than Ahimelech.</p>
  </body>
</item>