<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Abomination">
  <title>Abomination</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ABOMINATION</p>
<p class="fl">Repugnant or detestable act, person, or thing. The idea of abomination derives from the specific demands God’s holiness makes upon his people. Adjectives frequently used for abominations in the OT are “abhorrent,” “loathsome,” “unclean,” and “rejected.”</p>
<p>Of the four major Hebrew words translated “abomination,” the one most frequently used indicates violation of an established custom or ritual that, in turn, brings the judgment of God. Examples range from defective sacrifices (<a href="?bref=Deut.17.1">Dt 17:1</a>) to magic and divination (<a href="?bref=Deut.18.12">Dt 18:12</a>) or idolatrous practices (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.3">2 Kgs 16:3</a>). A second Hebrew word refers to the meat of certain kinds of animals that was ritually defiling, whether touched or eaten (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.10-13">Lv 11:10-13</a>). A third word designates three-day-old sacrificial meat (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.18">Lv 7:18</a>). A fourth word refers almost exclusively to idolatrous objects of pagan origin (<a href="?bref=Jer.4.1">Jer 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.7.30">7:30</a>). Apart from the specialized usage of “abomination of desolation,” the Greek word for “abomination” is used infrequently in the NT (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.15">Lk 16:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.2.22">Rom 2:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.16">Ti 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.4-5">Rv 17:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.8,27">21:8, 27</a>) and is translated by many English words. The primary connotation is anything that is abhorrent to a holy God.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CleannessandUncleannessRegulationsconcerning_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cleanness and Uncleanness, Regulations Concerning</a>; <a href="?item=DietaryLaws_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dietary Laws (After Moses)</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="AbominationOfDesolation"/>
  </body>
</item>