<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Adoption">
  <title>Adoption</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ADOPTION</p>
<p class="fl">Theologically, the act of God by which believers become members of “God’s family” with all the privileges and obligations of family membership. “Sons of God,” a common <span class="sc">kjv</span> expression, includes individuals of both sexes numbered among God’s children (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.6">Is 43:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.6.18">2 Cor 6:18</a>).</p>
<p>According to the NT, all persons are sinners by nature, and hence are called “children of wrath” (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.3">Eph 2:3</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>); however, those upon whom God bestows his love become “children of God” by grace (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.1">1 Jn 3:1</a>). The adoption through which this happens has its origin in God’s love and its foundation in Jesus Christ who is uniquely the Son of God. Theologians regard the term “Son of God” as referring preeminently to Christ’s deity (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.25-27">Mt 11:25-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.16.16-17">16:16-17</a>), for he is one in substance and glory with the Father. As the second person of the Trinity, Christ is distinguished from the Father as “the only begotten Son.” Believers in Christ, although “adopted,” are never seen as on a par with the uncreated, divine Son.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, in the beloved Son, sinners have been loved and predestined by God the Father to become his children by adoption (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.4-6">Eph 1:4-6</a>). That adoption is secured by Christ the Redeemer; through his death and resurrection he destroyed sin and its death penalty, restoring the righteousness and life requisite for the status of sonship. Christ is the head of the “new covenant” as its mediator and guarantor. His brothers and sisters, as its beneficiaries, become God’s heirs, and his joint heirs (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.17">Rom 8:17</a>). God gives to them the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of his Son, as the Spirit of adoption (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.15">Rom 8:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.4.6">Gal 4:6</a>). The indwelling Spirit gives believers assurance that they are indeed God’s children and enables them to cry out to God as Father (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.15-16">Rom 8:15-16</a>). Such intimacy with the Creator and Savior in prayer is one privilege of adoption.</p>
<p>Adoption was a privilege given to God’s people under the “old covenant” (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.4">Rom 9:4</a>). Both Israel as a whole and individual Israelites knew God as Father (<a href="?bref=Isa.64.8-9">Is 64:8-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.11.1">Hos 11:1</a>). Since the NT regards adoption as ultimately possible only through Jesus Christ, Israel’s adoption before the Incarnation was an under-age sonship comparable to the status of servanthood (<a href="?bref=Gal.4.1-7">Gal 4:1-7</a>). In Jesus the privilege of mature sonship was extended to include both Jews and Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.25-29">Gal 3:25-29</a>). Though adoption is a benefit enjoyed in the present experience of God’s people (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.1">1 Jn 3:1</a>), its full extent is realized only at their resurrection from the dead (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.21-23">Rom 8:21-23</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>