<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Age">
  <title>Age</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AGE</p>
<p class="fl">Long, but indefinite, period of time, past or future. The ages, past and future, make up the whole of time. God is spoken of as existing and planning “before the ages” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.7">1 Cor 2:7</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). He is the King of ages (<a href="?bref=1Tim.1.17">1 Tm 1:17</a>) and has a purpose that embraces the ages (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.11">Eph 3:11</a>). The Bible speaks of what God will do at the close or consummation of the age(s) (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.39-49">Mt 13:39-49</a>).</p>
<p>The NT, following on from earlier Jewish writings, speaks of the contrast between “the present age” (an “evil age,” <a href="?bref=Gal.1.4">Gal 1:4</a>) and “the age(s) to come” when, in God’s judgment, wrongs will be righted, and his people will come into their full inheritance (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.30">Mk 10:30</a>). There is a sense, however, in which it can be said that we are both living now in “the end of the ages” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.11">1 Cor 10:11</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) and that we experience “the powers of the age to come” (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.5">Heb 6:5</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) and its life.</p>
<p>Two other words are sometimes connected with the word “age.” One is “generation.” <a href="?bref=Col.1.26">Colossians 1:26</a> speaks of the mystery hidden “for ages and generations” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>, cf. <a href="?bref=Eph.3.21">Eph 3:21</a>), though there is no basis in the scriptural use of these words for dividing biblical times into dispensations, each involving some fresh development of the redemptive purpose of God. The other is the word “world.” <a href="?bref=Eph.2.2">Ephesians 2:2</a> speaks of unredeemed humanity as “following the course of this world” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). <a href="?bref=Heb.1.2">Hebrews 1:2</a> and <a href="?bref=Heb.11.3">11:3</a> speak of God’s creation of the world.</p>
<p>The Bible often speaks of the age of men and women, reckoned in years or in other ways. Wisdom is seen as belonging especially to the aged (<a href="?bref=Job.12.12">Jb 12:12</a>), though not necessarily found there (<a href="?bref=Eccl.4.13">Eccl 4:13</a>). Age should be respected (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.32">Lv 19:32</a>), and length of days is a blessing of God (<a href="?bref=Pr.16.31">Prv 16:31</a>). At the same time, the frailty of old age is recognized (<a href="?bref=Eccl.12.1-6">Eccl 12:1-6</a>), and <a href="?bref=Ps.90.10">Psalm 90:10</a> speaks of 70 years as the allotted human span which, if it is extended to 80, may well be “trouble and sorrow.” <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Eternity_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eternity</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>