<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ahijah">
  <title>Ahijah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AHIJAH</p>
<p class="list">1. Ahitub’s son who served as priest at Shiloh and had charge of the ark of the covenant at Gibeah during Saul’s last campaign (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.3,18">1 Sm 14:3, 18</a>). This Ahijah was evidently either the same person as Ahimelech or closely associated with him (<a href="?bref=1Sam.21.1-9">1 Sm 21:1-9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.22.9-20">22:9-20</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. One of King Solomon’s secretaries (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.3">1 Kgs 4:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Prophet of Shiloh who informed King Solomon’s official, Jeroboam, of the approaching revolt of the 10 northern tribes. Before Solomon died, Ahijah acted out a prophecy before Jeroboam, giving him 10 pieces of his robe, which he had torn into 12 segments, saying that God would tear 10 tribes from Solomon and give them to Jeroboam (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.29-39">1 Kgs 11:29-39</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.10.15">2 Chr 10:15</a>). Later, when Jeroboam had been unfaithful to Israel’s religion, he sent his wife to ask the prophet about their son Abijah’s illness (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.1-5">1 Kgs 14:1-5</a>). Aware of her identity although he was now old and blind, Ahijah predicted both the child’s death and the fall of Jeroboam and his family (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.6-17">1 Kgs 14:6-17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.28-30">15:28-30</a>). “The Prophecy of Ahijah from Shiloh” was evidently a written source for Solomon’s biography (<a href="?bref=2Chr.9.29">2 Chr 9:29</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Father of King Baasha of the northern kingdom of Israel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.27-28,33">1 Kgs 15:27-28, 33</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.22">21:22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.9">2 Kgs 9:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Jerahmeel’s son from Judah’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.25">1 Chr 2:25</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. Ehud’s son (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.7">1 Chr 8:7</a>). The Hebrew is difficult to translate; therefore, some English versions make Ahijah one of Ehud’s sons, while others make Ahijah the one who carried Ehud’s sons, Uzza and Ahihud, into exile.</p>
<p class="list">7. Warrior among David’s mighty men who were known as “the thirty” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.11.36">1 Chr 11:36</a>); also called Eliam the son of Ahithophel (<a href="?bref=2Sam.23.34">2 Sm 23:34</a>).</p>
<p class="list">8. Levite who oversaw King David’s temple treasury (<a href="?bref=1Chr.26.20">1 Chr 26:20</a>).</p>
<p class="list">9. Ancestor of the prophet Ezra (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Esd.1.2">2 Esd 1:2</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>