<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AmmonAmmonites">
  <title>Ammon, Ammonites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AMMON, AMMONITES</p>
<p class="fl">A Semitic people who occupied a fertile area northeast of Moab in Transjordan between the Arnon and Jabbok Rivers and extending eastward to the Syrian Desert. The chief city was Rabbah (Rabbath-ammon), modern Amman, capital of Jordan.</p>
<p>The Ammonites traced their ancestry to the younger daughter of Lot (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.38">Gn 19:38</a>). Their name in Hebrew originally meant “son of my paternal clan,” preserving the remembrance of an actual clan and personal name, and suggesting a kinship between the Ammonites and Israelites. The name occurred frequently in the ancient Near East from the middle of the second millennium on. One form was found in Assyrian inscriptions; other forms are seen in Ugaritic texts of the 15th century <span class="era">BC</span>, in the Mari texts, in the Amarna tablets, and in the Alalakh tablets.</p>
<p>The Ammonites originated in the southern Transjordan region about the beginning of the second millennium <span class="era">BC</span>. Though these people were of mixed ancestry, the languages they spoke were closely related to Hebrew. Ammonite was written in the old Canaanite-Phoenician script, which could probably be read and understood by Israelites. Ammonites intermarried with Hebrews (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.21,31">1 Kgs 14:21, 31</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.12.13">2 Chr 12:13</a>), and their personal names reflected early Arabic influences.</p>
<p>In language, ethnic background, and physical characteristics the Ammonites were difficult to distinguish from Amorites and were probably closely related. Both may have entered the land at about the same time, for when Joshua led the Israelites into Canaan, both the Ammonite kingdom and the Amorite kingdom of Heshbon were already well established.</p>
<p>The OT states that the territory of Ammon was once occupied by a race of giants called Rephaim or Zamzummim, about whom almost nothing is known (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.20-21">Dt 2:20-21</a>; “Zuzim,” <a href="?bref=Gen.14.5">Gn 14:5</a>). The Genesis Apocryphon found among the Dead Sea Scrolls mentions them as one of the people defeated by the alliance of four kings (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.1,5">Gn 14:1, 5</a>). The expedition of Chedorlaomer, king of Elam (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.1-24">Gn 14</a>), broke the power of those giants and probably made the occupation of the land by Esau, Ammon, and Moab much easier. King Og was “of the remnant of the Rephaim” known to the Ammonites (<a href="?bref=Deut.3.11">Dt 3:11</a>). His bed was evidently an object of veneration because of its unusual size.</p>
<p>When the Israelites arrived at Kadesh, they encountered the well-organized kingdom of Edom but were refused permission to pass through Edomite territory (<a href="?bref=Num.20.14-21">Nm 20:14-21</a>). They journeyed northward to Ammonite country, which was then occupied by the Amorite king Sihon. He also refused them permission to pass through his land, but the Israelites defeated him in battle and occupied his country (<a href="?bref=Num.21.21-24">Nm 21:21-24</a>). They were instructed by God through Moses not to try to occupy Ammonite territory, as it had already been given to the descendants of Lot (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.19,37">Dt 2:19, 37</a>).</p>
<p>Continuing northward, the Israelites defeated King Og of Bashan (<a href="?bref=Deut.3.1-11">Dt 3:1-11</a>), then went down to the Jordan Valley, where they camped on the plains of Moab. There Balak, king of Moab, hired a soothsayer, Balaam, to pronounce a curse on the Israelites, but Balaam pronounced a blessing each time instead (<a href="?bref=Num.22.1-24.25">Nm 22–24</a>). For supporting the Moabites in their actions, the Ammonites were excluded from the congregation of the Lord to the tenth generation (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.3">Dt 23:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.13.1-2">Neh 13:1-2</a>).</p>
<p>The Israelite tribes of Gad and Reuben and the half-tribe of Manasseh were attracted to the fertile Transjordan region that had belonged to the Amorites and Bashan and decided to settle there on the Ammonite frontier (<a href="?bref=Num.32.1-42">Nm 32</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.3.16">Dt 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.13.8-32">Jos 13:8-32</a>). Subsequently they built an altar at the Jordan River, which the other tribes at first interpreted as an act of rebellion in that they appeared to be establishing a rival place of worship (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.10-34">Jos 22:10-34</a>).</p>
<p>Before the Israelite conquest of Canaan, the Ammonites evidently had not attained the same level of political organization and settled life as the neighboring Moabites and Edomites. Even as late as the seventh century <span class="era">BC</span> the nation was essentially nomadic. Shortly after Israel settled in Canaan, the Ammonites allied with the Moabites and Amalekites when King Eglon of Moab tried to regain former Moabite territory at the north end of the Dead Sea (<a href="?bref=Judg.3.12-13">Jgs 3:12-13</a>).</p>
<p>By the end of the 12th century <span class="era">BC</span> the Israelites, then securely established in the land of Canaan, angered God by their worship of the deities of the Syrians, Sidonians, Moabites, Ammonites, and Philistines (<a href="?bref=Judg.10.6">Jgs 10:6</a>). The Ammonites, in their first recorded political expansion, launched an attack against Israel and were able to establish themselves in Gilead (<a href="?bref=Judg.10.7-8">Jgs 10:7-8</a>). They then crossed the Jordan and attacked the tribes of Judah, Benjamin, and Ephraim (<a href="?bref=Judg.10.9">Jgs 10:9</a>). In desperation the elders of Gilead turned for help to Jephthah, a social outcast but an able military leader (<a href="?bref=Judg.11.1-11">Jgs 11:1-11</a>). He defeated the Ammonites so decisively that it was unnecessary for him to wage further campaigns against Ammonite settlements west of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Judg.11.12-33">Jgs 11:12-33</a>).</p>
<p>Near the end of the 11th century an Ammonite king named Nahash came to power, determined to reestablish Ammonite dominion over Israelite settlements in Transjordan. He launched an aggressive military campaign around 1020 <span class="era">BC</span> that took him as far north as Jabesh-gilead. The inhabitants of the town were willing to surrender to him but delayed their surrender to appeal for help from Saul, the recently consecrated Israelite king. Saul quickly organized an army and decisively defeated the Ammonites (<a href="?bref=1Sam.11.1-11">1 Sm 11:1-11</a>). The victory ensured freedom from Ammonite domination in the Jordan Valley for several centuries, although later in his reign Saul was forced to fight further battles with the enemies of Israel, including Ammonites (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.47-48">1 Sm 14:47-48</a>).</p>
<p>When David became king, he took silver and gold from the Ammonites, Philistines, and Amalekites, either as spoils or as tribute (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.11-12">2 Sm 8:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.11">1 Chr 18:11</a>). Soon thereafter, David sent Joab at the head of a strong army to devastate the Ammonite countryside and besiege the capital city of Rabbah (<a href="?bref=2Sam.11.1">2 Sm 11:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.20.2">1 Chr 20:2</a>). The siege lasted many months, but Joab weakened the city and David then completed its capture (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.26-29">2 Sm 12:26-29</a>). In a ceremony of capitulation the Ammonite king’s massive golden crown was placed on David’s head (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.30">2 Sm 12:30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.20.1">1 Chr 20:1</a>). The conquered city was plundered, and its inhabitants were enslaved. Other Ammonite cities were taken, and the nation was added to the growing number of vassal states of Israel (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.31">2 Sm 12:31</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.20.3">1 Chr 20:3</a>). David appointed a governor over the Ammonites from the Ammonite royal family. Shobi, another son of Nahash (and therefore Hanun’s brother), became ruler of the Ammonites and aided David during his flight from Absalom’s rebellion (<a href="?bref=2Sam.17.27">2 Sm 17:27</a>). One of David’s best warriors was an Ammonite (<a href="?bref=2Sam.23.37">2 Sm 23:37</a>).</p>
<p>Ammonite relations with Israel remained generally peaceful during the reign of Solomon, David’s successor, with the Ammonites undoubtedly sharing in the prosperity and wealth of that period. After the death of Solomon, the kingdom split apart under Rehoboam and was further weakened by a campaign of Shishak, king of Egypt, that swept through Palestine and also through Ammonite territory. Taking advantage of the situation, the Ammonites declared their independence from Israel and Judah. The Ammonites joined the Moabites and Meunites to make war against King Jehoshaphat of Judah (reigning 871–848 <span class="era">BC</span>). In fear, Jehoshaphat sought help from God in prayer (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.1-12">2 Chr 20:1-12</a>). The Ammonites and their allies began fighting among themselves and destroyed each other, leaving behind great spoils for Jehoshaphat and his people—which took three days to be carried away (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.22-25">2 Chr 20:22-25</a>). Eventually the Ammonites recovered, so that by the end of the seventh century <span class="era">BC</span>, Ammon had again become completely independent and was the dominant state of south Transjordan. Ammonite independence was short, however, for in 599 <span class="era">BC</span>, according to the Babylonian Chronicle, Babylonian king Nebuchadnezzar led his troops into Syria and began raiding southern Palestine. In 593 <span class="era">BC</span>, the Ammonites met in Jerusalem with King Zedekiah of Judah and representatives from Edom, Moab, Tyre, and Sidon in a conspiracy to rebel against Babylon (<a href="?bref=Jer.27.1-3">Jer 27:1-3</a>). The prophet Jeremiah warned them that God would cause their plan to fail (<a href="?bref=Jer.27.4-22">Jer 27:4-22</a>). Nebuchadnezzar sent an army to crush the rebellion and attacked Jerusalem, which he destroyed after a lengthy and bitter siege (586 <span class="era">BC</span>), deporting many Jews to Babylonia. Ammon was not immediately invaded, however, and many Judeans sought refuge there (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.11">Jer 40:11</a>), including a man named Ishmael (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.13-16">Jer 40:13-16</a>). Ishmael plotted with Baalis, king of Ammon, to assassinate Gedaliah, whom Nebuchadnezzar had appointed governor over Judea, now reduced to a province of Babylonia. After carrying out the assassination, Ishmael escaped to Ammon (<a href="?bref=Jer.41.1-15">Jer 41:1-15</a>). Nebuchadnezzar then sent troops that sacked Rabbah and took captive many of the Ammonites. Though the city was not destroyed, the destruction of the countryside was thorough. In the third century <span class="era">BC</span>, Arab invaders poured in and destroyed the remaining organized political structure, thus marking the end of Ammon as a semi-independent state.</p>
  </body>
</item>