<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Anger">
  <title>Anger</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ANGER</p>
<p class="fl">The word normally used in the Bible to refer to rage, fury, and indignation. In most instances, anger is considered to be wrong. <a href="?bref=Ps.37.8">Psalm 37:8</a> (<span class="sc">nlt</span>), for example, commands: “Stop your anger! Turn from your rage!” Jesus paralleled anger with murder when he said, “If you are angry with someone, you are subject to judgment!” (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.22">Mt 5:22</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>)—just as if the person had actually committed the murder he felt in his angry heart. <a href="?bref=Eph.4.31">Ephesians 4:31</a> and <a href="?bref=Col.3.8">Colossians 3:8</a> both list anger, along with bitterness, wrath, malice, and slander, as attitudes that Christians must rid themselves of once and for all. In his list of attributes for a bishop or pastor of a church, the apostle Paul said that a Christian leader should not be prone to anger, that is, easily provoked (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.7">Ti 1:7</a>).</p>
<p>The Bible recognizes that humans get angry; it does not condemn the anger in and of itself but what often happens as the result. Humans have a habit of letting their anger get the best of them, causing them to sin. That is why the apostle Paul said, “Don’t sin by letting anger gain control over you” (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.26">Eph 4:26</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The longer a person allows anger to continue, the greater the danger that it will develop sinful qualities, giving Satan a foothold (see <a href="?bref=Eph.4.27">Eph 4:27</a>).</p>
<p>Anger of a good sort is also spoken of in the Bible. “Righteous indignation” refers to the extreme displeasure of a holy heart unable to tolerate sin of any kind. The anger of God contains this element: man should be good, yet he sins—and God is angry “because they forsook the covenant of the Lord, the God of their fathers, which he made with them when he brought them out of the land of Egypt, and went and served other gods and worshiped them, gods whom they had not known and whom he had not allotted to them” (<a href="?bref=Deut.29.25-26">Dt 29:25-26</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). It was in that sense also that Moses’ anger burned on Mt Sinai and caused him to smash the tablets of the covenant on the ground when he saw the golden calf and Israel’s idolatry (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.19">Ex 32:19</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT, Mark says that Jesus looked with anger at the Pharisees, who were hoping to catch him breaking their law (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.5">Mk 3:5</a>). Jesus’ anger was also shown in his cleansing of the temple (<a href="?bref=John.2.13-22">Jn 2:13-22</a>); it should have been a place of prayer but was being used as a place of business. So Jesus “entered the Temple and began to drive out the merchants and their customers. He knocked over the tables of the money changers and the stalls of those selling doves” (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.12">Mt 21:12</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). His holy indignation was neither a weakness nor a sin. Such anger is an appropriate response to iniquity and injustice, especially when they are apparently unpunished.</p>
  </body>
</item>