<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Aphek">
  <title>Aphek</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">APHEK</p>
<p class="list">1. Canaanite city west of the Jordan River conquered by Israel (<a href="?bref=Josh.12.18">Jos 12:18</a>) and later included in Ephraim’s territory. It was located near the source of the Yarkon River in the plain of Sharon. Aphek was later captured by the Philistines (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.1">1 Sm 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.29.1">29:1</a>). In Roman times Herod the Great rebuilt the city and named it Antipatris, mentioned in <a href="?bref=Acts.23.31">Acts 23:31</a>. Its modern name is Ras el-‘Ain.</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Antipatris_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Antipatris</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Place in Phoenicia (modern Lebanon) that remained unconquered after Joshua’s campaigns (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.4">Jos 13:4</a>). This Aphek was probably located near the source of the river Ibrahim, east of Byblos.</p>
<p class="list">3. Town given to Asher’s tribe in the distribution of conquered cities (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.30">Jos 19:30</a>). Asher’s tribe failed to drive out the pagan inhabitants (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.31">Jgs 1:31</a>, where it is spelled “Aphik”). Aphek was located on the plain of Acco, at the present site of Tell Kurdaneh near the source of the river Na’main.</p>
<p class="list">4. City east of the Jordan River, on the main highway between Damascus and the valley of Jezreel. The Syrian king Ben-hadad, defeated by King Ahab of Israel, retreated into Aphek, where a falling wall demolished the rest of his army (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.26,30">1 Kgs 20:26, 30</a>). A century later Elisha prophesied to King Joash of Israel that he would defeat the Syrians in the same city (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.17">2 Kgs 13:17</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfAphekFortress"/>
</body>
</item>