<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Arabah">
  <title>Arabah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ARABAH</p>
<p class="fl">Great valley dividing eastern and western Palestine. The Arabah extends south from the Sea of Galilee through the Jordan River valley to the Dead Sea and the Gulf of Aqaba. Commonly known as the Rift Valley, the Arabah is about 6 miles (10 kilometers) wide and 200 miles (322 kilometers) long. The Dead Sea, located in the Arabah, is the lowest point on the earth’s inland surface, 1,275 feet (388.5 meters) below sea level.</p>
<p>In general the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">arabah</span> means a wasteland or barren district. North of the Dead Sea to the Sea of Galilee, the valley is referred to by the Arabs as the Ghor (“depression”) and south of the Dead Sea as the Arabah.</p>
<p>In the OT the name Arabah is sometimes applied to the entire length of the valley, though at times the southern portion is alluded to (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.1">Dt 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.2.8">2:8</a>), and elsewhere the northeast portion is indicated (<a href="?bref=Deut.3.17">Dt 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.49">4:49</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.11.2">Jos 11:2</a>). It could refer to the portion east of the Jordan River (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.49">Dt 4:49</a>) or to the part west of the river (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.16">Jos 11:16</a>) or to the Jordan River valley (<a href="?bref=2Sam.4.7">2 Sm 4:7</a>). In the Hebrew OT, the plural of Arabah <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">Arboth</span><span class="ital">)</span> is found 17 times, and its meaning is “plains”—referring to the portion of the Arabah near Jericho or Moab. The Dead Sea is sometimes referred to as the Sea of the Arabah or Sea of the Plain (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.25">2 Kgs 14:25</a>). For the most part the section of the Arabah north of the Dead Sea was, and is today, fertile and productive.</p>
<p>It was from the Arabah that Joshua led the campaign to conquer Jericho. Abner fled to the northern Arabah after being defeated at Gibeon (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.29">2 Sm 2:29</a>). The murderers of Ishbosheth crossed the area to bring his head to David at Hebron (<a href="?bref=2Sam.4.7">2 Sm 4:7</a>), and Zedekiah was fleeing to the area when he was captured by the Babylonians (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.4">2 Kgs 25:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.39.4">Jer 39:4</a>).</p>
<p>The southern Arabah was the scene of Israel’s wanderings before entering the Promised Land. Farther north, the Arabah was the site of the final acts of Moses (<a href="?bref=Num.32.1-36.13">Nm 32–36</a>), who died and was buried in the Arabah (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.1">Dt 1:1</a>) in the plains of Moab east of the Dead Sea (<a href="?bref=Deut.34.1-6">Dt 34:1-6</a>).</p>
<p>South of the Dead Sea there were deposits of iron and copper, and <a href="?bref=Deut.8.9">Deuteronomy 8:9</a> may allude to this general area when it speaks of “a land whose stones are iron, and out of whose hills you can dig copper.” The land here is generally barren, though in ancient times careful use of irrigation made agriculture possible to a limited extent. Several important trade routes have passed through this area. The Arabah around the Dead Sea, prior to the destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah, was once an especially fertile area, “like the garden of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (<a href="?bref=Gen.13.10">Gn 13:10</a>).</p>
<p>The rejuvenation of this area is one of the subjects of prophetic promise. Ezekiel speaks of a great river that will spring from the temple and go down into the Arabah, making the waters of the sea fresh and creating a healthy environment for fish and other living creatures (<a href="?bref=Ezek.47.1-12">Ez 47:1-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.3.18">Jl 3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.14.8">Zec 14:8</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Palestine_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Palestine</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>