<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ArabiaArabs">
  <title>Arabia, Arabs</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ARABIA, ARABS</p>
<p class="fl">Peninsula in southwestern Asia, surrounded by sea on three sides and by the Fertile Crescent on the fourth. Politically, the Arabian peninsula is bounded on the north by the modern Hashemite kingdom of Jordan and by Iraq and on the south by the Indian Ocean. The Persian Gulf forms its eastern boundary and the Red Sea its western boundary. Its area is just over a million square miles (1,609,000 square kilometers), about one-third the area of the United States.</p>
<p>Classical geographers such as Strabo followed the example set by the geographer Ptolemy in dividing Arabia into three divisions: <span class="ital">Arabia Petraea</span> (Rocky Arabia) in the northwest, which included Sinai, Edom, Moab, and Transjordan; <span class="ital">Arabia Deserta,</span> which included the Syrian Desert; and <span class="ital">Arabia Felix</span> (Happy Arabia), which included the southern section of the Arabian peninsula.</p>
<p>When “Arabia” is used as a geographical term in the Bible, it sometimes includes both northern and southern sections. For example, <a href="?bref=2Chr.9.14">2 Chronicles 9:14</a> says that the kings of Arabia brought gold to Solomon as tribute. At other times the name Arabia refers only to the northwestern <span class="ital">Arabia Petraea.</span> For example, Paul said that after his conversion he went away to the deserts of Arabia (<a href="?bref=Gal.1.17">Gal 1:17</a>) and referred to Mt Sinai (<a href="?bref=Gal.4.25">4:25</a>), which is in that northwestern area. Many places named in the Bible as being in Arabia are more specifically in <span class="ital">Arabia Petraea.</span> Such sites include Buz, Dedan, Dumah, Ephah, the Hazor of <a href="?bref=Jer.49.28-33">Jeremiah 49:28-33</a>, Massa, Mesha, and Midian. Hazarmaveth, Ophir, Sabtah, Sephar, Sheba, and Uzal are in the south. Havilah and Parvaim are perhaps in the northeast, and authorities debate the location of Seba. The land of Uz, mentioned in the book of Job, is considered by many scholars to be located in the area between Edom and northern Arabia.</p>
<p>Arabia is thought by many to be one of the hottest countries. In some sections that conception is correct. The peninsula lies between seas on the east and west, but those bodies of water are too small to break the climatic continuity of the dry African-Asian continental masses. There are, however, some regions that enjoy temperate and semitropical climate. In the south much of the land is sufficiently elevated to avoid the intensity of tropical heat. The lowlands along the coast have a semitropical environment. Fogs and dews are common in the humid regions, but over inner Arabia the sun shines the year round, obscured only by an occasional sandstorm or an even rarer rain shower.</p>
<p>Arabia has long been desired for natural resources. Pharaohs of the first dynasty operated turquoise mines in Sinai, and the gold of Ophir and the frankincense and myrrh of South Arabia were world renowned. The queen of Sheba brought such precious spices to Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.2,10">1 Kgs 10:2, 10</a>), and trade between Israel and Arabia flourished. Solomon had a seaport at Ezion-geber on the Red Sea for his opulent commerce with Ophir (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.26-28">1 Kgs 9:26-28</a>). King Jehoshaphat of Judah, who also received tribute from Arabs (<a href="?bref=2Chr.17.11">2 Chr 17:11</a>), tried to revive trade with Ophir but failed (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.48">1 Kgs 22:48</a>).</p>
<p>Tribes associated with Arabia played a significant role in biblical history. The Ishmaelites or Midianites who took Joseph to Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.25-36">Gn 37:25-36</a>) were Arabians. So were the Amalekites who waged war with Moses in the wilderness of <span class="ital">Arabia Petraea</span> (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.8-16">Ex 17:8-16</a>). Moses’ father-in-law, Jethro, was a Midianite (<a href="?bref=Exod.18.1">Ex 18:1</a>). King Uzziah of Judah fought against Arabs (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.7">2 Chr 26:7</a>); the Meunites mentioned in the same verse were probably also from Arabia. Geshem the Arab, known also from secular inscriptions, resisted the rebuilding of the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.2.19">Neh 2:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.6.1,6">6:1, 6</a>).</p>
<p>Kedar was an important North Arab tribe condemned in Isaiah’s message about Arabia (<a href="?bref=Isa.21.13-17">Is 21:13-17</a>). Jeremiah also spoke against it, prophesying its destruction by Nebuchadnezzar, who conquered it (<a href="?bref=Jer.49.28-33">Jer 49:28-33</a>). Close allies of the tribe of Kedar were the Nabatean Arabs (<a href="?bref=Isa.60.7">Is 60:7</a>), who figure prominently in later history. They captured Petra, fulfilling the prophecy of Obadiah about Edom. References to Arabia and the Arabs in the Apocrypha and NT concern mostly the Nabatean Arabs (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.11.16">1 Macc 11:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.17">Gal 1:17</a>).</p>
<p>In southern Arabia four kingdoms developed: the Sabean, Minean, Qataban, and Hadramaut. Around 115 <span class="era">BC</span> the Himyarite kingdom gained control of southern Arabia, keeping it until about <span class="era">AD</span> 300. Three centuries later the Arabian peninsula witnessed the birth of Islam.</p>
  </body>
</item>