<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Aristobulus">
  <title>Aristobulus</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ARISTOBULUS</p>
<p class="fl">Name (of Greek origin, meaning “best advising”) used in intertestamental times by ruling families in Palestine.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Jewish priest in Alexandria (Egypt) and teacher of Ptolemy (ruled 180–146 <span class="era">BC</span>). A letter was sent to Aristobulus from the Judean Jews (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Macc.1.10">2 Macc 1:10</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Aristobulus I. First king of the Maccabean (also called Hasmonean) family. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Hasmonean_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hasmonean</a>.</p>
<p class="list">3. Aristobulus II. Son of Alexander Janneus (brother of Aristobulus I) and Salome Alexandra. In 67 <span class="era">BC</span> Aristobulus II defeated his older brother, Hyrcanus II, and became king. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Hasmonean_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hasmonean</a>.</p>
<p class="list">4. Aristobulus III. Grandson of Hyrcanus II and brother of Mariamne, wife of Herod the Great. Aristobulus was named high priest at the age of 17 (by Herod). When his acceptance as a Hasmonean by the people threatened Herod, Herod responded by arranging for his drowning (35 <span class="era">BC</span>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Hasmonean_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hasmonean</a>.</p>
<p class="list">5. Younger of the two sons of Herod the Great and Mariamne. Aristobulus and Alexander became threats to Herod after he executed their mother in 29 <span class="era">BC</span>. The two brothers were charged with attempting to poison their father in a trial before Caesar (12 <span class="era">BC</span>) but were acquitted and reconciled to him. This Aristobulus was the father of Herod, king of Chalcis; Herod Agrippa I, of Judea; Aristobulus (see #6 below); and Herodias, wife of Herod Antipas. Later, Herod the Great ordered both Aristobulus and Alexander strangled at Sebaste (7 <span class="era">BC</span>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=HerodHerodianFamily_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Herod, Herodian Family</a>.</p>
<p class="list">6. Son of Aristobulus (#5 above) and Bernice, mentioned by the Jewish historian Josephus for plotting against Herod Agrippa, his brother, and for opposing the plan of Petronius, governor of Syria, to erect a statue of Roman emperor Caligula in the temple in Jerusalem (<span class="era">AD</span> 40).</p>
<p class="list">7. Person whose family or household was greeted by the apostle Paul (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.10">Rom 16:10</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>