<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Armageddon">
  <title>Armageddon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ARMAGEDDON</p>
<p class="fl">Hebrew word in <a href="?bref=Rev.16.16">Revelation 16:16</a> meaning “Mount Megiddo.” It is generally thought that the term refers to the town of Megiddo, strategically located between the western coastal area and the broad plain of Jezreel in northern Palestine. The area of Megiddo was important commercially and militarily and was the scene of many important battles in Israel’s history. There the Lord routed Sisera before the armies of Deborah and Barak (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.1-5.31">Jgs 4–5</a>); Gideon was victorious over the Midianites and Amalekites (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.1-7.25">Jgs 6–7</a>); King Saul and his army were defeated by the Philistines (<a href="?bref=1Sam.31.1-13">1 Sm 31</a>); and King Josiah was slain in battle by the Egyptian army of Pharaoh Neco (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.29">2 Kgs 23:29</a>). Because of that long history the name seems to have become symbolic of a battlefield. Such is the depiction in the book of Revelation.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Rev.15.1-8">Revelation 15</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.16.1-21">16</a> describe seven angels who pour out seven bowls of the wrath of God upon the earth. The sixth angel pours out his bowl upon the great river Euphrates, and its waters are dried up (<a href="?bref=Rev.16.12-16">Rv 16:12-16</a>), preparing the way for the coming of the “kings of the East.” Also three demonic spirits go forth to cause the kings of the whole world to gather for a battle on the great day of God the Almighty (<a href="?bref=Rev.16.13-14">16:13-14</a>). Their gathering takes place at Armageddon (<a href="?bref=Rev.16.16">16:16</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=RevelationBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Revelation, Book of</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="HowDoWeInterpretArmageddon"/>
  </body>
</item>