<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AscensionofChrist">
  <title>Ascension of Christ</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ASCENSION OF CHRIST</p>
<p class="fl">Transference of the resurrected body of Jesus from this world to heaven. Among the NT writers, only Luke described Jesus’ ascension. <a href="?bref=Acts.1.9-11">Acts 1:9-11</a> pictures a scene in which Jesus was “taken up” and disappeared into a cloud. <a href="?bref=Luke.24.50-51">Luke 24:50-51</a> and <a href="?bref=Acts.1.12">Acts 1:12</a> locate that final event near Bethany, east of Jerusalem on the Mt of Olives.</p>
<p>Matthew concluded his history before Pentecost, but John suggested the Ascension in Jesus’ own comments: Jesus has departed, but he will return (<a href="?bref=John.21.22">Jn 21:22</a>); he cannot be touched, for he must ascend (<a href="?bref=John.20.17">20:17</a>); many will believe without having seen him (<a href="?bref=John.20.29">20:29</a>). Thus, the Gospels assume that (1) after the resurrection Jesus appeared to his disciples; (2) at some point in time those appearances ceased; and (3) although physically absent, Jesus is still spiritually present in his church. Other NT writings agree. The apostle Paul wrote that God raised Christ from the dead “and seated him in the place of honor at God’s right hand in the heavenly realms” (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.20">Eph 1:20</a>) or, as the writer of Hebrews put it, “in the place of honor at the right hand of the majestic God of heaven” (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.3">Heb 1:3</a>).</p>
<p>The Ascension, however, is more than merely a past event. It has further significance in the NT that can be summarized under two headings: (1) its meaning for Christ and (2) its meaning for the Christian.</p>
<p>For Christ, the Ascension is the necessary entrance into his heavenly “glorification” in which he sits on the right hand of the Father until his enemies become his footstool (<a href="?bref=Ps.110.1">Ps 110:1</a>—the OT text most quoted in the NT). The Ascension is proof of his glorification and his superiority over such OT heroes as David (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.33-36">Acts 2:33-36</a>). By his ascension he rises over all and fills all (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.10">Eph 4:10</a>), receiving “the name that is over every name” (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.9-11">Phil 2:9-11</a>). For the author of the book of Hebrews the Ascension is also proof of Christ’s superiority to angels; he sits enthroned while they are constantly being sent out to serve (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.13-14">Heb 1:13-14</a>). Angels, authorities, and powers are all subject to the ascended Christ (<a href="?bref=1Tim.3.16">1 Tm 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.22">1 Pt 3:22</a>).</p>
<p>For the Christian, the ascension of Christ is meaningful in four ways. First, without it there would be no gift of the Holy Spirit, who could not come until Jesus had ascended and sent him (<a href="?bref=John.16.7">Jn 16:7</a>). Without the Ascension, the church would have Jesus locally in one place, not spiritually present “wherever two or three are gathered” (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.20">Mt 18:20</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.28.20">28:20</a>).</p>
<p>Second, since a truly human Jesus has ascended to heaven, human beings can also ascend there. Jesus went “to prepare a place” for his followers (<a href="?bref=John.14.2">Jn 14:2</a>). The hope of those who are “in Christ” is that they will eventually ascend to be with him (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.1-10">2 Cor 5:1-10</a>).</p>
<p>Third, the Ascension proves that the sacrifice of Christ is finished and accepted by God. Jesus has passed through the heavens (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.14">Heb 4:14</a>) and entered the presence of God (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.20">Heb 6:20</a>), which is described as the inner sanctuary of the heavenly temple, the real temple of which the one on earth was a copy (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.24">Heb 9:24</a>). Having brought a single, once-for-all sacrifice to God (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.12">Heb 9:12</a>), Christ sat down (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.3">Heb 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.12">10:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.12.2">12:2</a>), showing that no repetition of his sacrifice is necessary.</p>
<p>Fourth, the Ascension means that there is a human being in heaven who sympathizes with humanity and can therefore intercede on humanity’s behalf (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.1">1 Jn 2:1</a>). Jesus has experienced everything humans experience—birth, growth, temptation, suffering, and death—and therefore he can serve effectively as an intermediary before God in heaven (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.17">Heb 2:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.5.7-10">5:7-10</a>). Christ’s ascension assures the church that God understands the human situation and that Christians can therefore approach him boldly in their prayers (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.14-16">Heb 4:14-16</a>).</p>
<p>Thus Christ’s ascension is an indispensable aspect of NT teaching. It is the basis for recognition of Christ’s exalted status and for the Christian’s confidence and hope.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Christology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Christology</a>; <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Life and Teachings of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>