<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ashes">
  <title>Ashes</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ASHES</p>
<p class="fl">Fine powder left after something has been thoroughly burned. The burning of sacrificial offerings on the tabernacle or temple altar produced ashes that were disposed of ceremonially (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.16">Lv 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.4.12">4:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.10-11">6:10-11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.9.13">Heb 9:13</a>). The ashes on pagan altars figured in several OT accounts (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.13.1-5">1 Kgs 13:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.4">2 Kgs 23:4</a>). Ashes thrown into the air by Moses during the contest of God with the Egyptian pharaoh spread like fine dust over all the land of Egypt and caused a plague of boils to break out among both people and animals (<a href="?bref=Exod.9.8-10">Ex 9:8-10</a>).</p>
<p>Ashes are frequently mentioned in the Bible in connection with the ancient custom of putting ashes on oneself as a symbol of extreme grief, penitence, humiliation, or sense of worthlessness. The Bible refers to ashes and dust almost interchangeably in this usage. Examples of such expressions of emotion include Tamar’s distress after being sexually assaulted by her half brother (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.19">2 Sm 13:19</a>), Mordecai’s agony over the Persian king’s order of genocide for the Jews of his realm (<a href="?bref=Esth.4.1-3">Est 4:1-3</a>), Daniel’s confession and pleading for his captive people (<a href="?bref=Dan.9.3">Dn 9:3</a>), and the king of Nineveh’s repentance after hearing Jonah’s preaching (<a href="?bref=Jon.3.6">Jon 3:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.10.13">Lk 10:13</a>). Ashes were spoken of as symbols of humility (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.27">Gn 18:27</a>), worthlessness or futility (<a href="?bref=Job.13.12">Jb 13:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.30.19">30:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.44.20">Is 44:20</a>), and destruction (<a href="?bref=Ezek.28.18">Ez 28:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.6">2 Pt 2:6</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Mourning_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mourning</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>