<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ashkelon">
  <title>Ashkelon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ASHKELON</p>
<p class="fl">City dating back to ancient times, also spelled Askelon (<span class="sc">kjv</span>). In the Bible, Ashkelon was one of the Philistines’ five main cities (the “pentapolis”), along with Gaza, Ashdod, Gath, and Ekron (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.3">Jos 13:3</a>). Ashkelon was located on the Mediterranean coast, 30 miles (48 kilometers) south of modern Tel Aviv, and was always an important port. Often in conflict with Egypt, it was captured by Ramses II (c. 1286 <span class="era">BC</span>) and by Merneptah (c. 1220 <span class="era">BC</span>).</p>
<p>Ashkelon is mentioned as one of the cities conquered by Judah (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.18">Jgs 1:18</a>). After the Philistine invasion of Canaan in the 12th century <span class="era">BC</span>, the city became one of the invaders’ major centers. When Samson’s riddle was answered through the duplicity of his Philistine wife, Samson vented his rage at Ashkelon, killing 30 men (<a href="?bref=Judg.14.19">Jgs 14:19</a>). Ashkelon was partially responsible for pushing the tribe of Dan from its allotment; so Samson, a member of that tribe, probably had a long-standing grudge against the city. Ashkelon also figures in the story of the Philistine control of the ark (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.1-6.21">1 Sm 4–6</a>). On hearing of the deaths of Saul and Jonathan, David lamented the loss of his king and of his friend, exclaiming that their deaths should not be published in Ashkelon (<a href="?bref=2Sam.1.20">2 Sm 1:20</a>). Various OT prophets refer to Ashkelon (<a href="?bref=Jer.25.20">Jer 25:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.47.5-6">47:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.1.8">Am 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.4-7">Zep 2:4-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.9.5">Zec 9:5</a>).</p>
<p>In the period of Israel’s decline King Pekah of Israel, King Rezin of Damascus, and the king of Ashkelon rebelled against Assyria. Tiglath-pileser III responded with three successive campaigns (734–732 <span class="era">BC</span>), the first of which conquered Ashkelon. Nebuchadnezzar destroyed the city and deported many of its inhabitants to Egypt during his conquest of Palestine (604 <span class="era">BC</span>). Successive invaders then took the city from each other: Scythians, Chaldeans, Persians, Greeks, and Maccabees. Ashkelon was the birthplace of Herod the Great, and ruins of his building projects are to be found there. Ashkelon is not mentioned in the NT but was a battleground in the Jewish rebellion against Rome (<span class="era">AD</span> 66).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfAshkelon"/>
</body>
</item>