<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ashurnasirpal">
  <title>Ashurnasirpal*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ASHURNASIRPAL*</p>
<p class="list">1. Ashurnasirpal I (1049?–1031 <span class="era">BC</span>), Assyrian king listed in the synchronistic Assyrian chronicle as the legitimate successor ofShamshi-adad IV (1053?–1050 <span class="era">BC</span>). Ashurnasirpal I ruled during a period of Assyrian weakness following the vigorous reign of Tiglath-pileser I (1115?–1077 <span class="era">BC</span>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Ashurnasirpal II (885–860 <span class="era">BC</span>), Assyrian king, son of Tukulti-ninurta II (890–885 <span class="era">BC</span>). His grandfather, Adad-nirari II (911–891 <span class="era">BC</span>), laid the foundations of the Neo-Assyrian period (900–612 <span class="era">BC</span>). Ashurnasirpal II, its first great monarch, consolidated his position by crushing rebellious middle Euphrates tribes and then conducted campaigns against Syria (877 <span class="era">BC</span>) and Philistia. In his annals he recorded the tribute received from the maritime towns of Philistia: “Gold, silver, tin, copper . . . large and small monkeys, ebony, boxwood, ivory . . . I received.” Ashurnasirpal’s westward expedition was the first of several Assyrian assaults on Syria, ultimately threatening Israelite forces as well. The expedition also established his reputation as a cruel and merciless opponent, a theme repeated constantly in his annals. A statue of Ashurnasirpal II recovered from Calah depicted him as a stern, egotistical despot. He fashioned the Assyrian army into a military machine that struck terror into the hearts of its opponents.</p>
<p class="list-text">Ashurnasirpal II was an outstanding example of the way aggressive rulers in the ancient world treated their enemies. In his annals he boasted: “The heads of their warriors I cut off, and I formed them into a pillar over against their city. . . . I flayed all the chief men . . . and I covered the pillar with their skins; some I walled up within the pillar, some I impaled upon the pillar on stakes.” Other atrocities included burning captives alive; mutilating prisoners by hacking off hands, noses, or ears; gouging out eyes; disemboweling pregnant women; and leaving prisoners in the desert to die of thirst.</p>
<p class="list-text">Ashurnasirpal II made Calah (Nimrud) his capital city, employing more than 50,000 prisoners in the work of reconstruction. A. H. Layard, excavating Nimrud in 1845, uncovered the royal palace with its colossal statuary. Ashurnasirpal II was succeeded in 859 <span class="era">BC</span> by his son Shalmaneser III, who reigned for 35 years. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=AssyriaAssyrians_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Assyria, Assyrians</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>