<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Laver">
  <title>Laver*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LAVER*</p>
<p class="fl">Basin filled with water that the priests used to wash their hands and feet before entering the Holy Place and before returning to serve at the altar (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.17-21">Ex 30:17-21</a>). In Solomon’s temple a large laver called the “molten sea” was placed between the altar of burnt offerings in the courtyard and the entrance to the inner temple. This consisted of the large basin and the pedestal on which it sat (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.18">Ex 30:18</a>); it was made of bronze or brass, melted and shaped from mirrors of highly polished metal given by Israelite women (<a href="?bref=Exod.38.8">38:8</a>).</p>
<p>In Solomon’s temple, in addition to the molten sea (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.23">1 Kgs 7:23</a>), there were ten smaller lavers, five on the north and five on the south sides of the sanctuary (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.38-39">1 Kgs 7:38-39</a>). Each held 40 baths (320–440 gallons, or 1,211.2–1,665.4 liters), one-fiftieth the capacity of the large laver. The lavishly decorated molten sea was used for the ablutions of the priests, while the ten lavers were no doubt used for the sacrifices (<a href="?bref=2Chr.4.6">2 Chr 4:6</a>). Later King Ahaz, possibly for religious or financial reasons, severed the lavers from their bases and the sea from its base, placing it on a stone pediment (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.17">2 Kgs 16:17</a>). The prophet Jeremiah, during King Jehoiakim’s reign, predicted that the molten sea and the bases would be carried into Babylon (<a href="?bref=Jer.27.19-22">Jer 27:19-22</a>), which in fact happened, according to <a href="?bref=Jer.52.17">Jeremiah 52:17</a>. No mention is made of the ten small lavers, which were perhaps already melted down and sold.</p>
<p>In Ezekiel’s description of the temple to come (<a href="?bref=Ezek.40.1-42.20">Ez 40–42</a>), there is no mention of a laver or molten sea. The apostle John, however, in <a href="?bref=Rev.4.6">Revelation 4:6</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.15.2">15:2</a> mentions a “sea of glass,” perhaps reminiscent of Solomon’s molten sea.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BronzeSea_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bronze Sea</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>