<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Lazarus">
  <title>Lazarus</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LAZARUS</p>
<p class="list">1. Lazarus the beggar. In one of Jesus’ most familiar parables (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.19-31">Lk 16:19-31</a>), he contrasted the earthly circumstances of a beggar named Lazarus with that of a nameless rich man. From the adjective for “rich” in the Latin Vulgate, the rich man came to be called in English “Dives.” The rich man relished the luxury of his wealth, while he ignored an ulcerated blind beggar lying at his gate. Jesus said that Lazarus died and went to Abraham’s bosom, while Dives suffered everlasting torment.</p>
<p class="list-text">The parable of Lazarus has been misinterpreted sometimes as a condemnation of wealth instead of a warning against enjoyment of wealth without regard for the poor. It teaches that decisions in the present life determine eternal destiny.</p>
<p class="list-text">In no other parable did Jesus identify a character by name. Some Bible students have therefore concluded that he was telling a true story. The name’s symbolism, however, seems to account for its use, since Lazarus was cast in the role of one “whom God helped.” In the Middle Ages the beggar Lazarus was venerated as the patron saint of lepers. Leper hospitals were called lazar-houses.</p>
<p class="list">2. Lazarus of Bethany. Jesus performed the most spectacular of all his miracles (excluding his own resurrection) when he restored Lazarus of Bethany to life four days after death. Lazarus lived with his two sisters, Mary and Martha. They were among Jesus’ most intimate friends (<a href="?bref=John.11.3-5,36">Jn 11:3-5, 36</a>). On several occasions he visited in their home, which also served as his headquarters during his final week on earth (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.17">Mt 21:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.38-42">Lk 10:38-42</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.1-12.11">Jn 11:1–12:11</a>). Lazarus was at the banquet in Jesus’ honor when Mary anointed Jesus’ feet with costly ointment (<a href="?bref=John.12.1-3">Jn 12:1-3</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The raising of Lazarus, the climax of the signs in John’s Gospel, receives the fullest treatment of Jesus’ miracles. It produced three notable results: (1) many Jews in the vicinity of Jerusalem believed in Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.11.45">Jn 11:45</a>) and some weeks later escorted him into the city (<a href="?bref=John.12.17-18">12:17-18</a>); (2) the Jewish leaders, hardened in their rejection of Jesus, resolved that he must die (<a href="?bref=John.11.53">11:53</a>); (3) those leaders also plotted Lazarus’s death (<a href="?bref=John.12.10-11">12:10-11</a>). The miracle not only showed Jesus’ power over death but set the stage for his own resurrection.</p>
  </body>
</item>