<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="LeviTribeof">
  <title>Levi, Tribe of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LEVI, Tribe of</p>
<p class="fl">Israelite tribe taking its name from the third son of Leah and Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.34">Gn 29:34</a>). The meaning of the name (“attached”) is a pun on Leah’s position as an unloved wife: now that she has borne three sons to Jacob, surely he will be “attached” to her. Elsewhere, by a similar pun, the tribe of Levi is described as “attached” to Aaron (<a href="?bref=Num.18.2">Nm 18:2</a>).</p>
<p>Levi appears with Simeon at the treacherous slaughter of the inhabitants of Canaanite Shechem (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.25-29">Gn 34:25-29</a>). This brings Jacob’s rebuke at the time (v <a href="?bref=Gen.34.30">30</a>) and his deathbed curse (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.5-7">49:5-7</a>), foretelling that the descendants of Levi and Simeon will be scattered throughout Israel. This does not seem a likely background for God’s priestly tribe, but so it proved to be, for it was as a priestly tribe that Levi was scattered through Israel, while Simeon merely melted into the desert south of Judah.</p>
<p>At first Levi was apparently a “secular” tribe like any other. True, Moses and Aaron were of Levi (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.1">Ex 2:1</a>), but no stress is laid on this. Levi’s later position was God’s reward for its costly faithfulness when Israel rebelled against God (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.25-29">32:25-29</a>); this inaugurated the “covenant with Levi” (<a href="?bref=Num.18.19">Nm 18:19</a>). Henceforth the tribe of Levi would be accepted by God instead of Israel’s firstborn sons, who belonged to him by the law of “firstfruits” (<a href="?bref=Num.3.11-13">3:11-13</a>). Levi, as a tribe, could therefore own no tribal territory: God himself was their inheritance (<a href="?bref=Num.18.20">18:20</a>). However, they were given 48 villages, with their pasturelands, in which to live (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.1-42">Jos 21:1-42</a>). These included the six cities of refuge (ch <a href="?bref=Josh.20.1-9">20</a>).</p>
<p>Since Levi could not amass wealth, the tribe was to be supported by gifts and tithes (<a href="?bref=Num.18.21">Nm 18:21</a>); like the widow, orphan, and stranger, they were commended to the care of God’s people (<a href="?bref=Deut.14.29">Dt 14:29</a>). Since they were God’s tribe, Joab was unwilling to include Levi in David’s census (<a href="?bref=1Chr.21.6">1 Chr 21:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Num.1.49">Nm 1:49</a>). Naturally, Levi did not serve in war except in a religious capacity (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.21">2 Chr 20:21</a>). Their service pertained to the meeting tent (<a href="?bref=Num.1.50-53">Nm 1:50-53</a>) and later the temple (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.25-32">1 Chr 23:25-32</a>). Within Levi the Bible makes a clear distinction between (1) the high priest (sometimes merely called “the priest,” <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.9">1 Sm 1:9</a>), who came from one branch of Aaron’s family; (2) the rest of the priests, also of particular families; and (3) a mass of subordinate Levites, who had lesser tasks. In early days they packed and moved the portable tent of meeting (<a href="?bref=Num.1.50-51">Nm 1:50-51</a>), as well as did other duties; in later days they served as porters and choristers (<a href="?bref=1Chr.16.42">1 Chr 16:42</a>). The duties of Levi are summarized in <a href="?bref=Deut.33.8-11">Deuteronomy 33:8-11</a>, where oracular guidance and theological instruction are just as important as their priestly duties. It is therefore no surprise that Jehoshaphat later used them as teachers of law (<a href="?bref=2Chr.17.7-9">2 Chr 17:7-9</a>). Nevertheless, the ordinary Israelite thought of them primarily as priestly (<a href="?bref=Judg.17.13">Jgs 17:13</a>).</p>
<p>Later references to the lasting covenant with Levi are found in <a href="?bref=Jer.33.20-26">Jeremiah 33:20-26</a> and <a href="?bref=Mal.3.3-4">Malachi 3:3-4</a>. Members of the tribe returned from the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.36-42">Ezr 2:36-42</a>), apparently more coming from the priestly than the wider Levitical section. Barnabas, in NT days, belonged to the tribe of Levi (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.36">Acts 4:36</a>). Indeed, among modern Jews, wherever the surname Levy is found, a member of the tribe probably lives on.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PriestsandLevites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Priests and Levites</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>