<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Libertines">
  <title>Libertines*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LIBERTINES*</p>
<p class="fl">Freedmen of Jewish extraction. The only reference to Libertines in the NT is <a href="?bref=Acts.6.9">Acts 6:9</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>). Most modern versions render this Latin term with the more Anglicized “freedmen” (“Freed Slaves,” <span class="sc">nlt</span>) on the assumption that the designation is legal-political, not geographical. The appearance of Libertines with groups from various parts of the empire could be taken to mean that the Libertines were a group from the region of Liberatum in North Africa, at that time under Roman jurisdiction. A more probable understanding, however, is that the people who met in the synagogue of the Libertines were Jews who had formerly been slaves. Philo, a Hellenistic Jew of Alexandria, writes about Jews who had been captured during Pompey’s conquests and taken to Rome in 63 <span class="era">BC</span>, where they were sold as slaves but later released. When these Jews were set free, they settled in various parts of the empire: Cyrene, Alexandria, Cilicia, and Asia.</p>
<p>These Greek-speaking Jews, according to <a href="?bref=Acts.6.9">Acts 6:9</a>, worshiped in a synagogue of their own in Jerusalem. They could not speak the Aramaic of their Palestinian counterparts. In 1913 R. Weill found an inscription in Jerusalem relating to a certain Theodotus, son of Vettenos. The inscription refers to a synagogue that fits the description of <a href="?bref=Acts.6.9">Acts 6:9</a>. The early church found it necessary to debate its faith with the Libertines of this synagogue. Stephen, a man appointed earlier to deal with problems arising in the Greek-speaking element of the church (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.1-6">Acts 6:1-6</a>), appears as the able exponent of faith in Christ Jesus against the synagogue of the Libertines.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Freedmen_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Freedmen</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>