<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Liberty">
  <title>Liberty*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LIBERTY*</p>
<p class="fl">Quality or state of being free. In the ancient world slavery was universal. The law of Moses provided that a Hebrew slave serve six years and go free in the seventh (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.2">Ex 21:2</a>). This provision of the law lies behind <a href="?bref=Jer.34.1-22">Jeremiah 34</a>, a passage that makes two things plain: (1) what the law required was recognized, but (2) many failed to comply with it. But whatever the practice, the law enshrined the principle of freedom. After each 49 years there was to be a jubilee year when all property would be returned to its original owners and slaves would be freed (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.8-24">Lv 25:8-24</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.46.17">Ez 46:17</a>).</p>
<p>Liberty might be given a slave for other reasons. If his owner destroyed the sight in an eye or knocked a tooth out, the slave must be freed for the loss of his eye or tooth (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.26-27">Ex 21:26-27</a>). In a somewhat gloomy passage Job reflects that in Sheol “the slave is free from his master” (<a href="?bref=Job.3.19">Jb 3:19</a>). In another vein he appreciates the freedom of the wild ass (<a href="?bref=Job.39.5">39:5</a>).</p>
<p>When the Messiah comes, one of his tasks will be “to proclaim liberty to the captives” (<a href="?bref=Isa.61.1">Is 61:1</a>). OT believers thought of this liberty in terms of freedom from foreign domination. But the Messiah is concerned basically with setting people’s spirits free. Liberty is a way of life before God, as well as a state of being free from shackles.</p>
<p>In the NT freedom is sometimes seen as a literal release from captivity. For example, all four Gospels refer to the Jewish custom of having a prisoner set free at Passover (see <a href="?bref=Mark.15.6-15">Mk 15:6-15</a>). There are references also to the release of prisoners (see <a href="?bref=Acts.3.13">Acts 3:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.16.35">16:35</a>). Paul encouraged Christian slaves to get their freedom if they could (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.21">1 Cor 7:21</a>), and he personally advocated the freedom of Onesimus, a slave who had run away from his master, Philemon (see <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.1-25">Phlm</a>). But Paul did not advocate freedom from slavery as part of the Christian gospel. Rather, he emphasized freedom in Christ for all the believers—both those who are free and those who are slaves.</p>
<p>The freedom that matters is the freedom Christ gives. Jesus says plainly that people are really free when the Son sets them free (<a href="?bref=John.8.36">Jn 8:36</a>). Paul exults in the freedom that Jesus Christ brings (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.24-25">Rom 7:24-25</a>). The same idea can be expressed in terms of the truth making people free (<a href="?bref=John.8.32">Jn 8:32</a>); of course, these words must be understood in light of the fact that Jesus is himself the truth (<a href="?bref=John.14.6">Jn 14:6</a>). This is not the philosophical concept that error enslaves men while truth has a liberating effect. Truth here is that truth that is associated with Jesus, “the word of the truth, the gospel” (<a href="?bref=Col.1.5">Col 1:5</a>). Paul says, “Now the Lord is the Spirit, and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is freedom” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.3.17">2 Cor 3:17</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>The NT is insistent that, left to themselves, people cannot defeat sin. And this is a fact of life of which the modern world affords ample proof. We may earnestly desire to do good, but evil is too powerful for us. We cannot do the good we wish to do (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.21-23">Rom 7:21-23</a>). But because of Christ’s atoning work, the power of sin is broken. “For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus has set me free from the law of sin and death” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.2">Rom 8:2</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). This truth is insisted on again and again, and is expressed in a variety of ways.</p>
<p>But there is another freedom that belongs to the Christian—freedom from the law. There were many in the first century who saw the way of salvation as keeping the commandments of God. This was commonly urged among the Jews, and some of the first Christians seem to have taken up the idea from them. After all, it seems so obvious: if we lead good lives, we will be all right with God. The trouble with this position is that we do not lead good lives, for sin is too strong. But there is a further defect; namely, that the way of law is not the way for which Christ died. This is given special emphasis in Galatians, where Paul argues strongly that salvation is not by way of the law but by faith (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.1-25">Rom 4</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.1-29">Gal 3</a>). He complains of people who slipped in to spy on the freedom they had in Christ Jesus (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.4">Gal 2:4</a>). He points out that since Christ freed us, we ought not to get caught up in any form of bondage (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.1">5:1</a>).</p>
<p>In one striking passage Paul looks for the whole creation to be liberated from the bondage of decay (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.21">Rom 8:21</a>). It will in some way share in the liberty of the glory of God’s children. This points to a wonderful destiny for creation. And we should not miss the “glory” that the liberty of God’s children means.</p>
<p>There is an obvious temptation to presume on our freedom, since we do nothing to merit our salvation. But we are more than once warned not to misuse our liberty (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.1-4">Rom 6:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.13">Gal 5:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.16">1 Pt 2:16</a>). We must live as free people without making our liberty the means of bringing us into a new form of slavery of our own devising.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=SlaveSlavery_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Slave, Slavery</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>