<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Lord">
  <title>Lord</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LORD</p>
<p class="fl">“Lord” in English is the rendering of the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">‘adonai</span> or of the Greek <span class="greek">kurios</span><span class="ital">.</span> The Hebrew YHWH is usually rendered “<span class="divine-name">Lord</span>”; <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=YahwehYhwh_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Yahweh (YHWH)</a>. </p>
<p>God’s rule and authority as Lord rests ultimately upon his creation and ownership of all things and people (<a href="?bref=Ps.24.1-2">Ps 24:1-2</a>). God’s total supremacy over nature is emphasized by his being called the Lord over earthquakes, wind, fire (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.10-14">1 Kgs 19:10-14</a>), stars (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.26">Is 40:26</a>), beasts and sea monsters (<a href="?bref=Job.40.1-41.34">Jb 40–41</a>), and primeval chaos (<a href="?bref=Ps.74.12-14">Pss 74:12-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.8-10">89:8-10</a>).</p>
<p>The later prophets indicated that God is Lord or King of history because he directs the affairs of humans and nations (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.15-18">1 Kgs 19:15-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.10.5-9">Is 10:5-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.9.7">Am 9:7</a>) and he is the Lord of universal morality (<a href="?bref=Ezek.25.1-32.32">Ez 25–32</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.1.3-2.16">Am 1:3–2:16</a>). But he is especially the Lord of Israel; his expressed will represents their civil and religious constitution and demands absolute obedience (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.2">Ex 20:2</a>). The divine sovereignty was, however, Israel’s comfort under oppression and hope for the future, when a triumphant Day of the Lord would right its wrongs, punish its oppressors, and restore its glory (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.2-4,11-12">Is 2:2-4, 11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.8">34:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.30.1-5">Ez 30:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.31-3.1">Jl 2:31–3:1</a>).</p>
<p>In the Septuagint, the regular expression for “Lord/ lord/master” is <span class="greek">kurios</span><span class="ital">,</span> which in the Greek NT also is used of masters, husbands, and rulers (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.11">Mt 25:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.14.21">Lk 14:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.25.26">Acts 25:26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.6">1 Pt 3:6</a>); of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.25">Mt 11:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.8.2">Heb 8:2</a>); and of pagan gods (<a href="?bref=1Cor.8.5">1 Cor 8:5</a>). It is used of Jesus as a customary title of respect (“sir,” <a href="?bref=Matt.8.2">Mt 8:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.15.25">15:25</a>); it also retains its Septuagint associations of faith, reverence, and worship (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.3">Mt 3:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.13">Lk 7:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.14">Acts 5:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.10">9:10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.13-14">1 Cor 6:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.2.3">Heb 2:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.5.7">Jas 5:7</a>); it appears in phrases like “the Lord Jesus,” “the Lord’s Day,” “the Lord’s Table,” “the Spirit of the Lord” (who is also “Lord,” <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.17">2 Cor 3:17</a>), “in the Lord,” “from the Lord,” “light in the Lord,” “boast in the Lord.” Sometimes it is not clear whether God or Christ is intended (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.31">Acts 9:31</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.8.21">2 Cor 8:21</a>). The title is attributed to Jesus himself in <a href="?bref=John.13.13-14">John 13:13-14</a>; in <a href="?bref=John.20.28">John 20:28</a> Jesus accepts the title “My Lord and my God!”</p>
<p>In the first Christian sermon Jesus’ lordship is made central to salvation (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.21">Acts 2:21</a>). It appears that the public confession of Jesus as Lord was the approved focus and expression of Christian faith, and the basis of membership in the apostolic church (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.31">Acts 16:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.10.9">Rom 10:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.3">1 Cor 12:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.11">Phil 2:11</a>). Thus, it could become more a formal statement than a sincere expression of belief—hence, the warnings in <a href="?bref=Matt.7.21">Matthew 7:21</a> and <a href="?bref=Luke.6.46">Luke 6:46</a>.</p>
<p>From the first, such a confession was fraught with meaning. In common usage “lord” reflected the slave system and implied the absolute power exercised by the master over the purchased slave. So Paul unhesitatingly expounds the moral implications of Christian redemption (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.19-20">1 Cor 6:19-20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.22-23">7:22-23</a>; <span class="ital">see</span> photo). To Jewish minds, the title had messianic overtones of kingship and authority (<a href="?bref=Luke.20.41-44">Lk 20:41-44</a>), offending both Jews and Romans. Politically, “Lord” was a title claimed by Caesar. Therefore, it is significant that Jesus is called “King of kings and Lord of lords” during the age of Domitian when Caesar worship was mandated (<a href="?bref=Rev.17.14">Rv 17:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.16">19:16</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="LordJesusChristWrittenAsANomenSacrum"/>
<p>Among Greek-speaking Jews of the dispersion, familiar with the Septuagint, as among Gentiles, for whom “Lord” was the customary title for the many gods of polytheism, the application to Jesus of the epithet belonging to godhead was blasphemous, especially when associated with “Son of God,” prayer, praise, total devotion, and hope (<a href="?bref=1Cor.8.5-6">1 Cor 8:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.9-11">Phil 2:9-11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.14-17">1 Thes 4:14-17</a>). On every level, therefore, the adoring tribute given to Jesus was loaded not only with spiritual meaning but with positive and imminent danger.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Christology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Christology</a>; <a href="?item=GodBeingandAttributesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Being and Attributes of</a>; <a href="?item=GodNamesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Names of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>