<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Lucifer">
  <title>Lucifer*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LUCIFER*</p>
<p class="fl">Appellation from a Latin word meaning “light bearer.” The Latin term refers to the planet Venus appearing in the evening and the morning, which is the brightest object in the sky except for the sun and moon. Others have identified it with the crescent moon. It is also said by some to be the planet Jupiter. The Hebrew term, from which the Latin <span class="ital">lucifer</span> is derived, is found in <a href="?bref=Isa.14.12">Isaiah 14:12</a>: “How you have fallen from heaven, O morning star, son of the dawn! You have been cast down to the earth, you who once laid low the nations!” (<span class="sc">niv</span>). The Hebrew word means the “shining one.” It has cognates in Akkadian, Ugaritic, and Arabic. The Septuagint, Targum, and the Vulgate translate it as “morning star,” quite fitting in view of the appositional “son of the dawn.”</p>
<p>The Hebrew expression was probably never meant to be a name, but it has come to be used thus because the verse in which it occurs is applied to Satan. This apparently was done first by two of the church fathers, Tertullian and Origen. However, the popularity of Lucifer as a name for Satan may be attributed to its use in John Milton’s <span class="ital">Paradise Lost.</span></p>
<p>The event recorded in <a href="?bref=Isa.14.12">Isaiah 14:12</a> may be an example of a story quite commonly known in the time of Isaiah. This old Canaanite story concerned the morning star, who had attempted to rise high above the clouds and establish himself on the mountain where the gods assembled, in the uttermost part of the north. He had desired to take the place of the highest god, becoming ruler of the world. His attempts were thwarted, and he was cast into the underworld. This story of the minor star deity aspiring to ascend above the throne of the most high god served, in the purposes of Isaiah, as an excellent analogy to the pride and aspirations of the king of Babylon, the person with whom chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.13.1-22">13</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.14.1-32">14</a> are concerned. Isaiah states (<a href="?bref=Isa.14.3-4">14:3-4</a>) that Yahweh, the God of Israel, would give the people relief from the tyranny of their oppressors, and they would take up a taunt song against the king. Although he had sought to be great, he would be brought low; he who sought to be a god would, with his descendants, cease to exist on the earth. Though the Hebrews had no myths, illustrations from familiar gentile mythology often were used to express spiritual truth.</p>
<p>There are many who believe the expression (and surrounding context) refers to Satan. They believe the similarities among <a href="?bref=Isa.14.12">Isaiah 14:12</a>, <a href="?bref=Luke.10.18">Luke 10:18</a>, and <a href="?bref=Rev.12.7-10">Revelation 12:7-10</a> warrant this conclusion. However, although the NT passages do speak of Satan’s fall, the context of the Isaiah passage describes the defeated king of Babylon. The Babylonian king had desired to be above God and so fell from heaven. His doom is pictured as already accomplished. Though defeat is certain for Satan, he yet continues his evil acts against God’s people. Not until the final judgment (<a href="?bref=Rev.12.1-20.15">Rv 12–20</a>) will his fate be sealed and his activity stopped. Isaiah, then, is not speaking of Satan in <a href="?bref=Isa.14.12">14:12</a> but of the proud, and soon to be humiliated, king of Babylon.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Satan_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Satan</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>