<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Tabernacle">
  <title>Tabernacle</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">TABERNACLE</p>
<p class="fl">Place of worship during the earliest years of the history of Israel.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Introduction">Introduction</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#NamesfortheTabernacle">Names for the Tabernacle</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheTabernacleandItsFurniture">The Tabernacle and Its Furniture</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheTabernacleProper">The Tabernacle Proper</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheOuterCourtandItsFurnishings">The Outer Court and Its Furnishings</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheConstructionandConsecrationoftheTabernacle">The Construction and Consecration of the Tabernacle</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Introduction">Introduction</p>
<p class="fl">The tabernacle was the precursor of the temple during most of the period between the formation of Israel at Sinai and its final establishment in the Promised Land in the early period of the monarchy. A portable sanctuary in keeping with the demand for easy mobility, it was the symbol of God’s presence with his people and, therefore, of his availability, as well as a place where his will was communicated. At an early period it was anticipated that, when peace and security had been secured, a permanent national shrine would be established (<a href="?bref=Deut.12.10-11">Dt 12:10-11</a>). This was not realized until the time of Solomon, when the temple was erected (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.10-13">2 Sm 7:10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.1-5">1 Kgs 5:1-5</a>). Historical events, as well as the similarities in construction and underlying theology, illustrate the close connection between the tabernacle and temple.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TheTabernacle"/>
<p class="h2" id="NamesfortheTabernacle">Names for the Tabernacle</p>
<p class="fl">Several words and descriptive phrases are used:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. “Sacred residence,” “sanctuary,“ or “holy place” (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.8">Ex 25:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.10.17-18">Lv 10:17-18</a>) derive from the verb “to be holy.”</p>
<p class="list">2. “The tent” occurs 19 times and is also found in expressions such as “the tent of the testimony” (<a href="?bref=Num.9.15">Nm 9:15</a>), “the tent of the Lord” (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.28-30">1 Kgs 2:28-30</a>), “the house of the tent” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.23">1 Chr 9:23</a>), and “the tent of meeting” (e.g., <a href="?bref=Exod.33.7">Ex 33:7</a>). The last name appears approximately 130 times. The word involves the concept of meeting by appointment and designates the tabernacle as the place where God met with Moses and his people to make known his will.</p>
<p class="list">3. “Dwelling place” is the literal meaning of “tabernacle.” In <a href="?bref=Exod.25.9">Exodus 25:9</a> the word indicates the whole tabernacle (including the outer court), but in <a href="?bref=Exod.26.1">Exodus 26:1</a> it refers to the tabernacle proper (that included the Holy Place and the Holy of Holies). A variant of this is “the tabernacle of the testimony” (<a href="?bref=Exod.38.21">Ex 38:21</a>; <span class="sc">nlt</span> “Tabernacle of the Covenant”), which, with other expressions like “the tent of the testimony,” stresses the presence of the two tablets of the law.</p>
<p class="list">4. “The house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.19">Ex 23:19</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">The three-part construction of the tabernacle, composed of a general area and two restricted areas, was not unique. In other developed religions that included an organized priesthood there were three main levels of approach: one for all members of the community; one for the priests generally; and one for the chief religious leaders, which was an inner sanctuary, conceived as the dwelling place of the deity. Excavations of heathen sanctuaries in Palestine and Syria in the pre-Israelite period have revealed this type of divided sanctuary.</p>
<p>There is also widespread evidence of the use of portable, often complex, prefabricated structures during the second millennium <span class="era">BC</span>, usually as either staterooms for kings and other high dignitaries, or as sanctuaries. Rulers of settled communities used these structures when traveling to other areas within their kingdoms (e.g., Egypt and, to a lesser extent, Canaan). Also, nomadic or seminomadic peoples, such as the Midianites, used portable sanctuaries. In pre-Mosaic Egypt, craftsmen used techniques similar to those used in the construction of the tabernacle.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheTabernacleandItsFurniture">The Tabernacle and Its Furniture</p>
<p class="fl">The book of Exodus (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.1-40.38">Ex 25–40</a>) describes the tabernacle and its furnishings in detail. The materials used included items ranging from precious to common materials. Three metals are mentioned in descending order of importance: gold, copper, and silver. Gold alone was employed in the principal sanctuary furnishings. The total amount of metals used was approximately one ton (.9 metric ton) of gold, three of copper, and four of silver (<a href="?bref=Exod.38.24-31">38:24-31</a>). The relatively large amount of silver came from an offering (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.11-16">30:11-16</a>), which augmented the silver and gold already given by the Egyptians (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.35">12:35</a>). </p>
<p>Significantly, in God’s building specifications, the starting point was the furniture of the inner sanctuary (the Holy Place and the Holy of Holies). In the actual construction, this furniture was made after the tabernacle itself, presumably so that it could be immediately and adequately housed (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.9-27.19">Ex 25:9–27:19</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.36.8-37.28">36:8–37:28</a>).</p>
<p>The first item listed was the ark, the only furniture in the Holy of Holies. It was a wooden box sheathed in gold, approximately three and three-quarters feet (1.1 meters) long, with a width and height of two and a quarter feet (.7 meter). The supreme symbol of the covenant relationship between God and Israel, it was often called “the ark of the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (<a href="?bref=Deut.10.8">Dt 10:8</a>). Unlike contemporary arks in some neighboring countries, it contained no representation of the deity, only the Ten Commandments (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.16">Ex 25:16</a>), a jar of manna (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.33">16:33</a>), and Aaron’s rod (<a href="?bref=Num.17.10">Nm 17:10</a>)—all symbolic of various aspects of God’s provision (see <a href="?bref=Heb.9.4">Heb 9:4</a>).</p>
<p>The ark was transported by two poles that passed through rings attached to each lower corner (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.13-15">Ex 25:13-15</a>). These poles, left in place, projected underneath the veil into the Holy Place, serving as a reminder of the presence of the unseen ark.</p>
<p>Resting upon the ark was the mercy seat (<span class="sc">nlt</span> “atonement cover”), a rectangular slab of solid gold, to which were attached two cherubim. The inward-looking cherubim and the mercy seat formed a throne for the invisible God (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.22">Ex 25:22</a>), who is frequently described as enthroned above or upon the cherubim (<a href="?bref=Ps.80.1">Pss 80:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.99.1">99:1</a>). The noun “mercy seat” comes from a verb meaning “to make atonement.” The mercy seat was sprinkled with blood at the climax of the annual Day of Atonement (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.14">Lv 16:14</a>). The fact that the ark was placed <span class="ital">under</span> the mercy seat (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.21">Ex 25:21</a>) signifies that the law was under God’s protection and explains the references to the ark as his footstool (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.132.7">Ps 132:7</a>). Like the cherubim in the Garden of Eden (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.24">Gn 3:24</a>), those in the Holy of Holies probably had a similar protective function. In the ancient world, symbolic winged creatures like the cherubim were frequently placed as guardians of thrones and important buildings.</p>
<p>Like the ark, the portable table of the bread of the Presence (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.30">Ex 25:30</a>) was made of acacia wood overlaid with gold. It was marginally smaller, with a length of three feet (.9 meter), a width of one and a half feet (.5 meter) and a height of two and a quarter feet (.7 meter). The various auxiliary vessels and implements are detailed (v <a href="?bref=Exod.25.29">29</a>); presumably the dishes would be used for carrying the bread. On each Sabbath day, 12 loaves, symbolizing God’s provision for the 12 tribes of Israel, were placed in two rows on the table (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.5-9">Lv 24:5-9</a>). The table was located in the Holy Place, on the north side.</p>
<p>On the south side was the seven-branched golden lampstand (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.31-39">Ex 25:31-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.37.17-24">37:17-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.40.24">40:24</a>). It was the most impressive item of furniture in the Holy Place; like the cherubim and the mercy seat, it was made of pure gold. Six golden branches, three on either side, extended from a central shaft, and the whole lampstand was ornamented with almond flowers. From the biblical evidence, it is not clear whether the lampstand gave continuous illumination (<a href="?bref=Exod.27.20">Ex 27:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.24.2">Lv 24:2</a>) or night light only (<a href="?bref=1Sam.3.3">1 Sm 3:3</a> in most versions). <a href="?bref=Lev.24.4">Leviticus 24:4</a> strongly supports the former, and the reference in 1 Samuel probably reflects the laxity that had crept in during the period of the judges. In Scripture, the golden lampstand symbolizes the continuing witness of the covenant community (<a href="?bref=Zech.4.1-7">Zec 4:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.2.1">Rv 2:1</a>). The precise attention to the smallest detail is well illustrated in the listing of the supplementary items, all made of pure gold, required for the servicing of the lamps. Without this precise attention, the light would soon grow dim, and the sanctuary itself be defiled by carbon deposits (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.38">Ex 25:38</a>). Moreover, only the best-quality olive oil was used, thus ensuring the brightest possible light (<a href="?bref=Exod.27.20">27:20</a>).</p>
<p>The altar of incense (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.1-10">Ex 30:1-10</a>) may have been deliberately played down to give greater prominence to the sacrificial altar in the outer court, which is frequently referred to as <span class="ital">“the</span> altar.” In order to distinguish the altar of incense from the bronze altar of sacrifice, the former was called “the golden altar” (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.5">40:5</a>). The altar of incense was located in the Holy Place, immediately opposite the ark in the Holy of Holies but just outside the veil, between the table of the bread of the Presence and the lampstand. Made of acacia wood overlaid with gold, it was 18 inches (45.7 centimeters) square and 3 feet (.9 meter) high, with horns and a golden molding around the four sides. Like the ark, it was made readily portable by the provision of rings and carrying poles. The altar was used for the offering of incense every morning and evening and for anointing the horns for the yearly atonement (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.7-10">30:7-10</a>). The incense from a special recipe was forbidden for secular use. Originally, incense indicated something that ascended from a sacrifice, a pleasing aroma to God. Incense acknowledged God in worship (<a href="?bref=Mal.1.11">Mal 1:11</a>) and at an early date signified the prayers of the godly (<a href="?bref=Ps.141.2">Ps 141:2</a>). It also concealed God from human eyes (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.13">Lv 16:13</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheTabernacleProper">The Tabernacle Proper</p>
<p class="fl">The tabernacle was fundamentally a tent structure supported on a rigid framework. As with most of the other items, a triplication of detail underlines the importance of the tabernacle proper. The specifications are given in <a href="?bref=Exod.26.1-37">Exodus 26</a>, the construction in <a href="?bref=Exod.36.8-38">Exodus 36:8-38</a>, and the final erection in <a href="?bref=Exod.40.16-19">Exodus 40:16-19</a>. The overall dimensions were approximately 45 feet (13.7 meters) long, 15 feet (4.6 meters) wide, and 15 feet high.</p>
<p>The basic framework was a series of upright supports, each 15 feet (4.6 meters) high and 2½ feet (.7 meters) wide, and each standing on two silver bases (<a href="?bref=Exod.26.15-25">Ex 26:15-25</a>). Scholars used to think these supports or frames were solid planks of acacia wood, but most modern scholars accept that each comprised two upright sides connected by horizontal pieces like a ladder. Such sections would be considerably stronger, would keep their shape better, and would allow a view of the beautiful inner layer of curtains from within the sanctuary. On the south and north sides were 20 such frames, with 6 more at the western end. In addition, on the western side were two corner pieces to which all the walls were attached by clasps (vv <a href="?bref=Exod.26.23-25">23-25</a>). A series of bars, which passed through gold rings attached to each upright frame, provided further security and alignment (vv <a href="?bref=Exod.26.26-29">26-29</a>). There were five such bars on each of the three sides. The central one on both the south and the north sides extended the entire length; the other four probably extended halfway, so that each frame was effectively secured by three bars. All the wooden sections were sheathed in gold.</p>
<p>Over this framework several layers of coverings formed the top, sides, and back of the tabernacle. The first layer of ten linen curtains was dyed blue, purple, and scarlet, and embroidered with cherubim (<a href="?bref=Exod.26.1-6">Ex 26:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.36.8-13">36:8-13</a>). Each measured 42 feet by 6 feet (12.8 meters by 1.8 meters). Pairs joined along their length formed five sets of curtains. The two large curtains were themselves attached with 50 golden clasps that passed through a similar number of loops in each. Probably the curtains were stretched over the structure like a tablecloth.</p>
<p>Eleven curtains or tarpaulins of goat hair, each 45 feet by 6 feet (13.7 meters by 1.8 meters), formed the next layer. These were divided into two sets by joining together five and six curtains respectively, and were linked using a similar method as the under curtain, except that bronze clasps instead of gold were used. The extra length of the goat-hair tarpaulins provided an overlap to protect the under curtain, and the larger tarpaulin overlapped at both the front and the rear of the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.26.7-9,12-13">Ex 26:7-9, 12-13</a>). Two further layers ensured complete weatherproofing, one of ram’s skins dyed red and one of goatskins.</p>
<p>A veil made of the same material as the under curtaining divided the sanctuary and hung under the golden clasps that joined the two curtains, supported by four pillars of acacia wood plated with gold and resting in silver bases. The cherubim on both the veil and the curtains were symbolic guardians of the sanctuary. The positioning of the veil made the Holy of Holies a perfect cube of 15 feet (4.6 meters). The layers of overlapping material and the attention given to the joints emphasizes the darkness of the innermost shrine. God was surrounded by darkness, carefully isolated from any unauthorized sight (<a href="?bref=Ps.97.2">Ps 97:2</a>). The Holy Place occupied an area 30 feet by 15 feet (9.1 meters by 4.6 meters), exactly twice the area of the Holy of Holies. A screen made from the same fabric as the main curtain stood between the Holy Place and the outer court and hung from golden hooks on five posts of acacia wood, overlaid with gold and resting on bronze sockets. There is no mention of embroidered seraphim on this section, which formed the tabernacle’s eastern wall.</p>
<p>The tabernacle, while probably having a somewhat squat appearance suggestive of strength, could be easily dismantled, transported, and reassembled. By the standards of that age, it was a fit dwelling place for God, constructed by the best human skills and the highest quality materials.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheOuterCourtandItsFurnishings">The Outer Court and Its Furnishings</p>
<p class="fl">The court of the tabernacle was a rectangle 150 feet (45.7 meters) long on the north and south sides and 75 feet (22.9 meters) wide on the east and west (<a href="?bref=Exod.27.9-18">Ex 27:9-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.38.9-19">38:9-19</a>). The tabernacle itself was at the western end. Curtains of fine-twined linen 7½ feet (2.3 meters) high screened the entire tabernacle area. In the eastern section, there was a central entrance, 30 feet (9.1 meters) wide. An embroidered curtain of the same height screened this doorway, which was probably recessed to facilitate entrance on either side. Silver rods supported all the curtains. These rods passed through silver hooks attached to the silver-plated posts that rested on bronze bases (<a href="?bref=Exod.38.17">38:17</a>).</p>
<p>The altar of burnt offering (<a href="?bref=Exod.27.1-8">Ex 27:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.38.1-7">38:1-7</a>), at the eastern end of the court adjacent to the entrance (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.29">40:29</a>), was a reminder that there could be no approach to God except by the place of sacrifice. Seven feet (2.1 meters) square and four and a half feet (1.4 meters) high, it was small in comparison to the gigantic altar in Solomon’s temple (<a href="?bref=2Chr.4.1">2 Chr 4:1</a>). Basically, it was a hollow wooden framework overlaid with bronze, light enough to be carried on bronze-plated poles that passed through bronze rings at each corner. The grating (<a href="?bref=Exod.27.4-5">Ex 27:4-5</a>) was probably inside the altar at the middle, although some scholars believe that it extended around the lower, outer sides of the altar, to provide draft and to allow the sacrificial blood to flow to the base of the altar. The horns, possibly symbolizing the sacrificial victims, could be used to tether the animals about to be sacrificed. In Israel, a person could claim sanctuary by clinging to the horns of the altar (e.g., <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.50">1 Kgs 1:50</a>), with the possible symbolism that he was offering himself as a sacrifice to God and so claiming his protection. The lower part of the altar may have been partly filled with earth to absorb the blood (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.24">Ex 20:24</a>). All the accessories were bronze: ash buckets, shovels for removing the ashes and filling the base with earth, basins for the blood, carcass hooks, and fire pans (<a href="?bref=Exod.27.3">27:3</a>).</p>
<p>No specifications concerning the size of the laver (<span class="sc">nlt</span> “washbasin”) have survived (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.17-20">Ex 30:17-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.38.8">38:8</a>). It was made from the mirrors of the women who served at the entrance to the court. The laver stood between the altar of sacrifice and the tabernacle. Failure to wash at the laver prior to ministering was punishable by death—a solemn reminder of the need for cleanliness and obedience before undertaking any task for God. The bronze pedestal may have been merely a support for the laver, but possibly it incorporated a lower basin in which the priests could wash their feet.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheConstructionandConsecrationoftheTabernacle">The Construction and Consecration of the Tabernacle</p>
<p class="fl">The God-given specifications required skills beyond the capabilities of Moses and Aaron. Prominent in the construction were Bezalel and Oholiab (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.1-11">Ex 30:1-11</a>), with a large supporting group of experts, who must have learned their craftsmanship in Egypt. In a remarkable community effort, the Israelites gave so generously that the flow of gifts had to be stopped (<a href="?bref=Exod.35.20-24">35:20-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.36.4-7">36:4-7</a>). In addition, many gave of their special skills (<a href="?bref=Exod.35.25-29">35:25-29</a>).</p>
<p>When all the items had been completed and placed in position (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.1-33">Ex 40:1-33</a>), every piece except the mercy seat and the cherubim was anointed with special oil (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.22-33">30:22-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.40.9-11">40:9-11</a>) and symbolically consecrated for its particular function. The climax came when the glory of the Lord filled the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.34">40:34</a>). He came to be present among his people, and thereafter the cloud by day and fire by night provided reassurance concerning his presence and guidance. Yet there could be no laxity in approaching him, and even Moses was excluded from the Holy of Holies. The tabernacle was erected exactly one year after the deliverance from Egypt and a mere nine months after the Sinai revelation.</p>
<p>Thereafter, when Israel camped, the Levites surrounded the tabernacle on three sides (<a href="?bref=Num.1.53">Nm 1:53</a>), with the families of Moses and Aaron occupying the remaining eastern side (<a href="?bref=Num.3.14-38">Nm 3:14-38</a>). This prevented any unauthorized intrusion into the sacred area. When the tabernacle was moved, the dismantlement was carefully regulated (<a href="?bref=Num.4.5-15">4:5-15</a>). The Kohathites were responsible for transporting the more sacred items, using the carrying poles; the Gershonites dealt with all the soft furnishings, the altar of sacrifice, and its accessories; and the Merarites carried the hard furnishings, such as the frames, bars, and bases. Even on the march, the tabernacle remained central, with six tribes preceding and the remaining six following (<a href="?bref=Num.2.1-34">Nm 2</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>