<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Torah">
  <title>Torah*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">TORAH*</p>
<p class="fl">Word translated “law” in the OT, derived from the Hebrew verbal root <span class="hebrew">yarah</span><span class="ital">,</span> which means “to throw” or “to shoot.” The idea behind the word is to inform, instruct, direct, or guide. In Jewish tradition it is most frequently used to designate the text of the first five books of the Bible, also called the Pentateuch. Quite properly, however, the word has a wider meaning, acknowledged by OT usage, which embraces all directives that come from God. This is true in the NT as well where <span class="hebrew">torah</span>—represented by the Greek <span class="greek">nomos</span>—may refer to either the Mosaic legislation (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.14">Rom 7:14</a>) or a broad behavioral principle (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.31">9:31</a>).</p>
<p>For the Jew, the law includes what has been called the “oral Torah,” that is, the sayings of the rabbis and venerated fathers of Judaism throughout the centuries. Such verbal tradition, while not part of the canonical books of the OT, seeks to interpret the texts of the Law to enable people to comply with the will of God. This method has often resulted in lessening the demands in the Law through reinterpreting them. Without temple worship, priesthood, or sacrifice—all prescribed by the Torah—such compromise with the Torah’s demands became inevitable. These oral traditions were firmly entrenched at the time of Christ’s advent and were held by many Jews to have been implicit in the Torah given to Moses (cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.7.3">Mk 7:3</a>).</p>
<p>The Pharisees believed that the failure of the Jews to obey the Torah resulted in the great Babylonian captivity in the seventh century <span class="era">BC</span>. Furthermore, it is commonly taught that until the Torah is rigorously subscribed to by all Jews, the Messiah will not appear upon the earth.</p>
<p>For the Sadducees, the Torah represented the only part of the OT that they accepted as authoritative. Their tendency, however, was to deemphasize the supernatural elements in the Pentateuch. Contrary to their viewpoint on resurrection, Jesus Christ quoted from the Torah to affirm eternal life (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.22.31-32">Mt 22:31-32</a>).</p>
<p>From the most ancient days, the reading of the Torah in the synagogue has been accompanied by great ceremony. To be called upon to read from these sacred scrolls is a high honor. It is written in Hebrew by a highly skilled craftsman known as a <span class="hebrew">sofer</span><span class="ital">,</span> or scribe. The Torah is found in the form of a roll, the scroll for which is of parchment taken from the skin of ceremonially clean animals. The rods around which the Torah is rolled are usually of wood, silver, or ivory. Ornately designed ends of the rods are magnificent aesthetic creations frequently wrought in precious metals and stones. A person reading from the scroll uses a delicate pointer, called a <span class="hebrew">yad</span><span class="ital">,</span> to follow the words. Use of the pointer safeguards the scroll, which would soon be damaged by the constant running of fingers over the fine manuscript. Moreover, the <span class="hebrew">yad</span> minimizes the possibility for error in oral recitation by preventing the reader from losing his place and possibly skipping some words of God’s sacred revelation.</p>
<p>Among Jewish orthodoxy it is maintained that inasmuch as the Torah was the gift of God to Israel, the gentile nations are not required to submit to its regulations. However, Maimonides, the medieval Jewish scholar, taught that Gentiles would have a share in the world to come by obeying the covenant God made with Noah. Seven commands are commonly linked to that agreement, namely, the abstaining from idolatry, incest, shedding of blood, profaning the name of God, injustice, robbery, and eating the flesh of live animals.</p>
<p>The new covenant maintains that the Torah, while a necessary stage in the outworking of redemption, was never given to enable individuals to receive salvation on the basis of obeying the law. Although <a href="?bref=Lev.18.5">Leviticus 18:5</a> appears to hold out the possibility of working for righteousness, flawless obedience to God’s will is beyond the reach of fallen humanity. The OT clearly bore witness to the role of grace in redemption by revealing the great patriarch Abraham to be justified by faith (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.1-21">Gn 15</a>). Since that covenant preceded the Torah by four centuries, it presents an unalterable witness to the way in which God receives sinful people. A primary function of the law is to reveal people’s fallen spiritual condition and thereby serve as a tutor leading them to Christ (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.24">Gal 3:24</a>). As a sinner is exposed to the demands of the law, he or she is convicted of great sinfulness (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.7">Rom 7:7</a>) and consequently seeks the grace of God in Christ. It is clear that Jesus Christ held the Torah in high regard, the purpose of his ministry being the fulfillment of its contents. That great work of satisfying the demands of the law is reckoned in the lives of all who entrust themselves to Christ; he is the end of the law so that everyone who has faith in him may be justified (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.4">Rom 10:4</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>; <a href="?item=LawBiblicalConceptof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Law, Biblical Concept of</a>; <a href="?item=Talmud_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Talmud</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>