<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TraditionOral">
  <title>Tradition*, Oral</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">TRADITION*, Oral</p>
<p class="fl">Oral tradition is both sharply distinguished from written tradition and yet closely connected with it. Many literary traditions are based on oral traditions, making it necessary to investigate how transitions were made from one to the other.</p>
<p>In the ancient Near East, all significant events were committed to writing by the scribes. At the same time, an oral version of the occurrences would enable the information to be disseminated in contemporary society, and perhaps also to subsequent generations. It is important to realize the coexistence of written and oral forms of the same material, so that the way in which material was transmitted will be understood properly.</p>
<p>Oral transmission was very important in Judaism, and one of the strongest characteristics of rabbinic theology is the importance attached to the oral law in addition to the written Law. This oral law consisted of traditional interpretations that had been handed down from teacher to pupil. In the course of the passing on of the tradition, further explanations of basic principles were added. Rabbinic literature supplies many indications of the careful methods that were used in the schools for the study of the Law. The teacher’s main aim was to ensure that the disciples accurately memorized the content of the teaching. There is no doubt that in rabbinic Judaism the passing on of the oral tradition had developed into a highly organized technique.</p>
<p>Such care is not surprising in view of the fact that the oral law carried equal weight with the written Law. It was essential that the transmission of this tradition should not be left to chance. Authorized oral tradition was an essential feature of Jewish life. There is little doubt that in the earliest period the words and works of Jesus were passed on by word of mouth. Whether Jesus himself followed the rabbinic teaching method is doubtful, but as much care went into preserving his teachings as the rabbis used in preserving their oral law.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>; <a href="?item=Pharisees_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Pharisees</a>; <a href="?item=Talmud_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Talmud</a>; <a href="?item=Tradition_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tradition</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>