<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TreeofLife">
  <title>Tree of Life</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">TREE OF LIFE</p>
<p class="fl">Tree placed by God in the midst of the Garden of Eden (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.8-9">Gn 2:8-9</a>), a tree whose fruit could give eternal life. God told Adam that he could eat from every tree of the Garden except the tree of the knowledge of good and evil (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.2.16-17">16-17</a>). When Adam and Eve disobeyed God by eating from the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, they were expelled from the garden lest they “take also of the tree of life, and eat, and live for ever” (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.22">3:22</a>).</p>
<p>The Genesis narrative suggests that God intended the tree of life to provide Adam and Eve with a symbol of life in fellowship with and dependence on him. Human life, as distinguished from that of the animals, is much more than merely biological; it is also spiritual—it finds its deepest fulfillment in fellowship with God. Life in the fullness of its physical and spiritual dimensions, however, could remain a person’s possession only so long as he or she remained obedient to God’s command (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.17">Gn 2:17</a>). Apart from Genesis, the only other OT occurrences of the phrase the “tree of life” are found in Proverbs (quoted here from <span class="sc">rsv</span>), where it symbolizes the enrichment of life in various ways. In <a href="?bref=Pr.3.18">Proverbs 3:18</a> wisdom is referred to as “a tree of life to those who lay hold of her”; in <a href="?bref=Pr.11.30">11:30</a> “the fruit of the righteous is a tree of life”; in <a href="?bref=Pr.13.12">13:12</a> a fulfilled desire is as “a tree of life”; and in <a href="?bref=Pr.15.4">15:4</a> “a gentle tongue is a tree of life.”</p>
<p>The book of Revelation contains the only references to the tree of life in the NT (<a href="?bref=Rev.2.7">Rv 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.22.2,14,19">22:2, 14, 19</a>). The Bible begins and ends with a Paradise in the midst of which is a tree of life. The way to the tree of life, which was closed in <a href="?bref=Gen.3.1-24">Genesis 3</a>, is open again for God’s believing people. This was made possible by the second Adam, Jesus Christ. Those who have washed their robes in the blood of Christ (cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.7.14">Rv 7:14</a>) and have sought forgiveness of their sin through the redemptive work of Christ, receive the right to the tree of life (<a href="?bref=Rev.22.14">22:14</a>), but the disobedient will have no access to it.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=AdamPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Adam (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=Eve_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eve</a>; <a href="?item=FallofMan_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Fall of Man</a>; <a href="?item=GardenofEden_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Garden of Eden</a>; <a href="?item=TreeofKnowledgeofGoodandEvil_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>