<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Obedience">
  <title>Obedience</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OBEDIENCE</p>
<p class="fl">Act or instance of submitting to the restraint or command of an authority; compliance with the demands or requests of someone over us. The general words for obedience in both Hebrew and Greek refer to hearing or hearkening to a superior authority. Another major Greek word includes the idea of submission to authority in the sense of arranging or ordering oneself under someone in a place of command. A third Greek word suggests obedience that is a result more of persuasion than of submission.</p>
<p>Obedience to God and human authorities is an obligation stressed in both the OT and NT. Abraham was additionally blessed on one occasion because he obeyed God in offering Isaac on the altar (<a href="?bref=Gen.22.18">Gn 22:18</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.26.5">26:5</a>). God’s continued blessing upon Israel by virtue of the Sinai covenant was contingent upon their obeying his voice and keeping his covenant (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.5">Ex 19:5</a>). On the verge of entering Canaan, Moses placed before Israel a blessing and a curse—the former if they listened to and obeyed the commandments of the Lord, and the latter if they did not (<a href="?bref=Deut.11.22-28">Dt 11:22-28</a>).</p>
<p>Deuteronomy warns that the penalty for stubborn and rebellious children is, first of all, chastisement, and then death by stoning if they persistently refuse to listen (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.18-21">Dt 21:18-21</a>).</p>
<p>One evidence that a person is a child of God is continued obedience to the commandments of God (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.3-5">1 Jn 2:3-5</a>). Jesus said that those who love him would keep his commandments (<a href="?bref=John.14.15">Jn 14:15</a>). And Peter, speaking of Christians, calls them “obedient children” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.14">1 Pt 1:14</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Heb.5.9">Heb 5:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.8">11:8</a>).</p>
<p>Christians are to render obedience to a variety of people: believers to the Lord (<a href="?bref=John.14.21-24">Jn 14:21-24</a>; <a href="?bref=John.15.10">15:10</a>), wives to their husbands (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.22-24">Eph 5:22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.18">Col 3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.2.5">Ti 2:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.1,5">1 Pt 3:1, 5</a>), children to their parents (<a href="?bref=Eph.6.1">Eph 6:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.20">Col 3:20</a>), citizens to their governmental officials (<a href="?bref=Rom.13.1-7">Rom 13:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.1">Ti 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.13-14">1 Pt 2:13-14</a>), and servants to their masters (<a href="?bref=Eph.6.5">Eph 6:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.22">Col 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.2.9">Ti 2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.18">1 Pt 2:18</a>).</p>
<p>However, in spite of the strong stress on obedience in the Bible, such obedience is never made the grounds for justification before God. Paul declares that salvation is a gift of God that will produce good works (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.8-10">Eph 2:8-10</a>). So, too, James speaks of works of obedience as flowing from faith (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.14-26">Jas 2:14-26</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus himself, on the night of his betrayal, emphasized by repetition that love for him is measured by obedience to his commandments (<a href="?bref=John.14.15,21,23-24">Jn 14:15, 21, 23-24</a>; <a href="?bref=John.15.10">15:10</a>). He underscored this by asserting that his own love for the Father was evidenced by his obeying the Father’s commands (<a href="?bref=John.14.31">14:31</a>). The Bible mentions many people whose obedience to God comes from their faith and love for him (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.1-40">Heb 11</a>). For example, Abel believed God and offered a more excellent sacrifice (v <a href="?bref=Heb.11.4">4</a>); Noah put his faith in God’s word and prepared an ark (v <a href="?bref=Heb.11.7">7</a>); by faith Abraham left Ur at God’s direction, not knowing his destination (v <a href="?bref=Heb.11.8">8</a>); Moses put his faith in God and refused the privileges of being called Pharaoh’s son, choosing rather to identify with Israel, God’s people (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.11.24-25">24-25</a>). The greatest example of obedience based on trust in God is Jesus Christ himself. He emptied himself, taking the form of a bond servant; he humbled himself and became obedient to death, even death on a cross (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.7-8">Phil 2:7-8</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>