<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="OfferingsandSacrifices">
  <title>Offerings and Sacrifices</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OFFERINGS AND SACRIFICES</p>
<p class="fl">Major ritual expressions of religious life with accompanying rites, such as libations, effusions, and sacred meals. The ideology expressed in Israel’s ritual complex made its religion unique in the ancient Near East. The concepts of OT ritual also underlie NT theology with regard to sin and reconciliation to God through the atoning death of Jesus Christ.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PerformanceandOrderofSacrifices">Performance and Order of Sacrifices</p>
<p class="fl">The main source for a description of the correct performance of sacrificial ritual is the opening section of Leviticus (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.1-7.38">Lv 1–7</a>). It consists of two separate parts. The first (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.1-6.7">1:1–6:7</a>) is didactic, dealing with two categories of sacrifice: those of a “pleasing odor,” namely, the burnt (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.1-17">1:1-17</a>), the grain (<a href="?bref=Lev.2.1-16">2:1-16</a>), and the peace offerings (<a href="?bref=Lev.3.1-17">3:1-17</a>); and the expiatory sacrifices, namely, the sin (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.1-5.13">4:1–5:13</a>) and the guilt or trespass offerings (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.14-6.7">5:14–6:7</a>). Attention is paid to the minute details of each ritual, and they are grouped according to their logical or conceptual associations.</p>
<p>The grain (or cereal) offering follows the burnt offering because it always accompanied it in actual practice (<a href="?bref=Num.15.1-21">Nm 15:1-21</a>; chs <a href="?bref=Num.28.1-29.40">28–29</a>); it also went with the peace offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.12-14">Lv 7:12-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.15.3-4">Nm 15:3-4</a>). Special emphasis is placed on burning the inward parts of a sacrifice on the altar to make a “pleasing odor to the Lord” (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.9,17">Lv 1:9, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.2.2,9,12">2:2, 9, 12</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.3.5,11,16">3:5, 11, 16</a>). When the Lord smelled the pleasing odor (<a href="?bref=Gen.8.21">Gn 8:21</a>), it was a sign of divine favor; refusal indicated God’s displeasure (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.31">Lv 26:31</a>). The officiating priest evidently knew how to read the signs and would tell the offerer whether his sacrifice had been accepted (<a href="?bref=1Sam.26.19">1 Sm 26:19</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Amos.5.21-23">Am 5:21-23</a>).</p>
<p>The sin and guilt offerings were expiatory (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.1-6.7">Lv 4:1–6:7</a>, <a href="?bref=Lev.20.1-27">20</a>). The situations requiring such offerings are listed, and special emphasis is laid on the handling of the blood in the ritual.</p>
<p>The second major section in this passage (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.8-7.38">Lv 6:8–7:38</a>) stresses the administrative details for the various offerings. This section consists of a series of “instructions” for each type of offering pertaining to the distribution of the sacrificial materials. Some went to the priest(s), some went to the offerer, and others were burned on the altar or disposed of outside the camp. Those sacrifices designated as “most holy” were to be eaten only by qualified members of the priesthood (<a href="?bref=Lev.2.3,10">Lv 2:3, 10</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.10.12-17">10:12-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.14.13">14:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.18.9">Nm 18:9</a>).</p>
<p>The burnt offering is discussed first because it was entirely consumed on the altar (and thus not eaten by anyone). After it, there follow the sacrifices distributed to the officiants (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.17,26,29">Lv 6:17, 26, 29</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.7.1,6">7:1, 6</a>), and at the end come the peace offerings, a significant portion of which was returned to the offender.</p>
<p>The order in which the sacrifices are treated in this passage also corresponds to their relative frequency in the rituals of the sacred calendar (<a href="?bref=Num.28.19">Nm 28:19</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.31.3">2 Chr 31:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.17">Ez 45:17</a>). This would be particularly important for the priests and Levites on duty at the temple because they were responsible for the logistics of the daily sacrificial ritual, especially on the high holidays; management of the temple storehouse was a formidable task (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.28-32">1 Chr 23:28-32</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.26.15,20-22">26:15, 20-22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.13.10-11">2 Chr 13:10-11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.30.3-19">30:3-19</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.9-11">34:9-11</a>).</p>
<p>Each section concerning a particular offering concludes with the logistic or administrative details peculiar to it. There then follows a summary of the matters treated thus far (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.7-10">Lv 7:7-10</a>), and the section concludes with a treatment of the peace offerings (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.7.11-36">11-36</a>). The latter did not play a role in the sacred calendar except during the Feast of Weeks (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.19-20">23:19-20</a>); on all other occasions, with the two exceptions of the Nazirite vow and the installation of the priesthood, peace offerings were purely voluntary sacrifices and thus not subject to any fixed bookkeeping.</p>
<p>In other biblical contexts, the sacrifices are listed according to the same “bookkeeping” or “administrative” order: burnt, grain, and drink; sin (or guilt); and sometimes peace offerings. An example is the roster of donations made by the tribal leaders for dedication of the altar (<a href="?bref=Num.7.1-89">Nm 7</a>). The information is organized like an everyday ledger from the temple storehouse; the summary classifies the animals as burnt, grain, sin, and peace offerings (vv <a href="?bref=Num.7.87-88">87-88</a>) in accordance with the respective entries from each donor (vv <a href="?bref=Num.7.15-17">15-17</a>). The Levitical scribe had two purposes for such a record: to credit the offerers and to record the treasures and food supplies coming in. Much of the foodstuffs being given as offerings was actually apportioned to the officiating priests (<a href="?bref=Num.18.8-11">Nm 18:8-11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.31.4-19">2 Chr 31:4-19</a>).</p>
<p>When prescriptions were made as to the type and number of offerings to be brought (e.g., <a href="?bref=Num.15.24">Nm 15:24</a>), the “bookkeeping” order is generally followed. This was true of the calendarial sacrifices; burnt and grain offerings and libations were listed, followed by a sin offering for each of the following: New Moon (<a href="?bref=Num.28.11-15">Nm 28:11-15</a>), each day of Passover (vv <a href="?bref=Num.28.19-22">19-22</a>), the Festival of Weeks (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.18-19">Lv 23:18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.28.27-30">Nm 28:27-30</a>), Trumpets (<a href="?bref=Num.29.2-5">29:2-5</a>), Day of Atonement (vv <a href="?bref=Num.29.8-11">8-11</a>), and each day of the Feast of Tabernacles (vv <a href="?bref=Num.29.12-16">12-16</a>).</p>
<p>For sacrifices required in specific cases, the instructions as to what offerings to bring follow this sequence (e.g., the purification of a woman after giving birth, <a href="?bref=Lev.12.6-8">Lv 12:6-8</a>). Note also the offerings given at the successful termination of a Nazirite vow; the Nazirite brought burnt, sin, and peace offerings (with some special grain offerings, <a href="?bref=Num.6.14-15">Nm 6:14-15</a>). However, the priest conducted the actual ritual according to a different order; the sin offering was made first, followed by the burnt offering and finally the peace offering (vv <a href="?bref=Num.6.16-17">16-17</a>). In the case of an incomplete vow, the first step was to offer a sin offering and then a burnt offering to renew the vow (v <a href="?bref=Num.6.11">11</a>). The reconsecration of the Nazirite required a separate guilt offering—a distinct ritual act (v <a href="?bref=Num.6.12">12</a>).</p>
<p>The description of the offerings made by the prince of Israel in the latter days presents the same contrast between the two orders of sacrifices. On festival holidays the prince brought burnt, grain, and drink offerings, but he offered them as sin, grain, burnt, and peace offerings (<a href="?bref=Ezek.45.17">Ez 45:17</a>). This second order of sacrifices in which the sin offering precedes the burnt offering was also followed in the rededication of the altar (<a href="?bref=Ezek.43.18-27">43:18-27</a>).</p>
<p>The same “procedural” sequence of sacrifices appears in other instances: the purification of the leper—guilt and sin offerings (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.19">Lv 14:19</a>), followed by a burnt offering (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.14.12-20">12-20</a>); the man with a discharge—sin and burnt offerings (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.15">15:15</a>); likewise the woman with a discharge (v <a href="?bref=Lev.15.30">30</a>). The same order is followed for the sacrifices on the Day of Atonement (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.3-6,11,15,24">16:3-6, 11, 15, 24</a>).</p>
<p>The book of Leviticus furnishes two examples of the proper order in which sacrifices were offered. One is the ordination of Aaron and his sons. The sin offering came first and then the burnt offering (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.10-18">Ex 29:10-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.14-21">Lv 8:14-21</a>). The focal point in this ritual was the sacrifice of ordination, or literally “installation,” a special form of peace offering (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.19-34">Ex 29:19-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.22-29">Lv 8:22-29</a>). The second passage is the formal inauguration of the sacrificial system at the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Lev.9.1-24">Lv 9</a>). The sacrifices for Aaron were sin and burnt offerings, followed by those for the people: sin, burnt, grain, and peace offerings (<a href="?bref=Lev.9.7-22">9:7-22</a>).</p>
<p>The same sequence is followed at the cleansing and restoration of the temple in Jerusalem conducted by King Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.20-36">2 Chr 29:20-36</a>). A great sin offering was first, followed by the burnt offerings accompanied by music and song. Then the king proclaimed that the people had committed themselves to the Lord; in this new state of purity they could now share in the sacrifices of devotion (burnt offerings) and thanksgiving (peace offerings).</p>
<p>The procedural order of the sacrifices embodies the OT ideology of how God may be approached. First, atonement for sin had to be made and then total consecration of self; these are symbolized by the sin and/or guilt offerings and the burnt and grain offerings, respectively. When these conditions were met, the offerer could express his continued devotion by more burnt offerings and also take part in the fellowship sacrifices (peace offerings) in which he himself got a large portion of the slaughtered animal (to share with his friends and the poor in his community; <a href="?bref=Deut.12.17-19">Dt 12:17-19</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="DescriptionofSacrifices">Description of Sacrifices</p>
<p class="fl">The ensuing description of the different types of sacrifice will treat them in accordance with the “procedural” order, that is, as symbolic stages in one’s approach to God.</p>
<p class="h3">Expiation</p>
<p class="fl">These two offerings were required for making atonement for sins and trespasses:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Sin offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.1-5.13">Lv 4:1–5:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.24-30">6:24-30</a>). Different animals were specified in accordance with the rank of the offerer. A high priest had to bring a young bull (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.3">4:3</a>), as did the congregation as a whole (v <a href="?bref=Lev.4.14">14</a>), except when the matter was a ritual infraction (<a href="?bref=Num.15.24">Nm 15:24</a>). A ruler would bring a male goat (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.23">Lv 4:23</a>), but a commoner could provide a female goat (v <a href="?bref=Lev.4.28">28</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.15.27">Nm 15:27</a>) or a lamb (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.32">Lv 4:32</a>). If he was indigent, he could offer two turtledoves or two young pigeons (one of which would be a burnt offering; <a href="?bref=Lev.5.7">5:7</a>), or if he was extremely poor, he might even substitute a tenth of an ephah of fine flour (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.11-13">Lv 5:11-13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.9.22">Heb 9:22</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="SacrificialOffering"/>
<p class="list-text">The offerer brought the animal to the entrance of the temple court and laid his hand on it (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.4">Lv 4:4</a>). He did not confess his sin in this act because the animal was not being sent away (cf. the goat for Azazel, <a href="?bref=Lev.16.21">16:21</a>); rather, he was identifying himself with the sacrifice. The offerer had to kill the animal on the north side of the altar (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.24,29">4:24, 29</a>). The animals were never slaughtered on the altar proper. The officiating priest collected the blood; when it was a bull for himself or for the congregation, he sprinkled some of the blood before the veil inside the tent of meeting and put some on the horns of the incense altar (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.4.5-7">5-7</a>, <a href="?bref=Lev.4.16-18">16-18</a>). On the Day of Atonement he brought the sacrificial blood for himself and for the people into the Holy of Holies (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.14-15">16:14-15</a>). From all other animals, the blood was applied to the horns of the altar of burnt offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.25,30,34">4:25, 30, 34</a>); the blood of fowl was sprinkled on the side of the altar (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.9">5:9</a>). Finally, the remaining blood from any offering was poured or drained out at the base of the altar (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.7">4:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The choicest of the internal organs, namely, the fatty tissue over and on the entrails, the two kidneys and their fat, and the appendage to the liver, were all offered to the Lord on the altar (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.8-10">Lv 4:8-10</a>). The carcass and the other entrails were burned outside the camp when it was a bull for the priest or for the people. This was also true of the bull for the ordination of the priests (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.10-14">Ex 29:10-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.14-17">Lv 8:14-17</a>). Otherwise, the priest who conducted the rites received the edible flesh as his portion. He had to eat it within the temple area, and its preparation was governed by strict rules of ritual purity (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.25-30">Lv 6:25-30</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.10.16-20">10:16-20</a>). A sin offering of one male goat was presented at each of the sacred holidays: the New Moon (<a href="?bref=Num.28.15">Nm 28:15</a>), each day of Passover (vv <a href="?bref=Num.28.22-24">22-24</a>), the Festival of Weeks (v <a href="?bref=Num.28.30">30</a>), the Festival of Trumpets (<a href="?bref=Num.29.5">29:5</a>), the Day of Atonement (v <a href="?bref=Num.29.11">11</a>), and each day of the Feast of Tabernacles (vv <a href="?bref=Num.29.16,19">16, 19</a>). The high priest also offered a bull for himself and then sacrificed one of the two goats on the Day of Atonement. Certain purification rites required lesser sin offerings, namely, lambs or birds: childbirth (<a href="?bref=Lev.12.6-8">Lv 12:6-8</a>), cleansing from leprosy (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.12-14,19-22">14:12-14, 19-22</a>), and abscesses and hemorrhages (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.14-15,29-30">15:14-15, 29-30</a>) or after defilement while under a vow (<a href="?bref=Num.6.10-11">Nm 6:10-11</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Guilt offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.14-6.7">Lv 5:14–6:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.7.1-7">7:1-7</a>). The guilt or trespass offering was a special kind of sin offering (cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.5.7">5:7</a>) required whenever someone had been denied his rightful due. Reparation of the valued amount that had been defrauded had to be made, plus a fine of one-fifth (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.16">5:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.5">6:5</a>). The animal was usually a ram (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.15,18">5:15, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.6">6:6</a>). The cleansed leper and the defiled Nazirite had to bring a male lamb (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.12,21">Lv 14:12, 21</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.6.12">Nm 6:12</a>). The offerer apparently handled the sacrifice as he would a sin offering, but the priest had to sprinkle the blood around the altar (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.2">Lv 7:2</a>). Viscera were burned on the altar as usual (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.7.3-5">3-5</a>). Some of the blood was then applied to the tip of the cleansed leper’s right ear and to his right thumb and big toe (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.14">14:14</a>). Again the priest received most of the animal’s flesh for food (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.6-7">7:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.14.13">14:13</a>). A guilt offering was required whenever another party had suffered some loss. Ritual infractions, such as eating the “holy things” without proper authorization (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.14-19">5:14-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.22.14">22:14</a>), called for payment of the sum that should have gone to the Lord plus the fine of one-fifth that went to the priest (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.16">Lv 5:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.16">2 Kgs 12:16</a>). The leper belongs in this category, since during the time of his infection he was unable to render service to God (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.12-18">Lv 14:12-18</a>). The same applies to the Nazirite who had suffered defilement while he was set apart to God by the vow; thus a guilt offering was required (<a href="?bref=Num.6.12">Nm 6:12</a>). Violation of another person’s property rights could be expiated only by the guilt offering and its additional one-fifth. Such matters included cheating on deposits or security, robbery or oppression, failing to report the find of some lost property, or false swearing or failing to testify (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.1-5">Lv 6:1-5</a>). Intercourse with a betrothed slave girl was also a violation of property rights (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.20-22">19:20-22</a>). If the offended party was no longer living and had no surviving kinsmen, the payment went to the priest (<a href="?bref=Num.5.5-10">Nm 5:5-10</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Consecration Offerings</p>
<p class="fl">These rituals usually come to mind when one hears the word “offering.” They represent acts of personal commitment that must accompany the repentance expressed in the sin and guilt offerings. They were also a prerequisite for the fellowship or communal sacrifices that might follow.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Burnt offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.3-17">Lv 1:3-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.8-13">6:8-13</a>). The burnt offering could be a bull, a sheep, or a bird. The offerer presented the animal, laid his hand on it, and killed it on the north side of the altar. The bird was simply given to the priest. The latter collected the blood, presented it before God, and then sprinkled it around the altar. When the offering was a bird, he wrung off its head and drained the blood at the side of the altar. Though the slaughtering and sprinkling of the blood relates the burnt offering to the expiatory sacrifices of the previous section, the main emphasis here is on killing the animal, washing its unclean parts, and then carefully arranging all of the pieces on the altar. All of this was then consumed on the altar as a pleasing odor to the Lord. Since burnt offerings were offered morning and evening, a good supply of wood by the altar was necessary. The officiating priest, dressed in proper garments, had to keep the fire burning continuously (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.8-13">6:8-13</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Burnt offerings played a prominent role in the sacrifices of the ritual calendar. The continual burnt offering was made twice a day, a male lamb morning and evening (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.38-42">Ex 29:38-42</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.28.1-8">Nm 28:1-8</a>). Two additional lambs were sacrificed each Sabbath (<a href="?bref=Num.28.9-10">Nm 28:9-10</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Except for these daily offerings, a sin offering of one goat was usually made along with the burnt offerings on the following holidays: For the New Moon at the beginning of each month, two young bulls, one ram, and seven male lambs were offered (<a href="?bref=Num.28.11-14">Nm 28:11-14</a>). The same were required for each day of the Passover festival (vv <a href="?bref=Num.28.19-24">19-24</a>) and again on the Feast of Weeks (vv <a href="?bref=Num.28.6-29">6-29</a>). On the Festival of Trumpets and the Day of Atonement, the requirement was one bull, one ram, and seven lambs (<a href="?bref=Num.29.2-4">29:2-4</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The great Feast of Tabernacles was characterized by a series of elaborate burnt offerings, plus one goat per day as a sin offering. On the first day, 13 young bulls, 2 rams, and 14 male lambs were offered (<a href="?bref=Num.29.12-16">Nm 29:12-16</a>). Each successive day, the number of bulls was decreased by one until on the seventh day there were only seven (the rams and lambs remained the same; <a href="?bref=Num.29.17-25">29:17-25</a>). On the eighth day the animals required for Trumpets and Atonement were offered, namely, one bull, one ram, and seven lambs.</p>
<p class="list-text">Certain rituals of purification also required burnt offerings in addition to sin offerings: after childbirth (<a href="?bref=Lev.12.6-8">Lv 12:6-8</a>), abscesses (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.14-15">15:14-15</a>), and discharges (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.15.29-30">29-30</a>); or after defilement while under a Nazirite vow (<a href="?bref=Num.6.10-11">Nm 6:10-11</a>). Though it is not stated that grain offerings were required in these cases, they certainly were for the cleansing from leprosy (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.10,19-22,31">Lv 14:10, 19-22, 31</a>) and the completion of the Nazirite vow (<a href="?bref=Num.6.14-16">Nm 6:14-16</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Grain (Cereal) offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.2.1-16">Lv 2</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.14-23">6:14-23</a>). The Hebrew term referring to this particular offering means “gift,” or “offering,” including animals (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.3-5">Gn 4:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.6.18">Jgs 6:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.17">1 Sm 2:17</a>). But in the specific sacrificial context it signifies a combination of fine flour, olive oil, and frankincense that could be made up in the form of baked loaves, wafers, or morsels. The offering of firstfruits was to be crushed heads of new grain (<a href="?bref=Lev.2.14">Lv 2:14</a>). No leaven or honey was permitted on the cakes, although those same commodities could be accepted as a firstfruit offering. They would not go to the altar but were given to the priest. The offerer had to bring the prepared loaves or wafers to the temple. The priest would burn one handful on the altar as its “memorial portion” (v <a href="?bref=Lev.2.2">2</a>), keeping the remainder for his own food (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.16">6:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.7.9">7:9</a>). But when the priest was making a grain offering on his own behalf, he burnt it all on the altar (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.22-23">6:22-23</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">A grain offering was usually given with every burnt offering, especially those pertaining to the sacred calendar (<a href="?bref=Num.28.1-29.40">Nm 28–29</a>). The amounts of flour and oil were set according to the animal being sacrificed: three-tenths of an ephah of flour and one-half a hin of oil for a bull, two-tenths ephah and one-third hin for a ram, and one-tenth ephah plus one-fourth hin for a lamb (<a href="?bref=Num.15.2-10">15:2-10</a>). Other happy occasions for a grain offering included the cleansing of a leper (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.10,20-21,31">Lv 14:10, 20-21, 31</a>; unspecified quantity of grain with a bird) and the successful consummation of a Nazirite vow (<a href="?bref=Num.6.13-15">Nm 6:13-15</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Peace offerings were invariably followed by grain offerings (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.12-14">Lv 7:12-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.15.4">Nm 15:4</a>). The priest received one of each pair of cakes or wafers. The remainder was returned to the offerer to be eaten with the flesh of the sacrificial animal at a place of his choice.</p>
<p class="list-text">A special case where such offering was used was the one-tenth of an ephah of barley meal required in the jealousy ritual. It was to have no oil or frankincense (<a href="?bref=Num.5.15,18,25-26">Nm 5:15, 18, 25-26</a>). A very poor individual was permitted to bring one-tenth of an ephah of fine flour without oil or frankincense as a sin offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.11-13">Lv 5:11-13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Drink offering (<a href="?bref=Num.15.1-10">Nm 15:1-10</a>). The standard libation was one-fourth of a hin of wine for a lamb, one-third for a ram, and one-half for a bull. The wine (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.40">Ex 29:40</a>), also called “strong drink” (<a href="?bref=Num.28.7">Nm 28:7</a>), is probably an intentional substitute for the blood used by other nations (<a href="?bref=Ps.16.4">Ps 16:4</a>). The libation was classed as a “pleasing odor” offering (<a href="?bref=Num.15.7">Nm 15:7</a>). As with the burnt offering, the entire drink offering was expended; nothing was given to the priest (<a href="?bref=Num.28.7">28:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Drink offerings accompanied the daily offering (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.40-41">Ex 29:40-41</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.28.7">Nm 28:7</a>) and the Sabbath offering (<a href="?bref=Num.28.9">Nm 28:9</a>), as well as the New Moon festival. Reference is also made to them in connection with the second and following days of the Feast of Tabernacles (<a href="?bref=Num.29.18,21">29:18, 21</a>); for the first day their absence is probably unintentional. The same might hold true for the Passover, Firstfruits, and Feast of Trumpets (<a href="?bref=Num.28.16-29.11">Nm 28:16–29:11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.11">Ez 45:11</a>). A libation was required for the rites concluding a Nazirite vow (<a href="?bref=Num.6.17">Nm 6:17</a>) but not for cleansing a leper (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.10-20">Lv 14:10-20</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Fellowship Offerings</p>
<p class="fl">These sacrifices were voluntary on the part of the offerer and generally not imposed by regulations except for the Nazirite (<a href="?bref=Num.6.17">Nm 6:17</a>) and the Feast of Weeks (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.19-20">Lv 23:19-20</a>). An offerer who had already fulfilled the ritual requirements for atonement and personal consecration was permitted to make a fellowship offering. Burnt offerings often accompanied the fellowship sacrifices as a further expression of devotion.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Peace offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.3.1-17">Lv 3</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.7.11-36">7:11-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.22">Am 5:22</a>). This is the basic class of all fellowship or communal offerings; the others are simply subclasses of the peace offering. In terms of holiness, or restrictedness, they were not so rigidly confined as the other offerings. Animals from the herd or flock, male or female (<a href="?bref=Lev.3.1,6,12">Lv 3:1, 6, 12</a>), were permitted. The usual stipulation of freedom from blemish was in force, except in the case of the freewill offering, in which the animal could have one limb longer than the other (<a href="?bref=Lev.22.23">22:23</a>). Unleavened cakes were also required, at least for the thank (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.12-13">7:12-13</a>) and Nazirite (<a href="?bref=Num.6.15-19">Nm 6:15-19</a>) offerings. Each of these three types of peace offerings will be discussed below, with their special features.</p>
<p class="list-text">The first parts of the ritual—the presentation and laying on of the hand—were identical to those of the other sacrifices. However, the animal was slaughtered at the door of the sanctuary courtyard and not on the north side of the altar (<a href="?bref=Lev.3.1-2,7-8,12-13">Lv 3:1-2, 7-8, 12-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.7.29-30">7:29-30</a>). The priest collected the blood and tossed it against the altar as he did with the burnt offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.3.2,8,13">3:2, 8, 13</a>). The choice viscera were offered up as a “pleasing odor” (<a href="?bref=Lev.3.3-5,6-11,14-16">3:3-5, 6-11, 14-16</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The priest also received a certain portion of the offering. He was allowed to eat it in any ritually clean place and to share it with his family (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.14,30-36">Lv 7:14, 30-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.6.20">Nm 6:20</a>), in contrast to his portion of other sacrifices, which he had to eat somewhere in the temple compound (<a href="?bref=Num.18.10-11">Nm 18:10-11</a>). He received one of the cakes and the breast as a wave offering and the right thigh as a contribution for the offerer. This latter is the so-called “heave offering”; the technical term developed from a root signifying “to be high” and meaning “that which is lifted up.” The heave offering did not really represent a special kind of ritual ceremony.</p>
<p class="list-text">The ritual act of the peace offering culminated with a fellowship meal. Except for those parts on the altar or given to the priest, the body of the animal was returned to the man who offered it. He had to prepare it as a communal meal for himself, for his family, and for the Levite in his community (<a href="?bref=Deut.12.12,18-19">Dt 12:12, 18-19</a>). This would have to be at the official sanctuary (<a href="?bref=Deut.12.6-7,11-12,15-19">Dt 12:6-7, 11-12, 15-19</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.3-4">1 Sm 1:3-4</a>) and the participants had to observe strict rules of purity (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.19-21">Lv 7:19-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.19.5-8">19:5-8</a>). It may be contrasted with the ritual slaughtering of animals for a banquet that was permitted at any local altar (<a href="?bref=Deut.12.16,20-22">Dt 12:16, 20-22</a>). The flesh of the thank offering had to be eaten on the same day of the sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.15">Lv 7:15</a>), while that of the votive or freewill offerings could be finished off on the following day (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.7.16-18">16-18</a>). Whatever remained then had to be burned before the time limit expired.</p>
<p class="list-text">Only three times is there a specific demand for a peace offering: in the Feast of Weeks (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.19-20">Lv 23:19-20</a>), upon completion of a Nazirite vow (<a href="?bref=Num.6.17-20">Nm 6:17-20</a>), and at the installation of the priesthood (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.19-22,28">Ex 29:19-22, 28</a>). Other public ritual occasions included the inauguration of the temple (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.63">1 Kgs 8:63</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.7.5">2 Chr 7:5</a>). Events on a national level that evoked the peace offering were the successful conclusion of a military campaign (<a href="?bref=1Sam.11.15">1 Sm 11:15</a>), the end of a famine or pestilence (<a href="?bref=2Sam.24.25">2 Sm 24:25</a>), confirmation of a candidate to the throne (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.9,19">1 Kgs 1:9, 19</a>), or a time of religious revival (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.31-36">2 Chr 29:31-36</a>). On the local level, they were offered at the annual family reunion (<a href="?bref=1Sam.20.6">1 Sm 20:6</a>) or other festive occasions, such as the harvest of the firstfruits (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.29-31">Ex 22:29-31</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.9.11-14,22-24">1 Sm 9:11-14, 22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.16.4-5">16:4-5</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Wave offering. The first portion of the peace offering was “waved” before the Lord to signify that the priest was eating it as a representative of God (the actual motion evidently resembled the wielding of a saw or a staff, <a href="?bref=Isa.10.15">Is 10:15</a>). The same technical term, “wave offering,” was also used for other kinds of offering: precious metals donated for making the cultic artifacts (<a href="?bref=Exod.35.22">Ex 35:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.38.29">38:29</a>) and the guilt offering of the cleansed leper (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.12">Lv 14:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Freewill offering. These gifts, brought to the holy convocations that took place three times per year (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.16">Ex 23:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.20">34:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.16.10,16-17">Dt 16:10, 16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.35.8">2 Chr 35:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.3.5">Ezr 3:5</a>), were voluntary (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.16">Lv 7:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.22.18,21-23">22:18, 21-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.23.28">23:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.15.3">Nm 15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.29.39">29:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.12.6,17">Dt 12:6, 17</a>). Like the voluntary offering, the freewill offering could be a burnt rather than a peace offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.22.17-24">Lv 22:17-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.46.12">Ez 46:12</a>). If it was the latter, the flesh could be eaten on the second day but must be burned before the third (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.16-17">Lv 7:16-17</a>). Unlike some other peace offerings, the animal being sacrificed could have one limb longer than the other (<a href="?bref=Lev.22.23">22:23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Installation offering. This Hebrew term refers to the settings of precious stones (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.7">Ex 25:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.35.9,27">35:9, 27</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.29.2">1 Chr 29:2</a>), so “installation” seems an appropriate translation. It had to do with “filling the hand,” a ritual act that consecrated someone to divine service (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.41">Ex 28:41</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.32.29">32:29</a>) and required ritual purity and spiritual devotion (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.31">2 Chr 29:31</a>). The details of the original ceremony at the installation of the first priest is described in two passages (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.19-34">Ex 29:19-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.22-32">Lv 8:22-32</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Atonement_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Atonement</a>; <a href="?item=CleannessandUncleannessRegulationsconcerning_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cleanness and Uncleanness, Regulations Concerning</a>; <a href="?item=FeastsandFestivalsofIsrael_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Feasts and Festivals of Israel</a>; <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>