<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ointment">
  <title>Ointment</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OINTMENT</p>
<p class="fl">Various preparations, generally of a spicy nature with an oil base. In Palestine, olive oil was the chief base of ointments and was itself considered an ointment. The OT does not distinguish between “oil” and “ointment.” In Egypt and Mesopotamia, numerous vegetable oils and animal fats formed the basis of ointments. Among the vegetable oils, some of the more important include castor oil, sesame oil, linseed oil, radish oil, colocynth oil, and oil from various nuts.</p>
<p>Ointments played an important and visible role in antiquity. In the hot and dry climate of the Near East, ointments gave a measure of protection. Widespread medicinal uses, soothing qualities, and effectiveness in masking odors made the use of ointments a virtual necessity among all classes. The OT mentions apothecaries or perfumers (<a href="?bref=1Sam.8.13">1 Sm 8:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.16.14">2 Chr 16:14</a>), artisans who were organized into guilds (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.8">Neh 3:8</a>).</p>
<p>In general, ointments were made by boiling aromatic substances in oil (cf. <a href="?bref=Job.41.31">Jb 41:31</a>). Perfumed ointments were combinations of certain raw materials with specially prepared oil. In the OT, qualifying terms such as “fragrant” (<a href="?bref=Song.1.3">Sg 1:3</a>) or “precious” (<a href="?bref=Eccl.7.1">Eccl 7:1</a>) signify perfumed oils. Ointments could be stored in a variety of vessels, but flasks made of alabaster were preferred. An alabaster jar held the expensive ointment with which Mary anointed Jesus in Bethany (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.3">Mk 14:3</a>).</p>
<p>Ointments had a variety of uses. Among the Semites in particular, ointments acquired important associations. Aaron, his sons, the tabernacle, and its furnishings were all consecrated by holy anointing oil. This compound consisted of myrrh, cinnamon, calamus, and cassia mixed with olive oil (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.23-25">Ex 30:23-25</a>). Kings and prophets were anointed, but not with the holy anointing oil mixture.</p>
<p>As a cosmetic, perfumed ointments controlled unpleasant odors. Applications were made to the body (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.20">2 Sm 12:20</a>), clothing (<a href="?bref=Ps.45.8">Ps 45:8</a>), or personal objects (<a href="?bref=Pr.7.17">Prv 7:17</a>). Women utilized ointments for cleansing the skin and enhancing the attractiveness of their skin (<a href="?bref=Esth.2.12">Est 2:12</a>). The fragrance of certain ointments attracted the attention of the opposite sex (<a href="?bref=Song.4.10">Sg 4:10</a>). Not surprisingly, the Song of Songs has several references to fragrant ointments.</p>
<p>The use of ointments to refresh and soothe guests was a mark of hospitality in the ancient Near East. Cones of ointment placed on the heads of guests and allowed to drip down over the body were used by the Egyptians (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.133.2">Ps 133:2</a>). As a sign of respect and honor, the head of a guest was anointed with oil. Jesus chided a Pharisee who neglected this traditional mark of hospitality (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.37-40">Lk 7:37-40</a>). Mary anointed Jesus with a costly flask of nard, a fragrant ointment obtained from the roots of an aromatic herb from India (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.3">Mk 14:3</a>).</p>
<p>Ointments were used in the burial process. In the NT a corpse would be washed (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.37">Acts 9:37</a>) and anointed with ointments (<a href="?bref=Mark.16.1">Mk 16:1</a>). The body was wrapped in linen garments with spices and ointments (<a href="?bref=Luke.23.56">Lk 23:56</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.40">Jn 19:40</a>). Both the Jews and the Romans utilized nard for burials. A mixture of myrrh and aloes was used in the burial of Jesus.</p>
<p>Medicinal uses of ointment were frequent. Oil was applied to wounds (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.34">Lk 10:34</a>). Balm (probably an aromatic gum) had well-known medicinal uses and is associated with Gilead (<a href="?bref=Jer.8.22">Jer 8:22</a>). Balm was an item of export from Palestine (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.25">Gn 37:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.17">Ez 27:17</a>). Biblical reference is made to a famous eye ointment produced and exported by the city of Laodicea (<a href="?bref=Rev.3.18">Rv 3:18</a>). Ointments formed an important commodity for merchants in the Roman period (<a href="?bref=Rev.18.13">18:13</a>).</p>
<p>Anointing with oil came to be associated with gladness and joy (<a href="?bref=Ps.45.7">Ps 45:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.61.3">Is 61:3</a>). Thus, one was to refrain from anointing during times of mourning (<a href="?bref=2Sam.14.2">2 Sm 14:2</a>). The lack of oil for anointing was viewed as judgment (<a href="?bref=Mic.6.15">Mi 6:15</a>). Shields were anointed with oil to make them supple and possibly to help deflect projectiles (<a href="?bref=2Sam.1.21">2 Sm 1:21</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=MedicineandMedicalPractice_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Medicine and Medical Practice</a>; <a href="?item=Oil_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Oil</a>; <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants</a> (<a href="?item=OliveOliveTree_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Olive, Olive Tree</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>