<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="OnlyBegotten">
  <title>Only Begotten*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ONLY BEGOTTEN*</p>
<p class="fl">Phrase deeply entrenched in Christian language as descriptive of Jesus. The word traditionally translated “only begotten” does not carry the idea of birth at all. Literally, it means “only one of its kind,” “unique.” This can be readily seen in the way it is used in the NT and in the Septuagint (the Greek translation of the OT).</p>
<p>The Greek word for this phrase appears nine times in the NT, but only five of these occurrences, all from the Johannine writings, make reference to Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.1.14,18">Jn 1:14, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=John.3.16,18">3:16, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.9">1 Jn 4:9</a>). Three of the other occurrences are of an only son or daughter (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.12">Lk 7:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.42">8:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.38">9:38</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.11.34">Jgs 11:34</a> in the LXX). Because of its frequent use for an only child, the word often conveys the idea of something especially favored or precious. The remaining non-Johannine reference, in <a href="?bref=Heb.11.17">Hebrews 11:17</a>, is to Isaac as Abraham’s “favored” or “unique” son. Isaac was not Abraham’s “only begotten,” since he had other children, but Isaac was his favored and unique son fulfilling God’s promise. In the Septuagint for <a href="?bref=Ps.22.20">Psalm 22:20</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.35.17">35:17</a>, the psalmist, in his plea for deliverance, even uses this word of his own soul as that which is of great value. The Hebrew word that stands behind each of these OT texts also means “only” and does not carry any idea of birth.</p>
<p>Where the word is used of Jesus, its meaning is likewise not “only begotten” but “only” or “unique.” The word is used with “son” and should be understood as God’s <span class="ital">only</span> Son, indicating both God’s favor toward him and his uniqueness (<a href="?bref=John.3.16,18">Jn 3:16, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.9">1 Jn 4:9</a>). The statement at the baptism and transfiguration of Jesus in the Synoptics (“This is my beloved son”) expresses virtually the same idea. In fact, the word “beloved” is used in the Septuagint as an equivalent to the word “only” to translate the same Hebrew word. In <a href="?bref=John.1.14">John 1:14</a> the word “only” is used by itself to stress that the incarnate Word comes as a unique one from the Father. The final reference (<a href="?bref=John.1.18">Jn 1:18</a>) is especially interesting because of the fact that some texts read “the only son” while others read “the only God.” Because scribes could easily have written “only son” due to their familiarity with the other texts in John and because of the superiority of the texts that read “only God,” this latter reading is preferred. The attitude expressed toward the incarnate Word is the highest possible. No one has ever seen God, but the unique (or only) God who is in the bosom of the Father has revealed him.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Christology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Christology</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="ShouldTranslatorsUseTheExpressionOnlyBegotten"/>
  </body>
</item>