<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="OrdainOrdination">
  <title>Ordain, Ordination</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ORDAIN, ORDINATION</p>
<p class="fl">The act of officially investing someone with religious authority. Several synonyms are “appoint,” “institute,” “make,” and “establish.” In current usage, the words “ordain” and “ordination” are applied to persons, signifying selection and appointment to God’s service.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Throughout the OT, emphasis falls upon God’s choosing and appointing whom he wills. Priestly functions passed very early from the head of each household to the divinely chosen tribe of Levi (<a href="?bref=Deut.33.8-11">Dt 33:8-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.17.13">Jgs 17:13</a>). Through all subsequent clan rivalries—“Zadokite,” “Aaronic,” “Hasmonean”—this claim to inherited privilege persisted. Divine appointment through Levi was traced back to Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.4.14">Ex 4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.28.41">28:41</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.29.9">29:9</a>), claimed for the Ephraimite Samuel (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.28">1 Chr 6:28</a>), and still celebrated by Sirach (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.45.6-22">Ecclus 45:6-22</a>, c. 180 <span class="era">BC</span>). As the book of Hebrews states (<a href="?bref=Heb.5.1,4">Heb 5:1, 4</a>), no one takes the honor upon himself; he is “called by God, as Aaron was,” by birth into an inherited status.</p>
<p>The first Levites were presented at the tabernacle in the presence of the people, and acknowledged by “the laying on of hands” (<a href="?bref=Num.8.10,14-18">Nm 8:10, 14-18</a>). Similarly, Moses received instructions for the week-long consecration of Aaron and his sons, with elaborate sacrifices, vestments, anointing, and ritual (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.1-46">Ex 29</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.1-36">Lv 8</a>). In both cases, the careful preservation of these detailed instructions suggests that the ceremonies were retained, to some degree, in later years, though no repetition is recorded.</p>
<p>Alongside the priests there existed establishments of recognized prophets, or prophetic communities, sometimes with royal patronage (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.5">1 Sm 10:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.9-10">1 Kgs 1:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.17-19">18:17-19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.35">20:35</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.5-28">22:5-28</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.3-7">2 Kgs 2:3-7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.2">23:2</a>). The line of prophecy was also traced back to earliest days (see <a href="?bref=Gen.20.7">Gn 20:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.34.10">Dt 34:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.4.4">Jgs 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.7.25">Jer 7:25</a>). The phrase “sons of the prophets,” and an obscure hint in <a href="?bref=Jer.35.4">Jeremiah 35:4</a>, may imply that prophecy, like priesthood, was sometimes hereditary, but the manner of appointment and installation is unknown. The outstanding prophets were frequently opposed to the prophetic “schools” (Elijah, <a href="?bref=1Kgs.17.1-24">1 Kgs 17</a>; Micaiah, <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.5-28">1 Kgs 22:5-28</a>; Jeremiah, <a href="?bref=Jer.27.14-16">Jer 27:14-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.28.1-17">28</a>). Such men were appointed by direct, divine call (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.17.1">1 Kgs 17:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.17">21:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-13">Is 6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.1.1-19">Jer 1</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.7.15">Am 7:15</a>), though by God’s instruction Elisha was called and anointed by Elijah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.16">1 Kgs 19:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.61.1">Is 61:1</a>). Authentication of the prophet’s message lay not in appropriate installation ceremonies but in its self-evident truth; in the case of predictions, in their fulfillment (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.13-14,26-28">1 Kgs 22:13-14, 26-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.28.5-9">Jer 28:5-9</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Christian ordination is also a matter of divine choice. Neither Jesus, nor any disciple, came from the professional religious classes. In ordaining the 12 apostles, Jesus called to him those whom he desired, later insisting, “You did not choose me, but I chose you and appointed you” (<a href="?bref=John.15.16">Jn 15:16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The selection of Matthias rested upon prayer and the divine lot (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.24-26">Acts 1:24-26</a>). Paul contended that he had been set apart by God before he was born and did not receive his apostleship from or through men (<a href="?bref=Gal.1.1,15">Gal 1:1, 15</a>). Paul and Barnabas were commissioned by direction of the Spirit during worship, probably through a Christian prophet. Similarly, Timothy was first chosen as assistant to Paul by prophetic utterances that pointed to him (<a href="?bref=1Tim.1.18">1 Tm 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.4.14">4:14</a>).</p>
<p>At Corinth, various ministries of speaking, teaching, healing, and administration were directly conferred as gifts of the Spirit, who apportions as he sees fit (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.8-11,28">1 Cor 12:8-11, 28</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Eph.4.11">Eph 4:11</a>). Elders of the church at Ephesus were made guardians of the flock by the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.28">Acts 20:28</a>). The divine prerogative is everywhere clear: any attempt to obtain the privilege of ministry by personal initiative and unworthy means meets with sharpest condemnation (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.18-24">8:18-24</a>).</p>
<p>On the other hand, the assembled church “nominated” Barsabbas and Matthias before submitting the final choice to God (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.15,23">Acts 1:15, 23</a>). The believers chose the seven servers, then presented them to the apostles (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.2-6">6:2-6</a>). An assembled church, at the Spirit’s command, commissioned and sent off Paul and Barnabas (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.3">13:3</a>). Paul and Barnabas themselves appointed elders (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.23">14:23</a>), as Titus is instructed to do (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.5">Ti 1:5</a>), and probably Timothy also (<a href="?bref=1Tim.5.22">1 Tm 5:22</a>). Elders at Lystra and Iconium, with Paul, obeying a Christian prophet, appointed Timothy to leadership (<a href="?bref=1Tim.4.14">1 Tm 4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.1.6">2 Tm 1:6</a>). By the time letters were written to Timothy and Titus, elaborate lists of qualifications were required for church leaders (<a href="?bref=1Tim.3.1-13">1 Tm 3:1-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.2">2 Tm 2:2</a>).</p>
<p>The congregation of believers also participated in selecting leaders. This could have involved prayer, fasting, and casting lots (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.26">Acts 1:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.6.6">6:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.2-3">13:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.14.23">14:23</a>); sometimes “selection by hands” (Greek, <span class="greek">cheirotonein</span><span class="ital">,</span> originally meaning “election by raising hands,” later “selection by pointing to”; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.14.23">Acts 14:23</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.8.19">2 Cor 8:19</a>); and sometimes selection by group choice (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.15,23">Acts 1:15, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.6.2-5">6:2-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.3">13:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.16.2">16:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.4.14">1 Tm 4:14</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Foreordination_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Foreordination</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>