<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Orphan">
  <title>Orphan</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ORPHAN</p>
<p class="fl">Word coming from a Hebrew root meaning “to be alone” or “bereaved,” often rendered as “fatherless.” The idea describes any person who is without legal standing in the covenant community of Israel, who is unprotected or needy, and who is especially exposed to oppression. It also speaks of one who is bereft of one or both earthly parents (cf. <a href="?bref=Lam.5.3">Lam 5:3</a>).</p>
<p>Since God has a special concern for the fatherless (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.22-24">Ex 22:22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.10.18">Dt 10:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.10.14,18">Pss 10:14, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.27.10">27:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.68.5">68:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.146.9">146:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.17">Is 1:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.14.3">Hos 14:3</a>), OT legislation made special provision for them by protecting their rights of inheritance (<a href="?bref=Num.27.7-11">Nm 27:7-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.17">Dt 24:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.23.10">Prv 23:10</a>), ensuring their freedom to glean the fields and vineyards (<a href="?bref=Deut.24.19-21">Dt 24:19-21</a>), allowing their participation in the great annual feasts (<a href="?bref=Deut.16.11,14">16:11, 14</a>), and allotting them a portion of the tithe crops collected every three years (<a href="?bref=Deut.14.29">14:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.26.12">26:12</a>). Strong condemnation awaits those who oppress them (<a href="?bref=Deut.24.17">Dt 24:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.27.19">27:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.3.5">Mal 3:5</a>).</p>
<p>While the orphans of Israel were sometimes aided by friends and relatives (<a href="?bref=Job.29.12">Jb 29:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.31.17">31:17</a>), there was general failure to meet the requirements of the law, as is witnessed by the accusations of the inspired writers (<a href="?bref=Job.6.27">Jb 6:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.22.9">22:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.24.3,9">24:3, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.94.6">Ps 94:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.23">Is 1:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.10.2">10:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.5.28">Jer 5:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.22.7">Ez 22:7</a>). Consequently, the prophets never tire of pleading the orphan’s cause (<a href="?bref=Jer.7.6">Jer 7:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.22.3">22:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.7.10">Zec 7:10</a>).</p>
<p>The word is used only twice in the NT—once in a general sense to describe those who are “desolate” or “comfortless” (<a href="?bref=John.14.18">Jn 14:18</a>), and once in the specific sense to describe the “fatherless” (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.27">Jas 1:27</a>). In the spirit of an OT prophet, James declares that true religion involves the care of orphans.</p>
  </body>
</item>