<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Palace">
  <title>Palace</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PALACE</p>
<p class="fl">Residence for royalty. Excavations suggest that any city that enjoyed royal patronage would boast of a building that could be described as a palace. Royal cities had a second surrounding wall that shut off the royal palace and its outbuildings, forming the acropolis of the city. Jerusalem had the equivalent in the City of David, which formerly was the Citadel of Zion (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.7-9">2 Sm 5:7-9</a>).</p>
<p>The OT’s references to palaces in Palestine are vague—for example, David’s palace (<a href="?bref=2Sam.11.2,9">2 Sm 11:2, 9</a>), the palace of Tirzah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.18">1 Kgs 16:18</a>) and Ahab’s palace in Jezreel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.1">21:1</a>). Even the references to Solomon’s palace in Jerusalem are quite imprecise. In <a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.1-12">1 Kings 7:1-12</a> the construction of public and private buildings close to the temple went on for 13 years. Only the choicest of materials were used. But from the details supplied, it is quite impossible to reproduce plans of the House of the Forest of Lebanon, the Porch of Pillars, the Porch of the Throne, the palace for Solomon’s Egyptian wife, or the royal palace. What the situation of these buildings was in relation to one another is matter only for conjecture. Round about the whole complex was a great court of hewn stones and cedar beams.</p>
<p>Forced labor was universal in the ancient Near East. Samuel’s warning that a king would introduce the system into Israel (<a href="?bref=1Sam.8.12-17">1 Sm 8:12-17</a>) was fulfilled, and it came to full development under Solomon when he undertook his massive building program, including his palace. Solomon raised his workforce from all over Israel. The system incited Jeroboam to revolt (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.4,16">1 Kgs 12:4, 16</a>). King Asa used it (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.22">15:22</a>), and it continued on into Jeremiah’s time (<a href="?bref=Jer.22.13">Jer 22:13</a>). Nehemiah’s builders were volunteers (see <a href="?bref=Neh.3.5">Neh 3:5</a>).</p>
<p>Prominent among Solomon’s royal buildings was the temple. Apparently, it stood in the middle of a courtyard called the inner court (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.36">1 Kgs 6:36</a>), by contrast with the great court (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.12">7:12</a>), which included both the temple and the palace. The palace itself had an inner court too (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.8">8</a>), the northern wall of which was common to the inner court of the temple. Hence it was but a step from the king’s domain to the Lord’s domain.</p>
<p>The king’s enthronement took place in the palace, in the Porch of the Throne (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.46">1 Kgs 1:46</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.19">2 Kgs 11:19</a>). When he took his seat on the throne, it marked his assumption of power (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.11">1 Kgs 16:11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.13">2 Kgs 13:13</a>). Solomon’s throne in his palace became the symbol of royal power, although his throne was still called the throne of David (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.24,45">1 Kgs 2:24, 45</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.9.7">Is 9:7</a>). Solomon’s palace throne is described as one of the wonders of the world (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.18-20">1 Kgs 10:18-20</a>). It was around this throne that the high officials came to do him homage (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.47">1:47</a>).</p>
<p>The king’s daughters lived in the palace until their marriage under the care of women (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.7">2 Sm 13:7</a>). They wore a distinctive dress (vv <a href="?bref=2Sam.13.18-19">18-19</a>). The king’s sons were reared in the palace by nurses (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.2">2 Kgs 11:2</a>) and tutored under leading men of the city (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.1,6-7">10:1, 6-7</a>), until they were able to perform certain duties at the court (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.18">2 Sm 8:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.17">1 Chr 18:17</a>). Then they led an independent life and were provided for by the king (<a href="?bref=2Chr.21.3">2 Chr 21:3</a>). Amnon evidently lived outside the palace (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.5">2 Sm 13:5</a>), and Absalom had his own house (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.20">13:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.14.24">14:24</a>), lands, and livestock (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.23">13:23</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.14.30">14:30</a>). Palace or court officials surrounded the royal family (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.4-5">1 Kgs 10:4-5</a>). Whatever their office, they were called the king’s “servants.” There were those “who saw the king’s face,” meaning they were admitted to the king’s presence (<a href="?bref=2Sam.14.24,28,32">2 Sm 14:24, 28, 32</a>), or stood before the king (<a href="?bref=1Sam.16.21-22">1 Sm 16:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.52.12">Jer 52:12</a>). It was a signal mark of favor to be admitted to the royal table (<a href="?bref=2Sam.9.7,13">2 Sm 9:7, 13</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>