<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Pastor">
  <title>Pastor</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PASTOR</p>
<p class="fl">Word literally meaning “shepherd,” used in both the OT and NT in a figurative sense for rulers and leaders. Of the 12 times the word is used in the NT as a metaphor for “leader,” it is translated as “pastor” only in <a href="?bref=Eph.4.11">Ephesians 4:11</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>, <span class="sc">asv</span>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>, <span class="sc">niv</span>, <span class="sc">tev</span>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Pastors and teachers together formed a group who complemented the work of apostles, prophets, and evangelists. The titles “bishop” and “elder” refer to the same office in the NT (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.20.17,28">Acts 20:17, 28</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.5-7">Ti 1:5-7</a>), and “pastor” seems to be practically synonymous with them, as shown by Jesus being referred to as “the Shepherd and Bishop of your souls” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.25">1 Pt 2:25</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). The verb “to shepherd” is used to describe the work of local church leaders (<a href="?bref=John.21.16">Jn 21:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.20.28">Acts 20:28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.2">1 Pt 5:2</a>), and often the congregation is called a flock. It is the pastor’s responsibility to build up the body of Christ by watching over the congregation (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.28">Acts 20:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.13.7">Heb 13:7</a>) and countering false teaching (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.29-30">Acts 20:29-30</a>). More detailed information regarding the duties and responsibilities of pastors is found in Paul’s letters to Timothy and Titus, which have come to be called the Pastoral Letters.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Bishop_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bishop</a>; <a href="?item=DeaconDeaconess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Deacon, Deaconess</a>; <a href="?item=Elder_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Elder</a>; <a href="?item=Presbyter_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Presbyter</a>; <a href="?item=Shepherd_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shepherd</a>; <a href="?item=SpiritualGifts_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Spiritual Gifts</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>