<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Path">
  <title>Path</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PATH</p>
<p class="fl">A worn track or road. “Path(s)” and “pathway(s)” are used to translate a variety of words used in the Bible: (1) a well-trodden and much-used roadway (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.17">Gn 49:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.16.11">Pss 16:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.139.3">139:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.2.8,19">Prv 2:8, 19</a>); (2) a thoroughfare or highway (<a href="?bref=Isa.59.7">Is 59:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.8">Jl 2:8</a>); (3) a beaten track as across fields, over hills, and through valleys (<a href="?bref=Job.30.13">Jb 30:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.119.35">Ps 119:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.3.17">Prv 3:17</a>); (4) a track or passage in which the idea of flowing along is included (<a href="?bref=Ps.77.19">Ps 77:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.18.15">Jer 18:15</a>); (5) a circular path, as in a trench or in a parapet (<a href="?bref=Ps.65.11">Ps 65:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.2.9">Prv 2:9</a>); and (6) a narrow passage, as through a hole (<a href="?bref=Num.22.24">Nm 22:24</a>). “Path” is used to translate the Greek words meaning a worn track (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.3">Mt 3:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.3">Mk 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.4">Lk 3:4</a>) and a wheel rut (<a href="?bref=Heb.12.13">Heb 12:13</a>).</p>
<p>A careful review of the use of the terms “path(s)” and “pathway(s)” reveals that the Bible uses them literally to speak of a stretch of ground over which traffic passes. This could be in the form of a crooked mountain path, an unpaved and much-traveled way, or a well-prepared pavement. Biblical writers also used the words metaphorically to speak of or to describe the way human life is lived in relation to God, and how God directs, and can and does either enrich or impoverish human life. Writers used the terms figuratively to refer to human conduct and experiences in the midst of the various dimensions of human life. Especially colorful in the last two uses are such expressions as the path of life (<a href="?bref=Ps.16.11">Ps 16:11</a>), the plain (level) path (<a href="?bref=Ps.27.11">27:11</a>), the good path (<a href="?bref=Pr.2.9">Prv 2:9</a>), the path of the wicked (<a href="?bref=Pr.4.14">4:14</a>), the path of the just (v <a href="?bref=Pr.4.18">18</a>), the path of judgment (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.14">Is 40:14</a>), the right paths (<a href="?bref=Pr.4.11">Prv 4:11</a>), and paths of peace (<a href="?bref=Pr.3.17">3:17</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>