<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Peace">
  <title>Peace</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PEACE</p>
<p class="fl">Total well-being, prosperity, and security associated with God’s presence among his people. Linked in the OT with the covenant, the presence of peace was conditional, based on Israel’s obedience. In the prophetic writings, true peace is part of the end-time hope of God’s salvation. In the NT, this longed-for peace is understood as having come in Christ and can be experienced by the believers.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="hebrew">Shalom</span><span class="ital">,</span> the most prominent OT term for “peace,” held a wide range of connotations (wholeness, health, security, well-being, and salvation) and could apply to an equally wide range of contexts: the state of the individual (<a href="?bref=Ps.37.37">Ps 37:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.3.2">Prv 3:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.32.17">Is 32:17</a>), the relationship of person to person (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.21">Gn 34:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.9.15">Jos 9:15</a>) or nation to nation (e.g., absence of conflict—<a href="?bref=Deut.2.26">Dt 2:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.10.21">Jos 10:21</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.12">1 Kgs 5:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.122.6-7">Ps 122:6-7</a>), and the relationship of God and people (<a href="?bref=Ps.85.8">Ps 85:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.16.5">Jer 16:5</a>).</p>
<p>The presence of <span class="hebrew">shalom</span> in any of these contexts was not considered ultimately as the outcome of human endeavor but as a gift or blessing of God (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.6">Lv 26:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.33">1 Kgs 2:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.25.2">Jb 25:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.29.11">Pss 29:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.85.8">85:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.45.7">Is 45:7</a>). It is not surprising, therefore, to find “peace” tied closely to the OT notion of covenant. <span class="hebrew">Shalom</span> was the desired state of harmony and communion between the two covenant partners—God and his people (<a href="?bref=Num.6.26">Nm 6:26</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.54.10">Is 54:10</a>). Its presence signified God’s blessing in the covenant relationship (<a href="?bref=Mal.2.5">Mal 2:5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Num.25.12">Nm 25:12</a>), and its absence signified the breakdown of that relationship due to Israel’s disobedience and unrighteousness (<a href="?bref=Jer.16.5,10-13">Jer 16:5, 10-13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.85.9-11">Ps 85:9-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.32.17">Is 32:17</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Shalom</span> becomes a pivotal term in the prophetic writings. It was the “false” prophets who, forgetting the conditions for national well-being within the covenant relationship, assumed God’s loyalty to Israel (<a href="?bref=Ps.89.1-52">Ps 89</a>) would guarantee political peace forever (<a href="?bref=Jer.6.14">Jer 6:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.8.15">8:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.13.10,16">Ez 13:10, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.3.5">Mi 3:5</a>). Against such popular but false security, the preexilic prophets proclaimed the coming judgment precisely as a loss of this <span class="hebrew">shalom</span> due to Israel’s persistent disobedience and unrighteousness (<a href="?bref=Isa.48.18">Is 48:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.14.13-16">Jer 14:13-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.16.5,10-13">16:5, 10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.28.1-17">28</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.3.4,9-12">Mi 3:4, 9-12</a>).</p>
<p>The prophets did, however, point beyond the crises of exile and subsequent setbacks to a time when <span class="hebrew">shalom</span><span class="ital">,</span> characterized by prosperity and well-being (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.7">Is 45:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.25-26">Ez 34:25-26</a>), absence of conflict (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.2-4">Is 2:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.32.15-20">32:15-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.28-31">Ez 34:28-31</a>), right relations (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.1-5">Is 11:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.4.1-4">Mi 4:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.8.9-13">Zec 8:9-13</a>), restoration of harmony in nature (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.6-9">Is 11:6-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.47.1-12">Ez 47:1-12</a>), and salvation (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.7">Is 52:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.60.17">60:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.30-31">Ez 34:30-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.26-28">37:26-28</a>) would again return. Often this eschatological (or end-time) expectation of peace in the OT was associated with a messianic figure, as in <a href="?bref=Isa.9.6">Isaiah 9:6</a>, where the future Messiah is termed the “Prince of Peace.” Moreover, his reign would be one of “peace” not only for Israel but throughout the whole earth (<a href="?bref=Zech.9.9-10">Zec 9:9-10</a>). The OT ends with this hope of peace still unrealized in its full sense.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The Greek term for “peace” used predominantly in the NT is <span class="greek">eirene</span><span class="ital">,</span> a word expanded from its classical Greek connotation of “rest” to include the various connotations of <span class="hebrew">shalom</span> discussed above. As with <span class="hebrew">shalom</span><span class="ital">,</span> <span class="greek">eirene</span> could be used as a greeting or farewell (as in “peace be with you”—<a href="?bref=Luke.10.5">Lk 10:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.6.16">Gal 6:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.16">Jas 2:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=John.20.19">Jn 20:19</a>), or could signify the cessation of conflict (national—<a href="?bref=Luke.14.32">Lk 14:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.12.20">Acts 12:20</a>; or interpersonal—<a href="?bref=Rom.14.19">Rom 14:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.3">Eph 4:3</a>), or the presence of domestic tranquillity (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.15">1 Cor 7:15</a>).</p>
<p>The chief issue concerns how Jesus incorporated the OT hope for the eschatological peace of God into his ministry. In the “benedictus” of Zechariah (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.67-79">Lk 1:67-79</a>), the coming of Jesus as the Messiah is expected to “guide our feet into the way of peace” (v <a href="?bref=Luke.1.79">79</a>). So also the angelic testimony to the shepherds proclaims Jesus as the bringer of God’s peace to people (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.14">2:14</a>). That is, Jesus as the Messiah would usher in God’s reign of peace. Jesus’ self-understanding as expressed in the fourth Gospel corresponds to this association. This long-expected peace of God is Jesus’ farewell gift to the disciples (<a href="?bref=John.14.27">Jn 14:27</a>); it is given to them when he breathed his Spirit into them (<a href="?bref=John.20.19-22">20:19-22</a>).</p>
<p>The nature of this gift of peace brought by Jesus may be easier to explain by stating what it is not. It is not an end to tension or the absence of warfare. It is not domestic tranquillity nor anything like the worldly estimation of peace (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.51-53">Lk 12:51-53</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.27">Jn 14:27</a>; <a href="?bref=John.16.32-33">16:32-33</a>). Its presence may, on the contrary, actually disturb existing relations, being a dividing “sword” in familial relations (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.34-37">Mt 10:34-37</a>). Jesus’ gift of peace is, in reality, the character and mood of the new covenant of his blood that reconciles God to people (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.1">Rom 5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.20">Col 1:20</a>) and forms the basis of subsequent reconciliation between divergent people (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.14-22">Eph 2:14-22</a>).</p>
<p>The early church understood “peace” to be the final, end-time salvation of God given already through Jesus Christ (cf. <a href="?bref=Phil.4.7-9">Phil 4:7-9</a>). This understanding of “peace” altered the content of the common greeting “go in peace” as it was taken up in the Christian community. In Paul’s common “grace and peace” greeting (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.3">1 Cor 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.2">2 Cor 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.3">Gal 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.2">Eph 1:2</a>, etc.; cf. also <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.2">1 Pt 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Jn.1.3">2 Jn 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jude.1.2">Jude 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.1.4">Rv 1:4</a>), it is no longer a mere wish for peace that Paul extends to his readers but is a reminder of the messianic gifts available in the present time through Christ to the man of faith. In accord with this, Jesus is described as “peace” itself (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.14">Eph 2:14</a>), while God, too, because of his act of reconciliation through Christ, is known as a “God of peace” (<a href="?bref=Phil.4.9">Phil 4:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.15">Col 3:15</a>).</p>
<p>This gift of peace or reconciliation with God, made available through Christ, places an ethical demand on the Christian; it calls for the exercises of “peace” (as reconciliation between persons) within the church. Peace, as a fruit of the Spirit (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.22">Gal 5:22</a>), is to be the goal of the Christian’s dealings with others (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.18">Rom 12:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.14.19">14:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.12.14">Heb 12:14</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>