<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PeopleofGod">
  <title>People of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PEOPLE OF GOD</p>
<p class="fl">Designation for the collective group that believes in God. It is a common strand of Israel’s faith that it became the people of God because he chose it to be his own possession (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.6-7">Ex 6:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.19.5">19:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.7.6">Dt 7:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.2">14:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.26.18">26:18</a>). The idea of the covenant is linked to this (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.9-12">Lv 26:9-12</a>). In the preaching of the prophets, where the judgment of God is often seen as leading to complete destruction, there is also the vision of the reestablishment and re-creation of the people of God (<a href="?bref=Jer.32.37">Jer 32:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.2.1,23">Hos 2:1, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.20">Ez 11:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.36.28">36:28</a>). In the development of Judaism after the exile, the idea emerges that it is only the Israel of the future, the final messianic community, that will be “people of God” in the full sense of that term.</p>
<p>It is evident from a number of passages in the NT that the church knew itself to be this future people of God. The clearest passage is <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Peter 2:9</a> (<span class="sc">rsv</span>): “You are a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, God’s own people.” The expressions “royal priesthood” and “holy nation” are taken from <a href="?bref=Exod.19.6">Exodus 19:6</a>, which so powerfully expresses both the participation in God’s reign and the priestly service of the people of God in the world. Just as the original people of God were called to proclaim God’s mighty acts of deliverance (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.20-21">Is 43:20-21</a>, LXX), so the new people of God are called to “declare the wonderful deeds of him who called you out of darkness into his marvelous light” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Pt 2:9</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BodyofChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Body of Christ</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>