<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PergamosPergamum">
  <title>Pergamos*, Pergamum</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PERGAMOS*, PERGAMUM</p>
<p class="fl">City just north of the Caicus River, in the southern part of Mysia (western Turkey), and one of the greatest cultural centers of the Hellenistic era. The early geographer Strabo (63 <span class="era">BC</span>–<span class="era">AD</span> 24?) called the area around Pergamum the richest land in Mysia. It is mentioned only twice in the Bible (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.11">Rv 1:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.2.12">2:12</a>; <span class="sc">kjv</span> “Pergamos”), both times referring to one of the seven churches of Asia to which the last book of the NT was written.</p>
<p>The province of Mysia was combined with Lydia and Caria to form the Roman district of Asia, comprising the western portion of modern Turkey. Pergamum lies less than 20 miles (32.3 kilometers) inland from the sea and about three miles (4.8 kilometers) north of the Caicus River on a large conical hill, 1,000 feet (304.8 meters) high, which is sandwiched between two smaller streams that flow into the Caicus, the Selinus on the west and the Cetius on the east. This natural position of strength, combined with its religious significance as a temple site, made it a desirable place to store wealth. Lysimachus, one of Alexander the Great’s generals, deposited an enormous sum of money here (9,000 talents), which was later used by Pergamene kings to create the glory of Pergamum. Although coins were minted in Pergamum before 400 <span class="era">BC</span>, it was not a great city until long after the death of Alexander.</p>
<p>The splendor of Pergamum began with Attalus I (241–197 <span class="era">BC</span>), who took the title of king and founded the Attalic dynasty. His wealth, success in battle (defeating the Gauls who moved into Galatia in 278 <span class="era">BC</span>), and his judicial alliance with the rising power of Rome contributed to his ability to embellish his kingdom with Hellenistic culture. He adorned it with temples, theaters, a library, and other public buildings.</p>
<p>He was succeeded by his son Eumenes II, who, because of his help in Rome’s conquest of the Seleucid kingdom of Syria, was given in 189 <span class="era">BC</span> all Seleucid territory northwest of the Taurus mountains, thus extending the Pergamene kingdom from the Taurus to the Dardanelles. Under Eumenes (197–159 <span class="era">BC</span>), Pergamum attained the height of its power and glory. He expanded the library to 200,000 volumes, almost rivaling the great one at Alexandria, and he constructed the altar of Zeus, which stood on a hill 800 feet (243.8 meters) above the city and could be seen for miles. It is tempting to imagine this altar as the place “where Satan’s throne is” (<a href="?bref=Rev.2.13">Rv 2:13</a>), especially since Pergamum was the chief center of worship for four of the greatest pagan deities—Zeus, Athena, Dionysus, and Asclepius. However, it may be that Revelation is referring to the fact that Pergamum was the center of emperor worship in Asia at that time.</p>
<p>The last king of the Attalic dynasty, Attalus III, died without leaving an heir in 133 <span class="era">BC</span>. In his will he gave all of his kingdom to Rome, with the exception of Pergamum and other Greek cities, which were given freedom as independent administrative units and were exempt from tribute. In order to reduce its obligation to police, the Roman consul bequeathed the easternmost territory of Phrygia to Pontus and Cappadocia. Thus, the newly created Roman province of Asia was smaller than the Pergamene Empire had been. Even though after 120 <span class="era">BC</span> Phrygia was reclaimed by the Roman senate (upon the death of Mithridates, king of Pontus), it was not actually incorporated into Asia until 85 <span class="era">BC</span>. At that time, the Roman provincial unit was again roughly comparable in size to the old Pergamene kingdom.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="RemainsOfAncientLibraryAtPergamum"/>
<p>Pergamum was built across the centuries in three separate areas. The upper city on top of the mountain was the northernmost area and was largely the domain of the royal family, the nobility, and the military commanders. It had an air of officialdom. The middle city, further south and lower down the mountain, contained the part of the city visited by the common people and included sports fields for the youth and temples frequented by those of less education. These facilities were not controlled directly by the city and the priesthood, and the general citizenship of Pergamum had unrestricted access to them. The third area, across the Selinus River to the southwest, contained the famous Asclepian of Pergamum, a center for the healing arts. This center had a medical school that produced the celebrated physician Galen. Here the god Asclepius was worshiped in a cylindrical temple, which was a small replica of the famed Pantheon built in Rome some 20 years before (<span class="era">AD</span> 130). There was also a lovely fountain, theater, pool, medical building, library, and various temples, the striking remains of which may still be seen.</p>
<p>The references in <a href="?bref=Rev.2.12-15">Revelation 2:12-15</a> to the Nicolaitans and those who held the doctrine of Balaam probably refers to the extensive influence of the immoral and idolatrous worship of Dionysus and Aphrodite, which was especially offensive to the known Jewish population (Josephus’s <span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 14.10.22), as well as to true Christians. Pliny (<span class="ital">Natural History</span> 5.30) considered Pergamum to be the most distinguished city of Asia and as such it would have been the natural place for emperor worship. The reference to the martyrdom of Antipas, “my faithful witness” (<a href="?bref=Rev.2.13">Rv 2:13</a>), can easily be understood in the light of the Jewish and Christian refusal to worship the emperor in this city.</p>
<p>Because of the extensive manufacture of writing material from sheepskin in Pergamum, the name parchment (Latin, <span class="ital">pergamena</span>) was given to the product.</p>
  </body>
</item>