<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Perizzite">
  <title>Perizzite</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PERIZZITE</p>
<p class="fl">One of several population segments occupying the land of Palestine prior to and subsequent to the Israelite conquest (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.20">Gn 15:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.3.8,17">Ex 3:8, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.23.23">23:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.33.2">33:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.11">34:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.7.1">Dt 7:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.20.17">20:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.3.10">Jos 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.9.1">9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.11.3">11:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.8">12:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.11">24:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.20">1 Kgs 9:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.8.7">2 Chr 8:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.9.1">Ezr 9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.8">Neh 9:8</a>). The enumeration of these peoples throughout the OT serves a variety of purposes, none of which is strictly historical or geographical. It serves to inform the reader that, no matter how numerous, the doom of these people is sure when God’s time has come (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.20">Gn 15:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.3.8">Ex 3:8</a>). At other times, they are mentioned to illustrate the hostility of the enemies of God against Israel’s onward march into the land promised to them by the Lord (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.1">Jos 9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.11.3">11:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.11">24:11</a>). But they are also portrayed as conquered and reduced to servile labor (<a href="?bref=Josh.12.8">Jos 12:8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.20">1 Kgs 9:20</a>). In the postexilic period, they continue to be a threat to the purity of life of the covenant community recently settled in the land of their fathers (<a href="?bref=Ezra.9.1">Ezr 9:1</a>).</p>
<p>There are a few instances where the word “Perizzites” occurs in conjunction with “Canaanites” (<a href="?bref=Gen.13.7">Gn 13:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.34.30">34:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.1.4-5">Jgs 1:4-5</a>), and in one instance it is combined with “Rephaites” (<a href="?bref=Josh.17.15">Jos 17:15</a>). The name “Pirizzi” also occurs once in the tablets of El Amarna.</p>
<p>The exact identity of the Perizzites has thus far remained obscure. In a few instances in which the name occurs in conjunction with “Canaanites,” it seems to refer to one of the major components of Canaan’s population. Some have even suggested that the Perizzites were the pre-Canaanite population of Palestine, in view of the omission of them in the list of <a href="?bref=Gen.10.1-32">Genesis 10</a>. But this cannot be proven. Others have attempted to read this name as an appellative meaning “inhabitants of unwalled villages.” This view finds some support in another Hebrew word, <span class="hebrew">perazoth</span><span class="ital">,</span> “unwalled villages” (<a href="?bref=Esth.9.19">Est 9:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.38.11">Ez 38:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.2.4">Zec 2:4</a>; cf. also <span class="hebrew">perazi</span><span class="ital">,</span> “open country,” <a href="?bref=Deut.3.5">Dt 3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.6.18">1 Sm 6:18</a>). But the fact that the name occurs so frequently among other peoples whose identity is known should caution against such an approach.</p>
<p>Several commentators, instead of regarding the Perizzites as one of the major components of Canaan’s population, have sought to localize them, either in the vicinity of Bethel (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.13.7">Gn 13:7</a>) or of Shechem (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.30">34:30</a>), or in the territory of Judah (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.4-5">Jgs 1:4-5</a>). But these locales are by no means contiguous. The reference to the Rephaim (<span class="sc">nlt</span>, <span class="sc">niv</span> “Rephaites”) in <a href="?bref=Josh.17.15">Joshua 17:15</a> has prompted the suggestion that the Perizzites belonged to the Transjordan region, but this does not follow either from the immediate context or from the use of the word “Rephaim” elsewhere.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CanaanCanaanite_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Canaan, Canaanite</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>