<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Perseverance">
  <title>Perseverance</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PERSEVERANCE</p>
<p class="fl">Action or condition of steadfastness. OT Israel waited generations for fulfillment of promises that many believers never lived to see (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.1,13,21-22,39">Heb 11:1, 13, 21-22, 39</a>). The promise to Abraham sustained hope for centuries before Canaan was possessed. The lesson of the wilderness journey, when the waning of initial zeal prevented the people from entering the Promised Land, was never forgotten (<a href="?bref=Heb.3.16-19">3:16-19</a>). Prophets looked constantly beyond failure and tragedy to distant horizons, and they nourished a patient faith (<a href="?bref=Jer.32.1-15">Jer 32:1-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.3.4-5">Hos 3:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-29">Jl 2:28-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.2.1-3">Hb 2:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.12.11-13">Dn 12:11-13</a>).</p>
<p>The NT everywhere urges similar perseverance. Among several Greek expressions, the usual word, <span class="greek">proskartereo</span><span class="ital">,</span> has the root meaning “to attend continually, adhere steadfastly” (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.9">Mk 3:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.8.13">Acts 8:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.7">10:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.13.6">Rom 13:6</a>), and is variously translated “devoted,” “continued,” “constant,” “[be] steadfast.”</p>
<p>This persistent patience is called for in prayer (<a href="?bref=Luke.18.1-8">Lk 18:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.4.2">Col 4:2</a>); in well doing (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.7">Rom 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.6.9">Gal 6:9</a>); in Christian teaching (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.42">Acts 2:42</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.3.14">2 Tm 3:14</a>); in affliction (<a href="?bref=2Thes.1.4">2 Thes 1:4</a>); in grace (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.43">Acts 13:43</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.6.1">2 Cor 6:1</a>); in faith (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.22">Acts 14:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.23">Col 1:23</a>); in divine love (<a href="?bref=John.15.9">Jn 15:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Jude.1.21">Jude 1:21</a>); in standing firm (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.13">1 Cor 16:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.15">2 Thes 2:15</a>); in abiding in Christ (<a href="?bref=John.15.4-10">Jn 15:4-10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.28">1 Jn 2:28</a>); in running with patience (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.12">Heb 6:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.12.1">12:1</a>); in not falling away (<a href="?bref=Heb.3.12">Heb 3:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.1-10">4:1-10</a>); and in being zealous to confirm our call and election (<a href="?bref=2Pet.1.10">2 Pt 1:10</a>).</p>
<p>The failure in perseverance of Judas (<a href="?bref=John.6.71">Jn 6:71</a>), Demas (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.10">2 Tm 4:10</a>), and Hymenaeus (<a href="?bref=2Tim.2.17">2 Tm 2:17</a>) must be kept in mind, as well as the dread possibility of neglecting so great a salvation (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.3">Heb 2:3</a>), being disqualified (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.27">1 Cor 9:27</a>), falling while we think we stand (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.12">1 Cor 10:12</a>), and committing apostasy (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.1-8">Heb 6:1-8</a>). For, as Jesus said, “He who endures to the end will be saved” (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.22">Mt 10:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.13">24:13</a>). Such extraordinary emphasis cannot be accidental. The pressures of pagan society, the danger of persecution, emotional reaction after a wonderful initial experience, and the apparent implication of “instant salvation,” made it imperative for Christians to understand that by their endurance they would inherit eternal salvation (<a href="?bref=Luke.21.19">Lk 21:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.3">Rom 5:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.11">Col 1:11</a>).</p>
<p>Yet Scripture never implies that perseverance depends entirely upon human effort. In the OT, the redeeming purpose of God is unswerving; God’s covenant stands, though it needs to be renewed (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.31-34">Jer 31:31-34</a>). Divine love (Hebrew, <span class="hebrew">hesed</span>) connotes changeless loyalty; God “will never fail nor forsake” for “his own name’s sake.” The NT assurance is that Christ will raise his own at the last day—none shall pluck them from his hand or the Father’s. Christ will keep us from falling. God is faithful; he works in us to will and work for his good pleasure, and will not allow us to be tempted beyond our strength. Nothing, in heaven or earth, present or future, shall separate us from divine love. We are already sealed by the Holy Spirit as a guarantee of eternal salvation, and we are kept by the power of God unto a salvation yet to be revealed.</p>
<p>The scriptural tension between exhortation to perseverance and assurance of salvation has given rise to much debate. The intellectual paradox is resolved only in spiritual experience.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Assurance_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Assurance</a>; <a href="?item=Backsliding_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Backsliding</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>