<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Pharisees">
  <title>Pharisees</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PHARISEES</p>
<p class="fl">Religious sect active in Palestine during the NT period. The Pharisees are consistently depicted in the Gospels as Jesus’ antagonists. It is commonly held that the Pharisees represented mainstream Judaism early in the first century and that they were characterized by a variety of morally objectionable features. Accordingly, most Bible dictionaries and similar works of reference depict the Pharisees as greedy, hypocritical, lacking a sense of justice, overly concerned with fulfilling the literal details of the law, and insensitive to the spiritual significance of the OT. These and other characteristics are furthermore viewed as giving shape to Judaism more generally.</p>
<p>There are several problems with this common perception of Pharisaic Judaism. In the first place, the Gospels themselves give some important information that appears inconsistent with this view. Second, the primary documents of rabbinic Judaism (such as the Mishnah, the Talmud, and the Midrashim) are positive and praiseworthy. Third, it has become increasingly clear, especially since the discovery of the Dead Sea Scrolls, that prior to <span class="era">AD</span> 70 the Pharisees constituted only a small movement in a highly diversified society; whatever their popularity and influence, they can hardly be taken as representative of Judaism in general.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Origin">Origin</p>
<p class="fl">The origins of the Pharisees are obscure. According to Jewish tradition, Pharisaic (= rabbinic) Judaism can be traced back to Ezra and the beginnings of the scribal movement in the fifth century <span class="era">BC</span>. At the opposite extreme, a few scholars argue that, since there are no explicit references to the Pharisees in historical documents prior to the second century <span class="era">BC</span>, Pharisaism appeared suddenly after the Maccabean revolt (167 <span class="era">BC</span>). Many specialists take the position that perhaps as early as the third century <span class="era">BC</span> one can find evidence of an incipient form of Pharisaism (as in The Wisdom of Joshua [Jesus] ben Sirach, also known as Ecclesiasticus). It may well be, moreover, that the intellectual pursuits associated with the work of the scribes did have something to do with the development of the Pharisees. It is also probable that prior to the Maccabean revolt some distinctive Pharisaic concerns appeared in connection with the development of the Hasidim (“the faithful ones”—traditionalists who opposed Greek influence in Jewish society).</p>
<p>According to a popular and reasonable interpretation, the Hasidim became disillusioned with the Maccabean rulers, whose conduct violated Jewish sensibilities in several respects. Some of the Hasidim separated themselves from the nation and developed into nonconformist sects, such as that of the Essenes. Those who remained tried to exert their influence on Jewish life and developed into the sect of the Pharisees.</p>
<p>The Pharisees no doubt played a significant role in Jewish affairs during the next century, even though at times they had little political clout. By NT times, they were widely recognized as religious leaders. Josephus, who tells us that he belonged to this sect, wrote toward the end of the first century <span class="era">AD</span> that the Pharisees were “extremely influential among the townsfolk; and all prayers and sacred rites of divine worship are performed according to their exposition. This is the great tribute that the inhabitants of the cities, by practicing the highest ideal both in their way of living and in their discourse, have paid to the excellence of the Pharisees” (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 18.15). We cannot determine whether this description applies to the period before <span class="era">AD</span> 70, but the evidence of the Gospels themselves confirms it to some extent. For example, the parable of the publican and the Pharisee (<a href="?bref=Luke.18.9-14">Lk 18:9-14</a>), while it condemns the Pharisee, makes sense only if we appreciate the role reversal it announces: the wicked publican, not the one generally regarded as righteous, goes home justified.</p>
<p class="h2" id="BasicCharacteristics">Basic Characteristics</p>
<p class="fl">It is not possible to give an accurate characterization of the Pharisees, since scholars disagree sharply concerning their fundamental distinctiveness. Some stress the notion of “separateness,” partly on the basis of the supposed etymology of the name (from Hebrew <span class="hebrew">parush</span><span class="ital">,</span> “separated one,” though other suggestions have been made). A more carefully nuanced viewpoint calls attention to the Pharisees’ concern with ritual purity (cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.7.1-4">Mk 7:1-4</a>). Some of the evidence indicates that the Pharisees wished to apply the priestly rituals to the people generally (this factor may help to explain the relative ease with which the Pharisees adapted to the absence of the temple and its sacrifices after <span class="era">AD</span> 70). Still another position sees the Pharisees as the scholar class. The close connection between them and the scribes (experts in the law) gives credence to this view, as does the fact that much of the later rabbinic literature reflects an intellectual pursuit, particularly in its detailed logical argumentations regarding the meaning and application of the Torah.</p>
<p>These various approaches are not mutually exclusive. Moreover, there appears to be widespread agreement about one theological conviction that was foundational to Pharisaism, namely, their commitment to the notion of a twofold law: the written Torah (the OT, principally the Pentateuch) and the oral Torah (the traditions handed down through many generations of rabbis). This is certainly one feature that distinguished them from the Sadducees (cf. Josephus’s <span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 13.297-98). The latter accepted only the authority of the books of Moses and argued strongly that the importance that the Pharisees attached to oral traditions represented an unjustifiable innovation. These traditions, which sought to regulate the lives of the people before God, became more and more detailed over the course of time and were eventually brought together and written down as a single document, the Mishnah (dated c. <span class="era">AD</span> 210). Somewhere in its development the view arose that the oral law itself had been given by God to Moses and thus shared divine authority with the Scriptures.</p>
<p>A careful look at the NT helps in understanding that this feature more than anything else explains the nature of the conflict between the Pharisaic viewpoint and the message of the gospel. The apostle Paul, for example, stresses the distinctiveness of his apostolic preaching by contrasting it to “the traditions of the fathers,” which he zealously pursued in his youth (<a href="?bref=Gal.1.14">Gal 1:14</a>). Especially instructive is the key passage in <a href="?bref=Mark.7.1-37">Mark 7</a>, where it is written that the Pharisees complained to Jesus, “Why don’t your disciples live according to the tradition of the elders instead of eating their food with ‘unclean’ hands?” (v <a href="?bref=Mark.7.5">5</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Christ’s reply counters their criticism with a serious indictment: “You have let go of the commands of God and are holding on to the traditions of men. . . . Thus you nullify the word of God by your tradition that you have handed down” (vv 8, 13 ; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.15.1-6">Mt 15:1-6</a>).</p>
<p>The importance the Pharisees attributed to their interpretations of the law compromised the authority of God’s own revelation. To make matters worse, the genius of those interpretations was to distort the doctrine of grace by relaxing the divine standards. The very example used by Jesus in <a href="?bref=Mark.7.10-12">Mark 7:10-12</a> indicates that a rabbinic regulation—the Corban—made it possible for people to ignore the fifth commandment and feel justified in so doing.</p>
<p>The Pharisaic regulations were numerous and aggravating, but at least they could be fulfilled. Those who followed scrupulously the rabbinic traditions were in danger of concluding that their conduct satisfied God’s demands (cf. Paul’s description of his own preconversion attitude, <a href="?bref=Phil.3.6">Phil 3:6</a>). And a muted sense of one’s sin goes hand in hand with a false sense of spiritual security; the need to depend on God’s mercy no longer appears crucial. This is, of course, the point of the parable of the publican and the Pharisee (<a href="?bref=Luke.18.9-14">Lk 18:9-14</a>). In contrast, Jesus calls for a much higher righteousness than that of the Pharisees: “Be perfect, as your Father in heaven is perfect” (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.48">Mt 5:48</a>; cf. v <a href="?bref=Matt.5.20">20</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Essenes_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Essenes</a>; <a href="?item=Jew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jew</a>; <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>; <a href="?item=Sadducees_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sadducees</a>; <a href="?item=Talmud_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Talmud</a>; <a href="?item=Torah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Torah</a>; <a href="?item=Tradition_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tradition</a>; <a href="?item=TraditionOral_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tradition, Oral</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>