<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PhilemonLetterto">
  <title>Philemon, Letter to</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PHILEMON, L<span class="lc">etter to</span></p>
<p class="fl">The shortest of Paul’s Prison Epistles.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Origin">Origin</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Recipient">Recipient</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Purpose">Purpose</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Teaching">Teaching</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">In keeping with his custom and with the contemporary canons of the epistolary genre, the apostle Paul identifies himself as the author of this letter. He says that he was a prisoner at the time of writing (<a href="?bref=Phlm.1.9-10,13,23">Phlm 1:9-10, 13, 23</a>) because of his witness to Jesus Christ.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientGreekManuscriptOfPhilemon"/>
<p class="h2" id="Origin">Origin</p>
<p class="fl">It is difficult to ascertain the location of Paul’s imprisonment at the time of writing. Of Caesarea, Ephesus, or Rome, either of the latter locations seems to correspond to the data available in this epistle and in Colossians, with which it is closely related (<a href="?bref=Col.4.7-14">Col 4:7-14</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.23-24">Phlm 1:23-24</a>). The mention of Mark and Luke as Paul’s companions favor Rome as the point of origin of the letter (<a href="?bref=Phlm.1.24">Phlm 1:24</a>). However, the relative proximity of Ephesus to Colosse, where Philemon resided (about 100 miles, or 160.9 kilometers, away), and the announcement of Paul’s forthcoming visit to Colosse (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.22">22</a>) suggest Ephesus as the place of confinement. Although an Ephesian imprisonment is not explicitly mentioned in the book of Acts, the account of Paul’s missionary endeavors in that city make it clear that he met with considerable opposition (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.19">Acts 20:19</a>), which Paul describes in terms that could imply a time spent in prison (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.32">1 Cor 15:32</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.8-10">2 Cor 1:8-10</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Recipient">Recipient</p>
<p class="fl">This document is often improperly viewed as a personal note from Paul to Philemon, his convert and friend, church leader in Colosse, and slave owner. In reality, the epistle is addressed to Philemon, to Apphia (presumably Philemon’s wife), to Archippus, and to the congregation of believers that met in Philemon’s house (<a href="?bref=Phlm.1.1-2">Phlm 1:1-2</a>). Greetings are sent by the medium of the epistle on behalf of Epaphras, Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke, who represent together an impressive contingent of church leaders (vv <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.23-24">23-24</a>). Paul’s purpose in mentioning them is to make Philemon realize that his response to Paul’s plea will not be a private decision but one for which he will be accountable to the community of believers of which he is a part. In the body of Christ, matters that pertain to relationships of believers among themselves are of concern to the whole community. Such matters may not be treated as private issues, since they necessarily affect the well-being of the entire church (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.15-20">Mt 18:15-20</a>).</p>
<p>The epistle makes it clear that a warm bond of brotherly love existed between Paul and Philemon. The apostle calls Philemon his “beloved co-worker” (<a href="?bref=Phlm.1.1">Phlm 1:1</a>); he commends him in effusive terms for Philemon’s involvement in the missionary enterprise (vv <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.5-7">5-7</a>); he appeals to him on the basis of love (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.9">9</a>); he evokes their sharing of a common partnership (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.17">17</a>); he gently reminds Philemon that he owes his salvation to Paul (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.19">19</a>), and he says he trusts him to do what is requested of him and even more (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.21">21</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">The object of Paul’s letter pertains to a third party—Onesimus, the runaway slave of Philemon. After having committed some indiscretion not revealed in the letter (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.18">18</a>), the slave had escaped, and having traveled to the big city, he had sought anonymity among the heterogeneous groups of people that form the underclass of any metropolis. Through providential circumstances that remain shrouded in mystery, the fugitive slave had come under Paul’s influence; he had been converted by him (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.10">10</a>), had endeared himself to Paul’s heart (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.12">12</a>), and had become involved with him in the work of the gospel to the extent that Paul would have been glad to keep him in his service as his faithful and dear brother (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.13">13</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.4.9">Col 4:9</a>).</p>
<p>Paul knew that, had he kept Onesimus at his side as a coworker, Philemon would have been compelled to assent to his decision (<a href="?bref=Phlm.1.13-14">Phlm 1:13-14</a>). However, Paul decided to use the ambiguous situation that had developed as the occasion to make Philemon think through the implications of his faith on slavery, and to cause him to free Onesimus and elevate him to the status of brother, not only in a spiritual sense (“in the Lord”) but also in regard to his civil status (“in the flesh,” v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.16">16</a>). That Philemon acceded to Paul’s request and granted freedom to Onesimus is attested to by the preservation of this document. Had Philemon rejected Paul’s request, he would likely have destroyed the letter in order to erase from human memory what would have become incriminating evidence of his recalcitrance.</p>
<p>An intriguing postscript has been added to this story by the discovery of the repeated references to an elderly bishop named Onesimus who led the church at Ephesus in the early part of the second century, according to Ignatius’s letter to the Ephesians. The identification of the bishop with Philemon’s slave is suggested by the use in Ignatius’s letter of Paul’s play on words with the name of Onesimus in verses <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.11">11</a> and <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.20">20</a> (Onesimus means “useful” or “beneficial”). Should this be the case, it is conceivable that the former slave was the individual who collected the Pauline letters that were eventually integrated into the NT canon, including the letter to Philemon.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Purpose">Purpose</p>
<p class="fl">The purpose of Paul’s letter to Philemon was to dramatize the incongruity of the institution of slavery with Christianity and thus obtain the release of Onesimus. There is no evidence in the epistle that Paul was worried about Philemon’s inflicting upon Onesimus the harsh punishments that were prescribed by Roman law for runaway slaves. However, Paul was concerned that Onesimus not be reinstated as a slave but that he be received as a full-fledged member of Philemon’s family, and that he be treated with at least the same deference and dignity that might have been extended to Paul himself (vv <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.17,21">17, 21</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Teaching">Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">Among the many teachings contained in this small epistle, three deserve special mention.</p>
<p>First, the letter bears witness to the revolutionary challenge brought by the gospel to the sin-laden institutions of society. As such, it constitutes a condemnation of the practice of slavery. Jesus had denied his followers the right to own or control other human beings. Within the Christian community, mastery or leadership was to be exercised in servanthood from the bottom of the social ladder rather than hierarchically along lines of authority (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.42-45">Mk 10:42-45</a>). As a result, class differences had become irrelevant among Christians. In Christ, there was neither slave nor free but all were one in him (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.28">Gal 3:28</a>). Enslaved Christians who could obtain their freedom were to avail themselves of the opportunity (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.21">1 Cor 7:21</a>), and those who were free were to avoid becoming slaves of men (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.23">1 Cor 7:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.1">Gal 5:1</a>). Conversely, Christian slave owners were to act as servants to their slaves (<a href="?bref=Eph.6.9">Eph 6:9</a>), and all Christians were to be servants to one another (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.13">Gal 5:13</a>). Consequently, Philemon was to receive Onesimus “no longer as a slave” (<a href="?bref=Phlm.1.16">Phlm 1:16</a>).</p>
<p>Second, if adherence to the gospel prohibits a conservative maintenance of the status quo, it also rules out its violent overthrow. The revolutionary temper of the gospel is expressed in a posture of servanthood rather than in militant hostility. Onesimus was advised by Paul to demonstrate this theology of liberation by returning in submission to Philemon so as to allow the Holy Spirit to effect radical change in their relationship. The employment of Satan’s methods to achieve kingdom results rules out divine intervention and results in increased oppression.</p>
<p>Finally, the epistle provides a masterful model of inspired churchmanship. The situation that had developed between Philemon and Onesimus required the mediation of an advocate who could command the respect of the former in order to speak successfully on behalf of the latter. To win his case, Paul used the psychology of commendation (vv <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.4-7">4-7</a>); he emphasized his own self-sacrificial suffering for the sake of the gospel (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.9">9</a>); he played on Philemon’s goodwill (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.14">14</a>); he appealed to personal bonds of friendship (vv <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.17,20">17, 20</a>); he offered to assume responsibility for losses incurred (v 18); he reminded Philemon of his own indebtedness to Paul (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.19">19</a>); and he announced a forthcoming encounter that might have caused embarrassment had Philemon demurred at his request (v <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.22">22</a>). Paul’s approach is personal and pastoral, friendly but fervent. It exhibits a perfect balance of firmness and finesse. It demonstrates how genuine Christian leadership is to be exercised through persuasion and entreatment rather than by heavy-handed authoritarian impositions.</p>
<p>Although it is one of the shortest documents in the Bible, the Letter to Philemon stands as a timeless monument to the dignity and equality conferred by Christ on all humans regardless of rank, gender, class, or status. It also offers Christians a mandate and a methodology to pursue effective social reform.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PaultheApostle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paul, The Apostle</a>; <a href="?item=PhilemonPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Philemon (Person)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>