<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Philip">
  <title>Philip</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PHILIP</p>
<p class="list">1. Apostle whose name is placed fifth in each of the lists of the twelve after the two pairs of brothers, Simon Peter and Andrew, and James and John (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.3">Mt 10:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.18">Mk 3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.14">Lk 6:14</a>). John says that when John the Baptist bore witness to Jesus with the words, “Behold, the Lamb of God!” two of his disciples began to follow Jesus, and that one of these two was Andrew, who then declared to his brother Simon Peter, “We have found the Messiah,” and brought him to Jesus. (The other unnamed disciple was quite probably John himself, the writer of this account.) On the next day Jesus went to Galilee and there found Philip and addressed the call to him: “Follow me.” John adds that Philip was from Bethsaida. Philip in turn found Nathanael and told him, “We have found him of whom Moses in the law and also the prophets wrote,” and invited Nathanael, who was skeptical that any good could come out of Nazareth, to come and see for himself (<a href="?bref=John.1.35-51">Jn 1:35-51</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). From this is concluded that Philip was one of the first to follow Jesus and that he lost no time in persuading others to do the same.</p>
<p class="list-text">Like the other apostles, however, he still had much to learn about the person and the power of Christ. Hence, the testing question of Jesus to him on the occasion of the feeding of the 5,000, “How are we to buy bread, so that these people may eat?” and Philip’s puzzled response that even if they had 200 denarii (i.e., a large sum, roughly a person’s wages for half a year), it would not buy enough bread for each one to be given just a little to eat (<a href="?bref=John.6.5-7">Jn 6:5-7</a>). The miracle that followed taught him that the feeding of this multitude presented no problem to the one who is the Lord of all creation. Philip’s next appearance is in Jerusalem after Christ’s triumphal entry into the city, when “some Greeks” (i.e., Greek-speaking non-Jews) approached him with the request “Sir, we wish to see Jesus.” Philip informs Andrew, and together they bring them to Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.12.20-22">12:20-22</a>). This perhaps indicates that Philip was a person whom others found readily approachable, and also that he spoke Greek. In the upper room, prior to his arrest and trial, Jesus took the opportunity to impart further instruction to Philip, who had said, “Lord, show us the Father, and we shall be satisfied.” Philip hoped perhaps, in all devoutness, for the privilege of some special revelation (reminiscent of the request of Moses, <a href="?bref=Exod.33.18">Ex 33:18</a>). But Jesus taught him that he himself, the incarnate Son, is the all-sufficient revelation of the Father to humanity (<a href="?bref=John.14.8-10">Jn 14:8-10</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">There is a tendency to confuse the apostle with the evangelist (see below) of the same name. It seems probable, however, that after preaching in various parts, the apostle settled in Hierapolis, a city of the Roman province of Asia, and died there. Whether his was a natural or a martyr’s death is uncertain.</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ApostleApostleship_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Apostle, Apostleship</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Hellenistic Jew and one of the seven men appointed by the church in Jerusalem to supervise the daily ministry of assistance to the impoverished widows of the Christian community. They all, including Philip, had Greek names, and one of them, Nicolaus, was a proselyte (i.e., not a Jew by birth). Whether or not they were regarded as deacons in the technical sense is not absolutely clear from the account; this occasion has, however, been generally accepted as the origin of the order of the diaconate (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.1-7">Acts 6:1-7</a>). Of the seven, Stephen and Philip are the only ones of whom we have any further record in the NT. They are described as men of good repute, full of the Spirit and of wisdom (v <a href="?bref=Acts.6.3">3</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">That Philip became known as “the evangelist” is apparent from <a href="?bref=Acts.21.8">Acts 21:8</a>. The designation was well deserved, for when the Jerusalem Christians were scattered by the persecution led by Saul of Tarsus, Philip went to a city of Samaria and proclaimed the gospel with such power there that a great number of people joyfully turned to Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.1-8">Acts 8:1-8</a>). In the midst of this spectacular work, Philip was divinely instructed to leave Samaria and go down to the desert area in the southern part of the country. Humanly speaking, for him to turn away from the multitudes, who were so eagerly responding to his preaching and to go to the uninhabited territory in the south, must have seemed foolish. Yet Philip showed himself not only sensitive but also obedient to the will of God and followed this guidance without question. In the desert he found not a crowd but a single person, an important Ethiopian court official who had visited Jerusalem and was now returning to Africa. The wisdom of God in directing Philip to this place was fully vindicated, for the Ethiopian was reading <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">Isaiah 53</a>, the great gospel chapter of the OT. Philip gave him the good news that this prophecy pointed to Jesus Christ. The Ethiopian subsequently believed and was baptized and went on his way rejoicing (vv <a href="?bref=Acts.8.25-40">25-40</a>). The conversion of this one person meant not only that Philip was the first to proclaim the gospel to a Gentile but also that the gospel was taken by this Ethiopian courtier to the continent of Africa.</p>
<p class="list-text">The prevailing nationalistic pride of the Jews was such that they despised the Samaritans and regarded the Gentiles as ceremonially unclean. But Philip, by his eager preaching of Christ first to the Samaritans and then to the Ethiopian, reflected the way in which the gospel penetrated social barriers and dissolved racial prejudices and demonstrated that the grace of God in Christ Jesus is freely available to all. Subsequently, Philip made his home in the coastal town of Caesarea. There he hospitably entertained Paul and Luke when they were en route to Jerusalem at the conclusion of the apostle’s third missionary journey. Luke tells us that Philip had four unmarried daughters who were prophetesses (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.8-9">Acts 21:8-9</a>). Not long after this, when Paul was in custody in Caesarea for two years, the kindness and friendship of Philip must have meant much to him (<a href="?bref=Acts.23.31-35">23:31-35</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.24.23,27">24:23, 27</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Son of Herod the Great and Cleopatra and half brother of Antipas, whose mother was Malthace. He is called Herod in <a href="?bref=Luke.3.1">Luke 3:1</a>. The latter was tetrarch of Perea and Galilee from 4 <span class="era">BC</span> to <span class="era">AD</span> 39; Philip was tetrarch of Iturea and Trachonitis (plus certain other territories) to the northeast of Galilee for 37 years (4 <span class="era">BC</span> to <span class="era">AD</span> 33). His wife was his niece Salome, who danced for Herod in exchange for the head of John the Baptist (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.3-12">Mt 14:3-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.17-29">Mk 6:17-29</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=HerodHerodianFamily_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Herod, Herodian Family</a>.</p>
<p class="list">4. Son of Herod the Great and Mariamne and husband of Salome’s mother, Herodias, who left him to become the mistress of his half brother Herod Antipas. It was for this immoral relationship that John the Baptist rebuked Herod and was later imprisoned and beheaded (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.3-12">Mt 14:3-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.17-29">Mk 6:17-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.19-20">Lk 3:19-20</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>