<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Phinehas">
  <title>Phinehas</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PHINEHAS</p>
<p class="list">1. Eleazer’s son, grandson of Aaron (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.25">Ex 6:25</a>), and Abishua’s father (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.4,50">1 Chr 6:4, 50</a>). During the high priesthood of Eleazer, Phinehas had charge over the gatekeepers of the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.20">9:20</a>), as did Eleazer his father, when Aaron served as chief priest (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.3.32">Nm 3:32</a>). Phinehas, grieved by Israel’s sin with Baal of Peor at Shittim, killed an Israelite man and a Midianite woman for their licentious behavior (<a href="?bref=Num.25.7">25:7</a>). Following this act, the Lord turned away his anger toward Israel and made a covenant of peace with Phinehas, which was a covenant of a perpetual priesthood for him and his descendants (vv <a href="?bref=Num.25.11-13">11-13</a>); his deed was reckoned to him as righteousness from generation to generation forever (<a href="?bref=Ps.106.30">Ps 106:30</a>). Except for the brief interval when Eli acted as high priest (cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.1-3.21">1 Sm 1–3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.14.3">14:3</a>), Phinehas and his posterity officiated at the high priestly position until the destruction of the Jerusalem temple by the Romans in <span class="era">AD</span> 70.</p>
<p class="list-text">Following the Baal of Peor incident, Phinehas joined Israel in defeating the Midianites in war (<a href="?bref=Num.31.6">Nm 31:6</a>). After Israel took possession of the land of Canaan, Phinehas was given the town of Gibeah in the hill country of Ephraim for an inheritance (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.33">Jos 24:33</a>). He was sent with a small delegation of Israelite leaders to question the building of an altar on the west bank of the Jordan River by the tribes of Israel living east of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.13,30-32">Jos 22:13, 30-32</a>). Later, at Bethel, Phinehas promised Israel victory over Benjamin’s tribe in battle (<a href="?bref=Judg.20.28">Jgs 20:28</a>). His descendants Ezra the scribe (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.5">Ezr 7:5</a>) and Gershom (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.2">8:2</a>) returned with their families to Jerusalem following the exile.</p>
<p class="list">2. One of Eli’s two sons, who served as a priest at Shiloh (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.3">1 Sm 1:3</a>). According to 1 Samuel, Phinehas was a despicable priest, who, along with Hophni his brother, profaned the offered sacrifices (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.12-17">2:12-17</a>) and the sanctuary (v <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.22">22</a>), and scorned Eli (v <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.25">25</a>). His death was foretold to his father by a man of God (v <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.34">34</a>). In a subsequent war with the Philistines, Phinehas was killed on the same day his wife bore him a son, named Ichabod (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.11,17-19">4:11, 17-19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.14.3">14:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Eleazer’s father. Eleazer helped Meremoth and the Levites, Jozabad and Noadiah, take inventory of the temple’s precious metals and vessels during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.33">Ezr 8:33</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>