<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PillarofFireandCloud">
  <title>Pillar of Fire and Cloud</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PILLAR OF FIRE AND CLOUD</p>
<p class="fl">One of the most frequent modes of God’s appearing to humans in the OT; a visual manifestation of the presence of God common in the narratives of the exodus, Sinai covenant, the wilderness wanderings, and the dedication of the temple. The Bible refers to this phenomenon in a variety of ways: the pillar of cloud and of fire (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.24">Ex 14:24</a>); pillar of cloud (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.9-10">Ex 33:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.14.14">Nm 14:14</a>); pillar of fire (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.21">Ex 13:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.14.14">Nm 14:14</a>); cloud (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.34-35">Ex 40:34-35</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.1.33">Dt 1:33</a>); fire (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.33">Dt 1:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.12">4:12</a>). Though the Bible itself does not use this designation, the cloud and associated theophanies (God-appearances) are often called the “Shekinah glory” or simply “the Shekinah”—terms that have entered Christian theology from rabbinic literature.</p>
<p>The cloud theophany is associated with a variety of functions; common to all of them is that it is a visible expression of the presence of God. The cloud filled the tabernacle and was there day and night as a witness to the presence of God (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.34-38">Ex 40:34-38</a>). God appeared in the cloud on the Day of Atonement (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.2">Lv 16:2</a>). God’s acceptance of the temple built as his dwelling is shown when the cloud comes at the dedication (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.10-11">1 Kgs 8:10-11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.5.13-14">2 Chr 5:13-14</a>).</p>
<p>The cloud was also a protection for Israel. At its first appearance in the events of the exodus, the cloud positioned itself between the armies of Egypt and Israel, engulfing the Egyptians in darkness on the one side while lighting the way with its fire for Israel on the other (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.19-20">Ex 14:19-20</a>). The psalmist recalled how God “spread out a cloud as a covering, and a fire to give light at night” (<a href="?bref=Ps.105.39">Ps 105:39</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>).</p>
<p>The pillar also served as Israel’s guide during the exodus and wandering in the wilderness. “The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> guided them by a pillar of cloud during the day and a pillar of fire at night. That way they could travel whether it was day or night. And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> did not remove the pillar of cloud or pillar of fire from their sight” (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.21-22">Ex 13:21-22</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Whenever the cloud lifted from above the tent, the Israelites set out; wherever the cloud settled, the Israelites encamped (<a href="?bref=Num.9.17">Nm 9:17</a>). In spite of the sins of the people, the Lord God went ahead of them on their journey, in fire by night and in a cloud by day (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.33">Dt 1:33</a>). Subsequent generations would recount how God was their guide by day and night (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.12,19">Neh 9:12, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.14">Ps 78:14</a>).</p>
<p>The cloud also had an oracular function (<a href="?bref=Ps.99.7">Ps 99:7</a>). Not only did God speak from the cloud at Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.9,16">Ex 19:9, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.1-25">34:1-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.11-12">Dt 4:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.22">5:22</a>), he also spoke from there when Israel rebelled (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.10">Ex 16:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.14.10">Nm 14:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.16.42-43">16:42-43</a>), when Aaron and Miriam had a quarrel with Moses (<a href="?bref=Num.12.1-15">Nm 12:1-15</a>), and when the 70 elders were appointed. Only Moses had this ready access to the very words of God. When Moses went into the tabernacle, “the pillar of cloud would come down and hover at the entrance while the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke with Moses” (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.9">Ex 33:9</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). At the death of Moses the Lord appears in the pillar at the tent and speaks of the coming apostasy of the nation (<a href="?bref=Deut.31.14-29">Dt 31:14-29</a>).</p>
<p>Other theophanies having the features of cloud, fire, and light—or some combination—should probably be associated with the pillar of fire and cloud. Ezekiel saw an immense cloud with flashing lightning and surrounded by a brilliant light (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.4">Ez 1:4</a>); when he looked inside the cloud, he saw a fire, creatures in the service of God, the throne of God, and the awesome presence of the one who sat upon it and spoke (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.5-28">5-28</a>). Ezekiel also had a vision of the glory of God leaving the temple, and later a vision of its return (chs <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.1-22">10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.43.1-27">43</a>). In Daniel’s vision of the Ancient of Days, he sees one “like a son of man, coming with the clouds of heaven” to receive authority, glory, and power (<a href="?bref=Dan.7.13">Dn 7:13</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). The phrase “son of man” becomes Jesus’ favorite self-designation in the Gospels. At the Transfiguration, when he reveals his own glory, the clouds envelop him (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.5">Mt 17:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.7">Mk 9:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.34">Lk 9:34</a>). At his ascension he is received into the clouds, and angels remind the apostles of his promise to return in the same way (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.9-11">Acts 1:9-11</a>; see <a href="?bref=Matt.24.30">Mt 24:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.26">Mk 13:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.21.27">Lk 21:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.1.7">Rv 1:7</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Glory_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Glory</a>; <a href="?item=Shekinah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shekinah</a>; <a href="?item=Theophany_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Theophany</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>