<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Plague">
  <title>Plague</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PLAGUE</p>
<p class="fl">Word used to refer to a disease, disaster, or pestilence. Although there is a specific disease known as plague, the term “plague” as used in Scripture is not restricted to a single disease (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.37">1 Kgs 8:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.21">Lk 7:21</a>). Plague can indicate an epidemic disease or refer to widespread calamity like the 10 plagues of Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.7.1-12.51">Ex 7–12</a>).</p>
<p>There is no question that in the Hebrew mind plagues were part of the judgment God sent to individuals, families, and nations. God himself threatened to send plagues to the Israelites in proportion to their sins (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.21">Lv 26:21</a>) and took full responsibility for the Egyptian plagues (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.5">Jos 24:5</a>). The OT plagues demonstrated God’s control over the processes of nature, just as Christ’s miracles do in the NT.</p>
<p>At one point in the history of Israel, the Philistines won a battle and captured the ark of God (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.10-11">1 Sm 4:10-11</a>). When the ark was kept at Ashdod, however, God showed his power by allowing a fatal disease characterized by swellings or tumors to be prevalent (<a href="?bref=1Sam.5.6">5:6</a>). The Philistines sent the ark on to Gath, but people of all ages began to have tumors in the region of the groin (v <a href="?bref=1Sam.5.9">9</a>). A similar occurrence at the next city, Ekron, resulted in many deaths (v <a href="?bref=1Sam.5.12">12</a>).</p>
<p>Finally, after seven months, the Philistines decided to return the ark of God to Israel along with a guilt offering of five golden rats and five golden tumors (<a href="?bref=1Sam.6.1-4">1 Sm 6:1-4</a>). The selection of this unusual offering was made because the Philistine diviners associated the swarms of rodents that marred the land with the plague that was upon them (v <a href="?bref=1Sam.6.5">5</a>). The first Israelite village to receive the ark of God from the Philistines was punished with the same disease for looking into it (v <a href="?bref=1Sam.6.19">19</a>). The epidemic in Beth-shemesh left 50,070 people dead (cf. <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Disease_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Disease</a>; <a href="?item=ExodusBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Exodus, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=Pestilence_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Pestilence</a>; <a href="?item=PlaguesuponEgypt_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plagues upon Egypt</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>