<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PostexilicPeriod">
  <title>Postexilic Period*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">POSTEXILIC PERIOD*</p>
<p class="fl">A period in the Jews’ history after their exile to Babylon. This period extends from 539–c. 331 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#TheBiblicalPerspective">The Biblical Perspective</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheCollapseoftheBabylonianEmpire">The Collapse of the Babylonian Empire</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#ThePolicyofPersia">The Policy of Persia</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheReturnfromExile">The Return from Exile</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheReturnofEzra">The Return of Ezra</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#NehemiahsReturnandMinistry">Nehemiah’s Return and Ministry</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheRemainderofthePersianPeriod">The Remainder of the Persian Period</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#ReligiousFeaturesofthePostexilicPeriod">Religious Features of the Postexilic Period</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="TheBiblicalPerspective">The Biblical Perspective</p>
<p class="fl">The books that specifically cover the history of the postexilic or Persian period are Ezra, Nehemiah, Haggai, and Zechariah. These cover a period of over a century, only a portion of which is dealt with in detail, as the following table shows:</p>
<include_items src="../Charts/Charts.xml" name="BooksOfPostexilicTimes"/>
<p class="h2" id="TheCollapseoftheBabylonianEmpire">The Collapse of the Babylonian Empire</p>
<p class="fl">This occurred with dramatic suddenness, largely because of internal resistance to the policies of the last Babylonian king, Nabonidus (555–539 <span class="era">BC</span>). His neglect of the traditional Babylonian deity, Marduk, in favor of the moon god, Sin, was particularly resented. Nabonidus lived in Taima during the last decade of his reign, refusing to enter Babylon, where his son Belshazzar ruled as virtual king, as noted in <a href="?bref=Dan.5.1-31">Daniel 5</a>. Babylon fell to the Persians in October 538 <span class="era">BC</span> and the entire empire passed into their control.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ThePolicyofPersia">The Policy of Persia</p>
<p class="fl">This is well documented through contemporary inscriptions, notably the record of Cyrus, the first king of the Persian Empire (559–530 <span class="era">BC</span>), in the “Cyrus Cylinder.” A new phase in the relationship of conqueror to conquered peoples opened up, which contrasted with the policy of the Assyrian and Babylonian empires of crushing any opposition by massive force. Cyrus and his successors followed a conciliatory line, allowing exiled groups to return home, encouraging local faiths, posing as the champions of the territorial deities, and allowing local autonomy except where Persian interests were affected adversely. The cost of this operation, although considerable, must have been infinitesimal compared with that of keeping rebellious subjects under constant subjection.</p>
<p>The new enlightened policy is reflected in the decree of Cyrus, dated 538 <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1">Ezr 1:1</a>) and preserved in two versions. The first (vv <a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1-4">1-4</a>) is clearly the official proclamation, while the second (<a href="?bref=Ezra.6.3-5">6:3-5</a>) is a more prosaic memorandum dealing with building specifications, a record of Cyrus’s commitment stored in the official archives (vv <a href="?bref=Ezra.6.1-2">1-2</a>). The critical tendency to question the narrative in <a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1-11">Ezra 1</a>, especially on the score of the favorable references to the God of Israel and the vast financial support promised, has been nullified by the archaeological evidence, which shows an identical policy elsewhere. The Cyrus Cylinder, for example, notes, “The gods who live within them [i.e., the cities] I returned to their places. . . . All of their inhabitants I collected and restored to their dwelling places.”</p>
<p>In Judah itself there is no evidence for any warfare in this period, which suggests that the Persian takeover of the area was nonviolent. Judah was incorporated into the fifth Persian province, which included the entire area west of the Euphrates River (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.21">Ezr 7:21</a>). It was no more than a minor subdistrict, governed through Samaria.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheReturnfromExile">The Return from Exile</p>
<p class="fl">The continuance of a large Jewish community in Babylonia shows that not all the Jews responded to the invitation to return to their homeland, probably because of the prosperity acquired in exile. But 42,360 dedicated Jews (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.64">Ezr 2:64</a>) braved the challenge of a four-month 900-mile (1,448-kilometer) journey under Sheshbazzar (<a href="?bref=Ezra.1.8">1:8</a>), the officially appointed leader, and Zerubbabel his nephew (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.2">3:2</a>), who was probably the one to whom the Jews looked as leader. With great enthusiasm the Jews rebuilt the altar of sacrifice and resumed the observance of the traditional feasts (vv <a href="?bref=Ezra.3.1-6">1-6</a>), revealing both a sense of stewardship (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.68-69">2:68-69</a>) and careful attention to the requirements of the Law (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.2-4">3:2-4</a>). Soon after, work on the second temple commenced—the materials and master craftsmen being imported from Tyre and Sidon (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.7-9">Ezr 3:7-9</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.1-18">1 Kgs 5</a>). When the foundations were laid, the worshipers were doubtless aware that they were fulfilling God’s promise through Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.10-11">Ezr 3:10-11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.33.10-11">Jer 33:10-11</a>). But their high hopes were thwarted when there was opposition from neighboring areas (<a href="?bref=Ezra.4.4-5">Ezr 4:4-5</a>), selfishness in giving their own accommodations a higher priority than the Lord’s house (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.2-4,9">Hg 1:2-4, 9</a>), and a series of crop failures that further reduced morale (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.6,10-11">1:6, 10-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.17">2:17</a>).</p>
<p>Work on the temple was not resumed until Haggai and Zechariah appeared in 520 <span class="era">BC</span>. They encouraged Zerubbabel and Joshua (Jeshua) the high priest, rebuked the people for their apathy and selfishness, and promised God’s presence and blessing upon the temple project (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.12-2.9">Hg 1:12–2:9</a>). Zechariah’s preaching went beyond the building of the temple, including the rebuilding of Jerusalem itself (<a href="?bref=Zech.2.1-5">Zec 2:1-5</a>) and its world reputation (<a href="?bref=Zech.2.1-5,11-12">2:1-5, 11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.8.22">8:22</a>). The two leaders were addressed in ways that anticipated the Messiah (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.21-23">Hg 2:21-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.10-14">Zec 6:10-14</a>). But the Persian king Darius (521–486 <span class="era">BC</span>) was not alarmed when the rebuilding operation was reported to him (<a href="?bref=Ezra.5.1-6.13">Ezr 5:1–6:13</a>) and allowed the work to continue. In February 515 <span class="era">BC</span> it was dedicated (<a href="?bref=Ezra.6.14-16">6:14-16</a>). The Jewish community again had a focal point for its religion, but the political situation remained difficult, with no real security in a still-shattered city.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheReturnofEzra">The Return of Ezra</p>
<p class="fl">The traditional date of Ezra’s return is 458 <span class="era">BC</span> (preceding that of Nehemiah in 445 <span class="era">BC</span>). This is based on the premise that the King Artaxerxes noted in <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.7">Ezra 7:7</a> was Artaxerxes I Longimanus (464–424 <span class="era">BC</span>) and not Artaxerxes II Mnemon (404–359 <span class="era">BC</span>). However, some scholars, allowing that the king was Artaxerxes I, but believing that Nehemiah preceded Ezra, suggest that a tens unit has dropped out of “seventh” in <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.7">Ezra 7:7</a>, and that the date of Ezra’s return should be the 27th (438 <span class="era">BC</span>) or 37th year (428 <span class="era">BC</span>) of Artaxerxes I, making Ezra’s return a few years after Nehemiah’s. While this is plausible, there remains strong support for the traditional view. It accords with the order of the two books in the OT and requires no textual emendation. It also accounts for the section in <a href="?bref=Ezra.4.7-23">Ezra 4:7-23</a>, where, in the reign of Artaxerxes, an abortive effort was made by a recently returned group to rebuild the wall of Jerusalem. <a href="?bref=Neh.1.1-4">Nehemiah 1:1-4</a> suggests that this was regarded as important and its abrupt termination, by a decree of the king, caused Nehemiah great distress. The probability is that Ezra, recently returned, realized that little could be done in the way of major religious reformation until Jerusalem was secure, but in attempting to rebuild the wall he exceeded his mandate and was not able to function adequately until Nehemiah arrived, when the new security of Jerusalem allowed the great Law-reading ceremony of <a href="?bref=Neh.8.1-12">Nehemiah 8:1-12</a> to take place.</p>
<p>Ezra’s ministry concerned the teaching of the Law of Moses, the Pentateuch, which had long been extant in its final form by this time. <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.1-28">Ezra 7</a> shows that Artaxerxes was following the traditional Persian policy of encouraging good relationships with his subject peoples. Ezra’s appointment (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.12">Ezr 7:12</a>) was to a state office; it has frequently been paraphrased as “Secretary of State for Jewish Religious Affairs.”</p>
<include_items src="../Charts/Charts.xml" name="TheThreeReturnsFromExile"/>
<p class="h2" id="NehemiahsReturnandMinistry">Nehemiah’s Return and Ministry</p>
<p class="fl">Hanani and others (<a href="?bref=Neh.1.1-3">Neh 1:1-3</a>) informed Nehemiah of the complete failure of a recent attempt to rebuild the wall, probably that recorded in <a href="?bref=Ezra.4.7-23">Ezra 4:7-23</a>, and sought his mediation before the very king who had authorized the decree that compelled work on the wall to cease. A friend in high places was vital, and Nehemiah, a trusted and influential member of the court (<a href="?bref=Neh.1.11">Neh 1:11</a>), was approached for this delicate and dangerous task. <a href="?bref=Neh.1.4-2.8">Nehemiah 1:4–2:8</a> shows how well he prepared for and seized his opportunity. His appointment as the governor of Judah (<a href="?bref=Neh.5.14">5:14</a>) involved the removal of this area from the control of the governor of Samaria, which accounts for the unrelenting hostility of Sanballat (<a href="?bref=Neh.2.19">2:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.4.1">4:1</a>). The evidence of <a href="?bref=Neh.3.1-32">Nehemiah 3</a> suggests that the extent of Judah at this time was limited, probably not reaching as far north as Bethel or as far south as Hebron. Nehemiah was faced with opposition that included ridicule (<a href="?bref=Neh.2.19">2:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.4.1-3">4:1-3</a>), armed force (<a href="?bref=Neh.4.8,11">4:8, 11</a>), discouragement (v <a href="?bref=Neh.4.10">10</a>), internal economic problems (<a href="?bref=Neh.5.1-18">5:1-18</a>), intrigue (<a href="?bref=Neh.6.1-2">6:1-2</a>), intimidation, and blackmail (vv <a href="?bref=Neh.6.5-14">5-14</a>). In spite of these obstacles, the wall was completed in the incredibly brief period of 52 days (v <a href="?bref=Neh.6.15">15</a>).</p>
<p>In addition to this monumental achievement, Nehemiah completely reorganized the social and economic life of Jerusalem, dealing with alienated mortgages, excessive interest rates (<a href="?bref=Neh.5.1-13">Neh 5:1-13</a>), mixed marriages (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.30">10:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.13.23-30">13:23-30</a>), Sabbath observance (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.31">10:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.13.15-21">13:15-21</a>), and temple supplies (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.32-40">10:32-40</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.13.10-13">13:10-13</a>). Almost certainly, it was this political and economic security that allowed Ezra, who probably arrived 13 years earlier, to proceed with his great religious reformation based on the Law. Nehemiah’s book, usually called the “Nehemiah Memoirs,” was probably presented by him in the temple as a “votive offering” (as indicated by the form of <a href="?bref=Neh.5.19">5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.13.14,22,31">13:14, 22, 31</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheRemainderofthePersianPeriod">The Remainder of the Persian Period</p>
<p class="fl">Persian control, which probably centered on Lachish, was traditionally mild, except where her interests were directly threatened. There is no evidence of any major discontent in Judah, which enjoyed a considerable degree of autonomy. The Phoenician revolt of 351 <span class="era">BC</span>, which took Artaxerxes III (359–338 <span class="era">BC</span>) three years to subdue, was the only serious disturbance in the area. While Artaxerxes deported some Jews to Hyrcania, southeast of the Caspian Sea, that was probably a precautionary measure, and Judah does not appear to have been greatly involved in the revolt. The Jerusalem priests were allowed to mint their own coinage and levy a temple tax. Under the wider influence of the Persian Empire, Hebrew gradually fell out of popular usage as a spoken language, being replaced by Aramaic. As the international stature of Greece increased, so the influence of Hellenism began to be felt, even in Judah.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ReligiousFeaturesofthePostexilicPeriod">Religious Features of the Postexilic Period</p>
<p class="h3">The Decline of Prophecy</p>
<p class="fl">There were three main reasons for this:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. The prophetic movement as a whole became discredited after Jerusalem fell in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. The large number of popular cult prophets who had foretold a sudden end to the Babylonian oppression (e.g., <a href="?bref=Jer.28.1-4">Jer 28:1-4</a>) were proved decisively wrong. The suspicion that henceforth became attached to prophecy was increased further in the Persian period, when large numbers of itinerant “prophets” of various religions traveled widely. <a href="?bref=Zech.13.2-6">Zechariah 13:2-6</a> shows the stern measures advocated against such false prophets and fortune-tellers.</p>
<p class="list">2. There was a markedly different historical situation. The chastened remnant that survived had turned away from the blatant apostasy that characterized the preexilic period, so that the prophetic condemnation was not required with the same urgency. The temple and the Law had acquired a new prominence, and postexilic prophecy generally was concerned either with the rebuilding of the temple (e.g., Haggai and Zechariah) or the purification of its cult (e.g., Malachi). Once this goal had been realized, the role of the prophet was diminished. Another historical factor was the relatively large number of priests who returned from captivity, doubtless encouraged by the prospect of serving in the rebuilt temple. The main need at this time was for the priest, who revealed God’s will on the basis of the Law.</p>
<p class="list">3. There was an increasing stress on the transcendence of God, caused partly by an emphasis upon priestly mediation and partly by a fear of God that resulted from the recent judgment. The apocalyptic movement, with its emphasis on angelic intermediaries between humans and a transcendent God, encouraged this tendency. Correspondingly, the prophetic appeal for a personal, moral walk with God weakened.</p>
<p class="h3">The Rise of the Synagogue</p>
<p class="fl">Some type of local worship, independent of the temple and its sacrifices, must have developed in the Captivity, with the Law increasingly occupying a dominant position. Later on, the prophetic books were read and expounded, but the primary stress was always on the Law. This mode of worship later took root in the homeland, and the synagogue gradually developed into the focal point of the community for social relationships, education, and worship. It facilitated the worldwide continuance and expansion of the Jewish faith, independent of Jerusalem.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>; <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=EzraBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ezra, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=HaggaiBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Haggai, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=NehemiahBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Nehemiah, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=ZechariahBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Zechariah, Book of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>