<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PriscillaandAquila">
  <title>Priscilla and Aquila</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PRISCILLA AND AQUILA</p>
<p class="fl">Christian couple who were friends and possibly converts of the apostle Paul during his ministry at Corinth (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.1-3">Acts 18:1-3</a>). They are always mentioned together in the NT. Priscilla’s personal character or her leadership role in the church may account for her name coming before her husband’s in four out of six references (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.18,26">Acts 18:18, 26</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.16.3">Rom 16:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.4.19">2 Tm 4:19</a>).</p>
<p>Aquila was a Jew and a native of Pontus in Asia Minor. He had been expelled from Rome by the <span class="era">AD</span> 49 edict of Claudius (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.2">Acts 18:2</a>). Suetonius records that the emperor “banished from Rome all the Jews, who were continually making disturbances at the instigation of one Chrestus.” From Rome, Aquila and Priscilla went to Corinth, where Paul (on his second missionary journey) met them. There they lived together and worked at the same trade of making tents. After such close association with Paul, they were able to instruct even the learned Apollos, a Jewish teacher who then became a Christian (vv <a href="?bref=Acts.18.24-28">24-28</a>).</p>
<p>Both Priscilla and Aquila were Paul’s loyal friends and trusted coworkers (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.3-4">Rom 16:3-4</a>). When he left Corinth, they accompanied him and remained at Ephesus after he returned to Syria (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.18-19">Acts 18:18-19</a>). When Paul wrote the First Letter to Corinth, they were still at Ephesus, where their home was used as a place for Christians to gather (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.19">1 Cor 16:19</a>). Since the decree of Claudius was temporary, Priscilla and Aquila were again in Rome when Paul wrote to the Roman Christians (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.3">Rom 16:3</a>). When the Second Letter to Timothy was written, they were again in Ephesus (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.19">2 Tm 4:19</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>