<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Proselyte">
  <title>Proselyte*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PROSELYTE*</p>
<p class="fl">Gentile who converted to Judaism by being circumcised, baptized, and offering a sacrifice in the temple.</p>
<p>Foreigners who resided on some fairly permanent basis in Palestine in OT times were encouraged to become integrated into the full religious life of Israel through circumcision (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.48">Ex 12:48</a>). But “proselytizing,” or bringing willing Gentiles into the covenant community, occurred more frequently in the Jewish communities outside Palestine. Jews, living in most areas of the known world due to exile or commercial or military reasons, naturally carried their religious faith and practice with them. This Jewish way of life, particularly its monotheistic faith and high ethical standards, was attractive to many of the surrounding Gentiles accustomed to polytheism. The result was that many Gentiles attached themselves in varying degrees to the Jewish faith through the life of the synagogue (see <a href="?bref=Isa.56.1-8">Is 56:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.1.11">Mal 1:11</a>). Extrabiblical Jewish sources (Philo, Josephus) and Roman sources (e.g., Horace, Seneca, Tacitus) reveal that Jews carried on an aggressive mission to Gentiles in the centuries immediately preceding the life of Christ and then on into the early NT era (see <a href="?bref=Matt.23.15">Mt 23:15</a>).</p>
<p>The more zealous of those attracted to Judaism at this time became full members of the Jewish community through a rite involving three elements: circumcision (if male), a baptism representing a break with pagan background, and an offering in the temple at Jerusalem. Termed “proselytes,” these converts were considered true Jews in the sense of being obligated to follow the entire OT law.</p>
<p>There were other Gentiles who admired the monotheism and moral superiority of Judaism and were attracted to synagogue life but did not desire to take such a final step as circumcision. These were termed “God-fearers” (see <a href="?bref=Acts.10.22">Acts 10:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.16,26">13:16, 26</a>) or “devout” ones (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.2">10:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.4,17">17:4, 17</a>) and were regarded favorably by some Jews. But they were disregarded by others as no better than Gentiles.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=GodFearer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God-fearer</a>; <a href="?item=Jew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jew</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>