<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament">
  <title>Chronology of the Bible* (Old Testament)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CHRONOLOGY OF THE BIBLE* (Old Testament)</p>
<p class="fl">Branch of biblical studies that attempts to assign dates and sequences to OT events. Chronology is a science. It deals with evidence, theories, assumptions, and the balance of probabilities. Often it boils down to a matter of choosing among theories that are equally unable to solve all the problems raised by other points of view. OT chronology is an accredited branch of biblical studies primarily because it is essential for understanding the proper historical background of the biblical texts. In general, the chronology of the OT is understood well enough to vindicate the basic accuracy and sequential order of Scripture.</p>
<p>Both biblical and nonbiblical materials are utilized by students of OT chronology. Biblical data include (1) genealogies showing personal and tribal affiliations among various peoples; (2) specific numbers given by biblical authors to indicate a person’s longevity, a king’s reign, or the duration of a specific event; (3) synchronizing statements that date an event in a specific year of a king’s reign or relate it to a natural phenomenon assumed to be common knowledge at the time of writing (e.g., <a href="?bref=Amos.1.1">Am 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.14.5">Zec 14:5</a>).</p>
<p>From the abundance of such chronological passages in the OT, one might conclude that establishment of OT dates and sequences would be a simple procedure. Each of the three kinds of biblical materials, however, exhibits special problems that must be solved first.</p>
<p>Nonbiblical materials that shed light on OT chronology are quite numerous, and more are discovered year by year. They include (1) official records of important affairs such as military campaigns from countries like Egypt or Babylonia; (2) official inscriptions that are dedicatory or commemorate a great victory; (3) annals listing major accomplishments of a ruler year by year; (4) ostraca (inscribed pieces of pottery) containing letters, tax transactions and economic records, military dispatches between field leaders and command headquarters, or other information. Ostraca may be dated archaeologically and are often used to supplement the biblical record.</p>
<p>The chronologist tries to examine the pertinent biblical and nonbiblical information, notes areas of correlation among all the data, and finally establishes a working system into which the most facts can be fitted. New evidence uncovered at any time may necessitate shifts in the present working system. Although the basic structure of biblical chronology seems reasonably firm, many details will no doubt be subject to change as new evidence is discovered.</p>
<p>As a general rule, the earlier the period, the less certain one can be of one’s dating. In the second millennium <span class="era">BC</span>, for example, many dates can be assigned within a range of about 100 years. By the time of David and Solomon (c. 1000 <span class="era">BC</span>), the margin of error over which scholars debate is a decade or less. The range narrows as one comes toward the present, so that, with the exception of one or two problem eras, dates accurate to within one or two years are possible by roughly the middle of the ninth century <span class="era">BC</span>. Such limitations must be kept in mind in any examination of the major periods of OT history.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#PrepatriarchalPeriod">Prepatriarchal Period</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#FromAbrahamtoMoses">From Abraham to Moses</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#ConquestandConsolidation">Conquest and Consolidation</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheMonarchy">The Monarchy</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#JudahaftertheFallofIsrael">Judah after the Fall of Israel</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Beyond587bc">Beyond 587 <span class="era">BC</span></a></p>
<p class="h2" id="PrepatriarchalPeriod">Prepatriarchal Period</p>
<p class="h3">Biblical Evidence</p>
<p class="fl">In the first 11 chapters of Genesis are found accounts of the Creation (chs <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-2.13">1–2</a>), the fall (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.3.1-10">3</a>), Cain and Abel (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.4.1-14">4</a>), the Flood (chs <a href="?bref=Gen.6.1-9.29">6–9</a>), and the Tower of Babel (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.11.1-17">11</a>). Those events are set within a certain chronological framework.</p>
<p>According to <a href="?bref=Gen.5.1-32">Genesis 5</a>, a period of 10 generations elapsed between the Creation and the Flood. Although the individuals listed enjoyed a total life span of a hefty 847 years plus, the total time elapsing between Adam and the Flood was only 1,656 years.</p>
<p>According to <a href="?bref=Gen.11.1-32">Genesis 11</a>, another 10 generations elapsed from the time of the Flood until the time of Abraham (at least in the Septuagint, the third-century <span class="era">BC</span> Greek translation of the OT; the Hebrew Masoretic text has 9). In that period the average age attained by individuals in the list is 346 years (using a figure of 460 for Arphaxad’s son Cainan, who is included in v <a href="?bref=Gen.11.13">13</a> of the LXX; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.3.36">Lk 3:36</a>); the total elapsed time from the Flood to Abraham is only 520 years. Taken literally, that would mean that all of Abraham’s ancestors as far back as Noah’s son Shem were still alive at Abraham’s birth, and that a total of only 2,176 years elapsed from the time of Creation to Abraham.</p>
<p class="h3">Interpretation of the Biblical Data</p>
<p class="fl">A literalistic or slavishly mathematical interpretation of the figures, as has appeared in the margin of many <span class="sc">kjv</span> Bibles, requires a number of assumptions: that no names are omitted from the genealogies, that all the numbers given are consecutive, and especially that numbers used in an ancient biblical source carry the same meaning as that associated with them in the modern Western mind. Each assumption needs serious examination in the light of other established facts.</p>
<p>A cursory reading of other biblical genealogies, for example, reveals that not all the names of a given family were always included. Even Matthew recorded a total of 28 generations (two sets of 14 each) between David and Jesus, and comparison with OT genealogies reveals that Matthew omitted several names. Luke listed a total of 42 generations for the same interval. Omissions are also obvious when one compares the genealogical lists given in <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.1-8.40">1 Chronicles 1–8</a> with those recorded earlier in Genesis, Exodus, Numbers, Joshua, 1 and 2 Samuel, and 1 and 2 Kings.</p>
<p>Further, ancient peoples thought of numbers in a schematic or stylized way. Use of numbers among the ancient Near Eastern nations differed sharply from current Western practice. Examples of that practice are known from both biblical and nonbiblical sources. For example, a list of eight Sumerian kings who ruled in the city of Shurruppak before the “great flood” of the Jemdet Nar era (c. 3000 <span class="era">BC</span>) assigns each man an average reign of more than 30,000 years. Berossus, a Babylonian priest of Marduk living in the third century <span class="era">BC</span>, added two names to the eight found in that earlier list of kings and assigned an average of 43,200 years to each king. Such extraordinarily high numbers provide a perspective for considering the numbers of Genesis.</p>
<p>Therefore, although one can assume that the numbers assigned to the ages of the patriarchs preceding Abraham in Genesis had real meaning for those responsible for their preservation, they should not be employed in a purely literal sense to compute the length of the various generations mentioned in the text. Further, the numbers given in the Septuagint and in the Samaritan Pentateuch, another early version of the Pentateuch, diverge in many details from those of the Hebrew Masoretic Text. That means, among other things, that the Genesis numbers caused problems for even the earliest scholars of Scripture.</p>
<p class="h3">Nonbiblical Evidence</p>
<p class="fl">Archaeology provides no evidence that may be used to date either the Creation or any other account preserved in <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-11.32">Genesis 1–11</a>. The Flood is an example that illustrates some of the difficulties. Many claims have been made by persons from a wide variety of backgrounds (scientists, explorers, theologians, and others) to the effect that archaeology has proven the Genesis Flood narrative to be true. Yet no city so far excavated in Palestine and Syria (including some of the oldest towns in the world) shows archaeological evidence of the Flood.</p>
<p>Although several cities in Mesopotamia do exhibit evidence of a flood, three factors make it difficult to link that evidence with <a href="?bref=Gen.6.1-9.29">Genesis 6–9</a>. Each of the flood levels so far discovered dates from a different period. Further, since nearby sites show no evidence of flooding, all of the Mesopotamian flood evidence points to relatively small local floods. Finally, the evidence indicates no great cultural discontinuities of the sort that would result from destruction of an entire population. Thus, it seems that the ancient Mesopotamian floods discovered through archaeological research are of the same kind as the floods that still occur in the Euphrates River valley.</p>
<p>Clearly, certain questions one might ask of the Genesis narratives simply cannot be answered. Many who regard the Bible as the Word of God have concluded that the dating of events found in <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-11.32">Genesis 1–11</a> must be less important than the theological truths of salvation, faith, and obedience that these accounts present.</p>
<include_items src="../Charts/Charts.xml" name="SignificantOldTestamentEventsAndDates"/>
<p class="h2" id="FromAbrahamtoMoses">From Abraham to Moses</p>
<p class="h3">The Patriarchal Age</p>
<p class="fl">The date of Abraham is still a lively topic among biblical scholars who agree that Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob were indeed historical persons. Opinions range from an early-date view that estimates that the patriarchal age extended from 2086 to 1871 <span class="era">BC</span>, to a late-date view placing Abraham at around 1400 <span class="era">BC</span>. Since each position claims to fit the biblical data, a closer look at the two points of view is in order.</p>
<p>Many OT passages seem to support the view that puts Abraham at a comparatively early date. <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.1">First Kings 6:1</a> computes 480 years back from the founding of the temple in the fourth year of Solomon’s reign (961 <span class="era">BC</span>, according to the early-date view) to the exodus from Egypt, which would then be dated 1441 <span class="era">BC</span>. Counting 430 years as the period of the Israelite sojourn in Egypt (see <a href="?bref=Gen.15.13">Gn 15:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.12.40">Ex 12:40</a>) takes the date back to 1871 <span class="era">BC</span>. To that date are added the 215 years demanded by the total of (1) Abraham’s age upon entering Canaan (75 years according to <a href="?bref=Gen.12.4">Gn 12:4</a>); (2) 25 additional years before the birth of Isaac (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.5">Gn 21:5</a>); (3) 60 more years to the birth of Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.26">Gn 25:26</a>); and (4) the appearance of Jacob before the pharaoh at age 130 (<a href="?bref=Gen.47.9">Gn 47:9</a>). Those 215 years added to the previous total give a date of 2086 <span class="era">BC</span> for the entrance of Abraham into Canaan and a date of 2161 <span class="era">BC</span> for his birth.</p>
<p>Such a calculation does not use all of the chronological evidence presented in the OT; consequently, the date for Abraham is open to challenge. For example, the 480 years between the exodus and Solomon’s fourth regnal year represent a period of time into which the wilderness wanderings, the career of Joshua and his immediate successors, the period of the judges, Samuel, Saul, and David must all be placed. Although the OT does not specifically say how long were the careers of Joshua, Samuel, or Saul, even a modest reckoning pushes the total years required by all the biblical data together to approximately 600.</p>
<p>In addition, the length of time to be assigned to the Egyptian sojourn is problematic. The Samaritan Pentateuch and the Septuagint both view the number 430 (in <a href="?bref=Exod.12.40">Ex 12:40</a>) as applicable not only to the years in Egypt but to the years of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob in Canaan as well. Evidently Paul followed the Septuagint tradition when he dated the giving of the law 430 years later than the time of God’s promise to Abraham (see <a href="?bref=Gal.3.15-18">Gal 3:15-18</a>). That means the Septuagint figure cannot be dismissed lightly.</p>
<p>The late dating of Abraham (c. 1400 <span class="era">BC</span>) is based on two propositions: (1) The picture of patriarchal society portrayed in Genesis most closely parallels that reflected in the cuneiform tablets recovered from Nuzi, a town in northeastern Mesopotamia about 175 miles (282 kilometers) north of Baghdad. (2) Because those tablets must be dated in the 15th and 14th centuries <span class="era">BC</span>, the parallel patriarchal age must have fallen within the same general time period.</p>
<p>Those who hold the late-date view are aware that their date for Abraham cannot be equated with the set of numbers on which the early-date view depends. They point to other data, also from the OT. Joseph, who was already a highly placed Egyptian official when Jacob moved to Egypt, lived to be 110 years old (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.26">Gn 50:26</a>). Moses was a great-grandson of Levi, Joseph’s older brother. Since Joseph lived to see his own greatgrandchildren born (who would probably be younger than Moses since their great-grandfather was younger than his), the late-date view concludes that Joseph could have been alive when Moses was born. The four-generation genealogy of Moses (Levi-Kohath-Amram-Moses, in <a href="?bref=Exod.6.16-20">Ex 6:16-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.17-19">Nm 3:17-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.58-59">26:58-59</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.1-3">1 Chr 6:1-3</a>) was evidently thought to be complete according to <a href="?bref=Gen.15.16">Genesis 15:16</a>, which predicted that Abraham’s descendants would be freed from Egyptian bondage “in the fourth generation.”</p>
<p>However, a date of around 1400 <span class="era">BC</span> for Abraham cannot be aligned with certain other biblical data, including the long Egyptian sojourn demanded by <a href="?bref=Gen.15.13">Genesis 15:13</a> and <a href="?bref=Exod.12.40">Exodus 12:40</a> and a 40-year (or “one-generation”) wilderness existence. Some normally moderate scholars are forced to reduce the wilderness time to two years in order to maintain their late date for Abraham.</p>
<p>In short, the late-date theory is consistent with part of the biblical evidence (the genealogies of Moses), but the early-date theory conforms to another part (the actual year figures listed in scattered verses from Genesis and Exodus). The late-date theory holds that the genealogies represent more reliable information in Semitic societies generally, whereas the early-date theory computes years given in the biblical account literally throughout its scheme.</p>
<p>Because of problems attached to both positions, a large group of scholars take a middle ground in dating the patriarchal age. Archaeologically, they say, Abraham and his life and times fit perfectly within the early second millennium, but imperfectly within any later period. By placing Abraham roughly between 1800 and 1600 <span class="era">BC</span>, they provide enough latitude for a merging of all the available evidence, biblical and nonbiblical, into a workable chronological scheme. Archaeology provides four major bits of evidence for an early second-millennium patriarchal era.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Though the Nuzi tablets furnish a clear parallel to patriarchal social life, other tablets from other towns and an earlier era reflect many of the same customs common to Nuzi and Genesis. Since the Nuzians were Hurrians who came to northeastern Mesopotamia from elsewhere (perhaps Armenia), their social customs originated no doubt much earlier than the time of their tablets now in our possession. Accordingly, the 15th-century <span class="era">BC</span> date of the Nuzi tablets does not preclude an earlier date for Abraham.</p>
<p class="list">2. The names of several of Abraham’s ancestors listed in <a href="?bref=Gen.11.1-32">Genesis 11</a> can now be identified with towns in the northern area of Mesopotamia around Haran, the city from which Abraham migrated to Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.11.31-12.3">Gn 11:31–12:3</a>). Significantly, Haran flourished in the 19th and 18th centuries <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="list">3. Shortly after 2000 <span class="era">BC</span> Semitic nomads from the desert invaded the civilized communities of the Fertile Crescent. Those invaders, called Amorites in the OT, established themselves in several cities in northern Syria and Mesopotamia. One of the Amorite cities was Babylon, ruled by Hammurabi sometime around the beginning of the 18th century <span class="era">BC</span>. Although the King Amraphel of <a href="?bref=Gen.14.1">Genesis 14:1</a> is not linguistically identifiable with the Babylonian king Hammurabi, as earlier scholars believed, the picture of the times following the Amorite invasion still accords well with the Genesis narratives generally.</p>
<p class="list">4. Mari, another Amorite town, is now well known because of more than 20,000 tablets recovered from its royal palace and archives. Geographically, Mari is located in the general area of Haran. Chronologically, the tablets recovered come from the 18th century <span class="era">BC</span>. One 18th-century king of Mari, Zimri Lim, carried on extensive correspondence with Hammurabi of Babylon. The tablets from Mari also furnish valuable information about tribal and ethnic groups and their movements in the general region. Of basic importance for dating the Genesis materials are certain documents from Mari that include personal names very similar to Abraham (Abi-ram), Jacob, Laban, and several other West Semitic names.</p>
<p class="sp">Archaeological evidence neither proves nor disproves the actual existence of Abraham, Isaac, or Jacob. That is admitted on all sides. What archaeology has done is to provide a framework of probabilities within which the biblical patriarchal narratives appear more and more to be at home.</p>
<p class="h3">Date of the Exodus</p>
<p class="fl">The problem of dating the patriarchal age is closely related to the problem of assigning a date to the exodus of the Israelites from Egypt. Since the evidence does not permit a precise date for Abraham, a precise date for the entry of Joseph or Jacob into Egypt is likewise unobtainable. Further, the biblical evidence does not yield an exact figure for the length of the Israelite sojourn in Egypt.</p>
<p>For many years biblical scholars viewed <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.1">1 Kings 6:1</a> as a foundation upon which to build an unshakable date for the exodus. Because Solomon’s fourth year could be unquestionably fixed to within at least a 10-year span (967–958 <span class="era">BC</span>), the exodus too could be dated with the same precision simply by adding 480 years. But other biblical data raise serious questions about that simple procedure. When the Bible deals with all the events between the time of the exodus and the founding of Solomon’s temple, that is, from Numbers to <a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.18">1 Kings 5:18</a>, the precise numbers given total not 480 but closer to 600 years.</p>
<p>Because the evidence is insufficient to allow a precise date for the exodus, scholarly opinion remains divided between two possibilities. A 15th-century exodus is supported by several pieces of evidence. The chronology in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.1">1 Kings 6:1</a> appears to be independently corroborated by a passage in <a href="?bref=Judg.11.26">Judges 11:26</a>. It claims that Israel had occupied the area around Heshbon for 300 years preceding Jephthah’s own day. If Jephthah is dated at roughly 1100 <span class="era">BC</span>, one is obviously led back to an exodus in the middle of the 15th century. Also, three successive generations of pharaohs who ruled in the 16th and 15th centuries produced no male offspring, making it more likely that Moses would have become the foster son of a royal princess during that time; all of the 19th-dynasty kings (1306–1200 <span class="era">BC</span>) had legitimate male heirs.</p>
<p>In addition, a 15th-century date makes possible a connection between the Habiru invasion of Canaan (1400–1350 <span class="era">BC</span>)—described in the Amarna letters found at Tell el-Amarna, Egypt—and the invasion of Canaan by the Hebrews described in the OT book of Joshua. Related to that is a reference to “Israel” in the Merneptah Stele, a stone pillar inscribed with the deeds of the Egyptian king, Merneptah, of about 1220 <span class="era">BC</span>. It implies that the people referred to, met by Merneptah in the course of a Canaanite military campaign, had been in existence for some time. Finally, an excavator of Jericho, John Garstang, placed the destruction of that city at around 1400 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>Other evidence, however, strongly implies not a 15th- but a 13th-century date for the exodus. Many scholars assign a date between 1290 and 1275 <span class="era">BC</span> on the basis of that evidence. First, the 480 years of <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.1">1 Kings 6:1</a> discussed above may be interpreted as schematically representing 12 generations, as indicated by <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.3-8">1 Chronicles 6:3-8</a>. Thus if 12 generations averaged 25 years instead of 40 years, the reduction of 480 schematized years to 300 actual years would point to an exodus date of around 1266 <span class="era">BC</span>. Second, archaeological evidence exists that dates destruction at the assumed sites of several cities conquered by Joshua (Lachish, Debir, Bethel, and Hazor) to the late 13th century. Third, there is no biblical mention of Egyptian military campaigns (such as Merneptah’s 1220 <span class="era">BC</span> incursion); Israelites living in Canaan before the time of the militarily active pharaohs Seti I (1319–1301 <span class="era">BC</span>) and Ramses II (1301–1234 <span class="era">BC</span>) would certainly have been affected by such activity. Fourth, <a href="?bref=Exod.1.11">Exodus 1:11</a> mentions the city of Rameses, the capital built by Ramses II, according to his own inscriptions. A fifth line of argument comes from archaeological conclusions that Transjordan and the Negev Desert were not occupied by sedentary people between 1900 and 1300 <span class="era">BC</span>, whereas the Bible states clearly that the Israelites encountered stiff opposition from groups in that same region. Thus, it is argued, the Israelites must have entered that region after 1300 <span class="era">BC</span>. Sixth, connecting the Habiru with the Israelites of the Conquest lacks weight because many texts besides the Amarna tablets attest to the existence of Habiru groups virtually all over the ancient Near East. “Habiru” seems to be a much broader term, possibly meaning “trespasser,” and is probably unrelated etymologically or semantically to “Hebrew.” Seventh, and finally, Garstang’s work at Jericho has now been revised by archaeologist Kathleen Kenyon, who showed that the fallen walls that Garstang had dated about 1400 <span class="era">BC</span> in reality were destroyed in 1800 <span class="era">BC</span> or earlier.</p>
<p>So far, it has been impossible to decide with precision between the two centuries proposed for the exodus. The majority opinion among OT scholars generally, including a growing number of moderate or conservative scholars, is in favor of the 13th-century option. On the other hand, many other conservative scholars continue to favor the 15th-century date. Dogmatism is unwarranted since problems remain unresolved with either option.</p>
<p>In accordance with the majority opinion, however, a date of about 1290 <span class="era">BC</span> for the exodus will be used in dealing with subsequent problems.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ConquestandConsolidation">Conquest and Consolidation</p>
<p class="fl">The chronological task for the period of conquest and consolidation is to fit all the events narrated by the OT, chiefly in Joshua and Judges, between the exodus (c. 1290 <span class="era">BC</span>) and the times of David (c. 1000 <span class="era">BC</span>) and Solomon (d. 930 <span class="era">BC</span>). In other words, one must fit roughly 550 years of biblical events between Moses and David into a 290-year span.</p>
<p>Although assigning an early date for the exodus (c. 1447 <span class="era">BC</span>) would make the task somewhat easier, the mere addition of about 157 years does not by itself solve all the problems. Neither date allows enough time for all the OT events from Joshua to David to take place singly and consecutively. Accordingly, advocates of both dates assume that some of the judges ruled simultaneously rather than consecutively. The difference is one of degree only.</p>
<p>The book of Joshua furnishes most of the OT evidence regarding the conquest of Canaan by the Israelites. Unfortunately, the book of Joshua has no chronological notes that specify the amount of time elapsing during Joshua’s career. Further, there are no biblical references to major contemporary events in other parts of the ancient world, the dates of which could be used to fix the chronology. Rather, in what is obviously a telescoped account, the book of Joshua records the fall of Jericho and Ai, followed closely by a southern and then a northern campaign. After those victories, covering much of the total territory of Canaan, various parcels of land were distributed to the tribal groups of Israel; the tribes were expected to complete the task of destroying whatever Canaanite inhabitants remained in their particular region. One seeks in vain, however, for any statements indicating how long those events took.</p>
<p>In the book of Judges a slightly different circumstance prevails. There the OT furnishes a rather complete list of figures to indicate the duration of periods of foreign oppression, judgeships, and ensuing peace. The total number of years described for that period is 410, but that total does not include any time for the many “minor” judges. It seems obvious, therefore, that most if not all of the judges were simply local chieftains whose activity was simultaneous with that of other judges, at least for part of their reign. Unfortunately, the book of Judges provides no cross-reference system to indicate which judges were contemporaries of which others. Perhaps the best one can do is to assume general guidelines for the chronology of that period between Moses and David.</p>
<p>Two significant facts should be kept in mind. First, archaeological information seems to demand a Conquest date beginning about 1250 <span class="era">BC</span> rather than 200 years earlier. Assuming concurrent careers for the judges allows one to compress the literal OT figures into the general scheme demanded by other evidence.</p>
<p>Second, the ancient scribes evidently related the chronology of the period to a 40-year or generation-based schema, a practice that lasted until the time of the divided kingdom, when a regular dynastic chronology was introduced. In the face of so many careers being assigned exactly 40 years, the fact remains that the literal totals of such numbers cannot be harmonized with either the biblical or the archaeological evidence for the period. Accordingly, most scholars doubt that the number 40 was ever intended to be an exact mathematical calculation. That view permits enough leeway for cautious fitting of biblical and other evidence into a general timetable.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheMonarchy">The Monarchy</p>
<p class="h3">Types of Evidence</p>
<p class="fl">For the period of the Israelite monarchy, chronological evidence is abundant.</p>
<p>The OT itself strives to provide all the information necessary for the chronology of the period, including (1) a complete list of all the kings in Israel and in Judah both before and after the division of the kingdom; (2) the age of each king (except Saul) at his accession; (3) synchronisms of the northern kingdom of Israel and the southern kingdom of Judah showing in what year of his contemporary in the other kingdom each king came to the throne; and (4) precise calculations of the length of each king’s reign. In addition some important events are dated by reference to another event; others are coordinated with concurrent events in secular history.</p>
<p>Outside the OT an abundance of material provides evidence for a chronology of the period. By far the most important single source is a collection of Assyrian <span class="ital">limmu</span> lists. In Assyria a record of each king’s reign was kept on a particular kind of annal. Each year of reign was named after an individual of high rank in the court; the first year was named after the king himself, the second after the next highest-ranking official (though that name appears to have been selected by lot originally), and so on, down until the death of the king. The word <span class="ital">limmu</span> was used to introduce the name of the official after whom the current year was to be named, hence the designation <span class="ital">“limmu</span> lists.”</p>
<p>Assyrian <span class="ital">limmu</span> lists are tied precisely to the solar year, making the documents highly reliable. Further, in addition to many events in Assyrian history, notable natural phenomena were dated on the basis of the <span class="ital">limmu</span> in which they occurred. For example, a solar eclipse dated by the Assyrian scribes in the <span class="ital">limmu</span> year of Bur-Sagale has been computed astronomically as June 15, 763 <span class="era">BC</span>. Beginning with the year 763, then, and working both backward and forward, a complete list of Assyrian <span class="ital">limmu</span> officials has been obtained for the period between 891 and 648 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>With the accuracy of the Assyrian <span class="ital">limmu</span> lists corroborated by a number of sources, they can be used with confidence in reconstructing the chronology of the corresponding period of biblical history. That is especially true where a biblical writer related an Israelite or a Judahite event to a particular year in the reign of an Assyrian king whose <span class="ital">limmu</span> list indicates the precise years of his reign.</p>
<p>There are also records from Chaldean (Babylonian) king lists and from later Greek historians. Ptolemy, in the second century <span class="era">AD</span>, for example, gave dates for Babylonian kings from 747 <span class="era">BC</span> and continued with dates for Persian, Greek, and Roman rulers down to <span class="era">AD</span> 161. Finally, useful information is found in inscriptions from monuments, stelae, and other artifacts from Assyria and elsewhere.</p>
<p class="h3">Monarchical Chronology</p>
<p class="fl">The <span class="ital">limmu</span> list of the Assyrian king Shalmaneser III provides a basis for the first comparison of dates among Assyria, Israel, and Judah. In the <span class="ital">limmu</span> of Daian-Assur, Shalmaneser’s sixth year on the throne, Ahab of Israel was listed as one of the kings who fought against the Assyrians in the battle of Qarqar. Thus the date for that battle may be placed confidently in 853 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>Assyrian records also indicate that Shalmaneser III came into contact with an Israelite king 12 years later, in 841 <span class="era">BC</span>. That king was Jehu. Thus two fixed points are available for correlating the biblical information. Following the death of Ahab, which is not dated exactly by reference to the Assyrian records, two of his sons came to power. The first, Ahaziah, reigned two years (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.51">1 Kgs 22:51</a>); the second, Joram (also called Jehoram), reigned a total of 12 years (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.1">2 Kgs 3:1</a>). Recognizing a nonaccession-year reckoning by the Israelites in that era, the apparent total of 14 years may be reduced to an actual total of 12. Thus it seems evident that Ahab not only fought Shalmaneser III in 853 <span class="era">BC</span> but also died in that year. Ahab was then followed by his two sons for a total of 12 years before the accession of Jehu in time to account for his contact with Shalmaneser II in 841 <span class="era">BC</span>. Further, because Jehu murdered both the king of Israel (Jehoram) and the king of Judah (Ahaziah) at the same time (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.24-27">2 Kgs 9:24-27</a>), a fixed synchronism is provided between the two kingdoms for the year 841 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The first nine kings of Israel ruled an apparent total of 98 years or an actual total (taking into account Israel’s nonaccession-year policy) of 90 years. Zimri, who ruled only seven days (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.15-18">1 Kgs 16:15-18</a>), counts as one of the nine but does not insert an extra year in either the actual or apparent totals. The accession of Jeroboam I thus occurred in 930 <span class="era">BC</span> (adding 90 years to 841 <span class="era">BC</span>), and Rehoboam of Judah began to rule in that same year as well. Allowing Solomon the 40-year reign indicated in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.42">1 Kings 11:42</a> points to the year 970 <span class="era">BC</span> for his accession. The death of David would also be pinpointed in that period, although allowance must be made for the possibility of a short co-regency of David and Solomon before David’s death. The reign of Saul then falls approximately in the late 11th century <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>In Judah the period between the death of Solomon in 930 <span class="era">BC</span> and the murder of Ahaziah by Jehu in 841 <span class="era">BC</span> was occupied by the kingships of six men whose time on the throne totals 95 biblical years. Computation of that era in Judah is not as simple as for the Israelite kings for several reasons. Problems include a change from accession- to nonaccession-year reckoning sometime around 850 <span class="era">BC</span>, at least two co-regencies (Jehoshaphat with Asa and then Jehoram with Jehoshaphat), and the calendar differences between the two kingdoms. It is clear that the 95 apparent years must be reduced, on the basis of the differences in computation and calendar, to 90 actual years in order to bring the Judahite figures into line with the established Assyrian and Israelite synchronisms.</p>
<p>After the year 841, the next biblical event to be certified by nonbiblical materials is the fall of Samaria in 722 <span class="era">BC</span>. That date is furnished by the annals of Sargon II of Assyria (722–705 <span class="era">BC</span>), successor to Shalmaneser V (727–722 <span class="era">BC</span>). Although that date comes just 120 years after the fixed point of 841 <span class="era">BC</span> in Israelite history, the chronological materials for that period are quite difficult to interpret accurately. In the past, scholars resorted to assumptions of extensive co-regencies, to presumed confusion on the part of certain scribes over methods to be followed in computations, or to other theories in attempting to understand the period. In spite of the many difficulties, however, all the biblical and Assyrian dates for the period of the divided monarchy have been harmonized—with the exception of four figures related to the closing years of the Israelite kingdom, all connected in some way with the problematic reign of Hoshea.</p>
<p class="h2" id="JudahaftertheFallofIsrael">Judah after the Fall of Israel</p>
<p class="fl">Following the fall of Samaria in 722 <span class="era">BC</span>, OT chronology is concerned only with the southern kingdom of Judah until its destruction some 135 years later. Two events in the biblical record important for establishing a chronology for that period are the siege of Jerusalem by Sennacherib of Assyria in the late eighth century and the eventual fall of Jerusalem to the Babylonians in the early sixth century.</p>
<p class="h3">Sennacherib’s Invasion of Judah</p>
<p class="fl">The Assyrian invasion (704–681 <span class="era">BC</span>) is recorded in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.13-16">2 Kings 18:13-16</a>, where verse <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.13">13</a> dates the event to the 14th year of King Hezekiah. Sennacherib’s own inscriptions include a lengthier version of the affair. From them the date of 701 <span class="era">BC</span> is established, placing the accession of Hezekiah in 715 <span class="era">BC</span>. That much is simple, but problems still arise. For example, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.9">2 Kings 19:9</a> reports that Sennacherib was in contact with an Ethiopian king, Tirhakah (c. 690–664 <span class="era">BC</span>), during the course of his campaign, which included a siege of Jerusalem. Obviously, contact with a ruler who came to power in 690 <span class="era">BC</span> at the earliest could not refer to events in 701 <span class="era">BC</span>. It is possible, however, that Sennacherib actually made two invasions of Judah, the first in 701 and the second sometime later. The date of that supposed second invasion is not assured, although <a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.35-37">2 Kings 19:35-37</a> may imply that Sennacherib was murdered only shortly after his withdrawal from Jerusalem. Since Sennacherib was succeeded by his son Esarhaddon in the year 681, the presumed second invasion of Judah would have occurred somewhere in the last half of the same decade.</p>
<p>A number of scholars oppose the assumption of a second invasion of Jerusalem by Sennacherib. They suggest the possibility that Tirhakah, though king only from 690 <span class="era">BC</span>, may have led troops against Sennacherib as early as 701, before acceding to the throne. The reference to King Tirhakah in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.9">2 Kings 19:9</a> would then be understood as use of his eventual title in an effort to identify him to a later generation of readers.</p>
<p>However the question of the number of invasions is decided, it is certain that Sennacherib invaded Judah in 701 <span class="era">BC</span>, the 14th regnal year of Hezekiah. Such a synchronism establishes Hezekiah’s accession year as 715 <span class="era">BC</span>, but that date raises another problem. The fall of Samaria, now established at 722, is dated by <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.10">2 Kings 18:10</a> in the sixth year of Hezekiah’s reign. The most likely solution is that Hezekiah began a co-regency with his father, Ahaz, six years before Samaria fell. The possibility for confusion arises from the fact that one verse (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.13">2 Kgs 18:13</a>; repeated in <a href="?bref=Isa.36.1">Is 36:1</a>) synchronizes Sennacherib’s 701 <span class="era">BC</span> invasion with the 14th year of Hezekiah’s independent reign; another verse (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.10">2 Kgs 18:10</a>) correlates the fall of Samaria with the beginning of Hezekiah’s co-regency. Thus from about 728 to 715 <span class="era">BC</span> Hezekiah was co-regent with Ahaz. From 715 to 697 he reigned alone. From 696 to 686 his son Manasseh was co-ruler with him.</p>
<p>According to the chronological information given by a number of verses in 2 Kings, a total of 128 years and six months elapsed between the time of Hezekiah’s accession in 715 and the capture of King Jehoiachin in 597, a date to be discussed below. Thus another problem is to explain the more than 10-year excess apparently demanded by the biblical totals. The best solution appears to lie in the assumption that Manasseh first came to power in 697 as co-regent with his father, Hezekiah. Manasseh died in 642, following what <a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.1">2 Kings 21:1</a> states was a 55-year reign. Hezekiah, who came to the throne in 715, is said to have reigned 29 years (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.2">2 Kgs 18:2</a>), which would mean that he was king until 686, roughly 11 years after the time when Manasseh must have come to the throne in order to have completed a 55-year reign by 642.</p>
<p class="h3">Fall of Jerusalem</p>
<p class="fl">Contemporary Babylonian records are available to shed valuable light on the last few years of Judah’s existence. For the years 626–623, 618–595, and 556 <span class="era">BC</span> the Babylonian Chronicle, a formal record of Babylonian affairs of state, has been recovered. From information contained in that chronicle and other cuneiform documents of the period, three dates in Judah’s history may be fixed firmly. The first is the death of Josiah in 609; the second is the battle of Carchemish in 605; the third is the end of the reign of Jehoiachin, which is dated by the Babylonian Chronicle to the second month of Adar in the ninth year of Nebuchadnezzar, or March 16, 597.</p>
<p>After Jehoiachin’s capture, Zedekiah became puppet king of Judah for 11 years (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.18">2 Kgs 24:18</a>). On the tenth day of the tenth month during Zedekiah’s ninth regnal year (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.1">2 Kgs 25:1</a>), the final siege of Jerusalem was begun by the Babylonian army. That day was January 15, 588. On the ninth day of the fourth month during the 11th regnal year of Zedekiah, after a siege of almost 18 months, the wall of Jerusalem was broken through (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.3-4">2 Kgs 25:3-4</a>). The temple was burned on day seven of the following (fifth) month.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Beyond587bc">Beyond 586 <span class="era">BC</span></p>
<p class="fl">Following the tragedy of 586 <span class="era">BC</span>, several further developments are given chronological notice in the OT. <a href="?bref=Jer.52.30">Jeremiah 52:30</a> records a third deportation of Jews to Babylonia in the 23d year of King Nebuchadnezzar (582 or 581 <span class="era">BC</span>). Both <a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.27">2 Kings 25:27</a> and <a href="?bref=Jer.52.31">Jeremiah 52:31</a> give evidence of the release of King Jehoiachin from prison; the Babylonian Chronicle dates that event at 27 Adar, or March 21, 561 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>In 539 <span class="era">BC</span> the Babylonians themselves were destined to learn the meaning of defeat. In that year a Persian ruler, Cyrus the Great, launched a successful campaign against Babylon and its king, Nabonidus. Inheriting control over the exiled Jews and many other groups of people conquered earlier by Babylonia, Cyrus moved quickly to initiate a policy of tolerance toward his new subjects. In the first year of his rule Cyrus issued an edict making it possible for Jews to return to their former land (<a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1">Ezr 1:1</a>). On the first day of the following year, 1 Tishri (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.6">Ezr 3:6</a>), an altar was set up in Jerusalem. In Iyyar of the following year (April/May 536) work was begun on the temple itself (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.8">Ezr 3:8</a>).</p>
<p>After a period of frustrating work stoppages of varying lengths, the preaching of Haggai and Zechariah spurred on the Jews to complete the temple. Work resumed in 520 (<a href="?bref=Ezra.4.24">Ezr 4:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1,15">Hg 1:1, 15</a>) and was finally completed on 3 Adar, or March 12, 515 (<a href="?bref=Ezra.6.15">Ezr 6:15</a>). The final stages of OT chronology pertain to the careers of Ezra and Nehemiah. The traditional view of their era places Ezra in the seventh year of Artaxerxes I (458 <span class="era">BC</span>) and Nehemiah in the 20th (445 <span class="era">BC</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> “Date” under each OT book; <a href="?item=ConquestandAllotmentoftheLand_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Conquest and Allotment of the Land</a>; <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=Exodusthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Exodus, The</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=PatriarchsPeriodofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Patriarchs, Period of the</a>; <a href="?item=PostexilicPeriod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Postexilic Period</a>; <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>