<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Church">
  <title>Church</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CHURCH</p>
<p class="fl">A group or assembly of persons called together for a particular purpose. The term appears in only two verses in the Gospels (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.18">Mt 16:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.18.17">18:17</a>) but frequently in the book of Acts, most of the letters of Paul, as well as most of the remaining NT writings, especially the Revelation of John.</p>
<p>One way of referring to the body of Israel in the OT was simply “the congregation.” Groups claiming to be the true Israel spiritually rather then naturally called themselves “the congregation.” The term was used by the writers of the Dead Sea Scrolls as well as by early Christians; it is the actual meaning of the word “church.” Christians often referred to themselves simply as the church or the congregation (with “of God” being understood). The term could be applied either to all believers in the world or to any local group of them. It meant the total presence of God’s people in a given location. That is why the NT often uses the singular “church” even when many groups of believers are included together (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.31">Acts 9:31</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.1">2 Cor 1:1</a>); the term “churches” is rarely found (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.41">Acts 15:41</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.16.5">16:5</a>). Each group or the whole group was the place where God was present (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.18">Mt 16:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.18.17">18:17</a>); God had purchased the congregation with the blood of his Son (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.28">Acts 20:28</a>). The use of the word “church” in the NT is also somewhat dependent upon the Greek world. In the Greek world the word translated “church” designated an <span class="ital">assembly</span> of people, a meeting, such as a regularly summoned political body, or simply a <span class="ital">gathering</span> of people. The word is used in such a secular way in <a href="?bref=Acts.19.32,39,41">Acts 19:32, 39, 41</a>.</p>
<p>The specifically Christian usages of this concept vary considerably in the NT. (1) In analogy to the OT, it sometimes refers to a church meeting, as when Paul says to the Christians in Corinth: “When you meet as a church . . .” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.18">1 Cor 11:18</a>). This means that Christians are the people of God especially when they are gathered for worship. (2) In texts such as <a href="?bref=Matt.18.17">Matthew 18:17</a>, <a href="?bref=Acts.5.11">Acts 5:11</a>, <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.17">1 Corinthians 4:17</a>, and <a href="?bref=Phil.4.15">Philippians 4:15</a>, “church” refers to the entire group of Christians living in one place. Often, the local character of a Christian congregation is emphasized, as in the phrases, “the church in Jerusalem” (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.1">Acts 8:1</a>), “in Corinth” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.2">1 Cor 1:2</a>), “in Thessalonica” (<a href="?bref=1Thes.1.1">1 Thes 1:1</a>). (3) In other texts, house assemblies of Christians are called churches, such as those who met in the house of Priscilla and Aquila (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.5">Rom 16:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.19">1 Cor 16:19</a>). (4) Throughout the NT, “the church” designates the universal church, to which all believers belong (see <a href="?bref=Acts.9.31">Acts 9:31</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.4">1 Cor 6:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.22">Eph 1:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.18">Col 1:18</a>). Jesus’ first word about the founding of the Christian movement in <a href="?bref=Matt.16.18">Matthew 16:18</a> has this larger meaning: “I will build my church, and the powers of death shall not prevail against it” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>The church, both as a universal reality and in its local, concrete expression, is more specifically designated in Paul’s writings as “the church of God” (e.g., <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.2">1 Cor 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.32">10:32</a>) or “the churches of Christ” (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.16">Rom 16:16</a>). In this way a common, secular Greek term receives its distinctive Christian meaning and sets the Christian assembly/ gathering/community apart from all other secular or religious groups.</p>
<p>It is clear from the NT as a whole that the Christian community understood itself as the community of the end time, as the community called into being by God’s end-time act of revelation and divine presence in Jesus of Nazareth. So Paul tells the Christians in Corinth that they are those “upon whom the end of the ages has come” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.11">1 Cor 10:11</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). That is, God had visited his creation, had called out of both Judaism and the gentile world a new people, empowered by his Spirit to be present in the world, sharing the Good News (gospel) of his radical, unconditional love for his creation (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.11-22">Eph 2:11-22</a>). The Gospels tell us that Jesus chose 12 disciples who became the foundation of this new people. The correspondence to the 12 tribes of Israel is clear, and it shows that the church was understood both as grounded in Judaism and as the fulfillment of God’s intention in calling Israel to become “a light to the nations, that my salvation may reach to the end of the earth” (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.6">Is 49:6</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>; <a href="?bref=Rom.11.1-5">Rom 11:1-5</a>). It is this recognition that allows Paul to call this new Gentile-Jewish community, this new creation, “the Israel of God” (<a href="?bref=Gal.6.15-16">Gal 6:15-16</a>). In this new community the traditional barriers of race, social standing, and sex—barriers that divided people from one another and categorized them into inferior and superior classes—are seen to be shattered: “There is neither Jew nor Greek, slave nor free, male nor female, for you are all one in Christ Jesus” (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.28">Gal 3:28</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). This one entity is called “the body of Christ.”</p>
<p>Paul is alone among NT writers in speaking of the church as Christ’s body (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.5">Rom 12:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.27">1 Cor 12:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.22-23">Eph 1:22-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.12">4:12</a>; see also <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.16-17">1 Cor 10:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.12-13">12:12-13</a>), or as “the body” of which Christ is the “head” (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.15">Eph 4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.18">Col 1:18</a>). The origin of this way of speaking about the church is not clear. Among a number of suggestions, two are particularly revealing about Paul’s thought: (1) The Damascus road experience. According to the accounts in Acts (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.3-7">9:3-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.22.6-11">22:6-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.12-18">26:12-18</a>), Jesus identifies himself with his persecuted disciples. By persecuting these early Christians, Paul was actually fighting against Christ himself. It is possible that later reflection on this experience led Paul to the conviction that the living Christ was so identified with his community that it could be spoken of as his “body,” that is, the concrete expression of his real presence. (2) The Hebrew concept of corporate solidarity. Paul was a Hebrew of the Hebrews (<a href="?bref=Phil.3.5">Phil 3:5</a>), and his thinking was thoroughly Jewish. In that context, the individual is largely thought of as intimately tied into the nation as a whole; the individual does not have real existence apart from the whole people. At the same time, the entire people can be seen as represented by one individual. Thus, “Israel” is both the name of one individual and the name of a whole people. The “servant” of <a href="?bref=Isa.42.1-53.12">Isaiah 42–53</a> can be both an individual (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.1-4">Is 42:1-4</a>) and the nation of Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.1-6">49:1-6</a>). This idea of corporate solidarity (or personality) is the background for the intimate connection Paul makes between “the first Adam” and sinful humanity as well as between “the last (or second) Adam” (Christ) and renewed humanity (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45-49">1 Cor 15:45-49</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Rom.5.12-21">Rom 5:12-21</a>).</p>
<p>The reality of the intimate relation between Christ and his church is thus expressed by Paul as the organic unity and integration of the physical body (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.4-8">Rom 12:4-8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.12-27">1 Cor 12:12-27</a>). For Paul, the Lord’s Supper is a specific manifestation of this reality: “The bread which we break, is it not a participation in the body of Christ? Because there is one bread, we who are many are one body, for we all partake of the one bread” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.16b-17">1 Cor 10:16b-17</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Since this is the case, Paul goes on to argue, all the functions of the body have their legitimate and rightful place. Division within the body (i.e., the church) reveals that there is something unhealthy within. It is this image of the church as the “body of Christ” that lies behind Paul’s repeated call for and insistence upon unity within the Christian community.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="UnityWithChristMeansCommunityWithChristians"/>
  </body>
</item>