<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Coins">
  <title>Coins</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COINS</p>
<p class="fl">Pieces of metal used and accepted as a medium of exchange. A coin has a specific weight and bears some type of authentication to make it easily recognizable. The word “coin” originally referred to a wedge-shaped die or stamp used to “strike” the metal blank. The first coins may have been minted in the late eighth century <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#EarliestCoinsinPalestine">Earliest Coins in Palestine</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#CoinagefromtheMaccabeestoHerodAgrippaI">Coinage from the Maccabees to Herod Agrippa I</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#RomanCoinsinNewTestamentTimes">Roman Coins in New Testament Times</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="EarliestCoinsinPalestine">Earliest Coins in Palestine</p>
<p class="fl">Not until the time of Darius the Great (Darius I of Persia, 521–486 <span class="era">BC</span>) did an official government-sponsored coinage become current in Palestine. Those earliest coins were oval-shaped gold darics, along with some silver coins.</p>
<p>“Dram” is another term for the Persian gold daric. It is mentioned in <a href="?bref=Ezra.2.68-69">Ezra 2:68-69</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>), where Zerubbabel’s caravan offered gold darics amounting to $30,000 toward rebuilding the temple. This passage is the first mention of an actual coin in the Bible.</p>
<p>Almost at the same time that the Persian coins became current in Palestine, the widely popular silver tetradrachmas (four-drachma pieces) of Athens began to find their way to the mercantile centers of the Phoenician, Israelite, and Philistine coasts. Archaeologists have unearthed them in hoards throughout the eastern Mediterranean region. They continued to be used through the Persian period, which lasted until the Persian Empire was conquered by Alexander the Great in 334–330 <span class="era">BC</span>. The coin was thick and heavy in appearance, but being of high-quality silver, it was in great demand for international commerce. Presumably Greek merchants found they could obtain the most desirable Asiatic imports in exchange for that particular form of currency.</p>
<p>The silver didrachma, or half-drachma, in general use in the Greek Empire from the fourth century <span class="era">BC</span>, continued through Roman times. After Alexander’s conquests, of course, Greek coins were used throughout the Macedonian Empire from present-day Yugoslavia to Pakistan. They were almost certainly employed for business purposes in Judea, for example.</p>
<p>The shekels of the Phoenician trade centers of Tyre and Sidon, which had contributed substantially to the money supply in the Persian period, continued to be accepted in Judea even after the Alexandrian conquest. Typical of Sidon was a silver shekel portraying the battlements and walls of Sidon’s harbor, with a ship lying at anchor and two prancing lions in the foreground. A typical Tyrian shekel showed the god Baal robed and wearing a tiara. He was riding a hippocamp (winged horse with the tail of a fish) on the sea, with a fish or dolphin beneath. The reverse showed an Egyptian-type owl facing right, plus a shepherd’s crook and flail, both royal insignia in Egypt. The stater (or tetradrachma) found by the disciple Peter in a fish’s mouth and used to pay the temple tax for himself and Jesus may have been a Tyrian coin (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.27">Mt 17:27</a>; <span class="sc">rsv</span> “shekel”).</p>
<p>The talent, which represented a certain weight of gold or silver, was a common medium of exchange before the development of coinage. During the Maccabean period, John Hyrcanus saved the city of Jerusalem from destruction in 133 <span class="era">BC</span> by paying a ransom from a 900-year-old hoard stored in David’s sepulcher. Three thousand talents of silver were sent to the Seleucid king Antiochus VII Sidetes in return for his promise to withdraw his troops. Treasure plundered from the temple by the Romans in <span class="era">AD</span> 66 is recorded as amounting to 17 talents. In gold talents that sum would represent the equivalent of the purchase price of about 15 large houses in a modern Western city.</p>
<p class="h2" id="CoinagefromtheMaccabeestoHerodAgrippaI">Coinage from the Maccabees to Herod Agrippa I</p>
<p class="fl">Even though a native Jewish dynasty assumed the government of the Holy Land, it was many years before any indigenous Jewish coinage was minted. Presumably the inhabitants continued to use the coinage of Tyre and Egypt and of the Seleucid Empire for their commercial transactions. It was formerly supposed that silver shekels bearing images of the chalice and pomegranate cluster dated from the reign of Simon Maccabeus (142–134 <span class="era">BC</span>); more recent archaeological discoveries prove that those coins date from the first Jewish revolt (<span class="era">AD</span> 66–70).</p>
<p>When the time came to issue the first Jewish coins, the die makers faced several problems. No mint was available, and no local people were skilled in design or die sinking. Coins current in the Near East at that time, which showed a high degree of design and craftsmanship, each bore the portrait head of a ruler or a god. For the Jews to make such coins would have meant contravening the second commandment, “You shall not make for yourself a graven image” (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.4">Ex 20:4</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Not until well into Roman times was a coin struck in Palestine bearing a portrait head of a Roman emperor.</p>
<p>The earliest coinage of the Hasmonean dynasty (the regnal name of the Maccabees) was the small bronze lepton (plural, lepta) of John Hyrcanus I (134–104 <span class="era">BC</span>), son of Simon Maccabeus. The obverse showed two cornucopias with a pomegranate between them. That image symbolized the fertility that God had granted to the land. The reverse contained an inscription within a wreath, “John the high priest and the community of the Jews.” Small bronze lepta from the reign of Alexander Janneus, son of Hyrcanus I, have been found in great numbers. They were evidently much in demand for transactions at the temple, where money changers converted the gentile currency of visiting worshipers into the more acceptable Jewish money. Undoubtedly Hasmonean lepta were the coins Jesus scattered over the pavement of the Court of the Gentiles when he overturned the tables of the money changers (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.12">Mt 21:12</a>; <a href="?bref=John.2.15">Jn 2:15</a>). The lepton, or “mite,” of bronze or copper, worth <span class="sup">1</span>/<span class="sub">400</span> of a shekel, was mentioned by Jesus on another occasion. He praised a widow’s gift of two mites to the temple treasury with the comment that the rich “contributed out of their abundance; but she out of her poverty has put in everything she had, her whole living” (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.44">Mk 12:44</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Herod I came to power in Judea under the patronage of Mark Antony and secured the allegiance of the pro-Hasmonean Jews by marrying Mariamne, granddaughter of Hyrcanus II, in 38 <span class="era">BC</span>. Herod was empowered to strike his own bronze coins. Although he had a free hand to introduce innovations, Herod’s lepta followed tradition quite faithfully. The lepta carried an anchor with letters meaning “Of King Herod.” The reverse bore the double cornucopias with a pomegranate (or poppy) between them. Herod also minted a large bronze coin with what appears to be a Macedonian helmet on the obverse and a slender tripod on the reverse, along with an inscription of Herod’s name. Other designs he employed included wheat, eagles, and wreaths. He issued no silver coinage, relying instead on the available supplies of silver coins from Tyre, Syria, Asia Minor, Greece, and Rome.</p>
<p>After Herod’s death in 4 <span class="era">BC</span>, his son Herod Archelaus assumed control. Lepta from that period bore a hanging cluster of grapes with a Greek inscription, and on the reverse a two-plumed Macedonian helmet. Grapes were an allusion to Israel as the Lord’s vine (<a href="?bref=Isa.5.1-30">Is 5</a>).</p>
<p>When Herod Antipas began his rule, also in 4 <span class="era">BC</span>, he had no authority in Judea or Samaria. That portion of the former Jewish kingdom was placed under the control of Roman governors, or procurators, appointed directly by the emperor himself. Most familiar of the Roman procurators of Judea was Pontius Pilate (<span class="era">AD</span> 26–36). His bronze coinage showed some bold innovations; his designs included representations of instruments used in the Roman religion such as the augur’s wand (resembling a shepherd’s crook in shape) and a ladle used in connection with broth prepared at sacrifices. The reverse bore a wreath enclosing the regnal date of <span class="era">AD</span> 30–31. The two lepta put into the temple treasury (<a href="?bref=Luke.21.2">Lk 21:2</a>) could have been lepta issued by Pilate or his predecessor. More likely, however, they were the Hasmonean lepta of Hyrcanus or Janneus, which were free of any taint of pagan Roman influence.</p>
<p>Herod Agrippa I (<span class="era">AD</span> 37–44), grandson of Herod the Great, continued the family tradition of ingratiating himself with the Roman overlords. Many of Herod Agrippa’s lepta have been found, showing a conical tasseled umbrella (perhaps symbolizing his royal protection of the people of Palestine) plus a Greek inscription indicating his reign. The reverse showed a bound cluster of three wheat ears and bore the regnal year as the legend.</p>
<p class="h2" id="RomanCoinsinNewTestamentTimes">Roman Coins in New Testament Times</p>
<p class="fl">The Roman “as” came into circulation about 348 <span class="era">BC</span> as a bronze coin bearing the figure of an animal. The coin was named after the Roman one-pound weight, equivalent to 12 ounces (340 grams) in our modern system. At the time of Christ’s birth, the Roman “as” minted for use in the Asiatic provinces bore the head of the emperor Augustus, with a laurel wreath on the reverse. A smaller bronze quadrans, or quarter “as,” was also minted by the Romans.</p>
<p>Another bronze coin found in Greek and Roman currency was the assarion, first minted in the first century <span class="era">BC</span> but still in use in the Christian period. One type was stamped with a winged sphinx, with an amphora on the reverse. It is still debated whether the coin described as a “farthing” in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> was in fact a Greek assarion or a Roman “as” or quadrans. The coin is mentioned four times in the NT, most familiarly in the question “Are not two sparrows sold for a farthing?” (see <a href="?bref=Matt.5.26">Mt 5:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.10.29">10:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.42">Mk 12:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.6">Lk 12:6</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span> “penny”). There is no doubt that the <span class="sc">kjv</span> translators decided to make the coin seem more familiar to their readers by using the name of the smallest copper coin in circulation in England at that time.</p>
<p>The word translated “penny” in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> is the Greek form of “denarius,” the normal daily wage for a laborer in NT times. In the parable of the laborers in the vineyard, for example, the master agreed to pay each man “a penny” for his day’s work (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.2">Mt 20:2</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>; <span class="sc">rsv</span> “a denarius”). “Two pence” was the amount paid to the innkeeper by the good Samaritan (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.35">Lk 10:35</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). Because of the influence of the Roman denarius on British currency, the English penny has always been represented by the initial letter of its Roman equivalent.</p>
<p>When the denarius, or “penny,” is recognized as a normal day’s wage, the astonishment of Jesus’ disciples when they were expected to find food for 5,000 people is better understood. They exclaimed that “two hundred pennyworth” of food would not feed such a crowd (<a href="?bref=John.6.7">Jn 6:7</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>); that sum represented more than six months’ work.</p>
<p>As might be expected, the silver and gold coinage current in Palestine during the time of Christ and for the remainder of the first century <span class="era">AD</span> came primarily from Rome. The larger silver coins, however, that are referred to as tetradrachmas or staters in the NT came from Egypt, Phoenicia, or Antioch. The silver coin most frequently mentioned in the NT was the Roman denarius or the Greek drachma. Since few drachmas have been found in excavations dating from the first century, it is possible that the term was used in popular speech to refer to the denarius (plural, denarii), which was approximately the same size as the average Greek drachma. Actually, few Greek cities were permitted by their Roman overlords to continue minting drachmas.</p>
<p>Caesar Augustus issued a decree for all the Roman world to be enrolled (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.1-2">Lk 2:1-2</a>) in an empire-wide census just about the time that Jesus was born (6 or 5 <span class="era">BC</span>). During his long reign (27 <span class="era">BC</span>–<span class="era">AD</span> 14), Augustus authorized a large variety of denarii. They generally carried his likeness on their obverse with the inscription “Augustus, son of the divine one” (that is, son of Julius Caesar, who had been voted divine honors by the Roman Senate).</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Matt.22.19">Matthew 22:19</a> Jesus asked those trying to trick him with a question to show him a coin used to pay the government tax. They handed him a denarius bearing the portrait and inscription of Caesar (<a href="?bref=Matt.22.21">Mt 22:21</a>). That coin could have been a denarius of Augustus, who had died some 16 years before, or of Tiberius (<span class="era">AD</span> 14–37), who was then on the throne. The silver denarius of Tiberius read “Tiberius Caesar Augustus, son of the divine Augustus.” The reverse showed the high priestess of the vestal order, flaming torch in hand, seated on her throne facing right. The title “pontif(ex) maxim(us)” referred to Tiberius rather than to the priestess.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=MineralsandMetals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Minerals and Metals</a>; <a href="?item=Money_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Money</a>; <a href="?item=MoneyChanger_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Money Changer</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>