<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CommandmentstheTen">
  <title>Commandments, the Ten</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COMMANDMENTS, The Ten</p>
<p class="fl">List of commands given by God to Moses. The Ten Commandments are stated twice in the OT; first in the book of Exodus (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.2-17">20:2-17</a>), in a passage describing God’s gift of the commandments to Israel, and second in Deuteronomy (<a href="?bref=Deut.5.6-21">5:6-21</a>), in the context of a covenant renewal ceremony. Moses reminds his people of the substance and meaning of the commandments, as they renew their covenant allegiance to God. In the original language, the commandments are called the “Ten Words” (from which comes the name Decalogue). According to the biblical text, they are “words,” or laws, spoken by God, not the result of human legislative process. The commandments are said to have been written on two tablets. This does not mean that five commandments were written on each tablet; rather, all ten were written on each tablet, the first tablet belonging to God the lawgiver, the second tablet belonging to Israel the recipient. The commandments pertain to two basic areas of human living: the first five concern relationships with God, the last five, relationships between human beings. The commandments were given first to Israel in the making of the covenant at Mt Sinai, shortly after the exodus from Egypt. Though the date of the Sinai covenant cannot be fixed with certainty, it was probably around 1290 <span class="era">BC</span>. In order to understand the commandments, it is necessary first to understand the context in which they were given.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#TheContextoftheCommandments">The Context of the Commandments</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheMeaningoftheCommandments">The Meaning of the Commandments</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#ThePrincipleoftheCommandments">The Principle of the Commandments</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="TheContextoftheCommandments">The Context of the Commandments</p>
<p class="fl">The commandments are inseparable from the covenant. The making of a covenant between God and Israel at Sinai was the formation of a particular relationship. God made certain commitments to Israel and in return imposed certain obligations upon Israel. Although Israel’s obligations are expressed in detail in a mass of precise legal material, they are given their most precise and succinct expression in the Ten Commandments. The commandments set down the most fundamental principles of all Hebrew law, and the detailed laws contained in the Pentateuch are for the most part applications of the principles to particular situations. Thus, the role of the Ten Commandments in ancient Israel was to give direction to a relationship. They were not to be obeyed simply for the sake of obedience, as though obedience accumulated some kind of credit. Rather, they were to be obeyed in order to discover the fullness and richness of life in a relationship with God.</p>
<p>The commandments in ancient Israel were not an ethical code or compilation of advice on the fundamentals of morality. The covenant was between God and a nation; the commandments were directed toward the life of that nation and its citizens. Consequently, the initial role of the commandments was similar to that of criminal law in a modern state. Israel was a theocracy, a state whose king was God (<a href="?bref=Deut.33.5">Dt 33:5</a>). The commandments provided guidance to the citizens of that state. In addition, to break a commandment was to commit a crime against the state and the ruler of that state, God. Thus, the penalties were severe, for the breaking of the commandments threatened the covenant relationship and the continued existence of the state. This state context is important for understanding the commandments in their initial form.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheMeaningoftheCommandments">The Meaning of the Commandments</p>
<p class="fl">The commandments begin with a preface (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.2">Ex 20:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.6">Dt 5:6</a>) that identifies the lawgiver, God, who gave the commandments to a people with whom he already had a relationship. The lawgiver is the God of the exodus, who redeemed his people from slavery and granted them freedom. The preface is vital, for it indicates that God’s gift of law was preceded by an act of love and grace. The commandments were given to a people who had been redeemed; they were not given in order to achieve redemption. There are some variations in the manner of numbering the commandments. According to some systems, the preface is identified with the first commandments. It seems preferable, however, to understand the opening words as a preface to all ten commandments. In the notes on the Ten Commandments that follow, there is first an explanation of the original meaning, then some indication of the contemporary meaning.</p>
<p class="h3">First Commandment: Prohibition of Worshiping Gods Other Than the Lord (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.3">Ex 20:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.7">Dt 5:7</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The first commandment is in negative form and expressly prohibits the Israelites engaging in the worship of foreign deities. The significance of the commandment lies in the nature of the covenant. The essence of the covenant was a relationship, and the essence of relationship, from the biblical perspective, is faithfulness. God’s faithfulness to his people had already been demonstrated in the exodus, as indicated in the preface to the commandments. In turn, God required of his people, more than anything else, a faithfulness in their relationship with him. Thus, though the commandment is stated negatively, it is full of positive implications. And its position as first of the ten is significant, for this commandment establishes a principle that is particularly prominent in the social commandments (six through ten).</p>
<p>The contemporary significance of the commandment is in the context of faithfulness in relationship. At the heart of human life, there must be a relationship with God. Anything in life that disrupts that primary relationship breaks the commandment. Foreign “gods” are thus persons, or even things, that would disrupt the primacy of the relationship with God.</p>
<p class="h3">Second Commandment: Prohibition of Making Images (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.4-6">Ex 20:4-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.8-10">Dt 5:8-10</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The second commandment prohibits the Israelites from making images of the Lord. To make an image of God, in the shape or form of anything in this world, is to reduce the Creator to something less than his creation and to worship the created instead of the Creator. The temptation for Israel to worship God in the form of an image must have been enormous, for images and idols flourished in all the religions of the ancient Near East. But the God of Israel was a transcendent and infinite being, and could not be reduced to the limitations of an image or form within creation. Any such reduction of God would be so radical a misunderstanding that the “god” worshiped would no longer be the God of the universe.</p>
<p>In the modern world, the shape of the temptation has changed. Few are tempted to take power tools and shape from wood an image of God. Nevertheless, the commandment is still applicable and the danger against which it guards is always present.</p>
<p class="h3">Third Commandment: Prohibition of the Improper Use of God’s Name (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.7">Ex 20:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.11">Dt 5:11</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">There is a popular understanding that the third commandment prohibits bad language or blasphemy; however, it is concerned with the use of God’s name. God had granted to Israel an extraordinary privilege; he had revealed to them his personal name. The name, in Hebrew, is represented by four letters, <span class="ital">YHWH,</span> which are variously rendered in English Bibles as <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, Yahweh, or Jehovah. The knowledge of the divine name was a privilege, for it meant that Israel did not worship an anonymous and distant deity but a being with a personal name. Yet the privilege was accompanied by the danger that the knowledge of God’s personal name could be abused. In ancient Near Eastern religions, magic was a common practice. Magic involved the use of a god’s name, which was believed to control a god’s power, in certain kinds of activity designed to harness it for human purposes. Thus, the kind of activity that is prohibited by the third commandment is magic, namely, attempting to control God’s power, through his name, for a personal and worthless purpose. God may give, but must not be manipulated or controlled.</p>
<p>Within Christianity, the name of God is equally important. Through God’s name is access to God in prayer. The abuse of the privilege of prayer, involving calling upon the name of God for some selfish or worthless purpose or swearing falsely by it, is tantamount to the magic of the ancient world. In both, God’s name is abused and the third commandment is broken. Positively, the third commandment is a reminder of the enormous privilege of knowing God’s name, a privilege not to be taken lightly or abused.</p>
<p class="h3">Fourth Commandment: Requirement to Observe the Sabbath (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.8-11">Ex 20:8-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.12-15">Dt 5:12-15</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This commandment, once again, has no parallels in ancient Near Eastern religions; furthermore, it is the first of the commandments to be expressed in a positive form. While most of life was characterized by work, the seventh day was to be set aside. Work was to cease and the day was to be kept holy. The holiness of the day is related to the reason for its establishment. Two reasons are given, and though at first they appear different, there is a common theme linking them. In the first version of the commandment (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.11">Ex 20:11</a>), the Sabbath is kept in commemoration of Creation; God created in six days and rested on the seventh day. In the second version (<a href="?bref=Deut.5.15">Dt 5:15</a>), the Sabbath is observed in commemoration of the exodus from Egypt. The theme linking the two versions is creation: God not only created the world but also “created” his people, Israel, in redeeming them from Egyptian slavery. Thus, every seventh day throughout the passage of time, the Hebrew people were to reflect upon Creation; in so doing, they were reflecting upon the meaning of their existence.</p>
<p>For most of Christianity, the concept of “sabbath” has been moved from the seventh to the first day of the week, namely Sunday. The move is related to a change in Christian thought, which is identified in the resurrection of Jesus Christ on a Sunday morning. The change is appropriate, for Christians now reflect each Sunday, or “Sabbath,” on a third act of divine creation, namely the “new creation” that is established in the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead.</p>
<p class="h3">Fifth Commandment: Requirement to Honor Parents (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.12">Ex 20:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.16">Dt 5:16</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The fifth commandment forms a bridge between the first four, concerned primarily with God, and the last five, concerned primarily with human relationships. On first reading, it appears to be concerned with family relationships only: children are to honor their parents. Although the commandment establishes a principle of honor or respect in family relationships, it is probably also related to the responsibility of parents to instruct their children in the faith of the covenant (<a href="?bref=Deut.6.7">Dt 6:7</a>), so that the religion could be passed on from one generation to another. But instruction in the faith required an attitude of honor and respect from those who were being instructed. Thus, the fifth commandment is concerned not only with family harmony but also with the transmission of faith in God throughout subsequent generations.</p>
<p>With the fifth commandment, there is little need to convert its meaning into contemporary relevance. At a time in which so much education is undertaken beyond the confines of the family unit, the commandment serves a solemn reminder, not only of the need for harmonious family life, but also of the responsibilities of religious education which rest upon both parents and children.</p>
<p class="h3">Sixth Commandment: Prohibition of Murder (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.13">Ex 20:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.17">Dt 5:17</a>).</p>
<p class="fl">The wording of this commandment simply prohibits “killing”; the meaning of the word, however, implies the prohibition of murder. The word used in the commandment is not related primarily to killing in warfare or to capital punishment, both of which are dealt with in other portions of the Mosaic law. The word could be used to designate both murder and manslaughter. Since manslaughter involves accidental killing, it cannot be sensibly prohibited; it, too, is dealt with in other legislation (<a href="?bref=Deut.19.1-13">Dt 19:1-13</a>). Thus, the sixth commandment prohibits murder, the taking of another person’s life for personal and selfish gain. Stated positively, the sixth commandment preserves for each member of the covenant community the right to live.</p>
<p>In the modern world, a similar statute prohibiting murder exists in almost all legal codes, having become a part of state law, in addition to purely religious or moral law. Jesus, however, pointed to the deeper meaning implicit in the commandment. It is not only the act, but also the sentiment underlying the act, that is evil (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.21-22">Mt 5:21-22</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Seventh Commandment: Prohibition of Adultery (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.14">Ex 20:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.18">Dt 5:18</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The act of adultery is fundamentally an act of unfaithfulness. One or both persons in an adulterous act are being unfaithful to another person or persons. Of all such crimes, the worst is that which signifies unfaithfulness. It is for this reason that adultery is included in the Ten Commandments while other sins or crimes pertaining to sexuality are not included. Thus, the seventh commandment is the social parallel to the first commandment. Just as the first commandment requires absolute faithfulness in the relationship with the one God, so the seventh requires a similar relationship of faithfulness within the covenant of marriage.</p>
<p>The relevance of the commandment is apparent, but again Jesus points to the implications of the commandment for the mental life (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.27-28">Mt 5:27-28</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Eighth Commandment: Prohibition of Theft (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.15">Ex 20:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.19">Dt 5:19</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The eighth commandment establishes a principle within the covenant community concerning possessions and property; a person had a right to certain things, which could not be violated by a fellow citizen for his or her personal advantage. But while the commandment is concerned with property, its most fundamental concern is human liberty. The worst form of theft is “manstealing” (somewhat equivalent to modern kidnapping)—that is, taking a person (presumably by force) and selling him or her into slavery. The crime and the related law are stated more fully in <a href="?bref=Deut.24.7">Deuteronomy 24:7</a>. The commandment is thus not only concerned with the preservation of private property but is more fundamentally concerned with the preservation of human liberty, freedom from such things as slavery and exile. It prohibits a person from manipulating or exploiting the lives of others for personal gain.</p>
<p>Just as the sixth commandment prohibits murder, so the eighth prohibits what might be called “social murder,” that is, the cutting off of a man or woman from a life of freedom within the community of God’s people.</p>
<p class="h3">Ninth Commandment: Prohibition of False Witnessing (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.16">Ex 20:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.20">Dt 5:20</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The commandment is not a general prohibition against lies. The wording of the original commandment sets it firmly in the context of Israel’s legal system. It prohibits perjury, or the giving of false testimony within the proceedings of the law court. Thus, it establishes a principle of truthfulness and carries implications with respect to false statements in any context. Within any nation, the courts of law must be able to operate on the basis of true information. If law is not based on truth and righteousness, then the very foundations of life and liberty are undermined. If legal testimony is true, there can be no miscarriage of justice; if it is false, the most fundamental of human liberties are lost. Thus, the commandment sought to preserve the integrity of Israel’s legal system while guarding against encroachments on personal liberties.</p>
<p>The principle is maintained in most modern legal systems—for example, in the taking of an oath before giving evidence in court. But in the last resort, the commandment points to the essential nature of truthfulness in all interpersonal relationships.</p>
<p class="h3">Tenth Commandment: Prohibition of Coveting (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.17">Ex 20:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.21">Dt 5:21</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The tenth commandment is curious in its initial context. It prohibits the coveting, or desiring, of persons or things belonging to a neighbor (that is, a fellow Israelite). To find such a commandment in a code of criminal law is unusual. The first nine commandments prohibited acts, and a criminal act can be followed by prosecution and legal process if detected. But the tenth commandment, in contrast, prohibits <span class="ital">desires,</span> or covetous feelings. Under human law, it is not possible to prosecute upon the basis of desire, since proof would be impossible. While the crime involved in the tenth commandment could not be prosecuted within the limitations of the Hebrew system, it was nevertheless known by God, the “Chief Judge.” The genius of the commandment lies in its therapeutic nature. It is not enough merely to deal with crime once it has been committed; the law must also attempt to attack the roots of crime.</p>
<p>The root of almost all evil and crime lies within the self, in the desires of the individual. Thus evil desires are prohibited. If covetous desires are gradually eliminated, then natural desires may be directed toward God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ThePrincipleoftheCommandments">The Principle of the Commandments</p>
<p class="fl">The relevance of each commandment is understood in the underlying principle of the whole Decalogue. The principle of the whole is the principle of love, the heart of Israel’s religion. God loved Israel and called them in love. In return, he imposed one commandment upon Israel that superseded all others: “You shall love the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your might” (<a href="?bref=Deut.6.5">Dt 6:5</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). That is the central commandment of Israel’s religion. How to love the invisible, intangible God is partly explained in the Decalogue. For the person who loves God, the Ten Commandments provide guidance; they point to a way of life that, if lived, reflects love for God and leads to a deeper experience of God’s love. Therefore, the Ten Commandments continue to be a central part of Christianity. Jesus repeated the commandment to love from <a href="?bref=Deut.6.5">Deuteronomy 6:5</a> and he called it “the first and greatest commandment” (<a href="?bref=Matt.22.37-38">Mt 22:37-38</a>). Consequently, the Ten Commandments still serve as a guide for the Christian community.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CivilLawandJustice_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Civil Law and Justice</a>; <a href="?item=LawBiblicalConceptof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Law, Biblical Concept of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>