<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Communication">
  <title>Communication</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COMMUNICATION</p>
<p class="fl">The act of transmitting a message. Fire, light, and smoke signals were probably the earliest methods of communicating over any distance. The Babylonians were the first to employ a primitive heliograph system (reflected sunlight) for signaling over short distances. A classic use of fire beacons was related by Aeschylus, a Greek dramatist, who described the news of the fall of Troy being relayed to Clytemnestra of Mycenae (c. 1084 <span class="era">BC</span>) by a dozen or more fires lighted on mountaintops. Similarly, the Lachish letters mention the use of fire signals to coordinate Israel’s defense against the Babylonians in 587 <span class="era">BC</span>. One letter concludes, “Let my lord know that we are watching for the fire signals of Lachish according to the signs my lord has given, because we do not see Azekah” (see <a href="?bref=Jer.6.1">Jer 6:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.34.7">34:7</a>). Later, fire signals were communicated from lighthouses such as the famous one at Alexandria, Egypt.</p>
<p>Projected sounds have been used as a means of communication for thousands of years. Around 550 <span class="era">BC</span>, Cyrus of Persia built a network of towers from which a soldier shouted a message to a soldier in a nearby tower. According to legend, Alexander the Great had a giant megaphone that could carry a voice several miles. The historian Severus said that the Romans had brass speaking tubes to aid in defense along the northern wall in England. The Hebrews used the <span class="hebrew">shofar</span><span class="ital">,</span> a ram’s horn trumpet, to announce the new moon, the beginning of the Sabbath, and the approach of danger (<a href="?bref=Josh.6.4">Jos 6:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.7.16">Jgs 7:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.8.1">Hos 8:1</a>). Also, drum tattoos were used in communication. Even today Ashanti drummers in Ghana can render high and low tones that correspond to the tonal values of their language.</p>
<p>Archaeological excavations have uncovered thousands of ancient business and family letters written on clay tablets. As early as 2000 <span class="era">BC</span> the Assyrians maintained an informal postal service with eastern Anatolia (Asia Minor), using the caravans that frequently went between them. Later, Assyrian roads used by the army were also traveled by royal messengers of an efficient government mail service. A network of postal officials stationed in key population centers supervised the couriers and the mail. Clay tablets listing the place-names along a given route and the distances between them served as travel guides. Many royal letters of Assyria and other parts of the Middle East now help to reconstruct ancient history.</p>
<p>After the Persians ascended to power, they expanded the Assyrians’ postal service. The Persian “royal road” was built for government messengers, but it was open to all. It extended more than 1,600 miles (2,574 kilometers) from Sardis in Asia Minor to Susa, the Persian capital located near the head of the Persian Gulf (<a href="?bref=Esth.3.13">Est 3:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.8.10">8:10</a>). Royalty and officials traveling that highway found rest houses and inns about 15 miles (24 kilometers) apart, forts at strategic points, and ferries for river crossings. Ordinary travelers, averaging 18 miles (29 kilometers) a day, would spend three months traveling the full length of the road. The Persian dispatch service, however, relaying messages on fresh mounts between regular stages, probably traversed the same distance in two or three weeks. Describing a Persian messenger, the Greek historian Herodotus in the fifth century <span class="era">BC</span> reported that neither snow nor rain nor heat nor gloom of night prevented the swiftest possible completion of their appointed rounds.</p>
<p>At the same time as the Persians, the Chou dynasty in China had built up an efficient postal system. By the third century <span class="era">BC</span>, the Han dynasty of China and the Ptolemies of Egypt were operating the closest thing to a modern postal system that the ancient world was to know. A system of communication, necessary to rule the large Roman Empire, was devised in the reign of Caesar Augustus (27 <span class="era">BC</span>–<span class="era">AD</span> 14). The idea for the system came after the Romans annexed Egypt in 30 <span class="era">BC</span>. The Roman system did not stress speed or regularity, and although the mail moved speedily over short distances, it could take weeks over long distances or over water. Usually the mail system of the emperors did not benefit the ordinary public; rather, it was an added tax burden. Wealthy families had their own slaves deliver mail, businesses employed letter carriers, and the poor asked traveling friends to carry messages.</p>
<p>A letter written by Christian leaders in Jerusalem to the churches of Asia Minor was delivered by the apostle Paul and Barnabas (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.22-29">Acts 15:22-29</a>). Later, Paul requested Timothy (<a href="?bref=1Thes.3.2">1 Thes 3:2</a>), Tychicus (<a href="?bref=Col.4.7,9">Col 4:7, 9</a>), and Epaphroditus (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.25">Phil 2:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.4.18">4:18</a>) to serve as messengers.</p>
<p>One means of local communication was the Roman <span class="ital">album</span> (Latin for “white”), a white-painted public bulletin board displayed in the center of a city on which messages were painted in black.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Travel_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Travel</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>