<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Corinth">
  <title>Corinth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CORINTH</p>
<p class="fl">Prominent city of Greece, formerly the capital of the ancient province of Achaia, in which the apostle Paul preached. The site of ancient Corinth lies to the west of the isthmus separating the Peloponnesian Peninsula from mainland Greece. The ancient ruins, largely of Roman origin, are situated about four-fifths of a mile (1,285 meters) from present-day Corinth. The area was inhabited from Neolithic times. Corinth is dominated by an outcrop of rock known as Acrocorinth (Upper Corinth). The grandeur of the Greek period is evident in the remains of the temple of Apollo, whose massive columns dominate the site. Entrance to the ancient city is by means of a very broad avenue that lies in a straight line from the city gate. That avenue ends in the marketplace, with roads leading from there to the Acrocorinth. In the apostolic period the city was a bustling commercial and industrial center boasting a population of almost 700,000.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HistoryandArchaeology">History and Archaeology</p>
<p class="fl">By the mid-eighth century <span class="era">BC</span>, Corinth, strategically located along east-west trade routes, was a flourishing city-state. From 350–250 <span class="era">BC</span> it was the most prominent city in Greece. Then the Roman military machine began a relentless march to forge a vast empire. In 146 <span class="era">BC</span> Corinth was completely destroyed and lay in ruins for a century. In 46 <span class="era">BC</span> Julius Caesar moved a mixed group of Italians and dispossessed Greeks onto the site, and once more a magnificent city arose, this time as a Roman colony. As in most Roman cities, marble temples dominated the landscape. The city was supplied with water from an underground well. It became a cosmopolitan city attracting tradespeople from all over the world, though its reputation grew simultaneously as a center of luxury, indulgence, and vice. A large colony of displaced Jews (part of the Diaspora) developed in the city, the group that undoubtedly attracted the apostle Paul.</p>
<p>In 1896 the American School of Classical Studies at Athens secured permission to begin excavation of the ancient site. The finds are of special interest for study of the NT Corinthian epistles. An important archaeological find was a doorway lintel bearing a portion of an inscription designating the building as the “Synagogue of the Hebrews.” It may have marked the synagogue in which the apostle preached (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.4">Acts 18:4</a>). Another discovery was the <span class="greek">bema</span><span class="ital">,</span> or judgment place (vv <a href="?bref=Acts.18.12-17">12-17</a>), located in the center of the <span class="greek">agora</span><span class="ital">,</span> or marketplace. There Paul appeared before Gallio, proconsul of Achaia. The dates of Gallio are well established by other inscriptions. He must not have arrived in Corinth before July, <span class="era">AD</span> 51. Paul appeared before him after having ministered in the city for almost 18 months. That would date Paul’s arrival in Corinth as the beginning of <span class="era">AD</span> 50.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TheCorinthianCanal"/>
<p>Corinth is significant in the history of the church because of the ministry of the apostle Paul in response to his Macedonian vision (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.9-10">Acts 16:9-10</a>). He established churches in Philippi, Thessalonica, Berea, and possibly Athens on his way to Corinth. <a href="?bref=Acts.18.1-28">Acts 18</a> describes Paul’s work at Corinth, first with the Jews, who violently opposed him (v <a href="?bref=Acts.18.6">6</a>). At Corinth, Paul engaged in the longest ministry up to that time in either of his first missionary journeys. The Corinthian church, born in such a crucible of paganism, had to go through serious birth pangs. Paul’s letters to the group of believers there reflect a large catalog of troubles for Christians in the first century, a list not unlike the problems of Christians today.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="RemainsOfTheTempleOfApolloInCorinth"/>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CorinthiansFirstLettertothe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Corinthians, First Letter to the</a>; <a href="?item=CorinthiansSecondLettertothe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Corinthians, Second Letter to the</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="IsthmianGamesAtCorinthAndPaulSAthleticImagery"/>
  </body>
</item>