<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CovenanttheNew">
  <title>Covenant, the New</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COVENANT, The New</p>
<p class="fl">A gracious provision of God given through Jesus Christ for the redemption of fallen humanity—replacing and fulfilling the old covenant, which was expressed primarily through the Mosaic law. The expression “new covenant” is found principally in the NT.</p>
<p>Although the concept of a new covenant is found in several places in the OT (<a href="?bref=Ezek.34.23-31">Ez 34:23-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.24-28">37:24-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.12-32">Jl 2:12-32</a>), the actual phrase occurs only once (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.31-34">Jer 31:31-34</a>). That passage contrasts the new covenant that the prophet Jeremiah saw God making with Israel “after those days” (vv <a href="?bref=Jer.31.32-34">32-34</a>) with the covenant God had made with his people in the days of Moses. The contrast is seen, first of all, in the internal nature of the new covenant. Whereas the old covenant was written on tablets of stone (<a href="?bref=Exod.31.18">Ex 31:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.27-32">34:27-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.13">Dt 4:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.22">5:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.9.11">9:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.10.3-4">10:3-4</a>) and in a book (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.7">Ex 24:7</a>; cf. the phrase “old written code,” <a href="?bref=Rom.7.6">Rom 7:6</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), the new covenant is to be written on the human heart. One result is a clearer revelation of what God demands; another is the enablement of believers to fulfill those demands (see <a href="?bref=Rom.8.2-4">Rom 8:2-4</a>). The interior nature of the new covenant is spoken of in several other passages (<a href="?bref=Ezek.11.19-21">Ez 11:19-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.36.26-27">36:26-27</a>) and made explicit in the prophet Joel of a time when God “will pour out [his] spirit on all flesh” (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-32">Jl 2:28-32</a>).</p>
<p>A second contrast is in the way God’s people know him under the two covenants. There is no doubt that Israel under the old covenant “knew” God; God had revealed himself, though at times the nation tended to forget this (<a href="?bref=Judg.2.10">Jgs 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.4.1,6">Hos 4:1, 6</a>). What the prophets envisioned in the new covenant is a unique personal knowledge of God by each individual member of the covenant community.</p>
<p>Finally, the two covenants differ in regard to God’s dealing with human sin. Jeremiah promised that God would forgive the iniquity of his people and blot out their sin. Israel already knew that God delighted in mercy and forgiveness (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6-7">Ex 34:6-7</a>), but Jeremiah was saying that God would never again remember their sin (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.34">Jer 31:34</a>). Under the old covenant there was a reminder of sin year after year (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.3">Heb 10:3</a>); under the new covenant no remembrance of sin remains (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.14">14</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="ANewCovenant">A New Covenant</p>
<p class="fl">The expression “new covenant” is found at least six times in the NT (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.25">1 Cor 11:25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.6">2 Cor 3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.8.8,13">Heb 8:8, 13</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.15">9:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.12.24">12:24</a>; and probably <a href="?bref=Luke.22.20">Lk 22:20</a>, according to some manuscripts). In certain Greek manuscripts the phrase is also found in <a href="?bref=Matt.26.28">Matthew 26:28</a> and <a href="?bref=Mark.14.24">Mark 14:24</a>, where “new” seems to have been added by various scribes to “blood of the covenant,” in order to make these accounts conform to parallel accounts of the Lord’s Supper in 1 Corinthians or possibly in Luke.</p>
<p>Even though the term “new” is not found in the accounts in Matthew and Mark in the best Greek manuscripts, and was therefore probably not part of the original text, it is clear from all four accounts that Jesus saw the Lord’s Supper as instituting a different and therefore “new” covenant. The covenant was being sealed by his sacrificial death, that is, by his blood, just as the Mosaic covenant was sealed by the “blood of the covenant” (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.6-8">Ex 24:6-8</a>). The cup of the Lord’s Supper symbolizes the blood of Christ’s sacrifice, sealing the new covenant God has at last made with his people. The new covenant, ratified by Christ’s death, is what the church therefore commemorates each time it celebrates the Lord’s Supper.</p>
<p>In his institution of the Lord’s Supper, Jesus did not elucidate what the “newness” of the covenant entailed. Elsewhere he mentioned a “baptism with the Holy Spirit” (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.5">Acts 1:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.16">11:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.3.11">Mt 3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.8">Mk 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.16">Lk 3:16</a>; and <a href="?bref=John.1.33">Jn 1:33</a>, where this promise is found on the lips of John the Baptist; cf. also <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.13">1 Cor 12:13</a>). Yet both OT prophecies refer to the same new covenant that God would establish in the future, as shown in <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.6">2 Corinthians 3:6</a>. There the apostle Paul stated that God “has qualified us to be ministers of a new covenant” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.31.31">Jer 31:31</a>), not “in a written code but in the Spirit” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-32">Jl 2:28-32</a>), for “the written code kills, but the Spirit gives life” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="SuperiorityoftheNewCovenant">Superiority of the New Covenant</p>
<p class="fl">In <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.1-18">2 Corinthians 3</a>, Paul was showing that in contrast to the old (Mosaic) covenant (v <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.14">14</a>), which was a dispensation of death, carved in letters on stone (v <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.7">7</a>), the new covenant instituted by Jesus is one of far greater splendor (vv <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.8-9">8-9</a>), written on the human heart by the Spirit of the living God himself (v <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.3">3</a>).</p>
<p>The new covenant concept is treated most exhaustively and systematically in the book of Hebrews. In <a href="?bref=Heb.8.8-12">Hebrews 8:8-12</a> the quotation of <a href="?bref=Jer.31.31-34">Jeremiah 31:31-34</a> is the longest OT quotation found in the NT. In <a href="?bref=Heb.12.24">Hebrews 12:24</a> a different Greek word for “new” is used, but the meaning remains the same. The theme of the new covenant dominates the book of Hebrews, which was written to encourage faltering Christians by demonstrating the superiority of the Christian faith over their old Jewish beliefs and practices. In Hebrews the new covenant is seen as better than the old “obsolete” covenant in a number of ways.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. The new covenant has a better priesthood than the old covenant, since there is no longer any need for a continual change of priests due to death (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.23">Heb 7:23</a>). One continual priest now lives forever to make intercession before God on behalf of his people (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.7.24-25">24-25</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. The new covenant priest is better than those of the old covenant, since Jesus does not have to offer sacrifices continually for his own sins and then for the sins of his people. He has instead made one complete and perfect offering (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.27">7:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.25-28">9:25-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.12">10:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. The new covenant has a better sacrifice than the old covenant; what the blood of bulls and goats could not do, since the atonement they brought could at best be only partial (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.2-3">10:2-3</a>), the blood of Christ has done once for all (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.11-14">9:11-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.1-10">10:1-10</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. The new covenant is built on “better promises” than the old (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.6">8:6</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Whereas the old covenant was imperfect (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.7">8:7</a>) and thus became obsolete (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.13">8:13</a>), the new covenant is perfect and eternal (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.20">13:20</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. Whereas the old covenant provided a believer with no direct access to God (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.6-8">9:6-8</a>), the new covenant provides a direct access to God that can purify and perfect the believer’s conscience (cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.9.14">9:14</a> with <a href="?bref=Heb.9.9">9:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">7. The new covenant possesses a better “surety,” or guarantee, an oath sworn by God himself (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.20-22">7:20-22</a>).</p>
<p class="list">8. The new covenant assures the presence of the Holy Spirit in the life of each believer. The new covenant community has been touched by the promised Spirit (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.4">6:4</a>), who, according to Paul, is both the seal and guarantee of their inheritance (see <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.22">2 Cor 1:22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.5">5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.13-14">Eph 1:13-14</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Conclusion">Conclusion</p>
<p class="fl">The new covenant and its accompanying new commandment are both fulfillments of what was implicit in the old. The new covenant is written on the heart of each member of the new covenant community by the Holy Spirit. The power of God’s Spirit within, enabling the believer to carry out the new commandment (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.2-4">Rom 8:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.16-25">Gal 5:16-25</a>), is a distinctive feature of the new covenant.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Covenant_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Covenant</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>