<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CriminalLawandPunishment">
  <title>Criminal Law and Punishment*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CRIMINAL LAW AND PUNISHMENT*</p>
<p class="fl">The science or philosophy of law is called jurisprudence. Although modern jurisprudence bears little resemblance to biblical concepts of law, the Scriptures have played a definite role in its development. Today, criminal law is clearly distinguished from civil law; in Bible times the distinction was much less clear. Today, offenses against civil law (torts) are distinguished from minor crimes (misdemeanors) as well as from serious crimes (felonies). In the Bible, “crimes” included all punishable offenses, even religious offenses such as idolatry (worshiping a false god) or blasphemy (speaking or behaving with contempt toward God).</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#NearEasternContext">Near Eastern Context</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#HebrewCriminalLaw">Hebrew Criminal Law</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Punishment">Punishment</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Conclusion">Conclusion</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="NearEasternContext">Near Eastern Context</p>
<p class="fl">In ancient societies as in modern ones, laws were considered necessary to regulate individual behavior for the good of the community, state, or nation. Today laws are thought of as made by people for their own protection. In contrast, all ancient Near Eastern law codes were considered to have come directly from some divine source. Hebrew law, though distinct, followed the general pattern of Near Eastern law codes, as is known from those that have survived—such as the Code of Hammurabi and Assyrian and Hittite laws.</p>
<p>Conclusions about the “origin” of ancient laws should be made cautiously. Although evidence indicates that Hammurabi based his legislation partially on earlier Sumerian codes, he declared that his code had been received from Shamash, god of justice. That declaration must have been intended to convey primarily that his code had the express sanction of Shamash, since at least some people would recognize it as a compilation based largely on earlier laws. Similarly, the clear biblical statements about Moses receiving the law on Mt Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.1-24.18">Ex 19–24</a>) do not rule out the possibility that parts of the Decalogue (the Ten Commandments) may have existed in earlier codes. Possibly the Mosaic legislation included some social rules adapted from the period of Israel’s sojourn in Egypt.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HebrewCriminalLaw">Hebrew Criminal Law</p>
<p class="h3">Laws Governing Offenses against God</p>
<p class="fl">Since Hebrew law was designed for a group of people for whom religion was of paramount importance and whose faith was endangered by the influence of the beliefs of their pagan neighbors, it is not surprising that so much of Hebrew law dealt with crimes committed against God. The prohibition against worshiping idols is stated and repeated in the Torah, or Pentateuch (first five books of the Bible): “You shall not make for yourself a graven image, or any likeness of anything that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth; you shall not bow down to them or serve them” (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.4-5">Ex 20:4-5</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Sacrifice of infants, practiced in some pagan religions, was specifically prohibited in Israel. The penalty for that crime, as for the other forms of murder, was stoning to death (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.2">Lv 20:2</a>).</p>
<p>In the book of Leviticus, death by stoning was recorded as the appropriate punishment for blaspheming the name of God (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.11-16">Lv 24:11-16</a>). False prophecy was also a criminal offense; that accusation could apply to a person making a prediction in the name of a god other than the Lord, or implying falsely that one’s prophecy resulted from a communication with God. Jeremiah, whose prophecy of Nebuchadnezzar’s victory over the southern kingdom of Judah was for a time considered to be false, was almost lynched by a mob (<a href="?bref=Jer.26.8-9">Jer 26:8-9</a>).</p>
<p>The idea of keeping the seventh day holy stemmed from the celebration of God’s work in creating the universe in six days and resting on the seventh. Keeping the Sabbath required cessation of manual work for the entire family, including farm animals (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.23">Ex 16:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.20.8-11">20:8-11</a>). People were also required to meet together on the Sabbath for worship, which at a later period in Hebrew history included the reading of Scripture, prayer, and preaching. Anyone breaking the Sabbath could be sentenced to death, as happened to a man caught gathering firewood on the Sabbath (<a href="?bref=Num.15.32-36">Nm 15:32-36</a>).</p>
<p>Any type of premeditated crime was considered an offense against God, the giver of all law; hence, it was punishable by death (<a href="?bref=Num.15.30-31">Nm 15:30-31</a>). Hebrew law also insisted on donation of the firstfruits of harvest to the Lord without delay. That requirement was sometimes carried over to include a first child, whose life was dedicated to service in the temple (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.29-30">Ex 22:29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.15.19">Dt 15:19</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Personal Injury</p>
<p class="fl">Murder, an offense against “God’s image,” was one of many crimes punishable by death in OT times. The book of Exodus stated unequivocally that “anyone who hits a person hard enough to cause death must be put to death” (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.12">Ex 21:12</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). A murderer who killed by using a weapon such as a stone, a piece of wood, or iron could be killed in revenge by a relative of the deceased. If the original death happened accidentally, the community would sometimes help to conceal the killer and encourage him to hide in a nearby city of refuge, where he would be safe as long as he remained within its gates. He had to stay in that sanctuary until the death of the high priest then in office, after which he was free to return to his own city (<a href="?bref=Num.35.10-28">Nm 35:10-28</a>). The sixth commandment enjoined, “You shall not kill” (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.13">Ex 20:13</a>). The Hebrew word referred specifically to murder, not to all forms of killing. Killing an enemy in battle and the execution of a murderer were considered necessary and were not prohibited. More than one witness was required for any conviction, particularly in a murder case (<a href="?bref=Num.35.30">Nm 35:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.17.6">Dt 17:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.19.15">19:15</a>).</p>
<p>In the Code of Hammurabi a man responsible for an accidental injury to another was required to pay for the services of the physician. If the victim died, a fine was payable according to the victim’s rank. In a sense the Hebrews went further by requiring payment for any loss of time suffered by the injured person (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.18-19">Ex 21:18-19</a>).</p>
<p>Kidnapping was punishable by death in the OT. Exodus states that “Kidnappers must be killed, whether they are caught in possession of their victims or have already sold them as slaves” (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.16">Ex 21:16</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Joseph’s being sold into slavery by his brothers illustrates this kind of kidnapping.</p>
<p class="h3">Laws concerning Property</p>
<p class="fl">The book of Exodus is quite specific about anyone responsible for damage to the property or crops of another. If a field caught fire and the fire spread, damaging crops in other fields, the person who started the fire, or perhaps the owner of the first field to catch fire, was responsible for the damage (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.6">Ex 22:6</a>). Hammurabi’s code cited a similar instance of a man who neglected to keep a dike in repair and was therefore responsible for flood damage to his neighbor’s crops.</p>
<p>Injuries to animals, especially oxen, or injuries to people or property caused by such animals formed an important area of Hebrew law. If an ox that had been previously good-tempered killed a man, the owner would be blameless, although the ox would be put to death—a severe financial penalty for the owner. If an ox with a history of goring killed a man because its owner failed to restrain it adequately, both ox and owner would be put to death. The owner’s life could be ransomed by payment of an agreed-upon sum. If the person an ox gored was a servant, the ox was stoned and the owner paid a fine (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.28-32">Ex 21:28-32</a>). The Code of Hammurabi also recommended no punishment for a first offense by an animal, but if the owner knew that the ox was dangerous and had taken no steps to prevent harm, a fine in silver was payable—a very large fine for an upper-class victim, slightly less if the victim was a slave. However bad the circumstances and however vicious the ox, the Code of Hammurabi stopped at a fine for the offense, never imposing a death penalty on either the animal or the owner.</p>
<p>Negligence causing injury to an animal was also punished in Hebrew law. If an ox or a donkey fell into a pit carelessly left uncovered, the owner of the animal was reimbursed for its loss (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.33-36">Ex 21:33-36</a>).</p>
<p>In ancient cultures women were generally considered chattel (personal property), much like animals or slaves. A daughter was considered to be her father’s property until her marriage, then the property of her husband. Therefore, any offense against a married woman was regarded as an offense against the property of the husband. According to the Code of Hammurabi, a child could be sold into slavery as a servant or bondsman, usually in payment of the father’s debt (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.21.2-7">Ex 21:2-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.5.5-8">Neh 5:5-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.50.1">Is 50:1</a>). Parental authority was so highly regarded in biblical law that a stubborn and rebellious son could be brought before the elders on the grounds of being disobedient and a glutton or a drunkard. He might then be convicted and stoned to death on the spot by the men of the city (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.18-21">Dt 21:18-21</a>). Even that, however, was a protection of the child’s rights; some Near Eastern legislation allowed a parent to order the death of his offspring without reference to the elders or to anyone else. With daughters in particular being held in such low esteem, it is perhaps remarkable that a daughter could inherit property if there were no sons (<a href="?bref=Num.27.8">Nm 27:8</a>).</p>
<p>Adultery, prohibited in the Decalogue, was another crime against a man’s property, specifically his wife. The book of Deuteronomy goes into considerable detail about cases of adultery—the punishment for both persons being death (<a href="?bref=Deut.22.22">Dt 22:22</a>). If a man seduced a young woman who was not betrothed, he was required to pay her father the bride price (50 silver shekels); he could not divorce her but had to keep her as his wife for the rest of his life (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.16">Ex 22:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.22.28-29">Dt 22:28-29</a>).</p>
<p>In a situation where a wife was accused of adultery but without evidence, a trial was conducted. The husband would bring his wife to a priest and present a small offering (a tenth of a measure of barley meal, with neither oil nor frankincense on it), indicating the low esteem in which he now held his wife. The woman then stood before the Lord holding an earthen jar of “holy water.” Dust from the floor of the tabernacle was mixed with the water, and the cereal offering was placed in her hands. Her hair was loosened by the priest to show not only her grief but also to give an impression of abandonment. She was then required to take an oath. After that, the priest pronounced a curse upon her to the effect that her womb would be fertilized easily, but that she would have many miscarriages. She had to give her consent to that pronouncement. The priest then wrote the curses in a book and symbolically washed them off into the “bitter water.” The woman was required to drink the water while the priest waved the cereal offering from her hands before the Lord and burned some of it on the altar. The priest told her that if she was guilty, the water would make her thigh rot and her abdomen swell. If that happened, she would become an outcast; but if she were proved innocent, she would be free. Whatever the result, no blame for false accusation fell upon the husband (<a href="?bref=Num.5.12-31">Nm 5:12-31</a>).</p>
<p>If a slave was struck by his master in such a manner as to cause instant death, the slave’s death had to be avenged. If the slave lingered, possibly for days, he did not need to be avenged, his loss being a sufficient punishment for the owner (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.20-21">Ex 21:20-21</a>). It is unlikely that the Hebrews had much experience with that law, which had no parallels in Hammurabi’s code. If an owner injured his slave by causing the loss of an eye or a tooth, Hebrew law required that the slave be set free (vv <a href="?bref=Exod.21.26-27">26-27</a>). The Code of Hammurabi gave an example of a man injuring another man’s slave; the owner had to be paid half the slave’s value.</p>
<p>Little emphasis was placed on burglary or larceny in the Hebrew law code. A burglar was presumed to be repentant and ready to make restitution. After return of the stolen property and payment of a small additional fine, a thief could again “approach the Lord” (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.2-7">Lv 6:2-7</a>). By contrast, the Code of Hammurabi prescribed the death penalty for burglary. In Hebrew law, theft of an animal required restitution to be made in the ratio of at least two to one; if a bull or a cow had been stolen or sold, the thief had to restore the property fivefold. The Code of Hammurabi contained a similar statute: “If a man steal ox or sheep, ass or pig, or goat—if it be from a god or a palace, he shall restore thirtyfold; if it be from a freeman, he shall render tenfold. If the thief have nothing wherewith to pay, he shall be put to death.” In Hebrew law goods stolen from a home were simply to be restored without additional penalty. If the thief no longer had the goods and was unable to pay the equivalent value, he might be sold into slavery until restitution was made (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.1-4">Ex 22:1-4</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">General Laws</p>
<p class="fl">The Hebrew code as contained in Exodus and Deuteronomy included many general prohibitions. Some concerned business dealings such as the removal of boundary markers (<a href="?bref=Deut.19.14">Dt 19:14</a>). The use of false weights and measures was condemned (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.35">Lv 19:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.25.15">Dt 25:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.11.1">Prv 11:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.23">20:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.11">Mi 6:11</a>). Bribery was strictly forbidden (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.8">Ex 23:8</a>), yet no punishment was specified for those who broke that law. In the Code of Hammurabi, if a judge changed his decision and was unable to give a satisfactory explanation, particularly if bribery was suspected, the judge had to pay 12 times the amount of the penalty and lost his seat on the bench. In the Hebrew code, perjury was also dealt with, although again no punishment was specified. The Code of Hammurabi stated that for perjury in cases where the punishment was death, persons giving false testimony were to be sentenced to death themselves (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.23.1">Ex 23:1</a>).</p>
<p>A number of Hebrew laws reflected concern for the poor. For example, poor people were not to be subjected to usury if they were in debt, or left cold at night if their coats were taken as a pledge. Widows, orphans, and strangers were also to be treated with mercy and understanding (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.21-27">Ex 22:21-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.23.9">23:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.23.19">Dt 23:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.17">24:17</a>).</p>
<p>Some Hebrew laws concerned family behavior, such as those previously mentioned who cursed or disobeyed their parents (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.17">Ex 21:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.20.9">Lv 20:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.27.16">Dt 27:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Pr.20.20">Prv 20:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.30.17">30:17</a>). Family responsibilities were strong; an entire family frequently suffered punishment for the crime of one of its individual members (<a href="?bref=Josh.7.20-26">Jos 7:20-26</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.29">2 Sm 3:29</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.21.1-9">21:1-9</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.5.27">2 Kgs 5:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.5.7">Lam 5:7</a>). Over a period of time, as individual responsibility came to be recognized, parents were no longer put to death for the crimes of their children, or vice versa (cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.31.29-30">Jer 31:29-30</a>).</p>
<p>Sorcery and witchcraft were forbidden. The book of Exodus stated explicitly, “A sorceress must not be allowed to live” (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.18">22:18</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Sexual perversions, such as intercourse with animals, were forbidden under penalty of death. Regulations prohibiting marriage with close relatives were given in detail (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.17-21">Lv 20:17-21</a>).</p>
<p>In Hebrew law no parallel existed for some interesting items in the Code of Hammurabi concerning surgery. That code mentioned veterinary surgery and even operations on the human eye. A Babylonian surgeon had to be wary, for “if a physician makes a deep incision upon a man with his bronze lancet and causes the man’s death or operates on the eye socket of a man with his bronze lancet and destroys the man’s eye, then they shall cut off his hand.” Surgery was virtually unknown among the ancient Israelites except for the ritual practice of circumcision.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Punishment">Punishment</p>
<p class="fl">Near Eastern punishments for murder and personal injury were retaliatory and often of the same nature as the offense. Other methods of punishment tended to vary with individual countries or traditions. Many kinds of punishment were inflicted on people defeated in both a full-scale war or a small insurrection.</p>
<p class="h3">Physical Punishment</p>
<p class="fl">Many forms of punishment stopped short of killing but could nevertheless be quite severe.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. In the OT beating with rods or switches was the traditional form of discipline for children, fools, and slaves (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.20">Ex 21:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.13.24">Prv 13:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.26.3">26:3</a>). Scourging (also called flogging) was more severe than beating. The whip employed could be made of several strips of leather fastened at one end or of two interwoven leather strips. A whip nicknamed “scorpion” (because of the barbs in its end) was one of the cruelest instruments of punishment mentioned in the OT (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.11,14">1 Kgs 12:11, 14</a>). The severity of punishment could be increased by inserting pieces of metal or bone into the leather.</p>
<p class="list-text">Before a scourging, the victim would be examined for physical fitness. If death resulted from the blows, no blame was attached to the person administering the punishment. The victim was stripped to the waist and tied to a pillar, his hands bound with leather thongs. The severity of a scourging depended on the crime, although the Mosaic law set an upper limit of 40 lashes (<a href="?bref=Deut.25.1-3">Dt 25:1-3</a>). To guard against a miscount, that number was later lowered by one (<a href="?bref=2Cor.11.24">2 Cor 11:24</a>). Lashes might be administered both on the chest and the back. Under some law codes, scourging could be used as a private punishment; in that case, if the victim died, another life was forfeit.</p>
<p class="list-text">In offenses against the law, synagogue authorities administered scourgings (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.17">Mt 10:17</a>). A husband might be scourged by the elders of the city for defamation of his wife’s character (<a href="?bref=Deut.22.18">Dt 22:18</a>). Scourging was also used as a means of interrogating a prisoner—hence, a Roman captain’s comment that the apostle Paul should be “examined by scourging” (<a href="?bref=Acts.22.24">Acts 22:24</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The Romans usually reserved scourging for non-Roman citizens, such as slaves or aliens, as well as for those condemned to death. Normally, criminals were scourged after they had been condemned to death; it is therefore unusual to find the scourging of Jesus taking place before his condemnation. Pilate may have hoped to soften the people’s hearts by Jesus’ suffering so that they would not demand the death penalty (<a href="?bref=Luke.23.16,22">Lk 23:16, 22</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.1">Jn 19:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Citizens of the Roman Empire could never be beaten or scourged before sentencing (<a href="?bref=Acts.22.25">Acts 22:25</a>). Hence, the magistrates were afraid when they heard that Paul, a Roman citizen, had been beaten under those circumstances (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.37-39">16:37-39</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. The gouging out of the eyes of prisoners and captives was a common practice in the Near East. The Philistines blinded Samson before imprisoning him (<a href="?bref=Judg.16.21">Jgs 16:21</a>). The Babylonians did the same to King Zedekiah in 587 <span class="era">BC</span> before taking him into captivity (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.7">2 Kgs 25:7</a>). The Ammonite king Nahash was prepared to accept peace overtures from the men of the city of Jabesh on condition that all their right eyes be gouged out. Nahash’s purpose was to disgrace them and prevent them from further active participation in warfare (<a href="?bref=1Sam.11.1-4">1 Sm 11:1-4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Several forms of mutilation served as punishments in the Near East. The Israelites considered their own bodies sacred and made in God’s image, but that did not prevent them from mutilating their enemies by cutting off their thumbs and large toes.</p>
<p class="list-text">The Code of Hammurabi and the Assyrian law code prescribed mutilation of the eye, nose, ear, breast, tongue, lip, hand, and finger as punishments for specific crimes. In Assyria, punishment was often inflicted by the victim of the crime under supervision of court officials. The Code of Hammurabi also contained safeguards so that criminals were not punished in excess of the law’s sentence.</p>
<p class="list">4. Stocks are mentioned as a form of punishment in the later OT period. The prophets Hanani (<a href="?bref=2Chr.16.10">2 Chr 16:10</a>) and Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.20.2-3">Jer 20:2-3</a>) suffered the indignity of being placed in stocks. Both ankles, and sometimes the wrists and head as well, were placed in holes in two large pieces of wood. In Roman times, stocks were converted to a form of torture, with a prisoner’s legs stretched to holes increasingly far apart. In the NT, Paul and Silas had their feet placed in stocks by a Philippian jailer (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.24">Acts 16:24</a>). The same Greek word, meaning “confinement,” can refer to fetters chaining a prisoner or to an iron collar like that worn by runaway Roman slaves.</p>
<p class="h3">Capital Punishment</p>
<p class="fl">Capital punishment was common in many Near Eastern countries. Several methods were used.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Those who offended a king were beheaded with a sword (<a href="?bref=2Sam.16.9">2 Sm 16:9</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.31-32">2 Kgs 6:31-32</a>), as were idolaters and murderers (according to the Mishnah, the Jewish commentary on the law). The sword was probably used for private executions as well. Inhabitants of entire cities were sometimes “put to the sword” for their denial of the faith (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.27">Ex 32:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.13.15">Dt 13:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Certain sexual offenses were punished with death by burning (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.14">Lv 20:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.21.9">21:9</a>). Tamar, Judah’s daughter-in-law, was accused of adultery and ordered to be burned to death outside the city (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.24">Gn 38:24</a>). The Lord instructed that anyone whose feet touched the holy ground of Mt Sinai was to be shot with arrows or stoned (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.13">Ex 19:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Hanging may have been a form of execution in biblical times. But many scholars think the word translated “hanging” or “hanging on a tree” actually meant impalement (<a href="?bref=Num.25.4">Nm 25:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.21.22-23">Dt 21:22-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.8.29">Jos 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.21.6,9">2 Sm 21:6, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.9.14">Est 9:14</a>). A spiked wooden stake was set in the ground and the victim’s body was forced onto the spike, the tip of which probably protruded from the chest or mouth. Commonly practiced by the Assyrians, that form of execution was reserved for those guilty of the worst crimes and for prisoners of war or deserters. The Persian king Darius is reputed to have impaled 3,000 men when his army entered Babylon. Impalement was the penalty Darius set for changing his edict concerning the rebuilding of the temple (<a href="?bref=Ezra.6.11-12">Ezr 6:11-12</a>). It is not certain whether Haman was hung or impaled (see <a href="?bref=Esth.7.9-10">Est 7:9-10</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> and mg notes).</p>
<p class="list-text">Usually “hanging” was a means of exhibiting a corpse as a warning to local inhabitants (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.19">Gn 40:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.8.29">Jos 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.10.26">10:26</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.4.12">2 Sm 4:12</a>). Corpses were exhibited for only one day and were buried before nightfall. The hanging corpse was considered a defilement of the land that God had given (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.22-23">Dt 21:22-23</a>). According to the Mishnah, the hands were tied together and the body hanged from the arm of a wooden gallows.</p>
<p class="list">4. Crucifixion was a punishment employed by the Syrian king Antiochus IV Epiphanes in 167–166 <span class="era">BC</span>; according to Josephus, a first-century <span class="era">AD</span> Jewish historian, Jews who refused to give up their traditional faith were so executed. During the Maccabean period (167–40 <span class="era">BC</span>), Alexander Janneus crucified 800 rebellious Pharisees in an attempt to reestablish his authority. Crucifixion was a widespread form of execution: it was used in most places in the Roman Empire, including India, North Africa, and Germany. Between 4 <span class="era">BC</span> and <span class="era">AD</span> 70, on some occasions the number of people crucified at one time reached into the thousands.</p>
<p class="list-text">Three types of crosses seem to have been used: a cross with the crossbar below the head of the upright bar (Latin cross); a T-shaped cross (St Anthony’s cross); and an X-shaped cross (St Andrew’s cross). Matthew records that an inscription, “This is Jesus, the King of the Jews,” was placed over Jesus’ head (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.37">Mt 27:37</a>). That indicates that for Jesus’ crucifixion a Latin cross was used, as artists have traditionally depicted it. In crucifixions the victim was most likely affixed to the cross while it was still lying flat on the ground. Then the cross was raised into position and dropped into a hole. The hands were either nailed or bound to the cross; it is uncertain whether the feet were nailed with one or two nails. The weight of the body was supported by a piece of wood at the feet and possibly by another that was like a spike between the legs.</p>
<p class="list">5. Stoning was the most common Hebrew death penalty. The first stones were thrown by the prosecution witnesses, who were then joined by spectators. Stoning was the punishment for certain religious offenses (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.16">Lv 24:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.15.32-36">Nm 15:32-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.13.1-10">Dt 13:1-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.17.2-5">17:2-5</a>), adultery (<a href="?bref=Deut.22.23-24">Dt 22:23-24</a>), child sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.2">Lv 20:2</a>), divination of spirits (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.27">Lv 20:27</a>), and rebellion (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.18-21">Dt 21:18-21</a>). Before his conversion, the apostle Paul witnessed and consented to the stoning of Stephen (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.58-59">Acts 7:58-59</a>). Paul himself later survived a stoning at Lystra (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.19">14:19</a>). In Roman times, a person would occasionally be stoned as he stood on a gallows.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Conclusion">Conclusion</p>
<p class="fl">Hebrew law was part of the Torah (“instruction”) given by God to make his covenant people holy. At that time the Israelites were a seminomadic band of former slaves. Although there are similarities with the Code of Hammurabi and other laws of settled Near Eastern cultures, there are also many differences. Hebrew law often had a broader view, even in its less sophisticated cultural setting, as though its purpose was more to teach godly behavior than to stabilize society. The simplicity and directness of the Ten Commandments, in particular, continue to influence jurisprudence, even in modern secular society.</p>
<p>The Bible’s primary message is God’s love for his covenant people, yet it never overlooks the harsh realities of life in a fallen world. Human beings sin and they commit crimes; they suffer estrangement from God because of their sin and are punished for their crimes. Christians are constantly reminded of the realism of God’s love by the cross as the symbol of Christian faith. They see the crucifixion of Jesus Christ as the fulfillment of OT prophecy that the Lord put our iniquity on him (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.5-6">Is 53:5-6</a>). The NT conviction is that Christ died for our sins in accordance with the Scriptures (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.3">1 Cor 15:3</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CivilLawandJustice_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Civil Law and Justice</a>; <a href="?item=CourtsandTrials_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Courts and Trials</a>; <a href="?item=HammurabiLawCodeof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hammurabi, Law Code of</a>; <a href="?item=LawBiblicalConceptof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Law, Biblical Concept of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>