<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Baptism">
  <title>Baptism</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BAPTISM</p>
<p class="fl">Term generally meaning “to dip” or “immerse,” but representing a group of words employed to signify a religious rite for ritual cleansing. In the NT it became the rite of initiation into the Christian community, and it was interpreted theologically as a dying and rising with Christ.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#TheBaptismofJohn">The Baptism of John</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheBaptismofJesus">The Baptism of Jesus</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#JesusResurrectionCommandtoBaptize">Jesus’ Resurrection Command to Baptize</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#BaptismintheEarlyChurch">Baptism in the Early Church</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheTheologyofBaptisminPaulsandPetersEpistles">The Theology of Baptism in Paul’s and Peter’s Epistles</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="TheBaptismofJohn">The Baptism of John</p>
<p class="fl">John preached a “baptism of repentance for the forgiveness of sins” (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.3">Lk 3:3</a>). The origins of his rite are difficult to trace. Some say his baptism resembled the one practiced at Qumran, while others suggest it resembled the one practiced by Jews when initiating proselytes to Judaism. The members of the Qumran community viewed themselves as the covenant community of the last days and so dwelt in the desert, living an ascetic life and immersing themselves daily in acts of ceremonial cleansing. At the same time they taught that internal repentance must accompany the external act (1 QS 2:3). Its sacramental nature is seen in the fact that only a full member of the community could practice it, and then only after two probationary years (1 QS 5:6). Converts from pagan religions were admitted to Judaism only after fulfilling certain obligations, which included the study of the Torah, circumcision, and a ritual bath to wash away the impurities of the Gentile background.</p>
<p>John’s baptism both parallels and differs with these forms of baptism. The origin of his baptism may be found in the prophetic acted-out parable, which not only symbolized God’s message but also intended to make it a reality. John’s practice had several theological ramifications: (1) It was intimately connected with radical repentance, not only of the Gentile but surprisingly (to his contemporaries) also of the Jew. (2) It was eschatological at the core, preparing for the Messiah, who would baptize with the Holy Spirit and with fire (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.11">Mt 3:11</a>), and therefore looked to the final separation between God’s people and the wicked at the eschaton (i.e., “the End,” cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.3.12">Mt 3:12</a>). (3) It symbolized moral purification and so prepared the people for the coming kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.2">Mt 3:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.7-14">Lk 3:7-14</a>). In spite of the obvious connection between John’s ceremony and the early church, we cannot posit absolute dependence. In fact, it disappeared from Jesus’ ministry. At first, Jesus allowed his disciples to continue the rite (<a href="?bref=John.3.22">Jn 3:22</a>), but later he seemingly discontinued the practice (<a href="?bref=John.4.1-3">Jn 4:1-3</a>), probably for the following reasons: (1) John’s message was functional, while Jesus’ was personal/ontological. (2) John’s was forward-looking, expecting the coming kingdom, while Jesus’ was backward-looking, celebrating that event. (3) John’s was an interim practice, while Jesus’ was sacramental. Jesus’ ministry fulfilled John’s, so he severed himself from the latter’s modus operandi.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheBaptismofJesus">The Baptism of Jesus</p>
<p class="fl">This event has its origin in a complex interplay of motives, both divine and human, within the messianic consciousness of Jesus (see <a href="?bref=Mark.1.9-11">Mk 1:9-11</a> and parallels). For John it was Jesus’ stamp of approval upon his message and ministry. Jesus was in continuity with John’s kingdom proclamation. For Jesus, it was also an anointing that signified the inauguration of his messianic ministry. As seen in God’s “heavenly voice” of <a href="?bref=Mark.1.11">Mark 1:11</a> and parallels, this has two aspects: (1) The voice alludes to <a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Psalm 2:7</a>, establishing Jesus’ unique sonship. (2) It alludes to <a href="?bref=Isa.42.1">Isaiah 42:1</a>, establishing him as the messianic “servant of Yahweh.” (This is discussed at greater length in the article below.)</p>
<p class="h2" id="JesusResurrectionCommandtoBaptize">Jesus’ Resurrection Command to Baptize</p>
<p class="fl">Here we find the true basis of the church’s practice (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.19">Mt 28:19</a>). As already stated, the disciples stopped employing it, so it is here that we see the institution reconstituted as an ordinance based on the death and resurrection of Christ. It was no longer a forward-looking phenomenon but had now become a realized activity centering on the gospel message, certified by the risen Christ who is exalted to universal lordship. It also is an essential aspect of the discipling activity, as seen in the use of the participle “baptizing” after the main verb “make disciples.” Finally we might note that the act signifies the entrance of the believer “into” union with (literally “into the name of”) the triune Godhead.</p>
<p class="h2" id="BaptismintheEarlyChurch">Baptism in the Early Church</p>
<p class="fl"><a href="?bref=Acts.2.38">Acts 2:38</a> shows that baptism was a sacral institution from the very beginning. This takes it back to the earliest days of the church. In the primitive church it was an important part of the salvation process (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.38">Acts 2:38</a>, “repent and be baptized”) and was accomplished via confession and prayer “in the name of Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.38">Acts 2:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.8.16">8:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.48">10:48</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.19.5">19:5</a>). Probably there was a question-and-answer period in which the believer confessed his faith and dedicated himself to Christ. The result was reception into and identification with the messianic community of the new covenant, signifying both forgiveness of sins (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.38">Acts 2:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.31">5:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.43">10:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.38">13:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.18">26:18</a>) and the reception of the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.16">Lk 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.38,41">Acts 2:38, 41</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.17">9:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.47-48">10:47-48</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.16-17">11:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.19.5-7">19:5-7</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=BaptismofFire_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Baptism of Fire</a>; <a href="?item=BaptismofJesus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Baptism of Jesus</a>; <a href="?item=BaptismoftheSpirit_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Baptism of the Spirit</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="JordanRiver"/>
<p class="h2" id="TheTheologyofBaptisminPaulsandPetersEpistles">The Theology of Baptism in Paul’s and Peter’s Epistles</p>
<p class="fl">Paul’s basic statement is found in <a href="?bref=Gal.3.27">Galatians 3:27</a>, “baptized into Christ.” The rite of baptism is christological at the heart, signifying union with Christ. This is clarified further by <a href="?bref=Rom.6.3-8">Romans 6:3-8</a>, which equates baptism with dying and rising (cf. <a href="?bref=Col.2.12-13">Col 2:12-13</a>). At the same time baptism is related to the Spirit; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.13">1 Corinthians 12:13</a> connects “baptism by the one Spirit” with being “given that same Spirit.” Many see baptism as the outward confirmation of the inward “seal” by the Spirit (<a href="?bref=2Cor.1.21-22">2 Cor 1:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.13">Eph 1:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.30">4:30</a>). This leads us to the eschatological dimension of baptism. In connection to the present work of Christ and the Spirit, it shows the outpouring of salvation in the age of fulfillment. It serves as the initial rite that marks a believer's entry into the blessings of the new age (<a href="?bref=Titus.3.5">Ti 3:5</a>).</p>
<p>There is also a definite link between baptism and the OT covenants. The major connection is with the Abrahamic, especially with the circumcision that characterized it. Paul in <a href="?bref=Col.2.11-12">Colossians 2:11-12</a> combines Jewish circumcision with Christian baptism as pictures of the redemptive work of Christ. The debate today centers on the degree of continuity between them—does baptism perform the same function in the New Covenant, i.e., forensic and imputative? Whatever the theological ramifications, Paul at least cannot be made to say this. Rather, he borrows here the Judeo-Christian imagery of the “circumcision of the heart” (<a href="?bref=Deut.10.16">Dt 10:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.30.6">30:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.4.4">Jer 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.2.28-29">Rom 2:28-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.3.3">Phil 3:3</a>). Christians experience the fulfillment of what circumcision simply symbolized, an effective spiritual reality.</p>
<p>Baptism is also related to the Noahic covenant in <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.19-21">1 Peter 3:19-21</a>. There Noah’s deliverance through the waters is considered a picture of the effects of baptism. Baptism is the seal of the salvation covenant, which itself has been accomplished beforehand by the act of Christ and the faith decision of the individual.</p>
  </body>
</item>