<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Blasphemy">
  <title>Blasphemy</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BLASPHEMY</p>
<p class="fl">Profane or contemptuous speech or writing about (or action toward) God. In a general sense, “blasphemy” can refer to any slander, including any word or action that insults or devalues another being. In Greek literature the term was used for insulting or deriding living or dead persons, but it was extended to cover the gods as well, including both doubting the power of and mocking the nature of a god.</p>
<p>In the OT, “blasphemy” always means to insult God, either by attacking him directly or mocking him indirectly. Either way the glory and honor of God are lessened, so blasphemy is the opposite of praise. An Israelite might directly insult the “Name” by cursing God (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.10-16">Lv 24:10-16</a>) or deliberately disobey God’s law (<a href="?bref=Num.15.30">Nm 15:30</a>). Either of those blasphemies was punishable by death, as was idolatry, the ultimate blasphemy (<a href="?bref=Isa.66.3">Is 66:3</a>). It was thought that Gentiles, who had never experienced the power and majesty of the Lord, were the most likely blasphemers. Thus the king of Assyria blasphemed in equating the Lord with the gods of the nations he had already conquered (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.4-6,22">2 Kgs 19:4-6, 22</a>). For his arrogance the king was doomed by the word of the prophet Isaiah. God was also mocked when Israel was exiled (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.5">Is 52:5</a>), when Edom derided the desolate “mountains of Israel” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.35.12">Ez 35:12</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>), and when the enemy scoffed that God had not protected Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Ps.74.18">Ps 74:18</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.2.6">1 Macc 2:6</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT, blasphemy takes on the wider Greek meaning, for it includes slandering a human being (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.19">Mt 15:19</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Rom.3.8">Rom 3:8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.30">1 Cor 10:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.31">Eph 4:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.2">Ti 3:2</a>), as well as God. It even includes mocking angelic or demonic powers, which is just as wrong as mocking any other being (<a href="?bref=2Pet.2.10-12">2 Pt 2:10-12</a>, <a href="?bref=Jude.1.8-10">Jude 1:8-10</a>). In other words, slander, derision, and mocking of any kind are totally condemned in the NT.</p>
<p>The most common form of blasphemy in the NT is blasphemy against God. One might insult God directly (<a href="?bref=Rev.13.6">Rv 13:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.16.9">16:9</a>), mock his word (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.5">Ti 2:5</a>), or reject his revelation and its bearer (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.11">Acts 6:11</a>). Jesus was accused of blasphemy when he claimed to have a prerogative belonging to God—the power to forgive sins (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.7">Mk 2:7</a>). <a href="?bref=John.10.33-36">John 10:33-36</a> reports an attempt to stone Jesus; his accusers said to him, “You, being a man, make yourself God” (v <a href="?bref=John.10.33">33</a>). Jesus was condemned by the highest Jewish court, the Sanhedrin, on the charge of blasphemy, because he claimed to be the Son of Man (the Messiah) but in their view had given no evidence that he was such an exalted personage, thus appearing to mock the Messiah and, by extension, to mock God himself (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.64">Mk 14:64</a>).</p>
<p>The Bible makes clear that blasphemy is forgivable (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.32">Mt 12:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.28-29">Mk 3:28-29</a>), but if a person will not repent, the only remedy is to turn him or her over to Satan to be taught the lesson (<a href="?bref=1Tim.1.20">1 Tm 1:20</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="BlasphemyAgainstTheHolySpirit"/>
  </body>
</item>