<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="New">
  <title>New</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NEW</p>
<p class="fl">That which has just been made or come into existence—often replacing that which already existed, thereby turning the old into new.</p>
<p>That the second part of the Bible is called the <span class="ital">New</span> Testament indicates how fundamental the idea of “new” is to biblical revelation. Many key theological expressions incorporate the idea: new creation (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.17">2 Cor 5:17</a>), new birth (<a href="?bref=John.3.3">Jn 3:3</a>), new man (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.15">Eph 2:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.10">Col 3:10</a>), new commandment (<a href="?bref=John.13.34">Jn 13:34</a>), new covenant (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.31">Jer 31:31</a>), new life (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.4">Rom 6:4</a>), and various others.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheExpectationoftheNew">The Expectation of the New</p>
<p class="fl">The totality of the expectation of the <span class="ital">new</span> is best expressed in Jeremiah and Ezekiel and in the reference in the Psalter to the “new song” to be given to the people to sing (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.33.3">Pss 33:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.40.3">40:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.149.1">149:1</a>; cf., also <a href="?bref=Isa.42.10">Is 42:10</a>). Jeremiah speaks of the day when God will make a new covenant with the house of Israel (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.31-34">Jer 31:31-34</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.25-31">Ez 34:25-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.26-28">37:26-28</a>). In contrast with the old, this new covenant will be written upon the heart—that is, it will be internalized. Similarly Ezekiel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.36.22-32">Ez 36:22-32</a>) tells of the day when God, as an expression of his own holiness, will cleanse his people and will give a heart of flesh in place of the heart of stone. This will initiate the age of the Spirit and will create a new existence, characterized by security and freedom, in which the laws of God are carried out. The supreme feature of this new time is the new spirit within them (<a href="?bref=Ezek.11.19">Ez 11:19</a>). Joel speaks also of that day when the Spirit of God will be poured out on all flesh (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.28">Jl 2:28</a>). <a href="?bref=Isa.65.17">Isaiah 65:17</a> states the promise of “new heavens and a new earth,” words that often reflect national circumstances and hopes (for example, after the exile). However, they came to take on new eschatological significance beyond the hope of the nation Israel.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheComingoftheNew">The Coming of the New</p>
<p class="fl">The central proclamation of the presence of the kingdom in the world through Jesus is a declaration that the promised new age has broken into time in powerful ways. Jesus’ ministry is one of fulfillment; what has been promised by prophets has begun to take place. John the Baptist had prepared the way for the one who would give the promised Spirit. Giving this Spirit means giving new life. Through faith in Christ, one is born anew (<a href="?bref=John.3.3-7">Jn 3:3-7</a>). But Jesus had to die in order for this new life to be given. At the Last Supper the cup of wine Jesus shared with his disciples symbolized the blood of the new covenant (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.24">Mk 14:24</a>).</p>
<p>The early church expressed this significance in different metaphors. This “newness of life” is expressed sacramentally through baptism (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.4">Rom 6:4</a>). The eucharistic cup is the new covenant through blood (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.25">1 Cor 11:25</a>). An extended discourse on the old and new covenants shows that by the shedding of his blood Christ has become mediator of a new covenant (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.15">Heb 9:15</a>); by his blood he has opened up a new and living way into the Holy Place (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.19-20">10:19-20</a>). Paul restates the promise of Ezekiel for a heart of flesh (<a href="?bref=2Cor.3.3">2 Cor 3:3</a>), after which he gives an account of the ministry of the new covenant in contrast to the old. The church represents the appearance of the new age within the old.</p>
<p>The one who comes to Christ by faith is declared a new person, a new creation, for whom the old has passed away (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.17">2 Cor 5:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.6.15">Gal 6:15</a>). Jewish-Gentile hostility disappears in the resulting “new humanity” (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.15">Eph 2:15</a>). All other social distinctions (such as male-female, slave-free) pass away in the new humanity created afresh in Christ Jesus (<a href="?bref=Col.3.10-11">Col 3:10-11</a>).</p>
<p>The newness of a person in Christ is the foundation for NT ethics (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.24">Eph 4:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.12">Col 3:12</a>). The new commandment (<a href="?bref=John.13.34">Jn 13:34</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.8">1 Jn 2:8</a>) is not really new (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.7">1 Jn 2:7</a>), but now has new possibility and dimension by virtue of the power and pattern of Jesus. Though this new life is a gift of God, the <span class="ital">process</span> of being made new continues. Transformation by the renewing of the mind (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.2">Rom 12:2</a>) brings realization of the will of God. Paul declares the inner man being renewed day by day (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.16">2 Cor 4:16</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheRealizationoftheNew">The Realization of the New</p>
<p class="fl">As real as the new life of the believer may be, Scripture recognizes a tension between the new age that has come in history but is not yet fully realized. There is a projection to that time when all things are made new (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.5">Rv 21:5</a>). With the end of the old, there is a new heaven and new earth. The new Jerusalem (v <a href="?bref=Rev.21.2">2</a>) “descends” as the dwelling place of God. The people of God receive a new name (<a href="?bref=Rev.3.12">3:12</a>) as the former things pass away. To the redeemed of the Lord, a new song is given, the song of the Lamb slain from the very foundation of creation: “Worthy is the Lamb who was slain, to receive power and wealth and wisdom and might and honor and glory and blessing!” The antiphonal song returns, “To him who sits upon the throne and to the Lamb be blessing and honor and glory and might for ever and ever!” (<a href="?bref=Rev.5.12-13">5:12-13</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CommandmenttheNew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Commandment, The New</a>; <a href="?item=CovenanttheNew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Covenant, The New</a>; <a href="?item=JerusalemNew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jerusalem, New</a>; <a href="?item=ManOldandNew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Man, Old and New</a>; <a href="?item=NewCreationNewCreature_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New Creation, New Creature</a>; <a href="?item=NewHeavensandNewEarth_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New Heavens and New Earth</a>; <a href="?item=Regeneration_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Regeneration</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>