<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="RedeemerRedemption">
  <title>Redeemer, Redemption</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">REDEEMER, REDEMPTION</p>
<p class="fl">English words derived from a Latin root meaning “to buy back,” thus meaning the liberation of any possession, object, or person, usually by payment of a ransom. In Greek the root word means “to loose” and so to free. The term is used of freeing from chains, slavery, or prison.</p>
<p class="h2" id="OldTestamentandNewTestamentWords">Old Testament and New Testament Words</p>
<p class="fl">For a full understanding of the concept of redemption, it is necessary to look at the OT. There are three different words used in Hebrew, depending on the particular situation, that convey the idea of redemption. The meaning of these redemptive terms rests on legal, social, and religious customs that are foreign to modern culture. An understanding of the culture is needed for an understanding of the terminology and its use.</p>
<p>The first term used for redemption has a legal context. The verb <span class="hebrew">padah</span> is used when an animal substitutes for (or redeems) a person or another animal. The noun derived from the root means the ransom or the the price paid. When a living being, person or animal, requires redemption, the substitution must be made, or price paid; otherwise, the creature involved is killed (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.13">Ex 13:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.20">34:20</a>). However, there is evidence that this rule was not always strictly followed (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.8">Ex 21:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.6.23">Jb 6:23</a>).</p>
<p>The concept of redemption had special significance for the firstborn. The firstborn male, both man and beast, belonged to God. In theory the firstborn was sacrificed to him. This was done in the case of many animals, but the human firstborn and some animals were redeemed (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.13">Ex 13:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.20">34:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.18.15-16">Nm 18:15-16</a>). In the redemption of the firstborn son, an animal was substituted, although later a sum of money was paid (<a href="?bref=Num.18.16">Nm 18:16</a>).</p>
<p>The second term involved is the Hebrew root <span class="hebrew">ga’al</span><span class="ital">,</span> which is used primarily in relation to family rules and obligations, the laws governing family property rights and duties. For example, should a piece of property be lost by a family member, the next of kin had both the right and the obligation to redeem this property. This right of redemption protected the family inheritance. The noun derived from this root is equivalent to the English root “redemption,” and the person who buys back the property is the <span class="hebrew">go’el</span> or redeemer.</p>
<p>An Israelite who was forced to sell himself into slavery to pay his debts could be redeemed by a near relative or even by himself (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.47-49">Lv 25:47-49</a>). Land might also be redeemed in the same fashion (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.25-28">25:25-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.32.6-9">Jer 32:6-9</a>).</p>
<p>The right of redemption extended also to persons in special circumstances. The obligation of a man to marry his brother’s widow is well known. In the book of Ruth, the right of redemption is extended to a distant relative. In this story, Boaz redeemed not only the property but Ruth as well, and she became his wife (<a href="?bref=Ruth.3.13">Ru 3:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.1-6">4:1-6</a>).</p>
<p>The third term used in Hebrew is the root verb <span class="hebrew">kaphar</span><span class="ital">,</span> which means “to cover.” From this root come the terms meaning to cover sin, atone, or expiate. The noun derived, <span class="hebrew">kopher</span><span class="ital">,</span> means the price paid to cover sin, when the term is used in the religious sense.</p>
<p>The term is used to mean the payment made for any life that should be forfeited. A good illustration is the price paid by the owner of an ox that had gored a person to death. Under the law, the owner’s life was forfeited, but he could redeem himself by paying the required ransom (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.28-32">Ex 21:28-32</a>).</p>
<p>All three terms are translated by the same Greek verb, <span class="greek">luo</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “to loose.” The noun <span class="greek">lutron</span> (ransom), is used for all three terms on occasion. This indicates that while the Hebrew used different words for different situations, the same essential meaning of redemption was involved in all situations. The concept of redeeming or freeing was of primary concern.</p>
<p class="h2" id="GodasRedeemer">God as Redeemer</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT the object of God’s redemption is generally the people as a whole, or the nation, rather than individuals. The beginning of this concept of national redemption is seen in God’s freeing the people from slavery in Egypt. Though they were in bondage, their God ransomed them (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.6">Ex 6:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.15.15">Dt 15:15</a>).</p>
<p>As indicated by the terms used for redeeming or ransoming, the payment of a set price or the substitution of another life was involved. When the redemptive concept is applied to God as the subject, he delivers—without the payment of a price—by his might or power: “I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and I will free you from your slavery in Egypt. I will redeem you with mighty power and great acts of judgment” (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.6">Ex 6:6</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.15.15">Dt 15:15</a>). The same thought is carried forward in other times of need and deliverance, such as the time of exile. God is the national deliverer (e.g., <a href="?bref=Isa.29.22">Is 29:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.35.10">35:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.43.1">43:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.44.22">44:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.31.11">Jer 31:11</a>).</p>
<p>Again there is no suggestion that God paid a price to free his people. God redeems by his own power. “For this is what the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> says: ‘When I sold you into exile, I received no payment. Now I can redeem you without paying for you’ ” (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.3">Is 52:3</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). When Cyrus let the people free, it was again without payment of a price (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.13">45:13</a>).</p>
<p>In the Christian community, especially in the early centuries of the church, there arose the idea that a ransom price was needed to pay for sins. In fact, it was often taught that the sinner was, in effect, held captive by Satan. Christ’s death was the ransom price paid by God to Satan to free sinful people. This teaching is not supported by Scripture. The death of Christ is an atonement or expiation made for sin, but this does not mean that his death was a price paid to Satan. God is not pictured anywhere in Scripture as getting into such a commercial transaction with Satan. The redeeming work of the cross must always lie within the realm of divine mystery.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TheRedSea"/>
<p class="h2" id="RedemptionandtheMessiah">Redemption and the Messiah</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT redemption is closely linked with the messianic hope. From the time of the exodus on, God is revealed as deliverer. The hope of redemption is very strong during the Captivity. The prophets constantly speak of God as redeemer or deliverer. This hope was to be fulfilled ultimately through God’s anointed one, or Messiah, who would be of the line of David (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.1-6">Is 9:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1-9">11:1-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.5-6">Jer 23:5-6</a>).</p>
<p>The messianic hope grew stronger during the periods of exile and persecution. In fact, during the long centuries of persecution, this hope of a messianic deliverer was stronger than ever. This period, generally called the intertestamental period, lasted about four centuries and extended from the last of the prophets until the time of John the Baptist and Jesus.</p>
<p>Christians believe that in Jesus the Christ (or Jesus the Messiah) we see the fulfillment of the OT redemptive concept. The redemptive image is very evident in the Gospels. John the Baptist depicted Jesus of Nazareth as the fulfillment of God’s redemptive kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.12">Mt 3:12</a>) and hence, the Messiah of Israel. Jesus, the Son of Man, came to give himself as a ransom for many (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.28">Mt 20:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.45">Mk 10:45</a>). The work of the Messiah was vicarious and substitutionary.</p>
<p>The same thought occurs especially in the writings of Paul. Christ is the sin offering to the Father (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">Rom 3:25</a>). Redemption is by the giving of his life (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.28">Acts 20:28</a>) for a purchased people (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Pt 2:9</a>; see also <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.22-24">1 Cor 7:22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.14-17">2 Cor 5:14-17</a>). These are all words or expressions used to present the central idea of redemption or atonement. Jesus Christ is the one who in himself fulfilled the redemption concept of Scripture and by his sacrifice provided for the redemption of sinners.</p>
<p>The concept of redemption has deep meaning for God’s people. In the OT it illustrates the truth that God is the Savior of his covenant people. Although Israel fell into sin by denying God’s law, God did not destroy them but restored them to favor upon repentance.</p>
<p>In the prophets, especially, God’s redemptive work was to be completed through the Messiah and his redemptive sacrifice. The followers of Jesus believed that he was the Messiah who would provide redemption for the whole world. Coupled with the idea of redemption is the motivating force of divine love as the basis for restoration (<a href="?bref=John.3.16">Jn 3:16</a>). The one who believes will be freed from the bondage of sin and find favor again with his redeeming God.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Atonement_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Atonement</a>; <a href="?item=Ransom_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ransom</a>; <a href="?item=Salvation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Salvation</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>