<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Remnant">
  <title>Remnant</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">REMNANT</p>
<p class="fl">Group of people who survive a catastrophe brought about by God, ordinarily in judgment for sin. This group becomes the nucleus for the continuation of mankind or the people of God; the future existence of the larger group depends on this purified, holy remnant that has undergone and survived the judgment of God. The remnant concept is found in all periods of redemptive history where catastrophe—be it natural disaster, disease, warfare, or other instruments—threatens the continuity of God’s purposes. From the Creation account to the end of the OT, the concept is progressively sharpened.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheProblem">The Problem</p>
<p class="fl">The theological problem that the remnant concept addresses is the tension between the grace and promises of God over against his holiness and just judgment of sin. This tension between God’s grace and his judgment presents a distinction between the true and false people of God and between the present and future people of God. The holy, pure, and true people of God will survive his judgment on sin as a faithful remnant and will become the nucleus of a renewed, chosen people. The purposes of God are not frustrated but are effected among that true and renewed people.</p>
<p>The concept is one that cuts in two directions. On the one hand, depending on the imminent expectation of the biblical author, it may emphasize judgment, that God is on the verge of destroying his people because of their sin; the remnant itself may even be threatened because the contemplated judgment is so severe. On the other hand, the fact that a remnant survives emphasizes both the grace of God (his favor shown to those he has kept safe) and the dawning of a new age and a new community, which inherits the promises of God as it springs from that remnant.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="h3">Prior to the Patriarchal Period</p>
<p class="fl">The first passage exhibiting the remnant concept is the account of the fall of man. Though there is no immediate loss of life or numerical reduction, the judgment of God threatens the continued existence of mankind (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.15-19">Gn 3:15-19</a>). Judgment is averted by God’s grace, and Adam and Eve become the nucleus of humanity; the hopes of the future are focused in their offspring (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.16,20">3:16, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.4.1">4:1</a>). God’s purposes for mankind will be realized through the seed of the woman.</p>
<p>The Flood narrative is more specific. Because of the wickedness of mankind, God determined to blot out all life. However, a righteous man who was blameless before God, together with his family, received God’s favor (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.8-9">Gn 6:8-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.7">Heb 11:7</a>). Only Noah and those with him in the ark survived the judgment of God (<a href="?bref=Gen.7.23">Gn 7:23</a>). The continued existence of mankind focuses in the fruitfulness and increase of his sons (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.1">9:1</a>), introducing a new age and a new covenant (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.9.8-17">8-17</a>). God’s purposes for mankind will be realized in the seed of Noah.</p>
<p class="h3">From the Patriarchal Period to the Monarchy</p>
<p class="fl">Not all passages contributing to the development of the remnant motif involve the threat of universal judgment. The sins of the twin cities of Sodom and Gomorrah were so grievous that God determined to destroy them. For the sake of his servant Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.16-19">Gn 18:16-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.19.29">19:29</a>) and because of Lot’s righteousness (<a href="?bref=2Pet.2.8">2 Pt 2:8</a>), God spared Lot and his two daughters. Abraham’s negotiations with God to spare the entire city if 50, and finally even 10, righteous persons could be found there (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.22-33">Gn 18:22-33</a>) emphasize again that the righteous escape judgment. God will not sweep away the righteous with the wicked; even when they hesitated, he was merciful and led them out of the city (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.16,29">19:16, 29</a>).</p>
<p>The story of Joseph is the literary bridge from the children of Jacob, a family in Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.26-27">Gn 46:26-27</a>), to the thousands of children of Israel at the time of the exodus. The dominant theological motif in the story is the preservation of the patriarch’s family in the face of mortal threat from famine. God sent Joseph into Egypt to save lives and to preserve for his family a remnant (<a href="?bref=Gen.45.6-7">45:6-7</a>). Joseph’s brothers intended harm, but God turned it to good—to the saving of many lives (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.19-20">50:19-20</a>). Once again the purposes of God are not thwarted but will be realized in these survivors from the threat of extinction.</p>
<p>Obedience to the commands of God and trust in his promises are at issue when the spies return from reconnoitering Canaan (<a href="?bref=Num.13.1-14.45">Nm 13–14</a>). Representatives from all the tribes had explored the land. In spite of their agreement about its excellence, all but two of the spies reported that the land could not be taken. Because of their grumbling, God announced his intention to destroy them all and to recreate a greater nation from his faithful servant Moses. After Moses interceded on behalf of the people, the Lord relented. Instead of destruction for all, only Joshua and Caleb would enter the promised inheritance because of their faithful report. The people would remain in the wilderness 40 years until all died except these two. The transgressors would die, but the faithful remnant would receive the promise.</p>
<p>The law, too, stipulates that faithfulness is required to retain possession of the land. Disobedience would bring disease, defeat in war, drought, crop failure, attack by wild animals, death by sword and famine, cannibalism, destruction of cities, and exile into enemy lands (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.1-39">Lv 26:1-39</a>). But for those who were left, those who confessed their sins and repented—the remnant—God would keep his covenant with them, restore them to their land, and realize his purpose through them.</p>
<p class="h3">From the Monarchy to the Exile</p>
<p class="fl">Even in the apostate northern kingdom the Lord kept his faithful remnant. At the end of a three-year drought in punishment for sins in the northern kingdom (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.17.1">1 Kgs 17:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.1">18:1</a>) and after the victory over the priests of Baal at Mt Carmel, Elijah went to Mt Sinai, fleeing for his life from Jezebel (ch <a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.1-21">19</a>). There he lamented that Israel had given itself totally to false worship and that he alone was left of the faithful. God replied by instructing him to anoint Jehu as king and Elisha as his prophetic successor. Jehu and Elisha would destroy the apostate, while God preserved for himself the 7,000 who had not bowed the knee to Baal. The faithful remnant would be spared destruction.</p>
<p>The preexilic prophets emphasized the smallness of the remnant that would survive the destruction under Assyria and Babylon. Amos warned of great judgment that would threaten even the remnant itself. God would destroy the sinful kingdom, though not totally. Isaiah, too, speaks of the smallness of the remnant. Israel is left like a shelter in a vineyard, a hut in a melon field only narrowly avoiding the fate of Sodom and Gomorrah (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.8-9">Is 1:8-9</a>). It is left like a pole on a hilltop (<a href="?bref=Isa.30.17">30:17</a>), like the stump of a felled tree (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.13">6:13</a>). When the reaper gathers his harvest, Israel is the gleanings that are left, the few olives that remain in the top of the tree (<a href="?bref=Isa.17.4-6">17:4-6</a>). But from the stump of that felled tree will spring new life (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.11-13">6:11-13</a>). Those who survive in Jerusalem will be holy, and the Lord will bring a new shoot from the stump of Jesse, a righteous servant (the Branch) who will bring the remnant of the people of God from many nations (<a href="?bref=Isa.4.2-3">4:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1-16">11:1-16</a>). After God has purged away the iniquity of the people, Jerusalem would be known as the city of righteousness (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.21-26">1:21-26</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">During the Exile</p>
<p class="fl">From his vantage point among the exiles by the Kebar River (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1">Ez 1:1</a>), Ezekiel was concerned about the future remnant and the promises of restoration. In a vision (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.9.1-11">9</a>), he saw a scribe pass through the city of Jerusalem placing a mark on the foreheads of all who grieved for the sins committed in the city. Behind the scribe came a group of warriors slaying all who did not have the mark on their foreheads. Fearing the destruction of all the people, Ezekiel called out, “O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, will you destroy the entire remnant of Israel?” Immediately thereafter, he saw the glory cloud—the visible presence of God in the midst of his people—rise and depart from the temple (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.1-22">10</a>). Ezekiel prophesied judgment on the leaders of Israel, and Pelatiah (whose name means “escape”) died, prompting Ezekiel to ask again, “O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, will you destroy the entire remnant of Israel?” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.11.13">11:13</a>). The Lord will gather his people and restore them to their land as a pure people free of idolatry. Though their sins were great, there would yet be mercy and restoration for a purified nation. The glory cloud that Ezekiel saw departing from the temple will return to a new temple (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.43.1-27">43</a>). The people will no longer stray from God (<a href="?bref=Ezek.14.11">14:11</a>) but will enjoy a new and everlasting covenant (<a href="?bref=Ezek.16.60-62">16:60-62</a>). Ezekiel recalled the remnant motif as it applied to the wilderness community after the exodus: many will leave the land of bondage, and the rebellious will die along the way, not entering Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.20.35-38">20:35-38</a>). God will gather his flock, and they will have “one shepherd, my servant David” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.34.20-24">34:20-24</a>). God will remove their hearts of stone, give them hearts of flesh, and put his Spirit in them (<a href="?bref=Ezek.36.24-27">36:24-27</a>). Though Israel appears dead and incapable of living again, yet God will speak to these dry bones and bring them to life (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.1-14">37:1-14</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>