<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Revelation">
  <title>Revelation</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">REVELATION</p>
<p class="fl">Term from the Latin <span class="ital">revelatio,</span> referring to either (1) the act of revealing for the purpose of making something known or (2) the thing that is revealed. In theology it designates God’s own self-disclosure or manifesting of himself, or things concerning himself and the world; it may also mean the word itself, oral or written, that conveys such revelation. The equivalent NT terms are <span class="greek">apokalupsis</span> (apocalypse), which means unveiling, uncovering, or making someone or something known. The Greek word <span class="greek">phanerosis</span> is virtually synonymous, though usually with the nuance of clear, readily discernible presentation.</p>
<p>Rationalistic philosophy (as promoted by René Descartes, Immanuel Kant, J. G. Fichte, F. W. J. von Schelling, G. W. F. Hegel) finds in human reason the sole source for whatever shape revelation takes or is, acknowledging only natural religion and denying the reality of all supernatural divine revelation. Rationalists may at times admit the possibility of supernatural religion, but they cannot conceive of divine intervention.</p>
<p>Christian theology, on the other hand, is committed to the idea that the principle of knowledge is the Word of God, specifically the Scripture, despite the severe critique of higher criticism against any claim that the Scripture affords a secure, reliable, and independent base for theological truth. Modern critical theology has declared its support for what it calls “scientific theology,” for the “sure” judgments of natural science and the supposed improbability of all supernatural happenings. This has forced the Scripture, as the inspired Word of God, out of its authoritative, normative position. What the Scripture contains is not the account of what actually happened, or what God actually said or did, but merely the early church’s confession of faith as to what first-century followers of Christ supposed or contrived to have happened. The Bible, therefore, is not unique in its divine origin; it is only the unique product of early religious searchings and strivings.</p>
<p>Christian theology, on the other hand, asserts (on the basis of the scriptural text and the confirming mighty acts of God) that divine revelation is the first, last, and only source for theology. People have knowledge of God because of God’s initiative and activity. God is always the initiator and author of revelation; people are the recipients. God discloses what otherwise would be unknown; he uncovers what otherwise would be hidden (<a href="?bref=Deut.29.29">Dt 29:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.12">Gal 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.3.3">Eph 3:3</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="GeneralRevelation">General Revelation</p>
<p class="fl">God draws back the veil in a twofold manner. There is first of all what has come to be called “general revelation.” God reveals himself in nature, in history, and in all people as made in his image. The association of God’s revelation with nature, by which people have an intuitive knowledge of God’s existence, is of long standing and is a truth supported throughout Scripture—both in the OT (<a href="?bref=Ps.10.11">Pss 10:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.14.1,19">14:1, 19:1</a>) and in the NT (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.17">Acts 14:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.22-29">17:22-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.19-21">Rom 1:19-21</a>). That there is a God, that God is the Creator with almighty power, that God deals justly as the supreme Judge, or rules as the “wholly other” over his creatures—these things are known and recognized by many people. Thus, the fact that God <span class="ital">is,</span> is undeniable. So, when people deny God’s existence, as do atheists, it is a forced effort against an inner conviction worked by nature itself. Paul could expect concurrence from the Athenians when he asserted that it is in God, the one and only true God, that all people live and move and have their being (<a href="?bref=Acts.17.28">Acts 17:28</a>). Knowing God through nature, however, is not the end of revelation. Full and complete revelation comes when people encounter the personhood of God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="SpecialRevelation">Special Revelation</p>
<p class="fl">To know God from his revelation in nature still leaves him and his gracious purposes completely unknown. The gracious, loving heart of God intends the salvation of all people. By special revelation God purposes to share this with mankind in various ways. Mankind would know nothing at all of God’s messianic purposes in Christ, if God had not revealed his heart and purposes throughout Scripture. By inner, immediate illumination of their hearts and minds by God, the prophets and apostles spoke his Word as he gave them utterance (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.4-19">Jer 1:4-19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.13">1 Cor 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.2.13">1 Thes 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.1.16-21">2 Pt 1:16-21</a>). The zenith of God’s revelation was the coming in flesh of his beloved Son, Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=John.1.14-18">Jn 1:14-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.4.4-5">Gal 4:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.1.1-2">Heb 1:1-2</a>). Jesus’ revelation of the Father and the Father’s gracious will toward all people was direct, accurate, and preeminent (<a href="?bref=John.14.1-31">Jn 14</a>).</p>
<p>God did not merely illuminate the hearts and minds of his prophets and apostles to speak his Word, but in specific instances also inspired them to record in writing the thoughts, words, and promises that he wanted revealed and retained for all time. The sacred collection of writings forms a remarkably harmonious and unified whole by which God reveals his thoughts and purposes toward humanity. For this writing, the prophets and apostles were prompted to recount not only certain historical events and happenings but also what God revealed for special communication. The ultimate purpose of Scripture is to reveal Christ. To him all Scripture gives witness (<a href="?bref=John.5.39">Jn 5:39</a>; <a href="?bref=John.10.35">10:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.43">Acts 10:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.28">18:28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.3">1 Cor 15:3</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BibleInspirationofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bible, Inspiration of the</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>