<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Riddle">
  <title>Riddle</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">RIDDLE</p>
<p class="fl">Word puzzle widely used and esteemed in the ancient world, both as an everyday amusement and as a test of wisdom at a more serious level. The point of a riddle was the discovery of a concealed meaning. Riddles, therefore, may be broadly distinguished from fables, which, like Jotham’s celebrated plant fable (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.7-15">Jgs 9:7-15</a>), contained an easily discerned significance. Obviously, there is an intermediate area where there is no sharp differentiation. For instance, Ezekiel’s riddle (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.1-24">Ez 17</a>) has sometimes been classified as a plant fable.</p>
<p>Samson’s riddle at his wedding feast is the best-known biblical riddle (<a href="?bref=Judg.14.1-20">Jgs 14</a>). Probably it was a form of diversion used on such occasions (vv <a href="?bref=Judg.14.12-13">12-13</a>). The riddle took the form of a couplet: “From the one who eats came something to eat; out of the strong came something sweet” (v <a href="?bref=Judg.14.14">14</a>). Samson’s 30 young men threatened his betrothed, who wheedled the secret from him: “What is sweeter than honey? What is stronger than a lion?” (v <a href="?bref=Judg.14.18">18</a>).</p>
<p>Solomon’s wisdom was demonstrated in his ability to answer the “hard questions” (lit., “riddles”) of the queen of Sheba (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.1-4">1 Kgs 10:1-4</a>). His reputation for this kind of wisdom is further demonstrated by Ben Sirach: “Your soul covered the earth, and you filled it with parables and riddles” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.47.15">Ecclus 47:15</a>).</p>
<p>Josephus notes a contest of wits between Solomon and Hiram, with riddles being exchanged. Solomon won the earlier exchanges, but Hiram finally outwitted him by enlisting outside help (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 8.5.5). Such wisdom to solve riddles was, understandably, claimed by Israel’s wise men (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.49.4">Ps 49:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.1.6">Prv 1:6</a>). In <a href="?bref=Dan.8.23-24">Daniel 8:23-24</a> there is the apocalyptic vision of “a master of intrigue [who] will rise to power” (lit. “one who understands riddles”). Daniel himself possessed the same ability to “interpret dreams, explain riddles, and solve difficult problems” (<a href="?bref=Dan.5.12">Dn 5:12</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT riddles figure infrequently. The various “hard sayings” of Jesus (e.g., <a href="?bref=John.6.60">Jn 6:60</a>) are difficult to accept and are equally as hard to understand. Possibly the only true riddle is the number of the beast, 666 (<a href="?bref=Rev.13.18">Rv 13:18</a>). Various attempts have been made to identify a person, after the pattern of numerical references in contemporary literature. Of these, the emperor Nero is the most plausible candidate.</p>
  </body>
</item>