<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="RomansLettertothe">
  <title>Romans, Letter to the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ROMANS, Letter to the</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Audience">Audience</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurposeandTheologicalTeaching">Purpose and Theological Teaching</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">Written in the first person (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.5,10">Rom 1:5, 10</a>, etc.), this epistle was authored by the apostle Paul. (The first words of the first verse are “Paul, a slave of Christ Jesus, called an apostle.”) The actual transcription of the letter, however, was done by Tertius (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.22">16:22</a>), who acted as Paul’s amanuensis (secretary). The letter’s authenticity has never been disputed by reputable scholarship, liberal or conservative, and Romans stands at the head of virtually every ancient list or collection of Pauline letters.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</p>
<p class="fl">The destination of the letter is stated to be Rome (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.7">1:7</a>). That Paul was in Corinth at the time of the writing seems clear from his reference to Erastus in <a href="?bref=Rom.16.23">16:23</a> as the treasurer of the city. An inscription in the stone pavement beside the large theater in Corinth states that it was laid by Erastus, the city treasurer, in appreciation for his election. This could hardly be coincidental. Erastus evidently remained in Corinth, because it is mentioned as his home (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.20">2 Tm 4:20</a>). Furthermore, Paul refers to Gaius as his host at the time he wrote Romans (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.23">Rom 16:23</a>), probably the same Gaius who lived in Corinth (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.14">1 Cor 1:14</a>). Finally, Phoebe, likely the carrier of this epistle, was a deaconess of the church at Cenchrea, the eastern port of Corinth (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.1">Rom 16:1</a>).</p>
<p>From the epistle itself we can determine when Paul wrote it. <a href="?bref=Rom.15.23-28">Romans 15:23-28</a> indicates that Paul was just about ready to make his visit to Jerusalem with a contribution for its Christian poor from the churches of Macedonia and Achaia, after which his purpose was to visit Rome on his way to Spain (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.23-28">15:23-28</a>). He carried this contribution with him from Corinth, at the close of his third visit to that city, which lasted three months (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.2,23">Acts 20:2, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.24.17">24:17</a>). On this occasion certain persons accompanied him from Corinth, whose names are given by the historian of Acts (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.4">20:4</a>), and four of these are expressly mentioned in this epistle as being with the apostle when he wrote it—Timothy, Sosipater, Gaius, and Erastus (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.21,23">Rom 16:21, 23</a>). Paul’s visit to Jerusalem is usually dated around <span class="era">AD</span> 57–58. As such, the Epistle to the Romans was written around the same time.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">In a previous visit to Corinth, during his second missionary journey, Paul established the church there and remained in the city for 18 months (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.1,11">Acts 18:1, 11</a>). His arrival coincided with the arrival of Priscilla and Aquila, who had recently come from Rome. At the end of his 18-month stay, Paul was brought before the newly appointed proconsul, Gallio (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.12">Acts 18:12</a>), whose arrival can be dated from the Gallio inscription found at Delphi to the spring of <span class="era">AD</span> 51. Thus, Paul arrived in Corinth in the winter of <span class="era">AD</span> 49.</p>
<p>Leaving the city, he returned to Antioch, gave a report on his work, and set out on his last journey to collect the contribution for Jerusalem from the Gentile churches (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.25-29">Rom 15:25-29</a>), for which he had previously prepared (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.1">1 Cor 16:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.9.5">2 Cor 9:5</a>). Continued problems in Corinth (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.11">1 Cor 1:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.1">7:1</a>) necessitated his return to the city (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.3">Acts 20:3</a>), at which time he wrote Romans. It is clear from the last two chapters of the letter that he planned to take the contribution to Jerusalem almost immediately and from there go on to Rome (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.23-24">Rom 15:23-24</a>). The occasion for the letter, therefore, is to alert the Romans to his coming so that they can assist him in his journey to Spain (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.24,28">15:24, 28</a>). Rome was the only church, other than Colosse, which Paul did not establish. His letter, consequently, does not reflect awareness of specific problems in the membership there.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Audience">Audience</p>
<p class="fl">The Roman church at this time was composed of both Jewish and Gentile believers. The church was probably started by Jewish believers who were at Jerusalem on the Day of Pentecost (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.10">Acts 2:10</a>) and were among the 3,000 converts. Evidently, some of these took the gospel back with them to Rome. Probably some of the believers addressed in the salutations of the epistle were Christians already of long standing, if not among the earliest converts to the Christian faith. Thus, it is not improbable that up to the time of the apostle’s arrival, the Christian community at Rome had been dependent upon its own members for the increase of its numbers, aided perhaps by occasional visits from preachers.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientGreekManuscriptOfRomans"/>
<p>Evidently, the gospel had gone out to Gentiles, because there were Gentiles in the church, as is evidenced by Paul’s remarks throughout the letter. In fact, it is clear that the apostle wrote to them expressly as to a Gentile church (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.13,15">Rom 1:13, 15</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.15-16">15:15-16</a>). Perhaps the major constituency of the Gentiles were “God-fearers” (see <a href="?bref=Acts.10.2">Acts 10:2</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeandTheologicalTeaching">Purpose and Theological Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">Of all the epistles of Paul, this is the most elaborate and, at the same time, the most glowing. It has just as much in common with a theological treatise as with a personal, heartfelt epistle. The major theme running throughout the book is that both Jew and Gentile have fallen short of God’s glory and stand in need of salvation (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.21-31">Rom 3:21-31</a>). God’s righteousness has not been revealed only to the Jew—because God is not God only to the Jews but to the Gentiles as well, since there is only one God (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.29">3:29</a>). He will justify the Jews on the basis of the saving work of Christ at Calvary, and the Gentiles on the basis of that same act of faithfulness to Abraham’s promise (v <a href="?bref=Rom.3.30">30</a>). Their common faith gives them access to this grace (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.2">5:2</a>). The gospel is thus to the Jew first and also to the Greek (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">1:16</a>).</p>
<p>Once a person believes, that person is justified before God (chs <a href="?bref=Rom.1.1-3.31">1–3</a>). This new relationship with God provides the believer with a new life in Christ and makes him or her a part of God’s people (chs <a href="?bref=Rom.4.1-8.39">4–8</a>). This is the deepest and most difficult part of the whole epistle; it carries us directly to the eternal springs of grace, sovereign love, and the inscrutable purposes of God. After this, we are told about the calling of the Gentiles, the preservation of a faithful Jewish remnant amidst the general unbelief and the fall of the nation, and the ultimate recovery of all Israel to constitute, with the Gentiles in the latter day, one universal church of God upon earth (chs <a href="?bref=Rom.9.1-11.36">9–11</a>). The remainder of the epistle is devoted to the practical application (in church life) of the truths previously revealed (chs <a href="?bref=Rom.12.1-15.33">12–15</a>). And then the epistle concludes with Paul’s heartfelt salutations to several different believers in Rome (ch <a href="?bref=Rom.16.1-27">16</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Overview</p>
<p class="fl">The thematic statement of the first eight chapters of the letter is set forth in <a href="?bref=Rom.1.17">1:17</a>: “It is through faith that a righteous person has life” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). This quotation from <a href="?bref=Hab.2.4">Habakkuk 2:4</a> sets Paul’s teaching on faith over against that of the OT on works. Thus, he affirms the fact that his teaching on faith is not new but is squarely rooted in the OT prophets. What was new was that the Gentiles would be fellow citizens with the Jews on the basis of faith in Christ (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.5-6">Eph 3:5-6</a>). They would not have to become proselytes to Judaism in order to be acceptable to God, as some Jewish Christians demanded (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.1">Acts 15:1</a>). This was the mystery of which Paul spoke in Ephesians (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.6">Eph 3:6</a>).</p>
<p>The first part of the epistle dwells on the theme that righteousness is attained by faith. The first three chapters demonstrate that Jew and Gentile are under sin and that the redemption of Christ is applicable to both (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.21-22">Rom 3:21-22</a>). The fourth chapter demonstrates that Abraham is the father of Gentiles as well as Jews, because he is the spiritual father of believing Israel just as he is of believing Gentiles. Then, in chapters <a href="?bref=Rom.5.1-8.39">5–8</a>, Paul deals with the latter part of the theme of how a justifed person <span class="ital">lives</span> by faith. Whether Jew or Gentile, the person who accepts the righteous acts of God on Calvary through Christ will live free from the wrath of God (ch <a href="?bref=Rom.5.1-21">5</a>), the power of sin (ch <a href="?bref=Rom.6.1-23">6</a>), the enslaving power of the law (ch <a href="?bref=Rom.7.1-25">7</a>), and the power of death (ch <a href="?bref=Rom.8.1-39">8</a>).</p>
<p>In chapters <a href="?bref=Rom.9.1-11.36">9–11</a>, Paul discusses the nation of Israel “according to the flesh” (physical Jews) in relation to the future purpose of God, concluding that God has not cast off his people who were Israelites descended from Abraham (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.1-2">11:1-2</a>). He can regraft them back into the tree from which they have been cut off, if they will accept Jesus as their Messiah (v <a href="?bref=Rom.11.23">23</a>).</p>
<p>Then in his closing section, he discusses the implications of the first 11 chapters for everyday Christian living (chs <a href="?bref=Rom.12.1-16.27">12–16</a>), closing the book with a reminder of the importance of the “offering of the Gentiles” through his own ministry (ch <a href="?bref=Rom.15.1-33">15</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">In Detail</p>
<p class="fl">In the first chapter Paul argues that the pagan Gentile world was in a state of rebellion against God, and the wrath of God had been revealed against their ungodliness (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.18">1:18</a>). Even though God had given sufficient revelation of his existence to them in the world of nature, they had nevertheless become polytheistic and idolatrous, with all the accompanying moral degradations (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.1.20-23">20-23</a>). Thus, three times Paul emphasizes that God gave them up to their lusts (v <a href="?bref=Rom.1.24">24</a>), to dishonorable passions (v <a href="?bref=Rom.1.26">26</a>), and to a base mind and improper conduct (v <a href="?bref=Rom.1.28">28</a>). The meaning is that he passed over their sins (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">3:25</a>), overlooked their spiritual ignorance of his true existence (<a href="?bref=Acts.17.30">Acts 17:30</a>), and did not put a stop to such idolatry (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.42">7:42</a>).</p>
<p>The Jews fared little better because, even though they had received the law of Moses containing a revelation of the will of God for their nation, they had not kept the law (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.17-29">2:17-29</a>). Even the Gentiles had those among them who did by nature the things contained in the law and were acceptable because their consciences were pure (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.2.14-15">14-15</a>). For a Jew, keeping the law was insufficient unless he did so as a spiritual conviction, not as a mere legal requirement (v <a href="?bref=Rom.2.29">29</a>). God-fearing Gentiles who kept the essence of the law were a model for condemning the Jews who did not (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.2.14,27">14, 27</a>). However, the faithlessness of the chosen nation did not nullify the faithfulness of God to the fulfillment of the promise to Abraham (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.3">3:3</a>). Although the Jew had every advantage over the Gentile, he was no better off because both had given themselves over to the power of sin (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.3.1, 9">1, 9</a>). The situation now was that “all have sinned [both Jew and Gentile] and fall short of the glory of God” (v <a href="?bref=Rom.3.23">23</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>God had therefore made Christ the Redeemer for the sins of the world (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.21-31">3:21-31</a>). The righteousness of God had been manifested apart from the law, through the “faith of Christ” (v <a href="?bref=Rom.3.22">22</a>; i.e., the faithfulness of Christ to the promise) and was available to the Gentile as well as Jew on the basis of personal faith. If this righteousness were available only through keeping the commandments of the law, as good and holy as it was (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.12">7:12</a>), then God was a God of Jews only and not of Gentiles, because the law was given to the Jews (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.29">3:29</a>). But God is also the God of the Gentiles and justifies the Jew on the basis of Christ’s faithfulness, and the Gentile on the basis of that same faithful act. Christ died for all who believe in him (v <a href="?bref=Rom.3.22">22</a>). Thus God’s righteousness was manifested through Christ’s faithfulness (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.3.3,22">3, 22</a>) and provides the basis of salvation for everyone who believes (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.9">5:9</a>).</p>
<p>Several times in the fourth chapter Paul insists that Abraham was the father of the Jews and of the Gentiles (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.4.11-12">11-12</a>, <a href="?bref=Rom.4.16-18">16-18</a>). Christ’s faithfulness to the promise to Abraham that all nations (Gentiles) would be blessed through his seed (the descendants of Isaac) enabled Abraham to become the father of all nations, that is, of all who believe (v <a href="?bref=Rom.4.11">11</a>).</p>
<p>Having laid this broad theological base, Paul then argues that the impact of this justification or righteousness is that all believers experience salvation from the wrath of God and thereby experience peace (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.1,9">5:1, 9</a>). Sin entered the world through the first transgression and passed to all people (v <a href="?bref=Rom.5.12">12</a>). Justification, however, was brought by the second Adam, Christ, who gives salvation to those who believe and receive the abundance of his grace (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.5.16-18">16-18</a>).</p>
<p>The function of the law was not to save the Jew. It was added because of transgressions (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.19">Gal 3:19</a>); it served to intensify the awareness of sin, present in all people, to the point of transgression of the law (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.20">Rom 5:20</a>). Sin used the law to deceive and destroy those who tried to keep it (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.11">7:11</a>). Paul had known what it was to covet before he knew the law, but when he became subject to the dictates and penalties of the law at age 12 or 13, the commandment against covetousness became even more demanding and destroyed him (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.11">7:11</a>). After the law was known, the penalty for its disobedience was fully applicable. Sin had been intensified because it became a transgression of the law. This very fact caused the need for greater grace, because where sin abounded, grace abounded all the more (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.20">5:20</a>). But it would be a gross perversion of what it means to live free from wrath, law, sin, and death to argue that one should therefore continue in sin that grace may abound (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.1">6:1</a>). Paul argues that those who have been justified and saved by Christ have died to the power of sin, which no longer has enslaving power (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.6.2,6">2, 6</a>). The key thought here is that sin (i.e., Satan—sin personified) cannot exercise dominion over the believer (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.6.9, 14">9, 14</a>); it cannot reign over him (v <a href="?bref=Rom.6.12">12</a>) and make him its slave (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.6.17, 20">17, 20</a>).</p>
<p>In addition to being liberated from God’s anger, the law, and sin, those who have been justified by faith have been freed from death, and God will give life to their mortal bodies through his Spirit (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.2,11">8:2, 11</a>). If they live according to the flesh, they will die; but if they live by the Spirit, they will enjoy a liberating life (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.8.6-13">6-13</a>). Not even death will be able to separate them from the love of Christ (v <a href="?bref=Rom.8.38">38</a>). The Spirit leads them and helps in their human infirmity, praying and interceding for them just as Christ does (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.8.14,26,34">14, 26, 34</a>).</p>
<p>Paul does not discuss the pragmatic application of these theological principles until chapter <a href="?bref=Rom.12.1-21">12</a>. In between, he deals with the issue of how and why the Jews could have rejected the Messiah. How is it that they, of all people on earth, with the history of God’s personal involvement with them, could have rejected the Promised One? Chapters <a href="?bref=Rom.9.1-11.36">9–11</a> focus on this important question.</p>
<p>Paul’s answer is fourfold. First, it was God’s purpose by election. He chose Israel, knowing what would happen in the future. These were physical Jews, Israelites, who enjoyed all the special relationships to God that an elect people could experience: sonship, glory, covenants, the law, worship, the promises, the patriarchs, and Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.1-5">9:1-5</a>). God had elected them just as he had chosen Jacob over Esau before either was born, just as he had hardened the heart of Pharaoh, just as the potter molds the clay into the vessel he desires (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.6-26">9:6-26</a>). It had nothing to do with their character or inherent worth; it was strictly a matter of God’s purpose for them. There is no injustice on God’s part in making this choice, because it was necessary in order for God to show his power through them so that his name might be proclaimed in all the earth. He had chosen Israel to serve his purposes just as he had chosen Pharaoh and Jacob and Moses; their salvation was a matter of faith (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.1-40">Heb 11</a>). After all, only a remnant of Israel ever really believed (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.27-29">Rom 9:27-29</a>).</p>
<p>Second, Paul argues that Israel, in rejecting the Messiah and his gospel, is following a precedent that appears repeatedly throughout history (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.30-10.21">9:30–10:21</a>). The Jews did not seek righteousness by faith, and thus never found it. They based their righteousness on the law and thus stumbled over their own Messiah (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.30-33">9:30-33</a>).</p>
<p>Third, he argues that since a “remnant” of Israel has already believed the gospel, it is a clear indication that Israel as a whole will yet do so (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.1-16,26">11:1-16, 26</a>). So, even though he says that God has rejected Israel, he argues that God has not rejected them finally and irrevocably. He has broken them off the cultivated branch of the Abrahamic promise, but he has not rejected his people. The elect (remnant) obtained what it sought, but the rest were hardened for a period of time until they could be provoked to jealousy by the Gentiles’ inclusion into the kingdom. So Israel’s alienation is not necessarily final.</p>
<p>Fourth, Paul argues that since Israel’s rejection has been such a blessing for the inclusion of the Gentiles, the scenario of their conversion in large numbers would be like a resurrection from the dead. This argument runs throughout the rest of the chapter (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.17-36">11:17-36</a>). The Gentiles should not be haughty, because Israel stumbled so as to make their inclusion possible (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.11.17-19">17-19</a>). Israel did not stumble just so they could fall (v <a href="?bref=Rom.11.11">11</a>); their fall was a blessing to Gentiles and was a part of the purpose of God. And God, who broke them off for their unbelief, will be able to regraft them back into the tree from which they were cut off, if they do not persist in their unbelief.</p>
<p>Chapters <a href="?bref=Rom.12.1-16.27">12–16</a> deal with the pragmatic implications of Paul’s impressive arguments. Thus the chapter begins with “I appeal to you therefore . . .” (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.1">12:1</a>). What follows is a lengthy list of Christian virtues and responsibilities. Paul frequently includes advice in his letters so as to assist the young converts in their transition from paganism into the Judeo-Christian ethical and moral value system. He often even modifies some behavior patterns among Jewish converts. Chapter <a href="?bref=Rom.13.1-14">13</a> discusses the important relationship that should exist between Christians in the capital city of the Roman Empire and their government officials. They should recognize that civil government is, as such, ordained by God and has a right to exist even if those who hold the offices are corrupt. They are God’s servants to execute judgment on the disobedient (<a href="?bref=Rom.13.4">13:4</a>). Chapter <a href="?bref=Rom.14.1-23">14</a> encourages Christians enjoying freedom in Christ to live without influencing others to violate their own consciences in various matters, such as eating meat. Nor should those with weaker consciences try to restrict others who have found this precious freedom. Mutual love and respect is the mark of a true disciple of Christ. Chapter <a href="?bref=Rom.15.1-33">15</a> contains Paul’s travel plans and his understanding of his role as a priestly minister to Gentiles, offering their conversion to God symbolically on the altar at Jerusalem in the form of a large collection of money taken up among the Gentile churches. Chapter <a href="?bref=Rom.16.1-27">16</a> closes typically with greetings and commendations from various individuals. Twenty-seven people are greeted by name.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PaultheApostle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paul, The Apostle</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>