<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="RuthBookof">
  <title>Ruth, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">RUTH, Book of</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#AuthorandDate">Author and Date</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Purpose">Purpose</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Message">Message</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="AuthorandDate">Author and Date</p>
<p class="fl">The author of the book is unknown. The question of authorship has particular connection with the date of writing, and a few clues provide at least an educated guess. The book must have been written sometime after the beginning of David’s reign. The information in <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.18-22">Ruth 4:18-22</a>, which pertains to the historical significance of Ruth as David’s great-grandmother, bears this out. Since foreign marriages were not approved in the book of Ruth, it scarcely could have been written during the period in which Solomon began his policy of foreign marriages. Also, David’s close friendship with Moab might have prompted someone in his kingdom to write the book, thus presenting objective rationale for David’s actions (see <a href="?bref=1Sam.22.3-5">1 Sm 22:3-5</a>). Consequently, the author may have been someone close to David, possibly Samuel, Nathan, or Abiathar.</p>
<p>The time of the narrative is indicated by the opening statement: “In the days when the judges ruled. . . .” The dates of the judges probably comprise a period of about 300 years, beginning with the judgeship of Othniel and concluding with that of Samson, though Samuel also served as a judge. If the genealogical information is complete in <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.18-22">Ruth 4:18-22</a>, the events took place during the life of David’s great-grandfather and mark the birth of his grandfather. Allowing a 35-year generation span, the events would have taken place somewhere about the turn of the 11th century <span class="era">BC</span>, or about 100 years before David’s birth.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Purpose">Purpose</p>
<p class="fl">The book’s purpose is closely related to its date of composition. Assuming an early date, that is, one close to David’s lifetime, its principal thrust must be the authentication of the Davidic line. The book may be considered as a justification for including the godly Moabitess in the nation of Israel.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Introduction (<a href="?bref=Ruth.1.1-5">1:1-5</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Driven by famine, Elimelech, with his wife, Naomi, and his two sons, Mahlon and Chilion, cross the Jordan to stay for a period of time in Moab, where there is sufficient provision. The two sons, after marrying Moabite women, die, and their father dies as well. Naomi is left a widow, with two foreign daughters-in-law.</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="TheStoryofRuth"/>
<p class="h3">Return to Bethlehem (<a href="?bref=Ruth.1.6-22">1:6-22</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Hearing reports from Bethlehem that the famine has ended, Naomi makes preparations to return. Both of her daughters-in-law, Orpah and Ruth, accompany her for at least a portion of the journey. Probably thinking of the problems they might encounter as foreigners in Judah, Naomi strongly urges the girls to stay in their own land. Both of the young widows refuse, but Naomi presents the facts. First, she is not pregnant, so the chance of a younger brother fulfilling the levirate responsibility is not imminent. Second, she has no prospects of remarriage and consequently no prospect of further children. Then she also notes that even if the first two conditions were met immediately, the possibility of their waiting was impossible. Orpah is persuaded and kisses her mother-in-law good-bye.</p>
<p>But Ruth “clung to her” (<a href="?bref=Ruth.1.18">1:18</a>). The verb, having the connotation of being glued to something, is the same verb used of marriage (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Gn 2:24</a>). Ruth demonstrated her serious intentions by making five commitments (<a href="?bref=Ruth.1.16-17">Ru 1:16-17</a>). In essence, Ruth renounced her former life in order to gain a life that she considered of greater value. She decided to follow the God of Israel and his laws. Ruth’s appeal to the God of Israel was more than equal to Naomi’s pleas, and the two of them returned together.</p>
<p>Their arrival in Bethlehem was traumatic for Naomi. Having left Bethlehem with a husband and two sons, she returned empty. She told her friends to call her “Mara” (bitter). But she had returned at a propitious time, the beginning of the harvest season.</p>
<p class="h3">Reaping in the Fields of Boaz (<a href="?bref=Ruth.2.1-23">2:1-23</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The first verse of the chapter provides the setting for the narrative that follows by introducing Boaz, a wealthy relative of Elimelech.</p>
<p>In the second verse, Ruth volunteered to glean the fields by following the reapers and picking up the small amounts left behind. Gleaners were also permitted to harvest the grain in the corners of the fields—a provision for the poor contained in the law (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.9-10">Lv 19:9-10</a>).</p>
<p>Ruth happened to come to the field of Boaz. When he visited this field, he noticed Ruth, inquired about her, and learned her identity. His overseer reported that she had industriously worked the fields from early morning until that time. Boaz, attracted to her because of her loyalty and concern for Naomi, graciously made additional provisions for her. She was given a favored position in reaping, directly behind the main body of reapers. Further, she was to receive water that had been drawn for her by the young men—an unorthodox arrangement.</p>
<p>Ruth, falling before Boaz in a gesture of great humility and respect, asked why she—as a foreigner—should receive such favor. Boaz gave two reasons: her kindness to her mother-in-law, and her spiritual insight, which led her to seek after Israel’s God, “under whose wings you have come to take refuge” (<a href="?bref=Ruth.2.12">Ru 2:12</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>She was also given a place at the reapers’ table and, upon Boaz’s orders, returned to the fields, this time to reap from the unharvested grain. At the end of the day she returned home to Naomi and told her of the day’s events. Naomi informed Ruth that Boaz had the right of redemption (see discussion below). Ruth returned to his fields until the end of the harvest season.</p>
<p class="h3">Relying upon the Kinsman (<a href="?bref=Ruth.3.1-18">3:1-18</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Naomi advised Ruth to approach Boaz as a <span class="hebrew">go’el</span><span class="ital">,</span> or kinsman-redeemer. The plan suggested by Naomi seems peculiar, yet some thoughts may give a certain coloring to it. (1) Naomi seems to have believed that Boaz was the nearest kinsman, being ignorant of the yet nearer one (<a href="?bref=Ruth.3.12">3:12</a>). Consequently, according to Israelite law (<a href="?bref=Deut.25.5-19">Dt 25:5ff</a>.), it would be the duty of Boaz to marry Ruth to produce offspring, since her husband died. (2) The general presentation of Naomi’s character in this book is that of a God-fearing woman. It is certain that, however curious in its external form, there can be nothing counseled here that is repugnant to God’s law or shocking to a virtuous man such as Boaz. Otherwise, Naomi would have been frustrating her own purpose.</p>
<p>Boaz’s response to Ruth’s actions demonstrated his gentlemanly concerns for her. He explained to her that he was not the nearest kinsman but promised that he would take care of the necessary procedures the next day. Protecting her reputation, Boaz sent her home before daylight. Naomi predicted that Boaz would settle the matter that very day.</p>
<p class="h3">Redeeming the Inheritance (<a href="?bref=Ruth.4.1-22">4:1-22</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Boaz went to the place of business, the city gate. The city gate area comprised the forum where the public affairs of the city were discussed. Boaz indicated that he wished to discuss a matter of business with the nearer kinsman. Ten of the city elders acted as witnesses. The first matter at hand was to deal with the issue of property. Boaz asked this nearer kinsman if he was willing to acquire property for Naomi. This is stated in the traditional stipulation: “Your purchase of the land from Naomi also requires that you marry Ruth, the Moabite widow” (<a href="?bref=Ruth.4.5">4:5</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The nearer kinsman was unwilling to marry Ruth because this would inevitably cost him some financial loss, since he would have to divide his own property with any son of his born to Ruth. Thus he relinquished his rights by the custom of taking off his shoe. (The shoe was symbolic of the land rights that belonged to the inheritance.) So Boaz took the part of being the kinsman-redeemer. The marriage of Boaz and Ruth produced a son who, under Israel’s laws, was reckoned as Naomi’s child and heir.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Message">Message</p>
<p class="fl">First, the book of Ruth traces the lineage of Ruth to David. The completion of that line is in <a href="?bref=Matt.1.1-25">Matthew 1</a> and finds its fulfillment in Jesus.</p>
<p>A second teaching is the beauty of God’s grace. A foreigner, even a Moabitess, can be linked with Israel’s blessing.</p>
<p>Theologically, the concept of kinsman-redeemer as a type of Messiah is clearly evident. He must be a blood relative, have the ability to purchase, be willing to buy the inheritance, and be willing to marry the widow of the deceased kinsman.</p>
<p>And finally, the love that Ruth showed to Naomi provides a pattern of devotion. The women of Bethlehem told Naomi, “Your daughter-in-law . . . loves you so much and [is] better to you than seven sons!” (<a href="?bref=Ruth.4.15">4:15</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
  </body>
</item>