<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TimothyPerson">
  <title>Timothy (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">TIMOTHY (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Paul’s convert and companion, whose name means “one who honors God.”</p>
<p>Timothy first appears in <a href="?bref=Acts.16.1-3">Acts 16:1-3</a> as Paul’s disciple whose mother “was a believer; but his father was a Greek” (v <a href="?bref=Acts.16.1">1</a>). He was a third-generation Christian after his mother, Eunice, and grandmother, Lois (<a href="?bref=2Tim.1.5">2 Tm 1:5</a>). The apostle Paul was undoubtedly Timothy’s spiritual father, and refers to him as “my true child in the faith” (<a href="?bref=1Tim.1.2">1 Tm 1:2</a>); he perhaps converted Timothy on his first or second missionary journey. Timothy was the son of a Greek (or Gentile) father, and wasn’t circumcised. However, when Paul decided to take Timothy with him on the second journey, he had him circumcised to avoid being hindered in their missionary endeavors among the Jews.</p>
<p>Timothy, who had a good reputation among the believers at Lystra and Iconium (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.2">Acts 16:2</a>), became Paul’s companion and assistant on his second missionary journey at Lystra. He traveled with Paul into Europe following the Macedonian vision. When Paul decided to go to Athens, he left Silas and Timothy at Berea to establish the church there (<a href="?bref=Acts.17.14">17:14</a>). Timothy and Silas eventually joined Paul in Corinth (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.5">18:5</a>). He then appears with Paul in Ephesus on his third journey (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.22">19:22</a>), from where Paul sends him into Macedonia ahead of himself. The last mention of Timothy in <a href="?bref=Acts.20.4">Acts 20:4</a>, includes him in the list of friendly ambassadors who were to accompany Paul to Jerusalem with the offering for the Christian Jews.</p>
<p>Timothy is often mentioned in the letters of Paul. His name is included in the greetings that introduce 2 Corinthians, Philippians, Colossians, 1 and 2 Thessalonians, and Philemon. He was in Corinth on the second journey when Paul wrote 1 and 2 Thessalonians, at Ephesus on the third journey when Paul wrote 2 Corinthians, and in Rome during Paul’s first Roman imprisonment, when he wrote Philippians, Colossians, and Philemon. He is the recipient of 1 and 2 Timothy.</p>
<p>In the greetings ending <a href="?bref=Rom.16.21">Romans 16:21</a>, Timothy is listed along with others who send their good wishes to the believers in Rome. In <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.17">1 Corinthians 4:17</a> and <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.10">16:10</a>, Paul speaks words of praise for Timothy as he sends him with a message to Corinth (see also <a href="?bref=Phil.2.19-23">Phil 2:19-23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.3.2-6">1 Thes 3:2-6</a>). In <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.19">2 Corinthians 1:19</a> Timothy is named, along with Paul and Silas, as men who were proclaiming the good news about Jesus Christ. Paul put Timothy in charge of the church at Ephesus and wrote him two pastoral letters to help him succeed in <?oxy_comment_start author="jeffreygonzales" timestamp="20230901T195445+0200" comment="the task"?>his responsibility<?oxy_comment_end?>.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Heb.13.23">Hebrews 13:23</a> the author (probably not Paul) tells his readers that Timothy had been released from prison, and that he hoped to come with Timothy to visit them. Therefore, we know that Timothy experienced imprisonment.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=TimothyFirstLetterto_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Timothy, First Letter to</a>; <a href="?item=TimothySecondLetterto_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Timothy, Second Letter to</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>