<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Queen">
  <title>Queen</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">QUEEN</p>
<p class="fl">Word used to describe a reigning monarch, a queen consort, or a queen mother. The queen of Sheba became the epitome of wealth at the time of her visit to the luxurious court of King Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.1">1 Kgs 10:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.12.42">Mt 12:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.31">Lk 11:31</a>), when she arrived with a large retinue and camels bearing gold, jewels, and spices. Candace, queen of Ethiopia, is mentioned when a eunuch, a senior minister in her court, is converted by Philip while on a visit to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.27">Acts 8:27</a>).</p>
<p>In Jewish history, Athaliah, thinking that she had murdered all rival claimants to the throne within the royal family, reigned for six years (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.3">2 Kgs 11:3</a>). Also, Salome Alexandra succeeded her husband, Alexander Janneus, as ruler from 76 to 67 <span class="era">BC</span>. A queen consort normally played a minor role, although Bathsheba (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.15-31">1 Kgs 1:15-31</a>), who was determined to ensure the succession of her son, and Jezebel (ch <a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.1-29">21</a>), who plotted the false accusation leading to the death of Naboth, are notable exceptions. The powerful role was that of queen mother. She not only ruled over the royal household but also was held in respect both by the court and by the monarch (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.20.12">Ex 20:12</a>). Her requests were unlikely to be denied (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.20">1 Kgs 2:20</a>). As the mother of the king, she was unique, whereas his wives might share their position with several others. Maacah, queen mother of Abijam, even retained her authority during much of her grandson’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.2,10,13">1 Kgs 15:2, 10, 13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.15.16">2 Chr 15:16</a>). The queen mother was crowned (<a href="?bref=Jer.13.18">Jer 13:18</a>), and Bathsheba, powerful enough as queen, was seated at the right hand of King Solomon when she became queen mother (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.19">1 Kgs 2:19</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>