<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Galilee">
  <title>Galilee</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GALILEE</p>
<p class="fl">Area in northern Palestine that, in Israel’s earlier history, had boundaries that were not clearly defined but that became more precisely defined in the period of Roman rule. The English name Galilee comes from two Hebrew words meaning “circuit” or “district.”</p>
<p class="h2" id="HistoricalBackground">Historical Background</p>
<p class="fl">In OT times Galilee was not significant in Israelite life, but in NT times it was a prominent Jewish population center. Galilee is first mentioned in the Bible as the location of Kedesh, a city of refuge in the hill country of Naphtali (<a href="?bref=Josh.20.7">Jos 20:7</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Josh.21.32">21:32</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.76">1 Chr 6:76</a>).</p>
<p>Galilee originally designated the area occupied by the tribes of Naphtali, Zebulun (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.1">Is 9:1</a>), and possibly Asher (if Cabul in <a href="?bref=Josh.19.27">Jos 19:27</a> is the same city as in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.11-13">1 Kgs 9:11-13</a>). None of those tribes was able to completely expel the original Canaanite inhabitants (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.30-33">Jgs 1:30-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.2.1-4">2:1-4</a>), and as a result, Galilee tended to be racially mixed. The cities that King Solomon gave to Hiram, gentile king of Tyre, were within Galilee (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.11">1 Kgs 9:11</a>), and the gentile intermixture in that area may have influenced Solomon’s choice of those cities for a gift. This racially mixed condition is also the probable basis for the designation in <a href="?bref=Isa.9.1">Isaiah 9:1</a>, “Galilee of the nations” (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.4.15">Mt 4:15</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.5.15">1 Macc 5:15</a>).</p>
<p>During the monarchy, Galilee was a buffer zone between Israel and Syria, and it bore the brunt of Syrian invasions against Israel. This fact is cited by the prophet Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.1">Is 9:1</a>), but he saw it as the prelude to a brighter day when the messianic king would reign. Galilee was conquered by Syrian King Ben-hadad (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.20">1 Kgs 15:20</a>) and was probably recovered by Israel’s King Ahab. Galilee was later subjugated by the Arameans under Hazael (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.32">2 Kgs 10:32</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.18">12:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.22">13:22</a>) and regained by Jeroboam II (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.23-25">2 Kgs 14:23-25</a>). As a result of Assyrian conquests in the area of Damascus and Galilee in 732 <span class="era">BC</span> by Tiglath-pileser III (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.29">2 Kgs 15:29</a>), more Gentiles were imported into the area while many of the Jewish inhabitants were deported. This naturally led to greater gentile influence and domination in Galilee. Under the successive influence of Babylonia, Persia, Greece, and Syria, Galilee was constantly experiencing infiltration and migration. From the time of the Assyrian conquest of Israel to about the end of the second century <span class="era">BC</span>, Galilee’s population was dominated by Gentiles, with only a few Jews.</p>
<p>The Jews remaining in Galilee were brought to Judea by Simon Maccabeus in 164 <span class="era">BC</span> (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.5.21-23">1 Macc 5:21-23</a>). Galilee was conquered by Aristobulus I (104–103 <span class="era">BC</span>), who forced the inhabitants to be circumcised and to submit to Jewish laws, a work that probably already had been initiated by John Hyrcanus (134–104 <span class="era">BC</span>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="SeaOfGalilee"/>
<p>Herod the Great (ruler under Rome, 37–4 <span class="era">BC</span>) affixed Galilee to his kingdom, and more Jews were attracted there. Josephus recorded that Galilee had 240 cities and villages and 100,000 men available to fight against the Romans. After the death of Herod the Great, Galilee was included in the tetrarchy of Herod Antipas (4 <span class="era">BC</span>–<span class="era">AD</span> 39). With the banishment of Herod Antipas in <span class="era">AD</span> 39, Galilee was added to the territory of Herod Agrippa I, who ruled it until he died in <span class="era">AD</span> 44. Rome directly administered Galilee until it was put under the rule of Herod Agrippa II. By siding with the Romans during the Jewish revolts, he was able to retain his position until <span class="era">AD</span> 100. In spite of the Galileans’ attempt to gain independence, the revolutionary faction was brought under subjection by Vespasian in <span class="era">AD</span> 67. After Herod Agrippa II’s death, Galilee became part of the Roman province of Syria.</p>
<p>Following the fall of Jerusalem in <span class="era">AD</span> 70, the Sanhedrin and many other Jews of southern Palestine flocked to Galilee. As a result, such cities as Tiberias and Sepphoris became Jewish, and the dispersed Jews came to think of Galilee as their center. Tiberias became a center for Jewish learning, and it was there that such major contributions as the Tiberian system of vowel pointing the Hebrew consonantal text were made, as well as the formulation of the Mishnah and the Palestinian Talmud.</p>
<p>From about <span class="era">AD</span> 451 until the Muslim rule over Galilee began in the seventh century, Galilee was governed by the Christian patriarchate of Jerusalem, set up by the Council of Chalcedon in <span class="era">AD</span> 451. Muslim rule from the seventh century on was continuous except for the intervals caused by the twelfth-century Crusades and World War I. All of Galilee has been included in the modern state of Israel since its establishment in 1948.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Boundaries">Boundaries</p>
<p class="fl">Galilee was bounded on the east by the upper Jordan River and the Sea of Galilee and on the south by the plain of Esdraelon, which served as a natural boundary between Galilee and Samaria. At times the plain was included in Galilee, as it was during the intertestamental period (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.10.30">1 Macc 10:30</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.12.47-49">12:47-49</a>). While the northern boundary was uncertain and variable during Galilee’s history, in NT times it reached to Lake Huleh. The western boundary followed the Mediterranean Sea to Mt Carmel.</p>
<p>From the time of the divided kingdom until the Assyrian conquest of Galilee (734 <span class="era">BC</span>), it was the northernmost part of the kingdom of Israel. The area was divided into upper Galilee and lower Galilee by the plain of Ramah, which ran between Capernaum and Ptolemais (cf. <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.1.8">Jdt 1:8</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.12.49">1 Macc 12:49</a>; Josephus’s <span class="ital">War</span> 3.3.1). In the Mishnah (compilation of early rabbinical interpretation of the Law), Galilee is divided into three parts corresponding to the natural divisions of plain, hill country, and mountain. Under Roman rule, Galilee was about 25 to 30 miles (40 to 50 kilometers) from east to west and about 35 to 40 miles (55 to 65 kilometers) from north to south.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Geography">Geography</p>
<p class="fl">The attractive Galilean landscape is made up of volcanic limestone hills and fertile alluvial plains. Its climate is cooler than that of any other part of Palestine, and its beauty and fertility contrast sharply with the barren, sun-baked hills of southern Palestine.</p>
<p>The physical features range from the high mountains in the north to the plain of Esdraelon in the south. Mt Tabor is prominent on the east, while Mt Carmel stands out on the west. Much of upper Galilee is 3,000 feet (914.4 meters) above sea level, and in NT times it was largely forested and less densely inhabited than lower Galilee. Lower Galilee starts at 1,500 to 2,000 feet (450 to 600 meters) above sea level and descends sharply to the Sea of Galilee, more than 600 feet (182.9 meters) below sea level.</p>
<p>Besides the average annual rainfall of 25 inches (63.5 centimeters), Galilee is watered by the streams that flow from springs in the hills and are the main sources of the beautiful Kishon River at Janin, and the headwaters of the Jordan River, the largest river in Palestine. The ground is also moistened by heavy dews resulting from climatic conditions created by the Lebanon mountain range to the north.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Cities">Cities</p>
<p class="fl">Among the more notable cities in Galilee’s early history were Kedesh in Naphtali, a city of refuge (<a href="?bref=Josh.20.7">Jos 20:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.32">21:32</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.76">1 Chr 6:76</a>), and Hazor, about 10 miles (16.1 kilometers) north of the Sea of Galilee (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.10">Jos 11:10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.15">1 Kgs 9:15</a>). During the time of Christ, Chorazin (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.21">Mt 11:21</a>) and Capernaum (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.13">4:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.11.23">11:23</a>) were prominent cities located in the northeast near the Sea of Galilee. Capernaum seems to have been a center for Jesus’ ministry in the area (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.13">Mt 4:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.2.1">Mk 2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.33">9:33</a>; etc.). Nazareth is especially significant as the city of Christ’s childhood (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.22-23">Mt 2:22-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.39">Lk 2:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.16">4:16</a>; etc.). Nain (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.11-17">Lk 7:11-17</a>), located on the northern edge of the mountain now called Little Hermon, and Cana of Galilee (<a href="?bref=John.2.1-11">Jn 2:1-11</a>) also figured prominently in Christ’s ministry. Sepphoris and Tiberias were important cities during Roman administration.</p>
<p class="h2" id="RoadsandTravel">Roads and Travel</p>
<p class="fl">Many roads traversed Galilee, and those in NT times were superior due to Roman construction and maintenance.</p>
<p>Among the best-known trade routes was the Via Maris (the Way of the Sea), which ran through Galilee on its way from Damascus to Egypt. Another main road ran from Tiberias, near the Sea of Galilee, to Acco (Ptolemais), a port on the Phoenician coast. Major caravan routes also connected Galilee with the markets of the East. The area was tied together by a network of spurs and connecting roads that branched from the main highways.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Inhabitants">Inhabitants</p>
<p class="fl">The occupants of Galilee (Galileans) were basically Jewish in religious and patriotic orientation, but they were composed of various ethnic elements. The influence of this mixture was sufficient to cause recognizable differences in speech from that of southern Palestine (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.26.69,73">Mt 26:69, 73</a>). The Galileans absorbed more Greek and Roman influences than did the Judean Jews. The racial mixture, differences in speech, and location caused Judean Jews to view Galilee and its inhabitants with contempt (<a href="?bref=John.1.46">Jn 1:46</a>; <a href="?bref=John.7.41,52">7:41, 52</a>).</p>
<p>Lower Galilee was densely settled with villages, and in NT times the population was probably about three million. The fertility of the soil and resultant fruitfulness of the country produced a prosperous Jewish populace, particularly in the centuries immediately after the time of Christ.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Government">Government</p>
<p class="fl">Galilee was under the Roman rule of emperors Augustus and Tiberius during the time of Christ. Roman fortifications throughout Galilee were a constant reminder of the presence and influence of the Roman Empire. During Christ’s ministry, Rome installed the tetrarch Herod Antipas (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.1">Mt 14:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.23.5-7">Lk 23:5-7</a>) to rule the territory. He was appointed to office when 17 years old. Sepphoris was his first capital; in about <span class="era">AD</span> 22 he built Tiberias on the shore of the Sea of Galilee as his new capital, in honor of the emperor.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Products">Products</p>
<p class="fl">Abundant crops enabled Galilee to provide produce for the neighboring Phoenician cities of Tyre and Sidon around the middle of the first century <span class="era">AD</span>. Main crops included grapes, pomegranates, olives, and grains. Fishing in the Sea of Galilee was a prominent business in NT times (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.14-20">Mk 1:14-20</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="JesusandGalilee">Jesus and Galilee</p>
<p class="fl">Jesus was raised in Galilee (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.16">Lk 4:16</a>), and 11 of his 12 disciples were from there (Judas Iscariot was the only Judean).</p>
<p>The culture, commerce, farming, and fishing business of the area formed the background for much of Jesus’ ministry, as his parables show (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.1-8">Mt 20:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.21.33">21:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.3">Mk 4:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.6-9">Lk 13:6-9</a>). The first three Gospels are largely occupied with Christ’s ministry in Galilee, with much of it being spent around the Sea of Galilee. Most of his parables (19 of 32) were spoken here, and the vast majority of his miracles (25 of 33) were performed in Galilee. Jesus received his greatest response in this region. The Sermon on the Mount was spoken in Galilee, and one of its mountains was the scene of the Lord’s transfiguration. Many of the women who followed Christ and ministered to him also came from there (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.55">Mt 27:55</a>). Two of Christ’s most significant postresurrection appearances took place in Galilee (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.16-20">Mt 28:16-20</a>; <a href="?bref=John.21.1-23">Jn 21:1-23</a>), and one of Christ’s own titles, Jesus of Nazareth (<a href="?bref=John.1.45">Jn 1:45</a>), identified him as a Galilean.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Galileans">Galileans</p>
<p class="fl">Since Jesus and most of the 12 disciples were from Galilee, it was natural for the term to be applied to all of his followers, especially since it implied that the movement was not as pure as Judean Judaism. Some interpreters believe that <a href="?bref=Luke.22.59">Luke 22:59</a> is an example of the use of “Galilean” as a title; in <a href="?bref=Acts.1.11">Acts 1:11</a> and <a href="?bref=Acts.2.7">2:7</a> it is merely a geographical reference. One sure reference to Christians by that title appears in the work of the pagan philosopher Epictetus (<span class="era">AD</span> 50?–135?), who was impressed with how Christians died for their faith. It is not clear how common the title of Galilean was, but it had obviously spread from Judea to Rome, where Epictetus lived.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Palestine_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Palestine</a>; <a href="?item=SeaofGalilee_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sea of Galilee</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>