<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gaulanitis">
  <title>Gaulanitis*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GAULANITIS*</p>
<p class="fl">Small province east of the Sea of Galilee, situated between Mt Hermon and the Yarmuk River and extending perhaps to the Jordan River. It took its name from the ancient town of Golan. Archaeologists have discovered extensive ruins 17 miles (27 kilometers) east of the Sea of Galilee, which they consider to be the remains of Golan. Moses named Golan as a city of refuge for Manasseh’s half-tribe east of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.41,43">Dt 4:41, 43</a>), and Joshua assigned it to the Gershonite Levites (<a href="?bref=Josh.20.8">Jos 20:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.27">21:27</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.71">1 Chr 6:71</a>). According to Josephus, Alexander Janneus suffered a heavy defeat in this place and later destroyed the town (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 8.2.3). Josephus also identified a Judas who led a tax revolt as being from Gaulanitis (18.1.1), whereas Luke called him a Galilean (<a href="?bref=Acts.5.37">Acts 5:37</a>). Later, Josephus called him a Galilean as well (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 20.5.2; <span class="ital">War</span> 2.8.1). It is quite possible that this Judas lived in these places at different times.</p>
<p>After Herod’s death in 4 <span class="era">BC</span>, Philip inherited Gaulanitis, making his capital Bethsaida Julias, which he had rebuilt and named after Augustus Caesar’s daughter. Jesus traveled in this area (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.45">Mk 6:45</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.22">8:22</a>), and it remained under firm Roman control until <span class="era">AD</span> 66, when the Jewish war broke out. Jewish revolutionaries subsequently hid in its heights and the Romans fought several campaigns here.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Golan_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Golan</a>; <a href="?item=HerodHerodianFamily_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Herod, Herodian Family</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>