<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gaza">
  <title>Gaza</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GAZA</p>
<p class="fl">City near the Palestinian coast, about 50 miles (80.5 kilometers) west-southwest of Jerusalem. It has been occupied almost continuously since ancient times; modern Gaza has played an important part in the conflict between Arabs and Israelis. Gazite and Gazathite are biblical names for the residents of the town.</p>
<p>Set about midpoint of the length of the plain of Philistia, Gaza was a rich agricultural area where wheat and similar grains flourished. Situated some three miles (4.8 kilometers) from the Mediterranean, Gaza’s position as the greatest trading center of ancient Palestine did not come from the sea but from the highways, which brought caravans from all parts of the Fertile Crescent. This accessibility was also a handicap, for the roadways along the coast were the easiest route for the armies of Egypt, Assyria, Babylonia, Persia, Greece, and Rome. Often Gaza was the victim of their passage.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfGaza"/>
<p>In the records of secular history, Gaza first shows up in the annals of Thutmose III in the temple of Karnak. Thutmose wisely scheduled his Asiatic campaigns just after the Egyptian harvest and in time to seize the harvest of Palestine.</p>
<p>In Amarna Letter 289, Abdu-Heba of Jerusalem acknowledged that Gaza was loyal to the king of Egypt but complained that Addaya, the Egyptian ruler of Palestine whose residence was at Gaza, had taken the garrison the pharaoh had sent for Jerusalem. From the late 13th century <span class="era">BC</span>, there is a satirical letter that was composed as an exercise for training scribes. In this letter, written from one scribe to belittle another, various itineraries are traced, including one from the frontier of Egypt to Gaza.</p>
<p>Pharaoh Neco (610–595 <span class="era">BC</span>) captured and chastised Gaza and Ashkelon in the reign of Josiah and Judah (cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.47.1,5">Jer 47:1, 5</a>).</p>
<p>Tiglath-pileser III (745–727 <span class="era">BC</span>) refers to Hanno of Gaza, who fled to Egypt just prior to the capture of Gaza by the Assyrians. On the Oriental Institute Prism and the Taylor Prism, Sennacherib (705–681 <span class="era">BC</span>) tells of his invasion of Palestine and of how he shut up Hezekiah “like a bird in a cage.” He captured 46 of Hezekiah’s fortified cities and gave them to three minor kings, including Sillibel of Gaza, who is also mentioned by Esarhaddon (681–669 <span class="era">BC</span>) and Ashurbanipal (669–633 <span class="era">BC</span>). Reference to “the king of Gaza” also appears in the records of Nebuchadnezzar II of Babylon (604–562 <span class="era">BC</span>).</p>
<p>In 332 <span class="era">BC</span> Gaza was captured and punished by Alexander the Great. He was angered because it had held out against him for two months, so he killed all of the men and sold the women and children into slavery. During the Maccabean period, it was taken by Alexander Janneus, who slaughtered its inhabitants.</p>
<p>In the Bible, Gaza is first mentioned in <a href="?bref=Gen.10.19">Genesis 10:19</a>, where it is said that the territory of the Canaanites extended from Sidon to Gaza. In a summary of the conquests of Joshua, one of the dimensions of the conquered area is “from Kadesh-barnea to Gaza” (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.41">Jos 10:41</a>). Joshua destroyed all the Anakim in the land, but some remained in Gaza and other Philistine cities (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.22">11:22</a>). Another ancient people, the Avvim, “who lived in villages as far as Gaza,” were annihilated and replaced by the Caphtorim from Caphtor, or Crete (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.23">Dt 2:23</a>). Gaza, along with its towns and villages, was listed among the tribal inheritance of Judah (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.47">Jos 15:47</a>). At the time of Joshua’s advanced age, Gaza and the other four cities of the Philistine Pentapolis are said to be among the territories not yet taken (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.3">13:3</a>); in <a href="?bref=Judg.1.18-19">Judges 1:18-19</a>, however, it is reported that Judah took it.</p>
<p>During the time of the judges, Midianite raiders swept through Israel, looting and destroying, even as far as Gaza (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.4">Jgs 6:4</a>). In this period the main biblical interest in Gaza centers in the life and exploits of Samson. Philistine women were Samson’s weakness. He went to Gaza and found a prostitute with whom he had relations (<a href="?bref=Judg.16.1">16:1</a>). The people of Gaza learned that he was there and determined to kill him in the morning, but Samson arose at midnight and went to the gate of the city, took the doors, posts, and the bar of the gate and carried them to the top of a hill facing Hebron.</p>
<p>His involvement with another Philistine woman, Delilah, resulted in his capture by the Philistines, who gouged out his eyes and took him to Gaza (<a href="?bref=Judg.16.21">Jgs 16:21</a>), where he was bound and forced to grind at a mill in the prison. On a festival day in the temple of Dagon, the reveling worshipers called for Samson to be brought so they could make sport of him. His strength was returning, and God answered his prayer for vengeance. Samson dislodged the two pillars that were the support of the stone slab roof of the pagan temple, so Samson died, along with a great number of Gazites.</p>
<p>Gaza is named as the southern boundary of Israel during the time of Solomon, who ruled over “all the region west of the Euphrates from Tiphsah to Gaza” (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.24">1 Kgs 4:24</a>). Hezekiah defeated the Philistines as far as Gaza (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.8">2 Kgs 18:8</a>). When he rebelled against Assyria, Sennacherib came and took 46 of Hezekiah’s cities and gave them to the king of Gaza and two other kings.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Jer.47.1-7">Jeremiah 47</a> records a prophecy against the Philistines, which the Lord gave to the prophet before Pharaoh attacked Gaza (v <a href="?bref=Jer.47.1">1</a>; cf. v <a href="?bref=Jer.47.5">5</a>; see Neco above). Amos gives specific prophecies of judgment against Gaza (<a href="?bref=Amos.1.6-7">Am 1:6-7</a>). Zephaniah also states that Gaza would be deserted (<a href="?bref=Zeph.2.4">Zep 2:4</a>). <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-17">Zechariah 9</a> gives an oracle of judgment in which it is said that Gaza will suffer and that its king shall perish.</p>
<p>In the NT there is only one reference to Gaza (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.26">Acts 8:26</a>). Philip, who was preaching in Samaria, was told by an angel to go south to “the road that goes from Jerusalem to Gaza.” Here he met the treasurer of Cush, who was reading <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">Isaiah 53</a> as he rode in his chariot. Philip preached the gospel to this man and baptized him.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PhilistiaPhilistines_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Philistia, Philistines</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>