<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Geba">
  <title>Geba</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GEBA</p>
<p class="fl">Levitical city in the territory of Benjamin (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.24">Jos 18:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.17">21:17</a>), about seven miles (11.3 kilometers) northeast of Jerusalem and south of Michmash (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.5">1 Sm 14:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.10.29">Is 10:29</a>). It is easily confused with Gibeah, the hometown of Saul, which is also in Benjamin, to the southwest of Geba. Both names mean “hill.” The phrase “from Geba to Beersheba” indicated the northern and southern extremities of Judah’s tribe (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.8">2 Kgs 23:8</a>).</p>
<p>In the time of Saul the Philistines had a garrison at Geba (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.5">1 Sm 10:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.13.3">13:3</a>). Jonathan defeated this outpost and stirred up the Philistines, who swarmed into Israel with an army vastly outnumbering the forces of Saul. Saul and his men were at Geba (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.16">13:16</a>) and later approached Gibeah (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.2">14:2</a>). The Philistines had set up a garrison at Michmash, just opposite Geba. Jonathan proposed to his armor bearer that they go over to this outpost and suggested that if the Philistines called to them to come over, that would be a sign that the Lord had given their enemy into their hand. The Philistines did just that, so the two Israelites approached and killed some 20 of the Philistines, putting the garrison and the entire army to rout. During the reign of David, another horde of Philistine invaders was struck down by him “from Geba to Gezer” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.25">2 Sm 5:25</a>).</p>
<p>Men from Geba are mentioned among the Jews who returned from the Babylonian exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.26">Ezr 2:26</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span> “Gaba”; <a href="?bref=Neh.11.31">Neh 11:31</a>). At the dedication of the rebuilt Jerusalem wall, singers from the area of Geba participated (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.29">Neh 12:29</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>