<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gehenna">
  <title>Gehenna*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GEHENNA*</p>
<p class="fl">English transliteration of the Greek form of an Aramaic word, which is derived from the Hebrew phrase “the Valley of [the son(s) of] Hinnom.” The name properly designates a deep valley delimiting the territories of the tribes of Benjamin and Judah (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.8">Jos 15:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.18.16">18:16</a>). It is commonly identified with Wadi el-Rababi that runs from beneath the western wall of the Old City, forming a deep ravine south of Jerusalem.</p>
<p>The place became notorious because of the idolatrous practices that were carried out there in the days of Judah’s kings Ahaz and Manasseh, especially involving the heinous crime of infant sacrifices associated with the Molech ceremonies (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.3">2 Kgs 16:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.6">21:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.28.3">2 Chr 28:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.33.6">33:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.19.6">Jer 19:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.32.35">32:35</a>). The spiritual reformation of King Josiah brought an end to these sinister proceedings (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.10">2 Kgs 23:10</a>). The prophet Jeremiah referred to the valley in picturing God’s judgment upon his people (<a href="?bref=Jer.2.23">Jer 2:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.7.30-32">7:30-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.19.5-6">19:5-6</a>).</p>
<p>Subsequently, the valley appears to have been used for the burning of the city’s refuse and the dead bodies of criminals. Interestingly, a well-established tradition locates the scene of Judas’s suicide and the consequent purchase of the Potter’s Field on the south side of this valley.</p>
<p>The ravine’s reputation for extreme wickedness gave rise, especially during the intertestamental period, to use of its name as a term for the place of final punishment for the wicked (1 Enoch 18:11-16; 27:1-3; 54:1ff.; 56:3-4; 90:26; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Esd.7.36">2 Esd 7:36</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.30.33">Is 30:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.66.24">66:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.7.10">Dn 7:10</a>). Jesus himself utilizes the term to designate the final abode of the unrepentant wicked (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.22">Mt 5:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.10.28">10:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.18.9">18:9</a>). Since Gehenna is a fiery abyss (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.43">Mk 9:43</a>), it is also the lake of fire (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.42,50">Mt 13:42, 50</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.20.14-15">Rv 20:14-15</a>) to which all the godless will ultimately be consigned (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.15,33">Mt 23:15, 33</a>), together with Satan and his devils (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.41">Mt 25:41</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.20">Rv 19:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.20.10">20:10</a>).</p>
<p>Gehenna must be carefully differentiated from other terms relative to the afterlife or final state. Whereas the OT “Sheol” and NT “hades” uniformly designate the temporary abode of the dead (before the last Day of Judgment), “Gehenna” specifies the final place where the wicked will suffer everlasting punishment (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.49.14-15">Ps 49:14-15</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.10.28">Mt 10:28</a>). The Greek form “Tartarus” occurs only in <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.4">2 Peter 2:4</a> and identifies the particular abode of the angels who fell in the primeval satanic revolt.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DeadPlaceofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dead, Place of the</a>; <a href="?item=Death_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Death</a>; <a href="?item=Hades_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hades</a>; <a href="?item=Hell_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hell</a>; <a href="?item=Sheol_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sheol</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>