<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Genealogy">
  <title>Genealogy</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GENEALOGY</p>
<p class="fl">Record or study of descent involving a tracing backward or forward of the ancestry of a nation, tribe, family, or individual. The Hebrews were not the only people in the ancient world to take an interest in maintaining genealogical records. The Sumerian king list of the third millennium <span class="era">BC</span> contains records of the early rulers of Mesopotamia. In Babylonian records the word “son” was frequently used in the sense of “descendant of.” King Tirhakah of Egypt (c. 685 <span class="era">BC</span>) referred to his “father,” Sesostris III, who lived some 1,200 years before him. Greeks and Romans also kept genealogical records. However, the biblical genealogies, especially those in Genesis and <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.1-9.44">1 Chronicles 1–9</a>, are unique in the literature of the ancient Near East. Only at the beginning of the Islamic age are such broad genealogical records found. Even today among tribal Semites, such as Arab nomads, there is an intense interest in genealogy, and it is not unusual for an Arab to be able to recite accurately the names of his ancestors for 10 or 15 generations back, covering a period of several hundred years.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TermsUsed">Terms Used</p>
<p class="fl">The word “genealogy” occurs only once as a noun in the Hebrew OT (<a href="?bref=Neh.7.5">Neh 7:5</a>), where it refers to a register of those who returned to Jerusalem with Zerubbabel at the end of the exile. The verbal form of the same word is found a total of 20 times in 1—2 Chronicles, Ezra, and Nehemiah. The terms “generations” and “book of the generations,” used in Genesis and elsewhere in the OT, convey the same idea. The equivalent NT terms are found in <a href="?bref=1Tim.1.4">1 Timothy 1:4</a> and <a href="?bref=Titus.3.9">Titus 3:9</a> (“genealogies”) and <a href="?bref=Matt.1.1">Matthew 1:1</a>, which refers to the “book of the genealogy” of Jesus Christ.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeofGenealogicalRecords">Purpose of Genealogical Records</p>
<p class="fl">The keeping of genealogical records in ancient Israel was an important activity and served a number of useful purposes. God’s promise of a land to Abraham and his descendants made such records necessary to establish and preserve the allotment of the land; a genealogical record served as evidence of a legitimate title to the ancestral property. Genealogies were essential for the preservation of the exclusive priesthood that had been established by the Mosaic law. In the time of Josephus every priest was supposed to be able to prove his descent.</p>
<p>One of the most important reasons for keeping genealogical records was to establish and maintain the right of royal succession in Judah through the family of David. The belief that the Messiah would come from the Davidic house made such records even more important.</p>
<p>Other purposes served by these family records included the imposition of military duty according to families (<a href="?bref=Num.1.2-3">Nm 1:2-3</a>). Position in camp and on the march from Egypt was determined by tribes and families (<a href="?bref=Num.2.2,17">2:2, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.10.11-28">10:11-28</a>). Also, God’s blessings were passed from one member of the family to his descendants (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.1-46">Gn 27</a>). The stress placed on the purity of the congregation (<a href="?bref=Deut.7.1-4">Dt 7:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.23.1-8">23:1-8</a>) required complete family records, particularly in the postexilic period. With the insistence of Ezra and Nehemiah upon racial purity, and with the purging of foreign elements from among the people (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.59-63">Ezr 2:59-63</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.10.9-44">10:9-44</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.13.23-28">Neh 13:23-28</a>), written evidence of purity of descent became essential; interest in the compilation of genealogies became intense after the exile.</p>
<p>Lineage was ordinarily traced through the male members of the family, with females being mentioned only rarely (e.g., <a href="?bref=Gen.11.29">Gn 11:29</a>, Sarah and Milcah; <a href="?bref=Gen.22.23">22:23</a>, Rebekah; and <a href="?bref=Num.26.33-27.11">Nm 26:33–27:11</a>, where the property inheritance of the daughters of Zelophehad was involved). Matthew mentions three women: Tamar, Rahab, and Ruth; and in the second group alludes to Bathsheba (see discussion below).</p>
<p class="h2" id="PrincipalGenealogicalListsintheBible">Principal Genealogical Lists in the Bible</p>
<p class="fl">The principal sources of genealogical material in the OT are found in Genesis, Numbers, 2 Samuel, 1 Kings, 1—2 Chronicles (which contain the greatest amount of genealogical material in the Bible), Ezra, and Nehemiah. The genealogies of Jesus Christ in <a href="?bref=Matt.1.1-25">Matthew 1</a> and <a href="?bref=Luke.3.1-38">Luke 3</a> are the only NT records. Together they contain a genealogical record from Adam to Christ.</p>
<p>Grouped together by historical periods, the following are the principal genealogical lists found in the Bible:</p>
<p class="h3">Before the Flood</p>
<p class="fl">Three lists are from this period. The first, found in <a href="?bref=Gen.4.17-22">Genesis 4:17-22</a>, traces the descendants of Cain through seven generations and explains the hereditary origin of certain occupations and crafts. The second, <a href="?bref=Gen.4.25-26">Genesis 4:25-26</a>, begins the account of the descendants of Seth, the posterity of Adam whose faithfulness to God is contrasted with the ungodly posterity of Cain. The third list, <a href="?bref=Gen.5.1-32">Genesis 5:1-32</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.1-4">1 Chr 1:1-4</a>), traces the descendants of Adam through Seth down to Noah and his sons at the time of the Flood.</p>
<p class="h3">From Noah to Abraham</p>
<p class="fl"><a href="?bref=Gen.10.1-32">Genesis 10:1-32</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.4-23">1 Chr 1:4-23</a>), frequently called the “table of nations,” contains a list of the nations descended from the sons of Noah (Shem, Ham, and Japheth). <a href="?bref=Gen.11.10-26">Genesis 11:10-26</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.24-27">1 Chr 1:24-27</a>) traces the descendants of Shem to the time of Abraham, and <a href="?bref=Gen.11.27-30">Genesis 11:27-30</a> (see also <a href="?bref=Gen.22.20-24">Gn 22:20-24</a>) lists the descendants of Nahor, Abraham’s brother.</p>
<p class="h3">From Abraham to the Descent into Egypt</p>
<p class="fl">The descendants of Abraham by Hagar, Sarah, and Keturah are found in <a href="?bref=Gen.16.15">Genesis 16:15</a>, <a href="?bref=Gen.21.1-3">21:1-3</a>, and <a href="?bref=Gen.25.1-4">25:1-4</a> (introducing the Arabs as descendants of Abraham; cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.28-34">1 Chr 1:28-34</a>). <a href="?bref=Gen.19.37-38">Genesis 19:37-38</a> links the Moabites and Ammonites to Abraham through his nephew Lot. A very important genealogical list during this period is that of the descendants of Jacob, giving the account of the parentage, birth, and naming of the founders of the 12 tribes of Israel (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.31-30.24">Gn 29:31–30:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.35.16-26">35:16-26</a>). Esau is acknowledged as the ancestor of the Edomites; his Edomite descendants are traced through his three wives (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.34">Gn 26:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.36.1-43">36:1-43</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.35-54">1 Chr 1:35-54</a>). The list of Jacob’s family at the time he entered Egypt, numbering 70, is found in <a href="?bref=Gen.46.1-27">Genesis 46:1-27</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.6.14-16">Ex 6:14-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.1-51">Nm 26:1-51</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.1-8.40">1 Chr 2–8</a>). A partial list of the heads of the fathers’ houses of Reuben, Simeon, and Levi is found in <a href="?bref=Exod.6.14-25">Exodus 6:14-25</a>; the chief purpose of this genealogy is to establish Aaron and Moses as members of Levi’s tribe.</p>
<p class="h3">From the Exodus to the Conquest of Canaan</p>
<p class="fl">While the tribes were still in the desert after leaving Egypt, a census was taken to determine the total number of Israelites (<a href="?bref=Num.1.4-54">Nm 1:4-54</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.2.2-33">2:2-33</a>). During this same period, a genealogy of the family of Aaron was compiled, and a separate census was taken of the Levites (<a href="?bref=Num.3.1-39">3:1-39</a>). A list of the 12 spies who searched out the land and the tribes they represented is given in <a href="?bref=Num.13.4-16">Numbers 13:4-16</a>; the most important names on this list are Caleb and Joshua. Near the end of the wilderness wanderings, another census of the people was ordered; the total number was approximately the same as that of the first census almost 40 years earlier (<a href="?bref=Num.26.4-51,57-62">26:4-51, 57-62</a>). As the tribes neared the Promised Land, a list was prepared of the tribal representatives who would take part in the division of the land (<a href="?bref=Num.34.16-29">34:16-29</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Period of the Kings</p>
<p class="fl">During the entire period of the monarchy, over 400 years, the only genealogical records of any consequence are those that pertain to David. His descendants are traced through 20 rulers who sat upon the throne of Judah until the nation fell to the Babylonians in 586 <span class="era">BC</span> (1—2 Kgs; cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.11.1--2Chr.36.21">1 Chr 11:1—2 Chr 36:21</a>). A list of David’s children is found in <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.2-5">2 Samuel 3:2-5</a> and <a href="?bref=2Sam.5.14-16">5:14-16</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.3.1-9">1 Chr 3:1-9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.14.4-7">14:4-7</a>). His mighty men, an elite group of soldiers, are named in <a href="?bref=2Sam.23.8-39">2 Samuel 23:8-39</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.11.10-47">1 Chr 11:10-47</a>). His recruits at Ziklag are recorded in <a href="?bref=1Chr.12.1-22">1 Chronicles 12:1-22</a>. Those who were his musicians and doorkeepers when the ark was brought to Jerusalem are named in <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.1-24">1 Chronicles 15:1-24</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.16.5-6,37-43">1 Chr 16:5-6, 37-43</a>). David’s political and religious organization of the kingdom—including the Levites, priests, singers, porters and other administrative officials, and military officers—is found in <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.1-27.34">1 Chronicles 23–27</a>. In spite of the literary activity associated with the reign of Solomon, the only genealogical record preserved from this period is that of Solomon’s princes and 12 officers (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.1-19">1 Kgs 4:1-19</a>). The genealogy of one prophet is traced back four generations (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.1">Zep 1:1</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Postexilic Period</p>
<p class="fl">During the postexilic period, the keeping of genealogical records probably received its greatest impetus through the activity of Ezra and Nehemiah, primarily because of their insistence upon racial purity and the purging of foreign elements from the community. A list of the exiles who returned with Zerubbabel is found in <a href="?bref=Ezra.2.1-70">Ezra 2:1-70</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Neh.7.6-73">Neh 7:6-73</a>, where the same list is found). A list of those who returned with Ezra is included in <a href="?bref=Ezra.8.1-20">8:1-20</a>. Ezra’s own genealogy is also recorded (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.5">Ezr 7:5</a>). There is a list of the Jews who married foreign women that included priests, Levites, singers, porters, and other Israelites (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.18-44">Ezr 10:18-44</a>). <a href="?bref=Neh.8.4-7">Nehemiah 8:4-7</a> names the Levites and others who assisted Ezra when he read the law publicly. Nehemiah also contains a list of those who participated in the ceremony of sealing the covenant (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.1-27">Neh 10:1-27</a>) and a list of those who lived in Jerusalem and other cities (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.3-36">11:3-36</a>). His interest in the priesthood is reflected in the list of priests and Levites who returned with Zerubbabel (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.1-9">12:1-9</a>), of the high priests from Jeshua to Jaddua (vv <a href="?bref=Neh.12.10-11">10-11</a>), of the heads of the priestly families (vv <a href="?bref=Neh.12.12-21">12-21</a>), of the Levites and porters who served under the high priest (vv <a href="?bref=Neh.12.22-26">22-26</a>), and of the princes and priests who were present at the dedication of the rebuilt wall of Jerusalem (vv <a href="?bref=Neh.12.31-42">31-42</a>).</p>
<p>The final genealogical record that must be mentioned is the genealogy from Adam to Saul (<a href="?bref=1Chr.1.1-8.40">1 Chr 1–8</a>), the longest section of genealogical material in the Bible. It is properly included with the genealogies compiled during the postexilic period, as the unknown chronicler (some think he was Ezra) prepared this list around 400 <span class="era">BC</span> from extant records and documents available to him. His purpose seems to have been to conserve the purity of blood in the restored nation and to insist that the nation’s well-being depended on its faithfulness to God’s law.</p>
<p class="h3">The New Testament Period</p>
<p class="fl">The only genealogies of consequence in the NT are those concerning Jesus Christ in <a href="?bref=Matt.1.1-17">Matthew 1:1-17</a> and <a href="?bref=Luke.3.23-38">Luke 3:23-38</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>