<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gerar">
  <title>Gerar</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GERAR</p>
<p class="fl">City located in the western Negev. It was used as a geographical landmark defining the western boundary of the Canaanite territory from Sidon to Gaza (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.19">Gn 10:19</a>). Abraham resided temporarily in this city, at which time he deceived Abimelech the king by giving him the impression that Sarah was his sister (<a href="?bref=Gen.20.1-2">20:1-2</a>). Later, Isaac settled in this city and also disguised his marriage to Rebekah for fear of reprisals from the men of the city. Isaac eventually left the town, moving to the nearby valley of Gerar on account of his conflicts with the Philistines. Here the herdsmen of Gerar quarreled with Isaac’s servants over a newly dug well, and Abimelech, king of the Philistines, made a covenant with Isaac (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.1-26">26:1-26</a>). It is doubtful that King Abimelech of Gerar (<a href="?bref=Gen.20.2">20:2</a>) was the same person as Abimelech, king of the Philistines (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.8">26:8</a>). Abimelech was probably a surname or an official title.</p>
<p>During the patriarchal period, Gerar appeared as a dominant Canaanite city in the Negev; however, in Joshua’s recounting of the Conquest, this town was not named among the Philistine cities yet to be conquered (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.2-3">Jos 13:2-3</a>) or in the list of cities already defeated (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.21-22">15:21-22</a>). Later, in the period of the kings, Gerar was mentioned as the southernmost city to which the Ethiopian army fled before it was completely destroyed by King Asa of Judah (910–869 <span class="era">BC</span>) and his army (<a href="?bref=2Chr.14.13-14">2 Chr 14:13-14</a>). Perhaps the fertile valley of Gedor (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.39">1 Chr 4:39</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.26.17">Gn 26:17</a>), formerly inhabited by the sons of Ham (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.10.19">Gn 10:19</a>), was identical with the valley of Gerar. Gedor was possibly a later scribal error where the copyist confused the Hebrew letter <span class="ital">r</span> for a <span class="ital">d.</span></p>
<p>The site of Gerar is identifiable with Tell Abu Hureireh along the northwestern bank of the Wadi esh-Sheri’ah, 15 miles (24.1 kilometers) northwest of Beersheba and 12 miles (19.3 kilometers) southeast of Gaza.</p>
  </body>
</item>