<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GershonGershonites">
  <title>Gershon, Gershonites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GERSHON, GERSHONITES</p>
<p class="fl">Levi’s oldest son (also spelled Gershom) who went into Egypt with Israel (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.11">Gn 46:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.17">Nm 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.1">1 Chr 6:1</a>) and was ancestor of a division of Levites (Gershonites) who came out of Egypt with Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.16-17">Ex 6:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.18,21">Nm 3:18, 21</a>).</p>
<p>In the list of the allotment of Levitical cities, the Gershonites were listed as one of the largest Levitical groups in Israel (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.1-7">Jos 21:1-7</a>). Some passages indicate that they were at times dominant among the functioning Levitical groups (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.11">Gn 46:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.6.16">Ex 6:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.17">Nm 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.57">26:57</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.1,16">1 Chr 6:1, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.6">23:6</a>).</p>
<p>According to the book of Numbers, the Gershonites were encamped behind the tabernacle to the west during the wilderness wanderings (<a href="?bref=Num.3.23">Nm 3:23</a>). Early in the second year after the exodus from Egypt, the Gershonite males numbered about 7,500 (v <a href="?bref=Num.3.22">22</a>). Only those between the ages of 30 and 50 could serve in the tabernacle, which at the time of that early census totaled 2,630 men (<a href="?bref=Num.4.39-40">4:39-40</a>). They were responsible for the care and transportation of the external furnishings of the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Num.3.25-26">3:25-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.4.24,27-28">4:24, 27-28</a>) and were given two wagons and four oxen for the purpose, being supervised by Aaron and his sons (<a href="?bref=Num.4.27">4:27</a>).</p>
<p>After the initial settlement of Canaan, the Gershonites were allotted 13 cities among the tribes of Issachar, Asher, Naphtali, and Manasseh in the northern part of Palestine (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.6">Jos 21:6</a>).</p>
<p>During the time of King David, they were listed among the Levites appointed to service in the temple (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.6-11">1 Chr 23:6-11</a>). The Gershonite families of Ladan and Jehieli were in charge of the treasury of the house of God (<a href="?bref=1Chr.26.20-22">26:20-22</a>). At David’s request, music in the temple was directed in part by Asaph and his family, who were Gershonites (<a href="?bref=1Chr.25.1-2">25:1-2</a>). In the reign of King Hezekiah the Gershonites are mentioned among the Levites who cleansed the temple (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.1-6,12">2 Chr 29:1-6, 12</a>). In the postexilic period the descendants of Asaph celebrated the laying of the temple foundation (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.10">Ezr 3:10</a>) and the dedication of the city walls (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.31-36">Neh 12:31-36</a>) with music.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=LeviTribeof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Levi, Tribe of</a>; <a href="?item=PriestsandLevites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Priests and Levites</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>