<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Giants">
  <title>Giants</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GIANTS</p>
<p class="fl">English translation of four different Hebrew words. One of these words occurs in <a href="?bref=Job.16.14">Job 16:14</a>, where the Hebrew word is translated “warrior” in the <span class="sc">rsv</span>, and “giant” in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>. Another Hebrew word is translated “giants” in the <span class="sc">nlt</span> and “Nephilim” (a transliteration of the Hebrew) in the <span class="sc">rsv</span> (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.4">Gn 6:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.13.33">Nm 13:33</a>). The original meaning of this Hebrew term is unknown, but it seems to be used of a group or race of people. Since none of the terms translated “giants” has that actual meaning, we cannot be sure that the Nephilim were of unusual physical stature.</p>
<p>In several passages the <span class="sc">kjv</span> translates “giants” and the <span class="sc">rsv</span> translates “Rephaim” (e.g., <a href="?bref=Deut.2.20">Dt 2:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.3.11">3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.4">Jos 12:4</a>). That word, usually in plural form, refers to several tribes of people who inhabited Palestine and who may have been unusually large in physical size. They included the Anakim of Judah’s coastal area and hill country around Hebron (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.11">Dt 2:11</a>), the Emim of Moab (v <a href="?bref=Deut.2.10">10</a>), the Zamzummim of Ammon (v <a href="?bref=Deut.2.20">20</a>), and the inhabitants of Bashan (<a href="?bref=Deut.3.11">3:11</a>). The word also appears in Joshua (<a href="?bref=Josh.12.4">Jos 12:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.13.12">13:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.15.8">15:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.17.15">17:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.18.16">18:16</a>). Some interpreters have suggested that these people were the original inhabitants of Palestine who were distinct tribes of tall people and who were eventually conquered and absorbed by the Canaanites, Philistines, Hebrews, and other invading peoples. Other interpreters contend that they were not distinct racial tribes but were individuals of great stature, perhaps the result of disease, who were found among the various races and tribes of Palestine. Neither contention can be established with certainty. Another Hebrew term is translated “giant” in both the <span class="sc">kjv</span> and <span class="sc">nlt</span> (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.16-22">2 Sm 21:16-22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.20.4-8">1 Chr 20:4-8</a>).</p>
<p>Perhaps the most famous giant in biblical literature is Goliath of Gath, the Philistine soldier who challenged King Saul’s army at the valley of Elah and caused them to be dismayed and afraid (<a href="?bref=1Sam.17.1-58">1 Sm 17</a>). He is said to have been six cubits and a span tall, which has been variously interpreted as being between seven and a half and nine and a half feet (2.3 to 2.9 meters). David’s defeat of Goliath brought the youth prominence in Israel (<a href="?bref=1Sam.18.5-7">18:5-7</a>). Goliath is not referred to in the text as a “giant,” but his height marks him as one of gigantic size. King Og of Bashan was another unusually tall person (<a href="?bref=Deut.3.11">Dt 3:11</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Nephilim_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Nephilim</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>