<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GodNamesof">
  <title>God, Names of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GOD, Names of</p>
<p class="fl">God’s self-identifications expressing various aspects of his being.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#TheBiblicalIdeaofName">The Biblical Idea of Name</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheNamesofGodintheOldTestament">The Names of God in the Old Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheNamesofGodintheNewTestament">The Names of God in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="TheBiblicalIdeaofName">The Biblical Idea of Name</p>
<p class="fl">In the Scriptures the name and person of God are inseparably related. This is in keeping with the biblical conception of what a name signifies.</p>
<p>In the Hebrew language, the term for “name” most probably meant “sign” or “distinctive mark.” In the Greek language, “name” <span class="ital">(</span><span class="greek">onoma</span><span class="ital">)</span> is derived from a verb that means “to know.” A name, therefore, indicates that by which a person or object is to be known. But the idea of name is not to be taken in the sense of a label or an arbitrary means of identifying or specifying a person, place, or object. “Name” in biblical usage correctly describes the person, place, or object and indicates the essential character of that to which the name is given. Adam named the animals according to their nature (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.19-20">Gn 2:19-20</a>); Noah means “one who brings relief and comfort” (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.29">5:29</a>); Jesus means “savior” (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">Mt 1:21</a>). When a person was given a new position or a radical change took place in his life, a new name was given to indicate that new aspect—for example, Abraham (“father of many,” <a href="?bref=Gen.17.5">Gn 17:5</a>), and Israel (“one who strives with God” or “God strives,” <a href="?bref=Gen.32.28">32:28</a>). The name of a person or people expressed what the person or people thought the proper description or statement of character was.</p>
<p>With regard to the names of God, there are considerable differences, and these are most clearly seen when biblical scholars and theologians confront the question of whether the names of God are ascriptions given by God concerning himself or they are ascriptions given to God by people who observed his acts and reflected on his character as discerned through a study of divine deeds. Here are some examples of various kinds of divine names:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Proper names: El, Yahweh, Adonai, Theos (God), Kurios (Lord).</p>
<p class="list">2. Personal names: Father, Abba, Son, Jesus, Holy Spirit.</p>
<p class="list">3. Titles: Creator, Messiah/Christ, Paraclete/Comforter.</p>
<p class="list">4. Essential names: Light, Love, Spirit.</p>
<p class="list">5. Descriptive names: Rock, Ba’al, Master, Rabboni, Shepherd.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheNamesofGodintheOldTestament">The Names of God in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="h3">El and Related Names</p>
<p class="fl">The name <span class="hebrew">’El</span> is found over 200 times in the Hebrew Bible. It is best translated as “God.” The term <span class="hebrew">’el</span> has a number of possible meanings. The root is thought by some to be <span class="hebrew">’ul</span><span class="ital">,</span> which means “to be first” or “to be strong.” Others suggest the root is <span class="hebrew">’alah</span><span class="ital">,</span> which means “to precede” and suggests “leader” or “commander.” It can also mean “to be afraid.” Thus God as <span class="hebrew">’alah</span><span class="ital">,</span> as the strong one, is to be feared. Still others suggest the preposition <span class="hebrew">’el</span> (“to, toward”) as the root; the idea then is of “one giving self to others” or of “one to whom others go for help.” Some scholars suggest that the word <span class="hebrew">’alim</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “to bind,” should be considered as a root also—that is, “the strong one binds and holds firm control.” Common to these four suggested root meanings is the idea of strength, power, and of supreme excellence and greatness.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">’El</span> in the OT is used particularly in the earlier books, where it describes God’s exercising dynamic power as distinguished from authority. <span class="hebrew">’El</span> speaks of God as the great doer and producer. He is the One who exercises such power that whatever is made, done, kept, or destroyed is his doing (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.15.1-27">Ex 15</a>). <span class="hebrew">’El</span> is also used to express the idea that God is not to be identified as part of creation but as the One who is above, behind, and beyond creation (<a href="?bref=Ps.19.1">Ps 19:1</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span> is also commonly used as the name of God, occurring over 2,500 times in the OT. There are differences of opinion concerning the exact origin and meaning of this plural name. Some have suggested that <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span> is the plural form of <span class="hebrew">’El</span><span class="ital">,</span> but it seems more likely that it is a plural of <span class="hebrew">’Eloah</span><span class="ital">,</span> which appears in the poetical writings. Some critical writers have suggested that this plural form is borrowed from pagan polytheistic sources, but no such plural form is found among pagans as the name of a deity. Others have suggested that the plural form is used to indicate the triune nature of God, and support for this has been seen in the use of a singular verb with this plural noun. The biblical doctrine of the Trinity, as it is developed throughout the Scriptures, does not appear to be based on the use of this plural form of God’s name, even though the two positions are not contradictory.</p>
<p>The plural form, <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span><span class="ital">,</span> is best understood as expressing intensity. God makes himself known by this name as the Lord of intense and extensive glory and richness as he exercises his preeminence and power in the created cosmos. Hence, when the Scripture speaks of creation, it states, “In the beginning <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span> created the heavens and the earth” (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.1">Gn 1:1</a>). This name is repeated 35 times in <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Genesis 1</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.2.1-25">2</a> in connection with God’s power as revealed in Creation. In the book of Deuteronomy the name <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span> is used repeatedly to stress the majestic power of God that was shown in Israel’s release from bondage in Egypt, preservation in the wilderness, and preparation for entrance into the Promised Land. In this context, God <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span><span class="ital">)</span> is also recognized as the Lawgiver who will powerfully execute judgment on covenant breakers. The psalmists also used this named repeatedly as they acknowledged and praised God the majestic ruler who had demonstrated his omnipotence in many dimensions of life (see <a href="?bref=Ps.68.1-35">Ps 68</a>, in which <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span> appears 26 times.)</p>
<p>Some scholars point to the use of <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span> when God spoke to Abraham and said he would be <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span> to the patriarch and his seed; that is, God would be in a covenant relationship to them (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.1-8">Gn 17:1-8</a>). Included in this relationship is the idea that God is ever ready to use his power on behalf of those who are in covenant with him. Thus, <span class="hebrew">’</span><span class="hebrew">Elohim</span> also expresses the concept of God’s faithfulness in regard to the covenant and the promises and blessings involved in it.</p>
<p>The name <span class="hebrew">’</span><span class="hebrew">Eloah</span> occurs mainly in the poetical writings, no fewer than 41 times in Job. Isaiah used it to express the incomparable character of God (<a href="?bref=Isa.44.8">Is 44:8</a>). In like manner David asked, “Who is God [<span class="hebrew">’</span><span class="hebrew">Eloah</span>], but the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>?” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.22.32">2 Sm 22:32</a>). Moses was the first to use the name <span class="hebrew">’</span><span class="hebrew">Eloah</span> in his song (<a href="?bref=Deut.32.15-17">Dt 32:15-17</a>), referring to Israel’s God in the context of the “no-gods,” which had been chosen in place of the Rock of salvation and the incomparable One. This name was probably used to stress the fact that God is the only true and living One, the One to be adored and worshiped; he is to be revered with a holy fear.</p>
<p>Another closely related name is <span class="hebrew">’Elah</span><span class="ital">,</span> found in Ezra and Daniel. Some think <span class="hebrew">’Elah</span> is a Chaldee or Aramaic form of <span class="hebrew">’Eloah</span><span class="ital">.</span> Its root is said to be <span class="hebrew">’alah</span><span class="ital">,</span> which means “to fear” or “to be perplexed.” God as <span class="hebrew">’Elah</span> is the God to be feared and worshiped accordingly. In view of this meaning, it can be understood why, in the time of Israel’s exile and immediately after their return, this name was commonly used.</p>
<p>Three other names of God include the term <span class="hebrew">’El</span><span class="ital">:</span></p>
<p><span class="hebrew">’El ‘Elyon</span> is the name used to designate the God of Melchizedek (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.18-22">Gn 14:18-22</a>) as God Most High. In <a href="?bref=Ps.57.2">Psalms 57:2</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.78.56">78:56</a> the Hebrew reads <span class="hebrew">’Elohim ‘Elyon</span><span class="ital">.</span> It is believed that the term <span class="hebrew">‘Elyon</span> is derived from the verb <span class="hebrew">‘alah</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “go up, be elevated, to be exalted.” There are a number of instances where the term <span class="hebrew">‘Elyon</span> is used alone, but the context indicates that it is then used as a synonym for God (e.g., <a href="?bref=Num.24.16">Nm 24:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.83.18">Ps 83:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.14.14">Is 14:14</a>). The term <span class="hebrew">‘elyon</span> is used quite frequently as an adjective; it is then translated as “high, highest, upper, uppermost.” The basic ascription given to God when this name is employed is to One who is above all things as the maker, possessor, and ruler. He is incomparable in every way; he is subject to no one and no thing; he is the Exalted One.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">’El Shaddai</span> is used in the longer form seven times in the Scriptures (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.1">Gn 17:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.28.3">28:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.35.11">35:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.43.14">43:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.48.3">48:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.6.3">Ex 6:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.5">Ez 10:5</a>). In the shorter form <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">Shaddai</span><span class="ital">),</span> it appears more frequently: in <a href="?bref=Job.30.1-31">Job 30</a> times; in <a href="?bref=Ps.19.1">Psalms 19:1</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.68.14">68:14</a>; once in Ruth (<a href="?bref=Ruth.1.21">1:21</a>), Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.13.6">13:6</a>), Ezekiel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.24">1:24</a>), and Joel (<a href="?bref=Joel.1.15">1:15</a>). In these passages the combined ideas of God as the all-powerful, all-sufficient, transcendent, sovereign ruler and disposer are present. This meaning is generally accepted, but there are differences as to the exact meaning of the term <span class="hebrew">Shaddai</span><span class="ital">.</span> Some have begun with <span class="hebrew">shad</span> as the first concept to be considered; its meaning is “breast, pap, or teat,” and it is considered a “precious metaphor” of the God who nourishes, supplies, and satisfies. The root of <span class="hebrew">shad</span> <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">shadah</span><span class="ital">),</span> in Semitic usage, is to moisten. This meaning is not the preferred one in the context of which <span class="hebrew">’El Shaddai</span> appears; nor is <span class="hebrew">shed</span> (demon), which some scholars have sought to use because it appears in <a href="?bref=Deut.32.17">Deuteronomy 32:17</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.106.37">Psalm 106:37</a> speaking of Israel’s idolatry. In addition to the fact that <span class="hebrew">shed</span> is spelled differently, the connection between the concept of demon and God as all-powerful is difficult to establish. More acceptable is the suggestion that <span class="hebrew">Shaddai</span> is a composite term of <span class="hebrew">sha</span> (“the one who”) and <span class="hebrew">dai</span> (“is sufficient”). The later Greek versions have adopted this meaning. The most preferred explanation is that <span class="hebrew">Shaddai</span> is derived from the verb <span class="hebrew">shadad</span> (“to overpower, to deal violently, or to devastate”). A clear connection between <span class="hebrew">shadad</span> and <span class="hebrew">Shaddai</span> is said to be found in <a href="?bref=Isa.13.6">Isaiah 13:6</a> and <a href="?bref=Joel.1.15">Joel 1:15</a>. God as <span class="hebrew">’El Shaddai</span> is presented as the all-powerful One, totally self-sufficient, absolute ruler, and the One who can and does make final disposition. The Septuagint has adapted this meaning; it translates <span class="hebrew">’El Shaddai</span> as <span class="greek">Pantokrator</span><span class="ital">,</span> the “All-Ruler” or “Sovereign One.”</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">’El ‘Olam</span> is used to refer to God as the everlasting or eternal One, a clear instance where the name of God and an attribute of God are combined. The term <span class="hebrew">‘olam</span> has a wide range of uses. It is usually defined in lexicons as meaning “long duration, antiquity, and indefinite futurity.” It is used to speak of God’s existence, of God’s covenant and promises, and of the Messiah’s reign. Speaking to God, the psalmist said, “You are from <span class="hebrew">‘olam</span> (everlasting) to <span class="hebrew">‘olam</span> (everlasting)” (<a href="?bref=Ps.90.2">Ps 90:2</a>), and the prophet Isaiah spoke of God as the everlasting Creator (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.28">Is 40:28</a>) and as everlasting strength (<a href="?bref=Isa.26.4">26:4</a>), and Jeremiah spoke of God as everlasting King (<a href="?bref=Jer.10.10">Jer 10:10</a>). God’s everlastingness or eternity speaks of his infinity in relation to time. <span class="hebrew">‘Olam</span><span class="ital">,</span> as ascribed to God, should not be thought of as duration prolonged indefinitely backward and forward. Rather, the word speaks to God’s transcending all temporal limits; in addition, <span class="hebrew">‘olam</span> refers to the quality of God that differs essentially from time. The Scriptures speak of <span class="hebrew">’El ‘Olam</span> in contexts where the believer’s assurance of well-being, security, and hope are presented as prized possessions.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">’El Gibbor</span> is a name that speaks of God’s power and might. <span class="hebrew">Gibbor</span> alone is used in reference to mighty and heroic men. The two terms together always refer to God, and in some instances <span class="hebrew">Haggadol</span> (“the greatest”) is added (<a href="?bref=Deut.10.17">Dt 10:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.32.18">Jer 32:18</a>) to emphasize the greatness and awesome majesty of God. <span class="hebrew">’El Gibbor</span> is also used to describe the Messiah in <a href="?bref=Isa.9.6">Isaiah 9:6</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.45.4">Ps 45:4</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">’El Ro’i</span> is used once to describe God as the seeing One. Hagar described the Lord this way when she was found in the wilderness (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.13">Gn 16:13</a>). <a href="?bref=Ps.139.1-2">Psalm 139:1-2</a> expresses this concept of God as the all-seeing One from whose eye nothing is hidden (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.33.18">Ps 33:18</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> is a distinctly proper name of God. It is never used to refer to any pagan gods; neither is it used in regard to men. It appears 6,823 times in the OT, occurring first in <a href="?bref=Gen.2.4">Genesis 2:4</a>, where it is joined with <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span><span class="ital">.</span> <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> is used 164 times in Genesis, and it appears 1,800 times in Exodus through Joshua. It never appears in a declined form in the Hebrew language, and it never occurs in the plural form or with suffixes. It is abbreviated as <span class="hebrew">Yah</span> and <span class="hebrew">Yahu</span> (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.15.2">Ex 15:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.68.4">Ps 68:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.12.2">Is 12:2</a>; etc.).</p>
<p>The exact meaning of the name <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> is difficult to determine. Some have sought the root in the verb <span class="hebrew">hayah</span> (“to be”) or in an ancient form of that same verb, <span class="hebrew">hawah</span><span class="ital">.</span> There is no agreement as to whether the <span class="hebrew">qal</span> or <span class="hebrew">hiphil</span> form of the verb should be considered as the root. Those who opt for the <span class="hebrew">hiphil</span> form read <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> to mean “cause to be”; thus <a href="?bref=Exod.3.14">Exodus 3:14</a> would read, “I will cause to be what has come to be.” Others look to the <span class="hebrew">qal</span> form and then translate the name as “I Am” or “I Shall Be.” Still others are inclined to disassociate the name from the verb <span class="hebrew">hayah</span> and regard it as an original and independent term, expressing the uniqueness of Israel’s gracious God.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="GodsNameYHWHinAncientHebrewLetters"/>
<p>Translators of the OT have not agreed upon the correct translation of the name <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">.</span> Since it is translated into the Greek as <span class="greek">kurios</span><span class="ital">,</span> which means “Lord,” many have rendered <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> as “<span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.” But <span class="hebrew">’Adonai</span><span class="ital">,</span> which is best rendered “Lord,” appears with <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> in various instances. The <span class="sc">kjv</span>, for example, translates <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> as “God,” and <span class="hebrew">’Adonai</span> as “Lord.” Some modern translators have chosen to use <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> (see <span class="sc">jb</span> and <span class="sc">njb</span>). The name Jehovah, as used in the <span class="sc">asv</span> (1901), has been judged unacceptable. This name arose due to the Jewish practice of not pronouncing <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> because of <a href="?bref=Lev.24.16">Leviticus 24:16</a>, “He that blasphemes the name of <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> shall surely be put to death.” This warning against a vain or blasphemous use of the name was taken in an absolute sense, especially after Israel’s deportation (cf. <a href="?bref=Amos.6.10">Am 6:10</a>). Hence, when reading the OT the Jews substituted either <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span> or <span class="hebrew">’Adonai</span> for <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">.</span> From this, the practice of adding the vowels of <span class="hebrew">’Adonai</span> to YHWH (JeHoWaH) became established.</p>
<p>The interpretation of <a href="?bref=Exod.6.2-3">Exodus 6:2-3</a> has caused much debate. “And God said to Moses, ‘I am <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">;</span> I appeared to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, as <span class="hebrew">’</span><span class="hebrew">El Shaddai</span><span class="ital">,</span> but by my name <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> I did not make myself known to them.’ ” This passage has been understood to mean that the name <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> was not known or used prior to the time of Moses. But that is not what the passage states; rather, it speaks of the patriarchs not knowing God as <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">.</span> They knew him as <span class="hebrew">’El Shaddai</span> in actual revelatory historical deeds. They had not come to know God according to his unique character, that is, as <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">.</span> In other words, God had always been <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">;</span> he is saying to Moses that the descendants of the patriarchs would come to know the full, rich meaning of the name by the way God dealt with them.</p>
<p>This name <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> reveals God’s nature in the highest and fullest sense possible. It includes, or presupposes, the meaning of the other names. <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> particularly stresses the absolute faithfulness of God. God had promised the patriarchs that he would be their God, that he would be with them and deliver and bless them, keep them, and give them a land as a place of service and inheritance. Moses is told by God that Israel is about to behold and experience the unchangeableness of God as he steadfastly and wondrously remembers his word and executes it to the fullest degree. God would prove to be a faithful, redeeming, upholding, restoring God. In working out this redemption, God would demonstrate that he is all that his name implies: merciful, gracious, patient, full of loving-kindness, truthful, faithful, forgiving, just, and righteous (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.5-6">Ex 34:5-6</a>). Truly, Jacob had received an insight into the meaning of the name when he exclaimed, “I wait for thy salvation, O <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span>” (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.18">Gn 49:18</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">,</span> then, is the name par excellence of Israel’s God. As <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">,</span> he is a faithful covenant God who, having given his word of love and life, keeps that word by bestowing love and life abundantly on his own.</p>
<p>In view of the richness of the name <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">,</span> it can be understood why there were stringent rules regarding its proper use (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.11,16">Lv 24:11, 16</a>). It also explains why thankful, rejoicing, worshiping Israelites used the abbreviated form of <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> in song when they sang Hallelujah: “Praise Yah” (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.35">Pss 104:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.106.1">106:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.149.1">149:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.150.1">150:1</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> is used in a number of phrases that are considered names of or ascriptions of God. The most common of these compound names is <span class="hebrew">Yahweh Tseba’oth</span> (“hosts”). The word “hosts” is used frequently in the Pentateuch to refer to the armies of Israel (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.10.14-28">Nm 10:14-28</a>). This is because the word is derived from the verb <span class="hebrew">saba</span><span class="hebrew">’</span><span class="ital">,</span> which means “to wage” war. It also means “to serve” in some contexts; for example, <a href="?bref=Num.8.24">Numbers 8:24</a> clearly has reference to the service performed in the tabernacle. The noun <span class="hebrew">tseba’oth</span> first occurs in <a href="?bref=Gen.2.1">Genesis 2:1</a>, where it refers to the many components of the earth and heaven. Some would limit the reference in these contexts to the stars. Still others would suggest that the <span class="hebrew">tseba’oth</span> refers to the angels, appealing to <a href="?bref=Ps.33.6">Psalm 33:6</a> for confirmation.</p>
<p>The compound name <span class="hebrew">Yahweh Tseba’oth</span> first appears in <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.3">1 Samuel 1:3</a>. In view of the frequent use of <span class="hebrew">tseba’oth</span> in 1—2 Samuel to refer to armies (<a href="?bref=1Sam.12.9">1 Sm 12:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.14.50">14:50</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.17.55">17:55</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.2.8">2 Sm 2:8</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.8.16">8:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.10.16">10:16</a>), it is thought that the compound name refers to <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> as the God of armies, that is, God has his armies to serve him. These are considered to be armies of angels who are ministering servants to God. It has been correctly pointed out that the compound name <span class="hebrew">Yahweh Tseba’oth</span> is used most frequently by the prophets (Jeremiah, 88 times; Zechariah, 55 times; Malachi, 25 times; Haggai, 14 times) at times when God’s people had either suffered defeat at the hands of enemy armies or were threatened by defeat. Therefore, the compound name was used to remind them that their covenant God had great hosts to fight and work for him on behalf of his people. Thus, though Israel’s armies failed, their covenant God was sufficient for every possible circumstance. And it was to this <span class="hebrew">Yahweh Tseba’oth</span> that Israel’s commanders were to give allegiance (<a href="?bref=Josh.5.14-15">Jos 5:14-15</a>), and in whose name Israel was blessed (<a href="?bref=2Sam.6.18">2 Sm 6:18</a>).</p>
<p>Several other compound names occur infrequently:</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Yahweh-Nissi</span> (<span class="hebrew">nissi</span><span class="ital">,</span> “my banner”) is the name that Moses called on when he built an altar celebrating Israel’s God-given victory over the Amalekites (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.15">Ex 17:15</a>). Isaiah uses the term <span class="hebrew">nissi</span> when speaking of the coming Messiah who is to be the conqueror (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.10">Is 11:10</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Yahweh-Rapha</span> (<span class="hebrew">rapha’</span><span class="ital">,</span> “healer”) appears in <a href="?bref=Exod.15.26">Exodus 15:26</a>, when Israel is assured that God, their healer, will prevent the diseases of Egypt from affecting Israel. Although the name is only used once, God was often called upon and praised as the healing One (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.103.3">Ps 103:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.30.26">Is 30:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.14">Jer 6:14</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Yahweh-Rohi</span> (<span class="hebrew">ro‘i</span><span class="ital">,</span> “my shepherd”) appears in <a href="?bref=Ps.23.1">Psalm 23:1</a>. The concept of <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> as shepherd is explicated in <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.1-31">Ezekiel 34</a>. “I myself will be the Shepherd of my sheep” (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.15">15</a>). Jesus demonstrated this concept’s full meaning when as a shepherd he gave his life for his sheep.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Yahweh-Jireh</span> (<span class="hebrew">yir’eh</span><span class="ital">,</span> “to see ahead or to provide”) appears in <a href="?bref=Gen.22.14">Genesis 22:14</a>. Abraham gave this name to the place where God provided a substitute for his son Isaac, whom Abraham was to offer as a sacrifice to God. <span class="hebrew">Yahweh-Shalom</span> (<span class="hebrew">shalom</span><span class="ital">,</span> “peace”) is the name Gideon gave to the altar he built when the angel of the Lord came to give him orders to fight the Midianites (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.24">Jgs 6:24</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> appears with a few forms of the term <span class="hebrew">tsadaq</span><span class="ital">,</span> “righteousness.” <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> is spoken of as our righteousness in <a href="?bref=Jer.23.6">Jeremiah 23:6</a>; the thought evidently is that David’s Righteous Branch (the Messiah) will attribute God’s righteousness to those who are incorporated in the new covenant. This concept is expressed in the Pentateuch a number of times when it is said that God has provided a way for living righteously; that is, God provides a way of sanctification (cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.20.8">Lv 20:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.22.9">22:9</a>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">’Adonai</span> as a name for God appears about 360 times in the OT, though it is not uniformly used. It is first found in <a href="?bref=Gen.15.2">Genesis 15:2</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.8.1-22">8</a>, when Abram requests more definite information concerning a son and the Promised Land. It appears only 14 times after that in the Pentateuch. It appears repeatedly in the Psalms (over 50 times), and certain of the prophets use it frequently (Isaiah, 47 times; Jeremiah, 29 times; Ezekiel, over 150 times; and Amos, 27 times).</p>
<p>The word <span class="hebrew">’adan</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “master, ruler, owner, lord,” is thought to be the root of the noun <span class="hebrew">’adon</span><span class="ital">,</span> which is frequently used of men. For example, in Genesis and 1—2 Samuel the term is used often for men who own slaves or are in positions of authority. <span class="hebrew">’Adonai</span> is correctly described as the name of personal communication between the believer and God. In such communication the worshiper acknowledged God’s intense majesty and greatness and also the sense of belonging to this God. <span class="hebrew">’Adonai</span><span class="ital">,</span> coming from human lips, expressed honor for God and humble submission on the part of the believing person. <span class="hebrew">’Adonai</span><span class="ital">,</span> thus, is the name that expresses faith, assurance, security, ready service, and thanksgiving (<a href="?bref=Ps.16.2">Pss 16:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.57.9-10">57:9-10</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Old Testament Name Combinations</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT the names of God appear in various combinations. For example <span class="hebrew">’Elohim-Yahweh</span><span class="ital">,</span> <span class="hebrew">’Elohim-Yahweh-’Adonai</span><span class="ital">,</span> and <span class="hebrew">’Elohim-’Adonai</span> are very common. These combinations were an effort to express the fullness of God’s being and character as these had been revealed. Names of God in combination with “Israel” occur also as, for example, with <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span>-God-Israel (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.3">Jgs 5:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.17.6">Is 17:6</a>). God is also invoked in relation to Israel without the mention of one of his names—for example, <span class="hebrew">Qedosh Yisrael</span> (“Holy One of Israel,” <a href="?bref=Isa.43.14">Is 43:14</a>) and <span class="hebrew">’Abir Yisrael</span> (“Mighty One of Israel,” <a href="?bref=Gen.49.24">Gn 49:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.132.2">Ps 132:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.49.26">Is 49:26</a>). By means of these phrases, the covenantal relationship between God and his people was expressed and God’s unchanging character was positively acknowledged.</p>
<p class="h3">Old Testament Personal Names</p>
<p class="fl">The personal names of God are Father, Son, and Holy Spirit and variations of these.</p>
<p>The term <span class="hebrew">’Abh</span> (“father”) appears more frequently in Genesis than in any other book, and in the Pentateuch more than in any other division of the OT. But it is not used there of God but rather of one who has generated children (i.e., the male parent), the progenitor—head, chief, and ruler of the family group or clan. It is used often in the sense of the responsible one through whom God has spoken, with whom God has dealt, and through whom he has given a rich heritage to the children and descendants of the patriarchs.</p>
<p>In the poetical books, God is referred to as Father but is not directly named as such. Job is asked, “Has the rain a father?” (<a href="?bref=Job.38.28">Jb 38:28</a>). The reference is to God as the maker, source, and controller of rain. In <a href="?bref=Ps.68.5">Psalm 68:5</a> God in his holy dwelling place is the “Father of the fatherless”; the parallel phrase, “protector of widows,” indicates the sense. <a href="?bref=Ps.89.26">Psalm 89:26</a> says that David will cry to God, “Thou art my Father,” and the parallels use the terms “God” and “Rock of my salvation.” The idea here is of God as Creator and Savior who raised up, delivered, and protected David. In <a href="?bref=Ps.103.13">Psalm 103:13</a>, “Father” is used analogously, “As a father pities his children.”</p>
<p>Isaiah uses the term “Father” in relation to God four times. Three times it refers to the One who has made, saved, formed, kept, and directed Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.63.16">Is 63:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.64.8">64:8</a>). Isaiah says the promised child is to be named Everlasting Father (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.6">9:6</a>). Used in this sense, the term establishes the Son’s equality with the Father in stature, function, ability, and responsibility. Jeremiah also refers to God as Father in <a href="?bref=Jer.3.4,19">Jeremiah 3:4, 19</a>, meaning the origin, keeper, and friend of his people Israel. <a href="?bref=Mal.1.6">Malachi 1:6</a> and <a href="?bref=Mal.2.10">2:10</a> speak of God as the parent who deserves honor from his children and as the origin and ruler of all people.</p>
<p>The term “son” is one of the most-used terms in the OT; it commonly occurs in the sense of offspring and descendant. It also appears in the sense of follower or successor. There are a few indirect references to the second person of the Trinity.</p>
<p>The messianic <a href="?bref=Ps.2.1-12">Psalm 2</a> has such a reference: “You are my son” (v <a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">7</a>). It is stated in the context of the king speaking to one who rules and is to rule with and under the sovereign. The immediate reference may be to the theocratic king; however, the reference is revealed in the NT to be the second person of the Trinity (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.33">Acts 13:33</a>). Thus, the term “son” is applied to the promised Messiah who is set forth as the divine sovereign ruler and judge of the nations. The Son is perceived to be equal with the Father in deity and function. Not all biblical scholars accept this interpretation, but support is found in such NT passages as <a href="?bref=Heb.1.8">Hebrews 1:8</a> which quotes <a href="?bref=Ps.45.6">Psalm 45:6</a>. As stated above, Isaiah speaks of the son to be given (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.6">Is 9:6</a>), the One born of the virgin (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">7:14</a>), who is Immanuel, Mighty God, Everlasting Father, Prince of Peace.</p>
<p>The name “Holy Spirit” occurs only a few times in the OT. The Spirit is referred to frequently by terms and phrases such as “the Spirit of God” (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.2">Gn 1:2</a>), “the Spirit of the Lord God” (<a href="?bref=Isa.61.1">Is 61:1</a>), “the Spirit of the Lord” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.1">Ez 37:1</a>), “the Spirit” (<a href="?bref=Num.11.17">Nm 11:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.27.18">27:18</a>), “my Spirit” (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.3">Gn 6:3</a>), and “your Spirit” (<a href="?bref=Ps.51.11">Ps 51:11</a>). Though the character of the Spirit is not developed as clearly in the OT as in the NT, it can be safely stated that the relationship posited between God and the Spirit is such that there is no doubt that the OT teaches the deity of the Spirit. The character and function of the Spirit is referred to especially in relation to the work of creation (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.2">Gn 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.33.6">Ps 33:6</a>; etc.) and the equipping of servants for the service of God—for example, craftsmanship (<a href="?bref=Exod.35.31">Ex 35:31</a>), leadership (<a href="?bref=Num.11.17">Nm 11:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.27.18">27:18</a>), and prophecy (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.6">1 Sm 10:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.23.2">2 Sm 23:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.15.1">2 Chr 15:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.5">Ez 11:5</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheNamesofGodintheNewTestament">The Names of God in the New Testament</p>
<p class="h3">Proper Names of God</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="greek">Theos</span> is the NT equivalent of the OT names <span class="hebrew">’El </span>and <span class="hebrew">’Elohim</span><span class="ital">;</span> <span class="hebrew">‘Elyon</span> appears in the NT as <span class="greek">Hupsistos</span><span class="ital">,</span> the Highest (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.7">Mk 5:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.32,76">Lk 1:32, 76</a>). <span class="greek">Pantokrator</span> (<span class="hebrew">‘El Shaddai</span>) appears with <span class="greek">Theos</span> (<a href="?bref=2Cor.6.18">2 Cor 6:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.16.7">Rv 16:7</a>). This name was used not only to express God’s transcendency, power, sovereignty, and lordship, but also to express that God is one who has a close relationship with his people. This fact is established by the very frequent use of personal pronouns with <span class="greek">Theos</span><span class="ital">.</span> The name <span class="greek">Theos</span> appears over 1,000 times in the NT.</p>
<p><span class="greek">Kurios</span><span class="ital">,</span> “Lord,” is used to express the OT names <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span> and <span class="hebrew">‘Adonai</span> in the Septuagint, and the NT follows it. <span class="greek">Kurios</span> means “power,” so the meaning is not the same as with <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">;</span> yet the NT does give <span class="greek">Kurios</span> the full weight of meaning that the OT gave to <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">,</span> especially when used of Jesus Christ (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.2.36">Acts 2:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.9-11">Phil 2:9-11</a>; etc.)</p>
<p><span class="greek">Despotes</span> is used five times of God or Jesus in the NT (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.29">Lk 2:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.24">Acts 4:24</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.11">2 Pt 2:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Jude.1.4">Jude 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.10">Rv 6:10</a>). It expresses the idea of authority. The idea of brutality conveyed by the modern concept “despot” is absent from the NT usage even when applied to men, where its central thought is ownership (<a href="?bref=2Tim.2.21">2 Tm 2:21</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Personal Names of God</p>
<p class="fl">In the baptismal formula, which is part of the Great Commission (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.19-20">Mt 28:19-20</a>), the three personal names of God appear: Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. These names carry the OT meaning, but since the relationship of the three Persons is explicated, the NT meaning of the names is enriched.</p>
<p>“Jesus” is the personal name of the Son, the second person of the triune Godhead. It means “savior” (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">Mt 1:21</a>). The root of this name “to save” gave rise to names such as Joshua, Hoshea, and Hosea. The basic meaning of the OT root is “to bring into a safe, wide-open place.” Joshua, bringing Israel into Canaan, personally did what his name meant. The NT explanation (“save from sin”) is not contrary to the OT meaning. To be saved from sin is to be restored to fellowship with God and to enter into the paradise of the heavenly kingdom.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Christology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Christology</a>; <a href="?item=GodBeingandAttributesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Being and Attributes of</a>; <a href="?item=HolySpirit_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Holy Spirit</a>; <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Life and Teachings of</a>; <a href="?item=Messiah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Messiah</a>; <a href="?item=NamesSignificanceof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Names, Significance of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>