<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Governor">
  <title>Governor</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GOVERNOR</p>
<p class="fl">Biblical term translated from at least ten different Hebrew root words and five Greek roots. English versions do not render these words consistently; they use a variety of titles, such as “overseer,” “officer,” “leader,” “judge,” and “deputy,” to translate the same Hebrew word. The situation is similar in the Septuagint (Greek OT).</p>
<p>A governor was someone of superior rank who exercised authority over persons, territory, or both. Sometimes rank and power were his by virtue of the office; other times accession to office was based on noble lineage, wealth, and public attainment. A governor normally received authority from a king; therefore, he was a deputy in the territory he governed. Such was the case with Joseph (<a href="?bref=Gen.42.6">Gn 42:6</a>), Gedaliah (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.5">Jer 40:5</a>), Daniel (<a href="?bref=Dan.2.48">Dn 2:48</a>), and Zerubbabel (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1">Hg 1:1</a>). One Hebrew term for “governor,” however, could mean “absolute ruler” (<a href="?bref=Josh.12.2">Jos 12:2</a>) as well as a person who acted under authority.</p>
<p>The term most frequently used in the OT is evidently from an Akkadian expression meaning “lord of a district.” Such governors normally relied on military power to maintain their rule (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.24">2 Kgs 18:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.2.7">Neh 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.51.23,28">Jer 51:23, 28</a>). The satrap of the Persian and Greek periods was most probably a civil governor. The leader of a city-state was often known as “governor” in the preexilic period (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.26">1 Kgs 22:26</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.8">2 Chr 34:8</a>). The writer of <a href="?bref=Ps.22.28">Psalm 22:28</a> used that title to describe God as the ruler of his people. A temple official who imprisoned the prophet Jeremiah in the stocks (<a href="?bref=Jer.20.1">Jer 20:1</a>) was described as a “governor” (<span class="sc">rsv</span> “officer”). One who governed an army probably commanded one or more military units. What appears to be a special title is rendered “governor” in <a href="?bref=Ezra.2.63">Ezra 2:63</a> and <a href="?bref=Neh.7.65">Nehemiah 7:65</a>.</p>
<p>Translation problems from the Greek are also numerous. Different levels and functions in leadership were obviously intended by the various words used. This is most clearly indicated by the use of such terms as <span class="greek">ethnarch</span> (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.14.47">1 Macc 14:47</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.32">2 Cor 11:32</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>), one who governed as a deputy of a king, and by another word referring to Roman provincial officials. Such governors were mentioned in NT writings (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.10.18">Mt 10:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.2">Lk 2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.1">3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.23.24">Acts 23:24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.14">1 Pt 2:14</a>) and were responsible for maintaining law and order in their assigned territory. In NT times Judea was under the control of the governor of Syria. Archaic uses of “governor” occasionally appear in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>. The “governor” mentioned in <a href="?bref=Jas.3.4">James 3:4</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) is the ship’s pilot.</p>
  </body>
</item>