<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GreeceGreek">
  <title>Greece, Greek</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GREECE, GREEK</p>
<p class="fl">The biblical references to Greece and the Greek people are often ambiguous. In the OT some references have been understood to mean Greece or the Greeks. Javan, the fourth son of Japheth in the “table of nations” (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.1-32">Gn 10</a>), seems to fit a Greek identification (<a href="?bref=1Chr.1.5,7">1 Chr 1:5, 7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.66.19">Is 66:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.13">Ez 27:13</a>). The name Greece occurs clearly in <a href="?bref=Dan.8.21">Daniel 8:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.10.20">10:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.11.2">11:2</a>; and <a href="?bref=Zech.9.13">Zechariah 9:13</a>, and Greeks are mentioned in <a href="?bref=Joel.3.6">Joel 3:6</a>. In the NT the term “Greek” appears to have the special sense of Hellenist, that is, Jews living in Hellenistic cities (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.1">Acts 6:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.29">9:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.20">11:20</a>). The term in <a href="?bref=John.12.20">John 12:20</a>, <a href="?bref=Acts.14.1">Acts 14:1</a>, and <a href="?bref=Acts.16.1-3">16:1-3</a> seems to refer to Greeks specifically. But often in the NT the term “Greek” was used for non-Jews because the Jews recognized only Jews and non-Jews. Hence the term was virtually synonymous with Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">Rom 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.10.12">10:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.22,24">1 Cor 1:22, 24</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.3">Gal 2:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.28">3:28</a>). Sometimes the term “Greek” refers to the language (<a href="?bref=John.19.20">Jn 19:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.21.37">Acts 21:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.9.11">Rv 9:11</a>). The use of the term “Greek” for the Syrophoenician woman (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.26">Mk 7:26</a>) may be a cultural term. In Acts, references are made to Greeks in the synagogues as observers. These may have been Greeks as such, although certainty is not possible (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.1">Acts 14:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.4">17:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.4">18:4</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Geography">Geography</p>
<p class="fl">The ancient Greek homeland comprised the southern end of the Balkan Peninsula. But at times Greek speakers were to be found in the islands of the Aegean Sea, western Asia Minor, south Italy, and Sicily.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheEmergenceofGreekCulture">The Emergence of Greek Culture</p>
<p class="fl">After the Persian Wars ended (497 <span class="era">BC</span>), Athens entered into a remarkable period of greatness. Athens was rebuilt and its port of Piraeus was fortified. When the Athenian citizens embarked on a course of unbridled democracy, chaos seemed to threaten, but Pericles, a brilliant leader, restored the equilibrium of the state and Athens soon regained her glory. Vast buildings were erected on the Acropolis, notably the Parthenon (dedicated to Athena, the goddess of Athens). Athens became wealthy, partly from the contributions to the Delian League. Athenian sea power grew. There were present in Athens an abundance of slaves, artisans, craftsmen, foreign traders, artists, poets, philosophers, teachers, actors, athletes, scientists, physicians, historians, religious teachers, and experts in military and naval affairs. The great writers of the fifth and early fourth centuries <span class="era">BC</span> included dramatists like Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euripedes, historians like Thucydides and Herodotus, and philosophers like Socrates, Plato, and Aristotle. There occurred a flowering of art and architecture. It was a golden age of spectacular achievement in art, thought, literature, and architecture.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientTheaterInDelphi"/>
<p class="h2" id="TheAgeofHellenism">The Age of Hellenism</p>
<p class="fl">The great glory of Athens withered before the fourth century <span class="era">BC</span> was over. Philip of Macedon, with ambitions of empire, drove west, and by 338 <span class="era">BC</span> Athens and Thebes were overwhelmed—Greece became united into a Macedonian Empire. Philip was assassinated in 366 <span class="era">BC</span>, but Alexander, his son, educated in the Athenian tradition, took up his father’s work and before his own death in 323 <span class="era">BC</span> had conquered Persia and reached to the Punjab in India. In the end he exerted his control from the Caucusus to the Libyan Desert and the borders of Ethiopia as well. On the death of Alexander, his vast territories were divided among four generals. After some adjustments three divisions emerged—Egypt under Ptolemy; Asia Minor, Syria, and the East under Seleucus; and Macedonia under Antigonus.</p>
<p>Finally the whole of the Greek area came under the control of the Romans, who moved into Greek areas in 198 <span class="era">BC</span> and over the years established a number of Roman provinces, such as Achaia (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.12">Acts 18:12</a>). It was into the world of Hellenism, now under Rome, that the Christians moved with the message of the gospel in the first century <span class="era">AD</span>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGreeksinPalestine">The Greeks in Palestine</p>
<p class="fl">Excavations have shown that there was contact between Palestine and the Aegean areas over many centuries. From the middle Bronze period (the patriarchal age), middle Minoan II pottery has been found at a number of sites. The Philistines, who formed part of the Sea Peoples in the 13th century <span class="era">BC</span>, settled in areas of coastal Palestine and developed their own culture there, leaving a great deal of their distinctive pottery. During the period around 1370–1200 <span class="era">BC</span>, various peoples from the Aegean and western Asia Minor found their way to Palestine. Mycenaean pottery has been found in a number of sites. From a later period still, numerous examples of Attic black-figure ware from the sixth century <span class="era">BC</span>, and Attic red-figure ware from the period around 530–300 <span class="era">BC</span>, have been found in excavations. Silver coins struck in imitation of Attic drachmas come from the same period. With the rise of Hellenism and the occupation of Palestine by the Ptolemaic and Seleucid rulers, Greek influence increased greatly. The presence of Greek pottery, like Rhodian jars, and the influence of Greek architectural features in buildings emphasize the significance of the Greek influence in Palestine as well as throughout the Levant region and the hinterland. With the coming of the Romans, these influences continued. Greek was the language of commerce. Indeed, the NT was written in the Greek of ordinary people, and a wide variety of Greek inscriptions has come to light from Roman times.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Alexander_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Alexander #1</a>; <a href="?item=Alexandria_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Alexandria</a>; <a href="?item=Hellenism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hellenism</a>; <a href="?item=Hellenists_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hellenists</a>; <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="EgnatianWay"/>
</body>
</item>