<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gymnasium">
  <title>Gymnasium*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GYMNASIUM*</p>
<p class="fl">Ancient Greek institution devoted to physical education and intellectual development. By the Hellenistic period, gymnasiums had become centers for the propagation of Greek culture. Students received not only physical training but intellectual and social training also. Gymnasiums were privately owned and organized for children of wealthy families. Attendance was mandatory for Greek youths who wanted to gain citizenship in a particular city.</p>
<p>While under the control of the Ptolemies, a Macedonian dynasty, the city of Jerusalem did not have a gymnasium. At the time of the Seleucids, a Syrian dynasty concerned to Hellenize their subjects, the high priest bribed the ruler, Antiochus IV, in order to receive permission to build a gymnasium in Jerusalem (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.1.13-15">1 Macc 1:13-15</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Macc.4.9">2 Macc 4:9</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg).</p>
<p>The activities and practices of the gymnasium were abhorrent to conservative Jews because Jewish children educated there began to think and dress according to Hellenistic norms. The Greek practice of participating in athletic events in the nude was particularly upsetting to devout Jews. Many youths were removing the sign of their circumcision to enter the games (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.1.13-15">1 Macc 1:13-15</a>).</p>
<p>Alexandrian Jews were not so opposed to the gymnasium as Jews in Jerusalem, but the Greek population there was disturbed by the attendance of non-Greeks such as Egyptians and Jews. Roman policy made the graduates of the gymnasium Greek citizens, enabling them to participate in local government.</p>
<p>The apostle Paul and most early Christians seemingly did not have the same resentment toward gymnasiums as did the Jews in Jerusalem. Paul often described the Christian life in the language of athletic events that took place there (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.24-27">1 Cor 9:24-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.2">Gal 2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.7">5:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.1.30">Phil 1:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.16">2:16</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>