<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Uncircumcision">
  <title>Uncircumcision*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">UNCIRCUMCISION*</p>
<p class="fl">Natural condition of the male, that is, with the foreskin covering his penis. Since the Jews, among many other peoples, surgically removed this as a sign of their covenant with God (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.9-14">Gn 17:9-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.12.48">Ex 12:48</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.12.3">Lv 12:3</a>), the term came to designate “non-Jew” or “Gentile” (Philistines, Greeks, and Romans did not circumcise, but Egyptians and many Semitic peoples did). By extension, it connoted “those outside the covenant.”</p>
<p>The term “uncircumcision” occurs 20 times in the NT, most of the time meaning simply “Gentile,” as opposed to Jew. Paul argues strongly against making such distinctions. For Paul, the attitude of one’s heart toward God is much more important than ritual law, which has nothing to do with his salvation (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.25-27">Rom 2:25-27</a>). Abraham became a believer and was justified by God while he was uncircumcised, so circumcision has nothing to do with his salvation (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.30">3:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.4.9-12">4:9-12</a>). Formerly, Gentiles were excluded from the people of God (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.11-12">Eph 2:11-12</a>), but now Jewish and gentile believers have become one in Christ (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.7">Gal 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.6">5:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.6.15">6:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.11">Col 3:11</a>). Paul refuses to give way to those demanding circumcision for full church membership.</p>
<p>In one passage (<a href="?bref=Col.2.8-15">Col 2:8-15</a>), Paul speaks of uncircumcision metaphorically, meaning a person’s unregenerate state. Here uncircumcision is equivalent to “the flesh” (meaning one’s evil impulse or natural state). As literal flesh is cut away in the rite of circumcision, so this “flesh” is cut away by Christ at the time of conversion, as symbolized in baptism. The baptized person is one purified from “uncleanness” as a circumcised Gentile is purified from previous uncircumcised uncleanness.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Circumcision_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Circumcision</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>