<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Uzziah">
  <title>Uzziah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">UZZIAH</p>
<p class="list">1. Judah’s king from around 792 to 740 <span class="era">BC</span> (cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.21-22">2 Kgs 14:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.1-7">15:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.26.1-23">2 Chr 26:1-23</a>), the son of King Amaziah and Jecoliah of Jerusalem. Uzziah is the name he is called in Chronicles, but in Kings he is known as Azariah. Azariah means “the Lord has helped”; the meaning of Uzziah is “my strength is the Lord.” Azariah may have been his given name and Uzziah a throne name taken upon his accession. He came to the throne at the age of 16, after the death of his father, who was assassinated in Lachish as a result of a conspiracy arising from his apostasy.</p>
<p class="list-text">Uzziah was a capable, energetic, and well-organized person, with many diverse interests. The Lord blessed him in all of his undertakings, so that he prospered. He is characterized as one who “did what was right in the eyes of the Lord” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.3">2 Kgs 15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.26.4">2 Chr 26:4</a>). He determined to seek God and went to Zechariah (not the postexilic prophet) for spiritual instruction. Consequently, “as long as he sought the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, God made him prosper” (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.5">2 Chr 26:5</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The prophets of the Lord were active during his reign. Isaiah, Hosea, and Amos began their prophetic work in the time of Uzziah (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.1">Is 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.1.1">Hos 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.1.1">Am 1:1</a>). Uzziah was also active with military campaigns. His primary success was against Israel’s strong historical enemy, the Philistines. He broke down the walls of Gath, Jabneh, and Ashdod and built his own cities in Philistia. He also built many fortifications, such as fortified towers in Jerusalem and in the wilderness. He defeated some Arabs and also the Meunites, and he brought the Ammonites under tribute (<a href="?bref=2Chr.27.5-8">2 Chr 27:5-8</a>). Uzziah had an army “fit for war,” which was drafted according to census and organized into divisions. There were 2,600 officers and 307,500 fighting men who could wage war with mighty power. The army was well outfitted, with weapons, such as spears, bows, and sling stones, and with defensive equipment, including shields, helmets, and coats of armor (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.14">2 Chr 26:14</a>). <a href="?bref=2Chr.26.15">Second Chronicles 26:15</a> describes a kind of catapult, which was to be stationed on the towers and at the corners of walls for defensive purposes. This type of weapon could hurl arrows or large stones. Through his achievements and especially his military power, he became famous.</p>
<p class="list-text">But Uzziah had a sad downfall. As <a href="?bref=Pr.16.18">Proverbs 16:18</a> says, pride goes before a fall. His pride became clearly evident when he presumed the function of a priest. When he entered the temple to offer incense on the altar of incense, he was confronted for his presumptuous behavior by Azariah the priest and 80 other priests. When Uzziah became angry, the Lord struck him with leprosy, so that he was forced to live in isolation and could not enter the temple. His son, Jotham, became acting head of state and then succeeded to the kingship at the time of Uzziah’s death. </p>
<p class="list">2. Kohathite Levite and forefather of Samuel (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.24">1 Chr 6:24</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Father of Jonathan, David’s treasurer (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.25">1 Chr 27:25</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. One of Harim’s five sons who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife during the postexilic period (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.21">Ezr 10:21</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Esd.9.21">1 Esd 9:21</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Descendant of Perez from Judah’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.4">Neh 11:4</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>