<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Elohim">
  <title>Elohim*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ELOHIM*</p>
<p class="fl">General name for God in the OT. The etymology of <span class="hebrew">Elohim</span> is uncertain, but it is generally agreed that it is based on a root that means “might” or “power.” The word is plural in form, but when applied to the true God, it is used in a singular sense and most frequently with verbal elements. The most common explanation for the plural form of <span class="hebrew">Elohim</span> as applied to God is that it is “plural of majesty,” that is, all the majesty of deity is encompassed by him.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Elohim</span> also occurs as a designation of deity in other languages, such as Assyrian and Ugaritic; it is used of other nations’ gods, thus demonstrating its more general sense. It seems to be used in a general sense in the OT, particularly the Pentateuch (the five books of Moses), denoting God’s transcendence and capacity as creator of the universe. It is thus somewhat different from the designation <span class="hebrew">Yahweh</span><span class="ital">,</span> which usually connotes God in his personal relationships to people.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Elohim</span> is used as a designation of Israel’s rulers and judges (<a href="?bref=Ps.82.1,6">Ps 82:1, 6</a>), perhaps denoting their function as God’s earthly representatives (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.6">Ex 21:6</a>). That meaning of the word was used by Christ (<a href="?bref=John.10.34-36">Jn 10:34-36</a>) in a defense against his detractors.</p>
<p>The word is also used of angelic beings (<a href="?bref=Ps.8.5">Ps 8:5</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.2.7">Heb 2:7</a>), and in the expression “sons of God” (<a href="?bref=Job.1.6">Jb 1:6</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=GodNamesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Names of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>