<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EphraimTribeof">
  <title>Ephraim, Tribe of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EPHRAIM, Tribe of</p>
<p class="fl">Tribe descended from the patriarch Joseph’s second son. Both Ephraim and his brother Manasseh were regarded as sons also by their grandfather Jacob and became his heirs.</p>
<p>Many Bible commentators think that in naming his son Ephraim (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.52">Gn 41:52</a>), Joseph was making a play on words based on a Hebrew root meaning “to be fruitful.” In support of this theory they note that the hill country later assigned to Ephraim’s tribe was one of the most fertile areas in Palestine, and at present is still planted with vines and fruit trees, such as olive, pomegranate, and carob. Prior to Israelite settlement, the area was wooded (<a href="?bref=Josh.17.18">Jos 17:18</a>). During the monarchy, wild animals still roamed there (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.24">2 Kgs 2:24</a>).</p>
<p>It is difficult to determine the exact limits of Ephraim’s territory, since it is often mentioned with Manasseh’s tribe. Ephraim was allotted land in the heart of Canaan, the Promised Land, between the Jordan River and the Mediterranean Sea. One half of Manasseh’s allotment formed Ephraim’s northern boundary (<a href="?bref=Josh.16.5-9">Jos 16:5-9</a>).</p>
<p>Ephraim became a great tribe, and its members often held prominent positions. The first census taken in the wilderness lists the total of Ephraimite soldiers as 40,500 (<a href="?bref=Num.1.33">Nm 1:33</a>). After the wilderness wanderings, the number of warriors dropped to 32,500 (<a href="?bref=Num.26.37">26:37</a>). In Israel’s encampment around the tabernacle, Ephraim was the leader of the western camp, supported by the tribes of Manasseh and Benjamin (<a href="?bref=Num.2.18-24">2:18-24</a>).</p>
<p>Joshua the son of Nun, one of the 12 spies, was descended from Ephraim (<a href="?bref=Num.13.8">Nm 13:8</a>, “Hoshea”). Under Joshua’s leadership, Ephraim and the other tribes conquered Canaan and received their promised inheritance (<a href="?bref=Josh.16.1-10">Jos 16</a>).</p>
<p>In the days of the judges, the Ephraimites felt slighted when they were not called upon to assist others in their battles. They quarreled with Gideon because of his belated invitation to help against the Midianites (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.1-6">Jgs 8:1-6</a>), as well as with Jephthah of Gilead, who defeated the Ammonites (<a href="?bref=Judg.12.1-6">12:1-6</a>). The judge Abdon came from Ephraim’s tribe (v <a href="?bref=Judg.12.13">13</a>). The idolatrous Micah (<a href="?bref=Judg.17.1">17:1</a>), as well as the prophet Samuel, lived in Ephraim (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.1">1 Sm 1:1</a>). The military and political importance of the Ephraimites is reflected in the Song of Deborah (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.14">Jgs 5:14</a>), an ancient biblical poem.</p>
<p>Judah was Ephraim’s main rival, and even under David, that animosity was evident (<a href="?bref=2Sam.18.1-33">2 Sm 18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.19.41-20.22">19:41–20:22</a>). Discontent in the north with Solomon’s rule (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.26-40">1 Kgs 11:26-40</a>), combined with a foolish decision by Rehoboam, Solomon’s son, brought about the division of the kingdom. The 10 northern tribes (Israel) were then ruled by Jeroboam I.</p>
<p>After the northern tribes seceded, the capitals of the northern kingdom—Shechem, Tirzah, and Samaria—were situated in Ephraim. The establishment of Samaria by King Omri of Israel gave the Ephraimites more direct access to the great north-south trunk road (Via Maris) through the western plain. This contact with trade routes gave the northern kingdom greater world consciousness and brought greater temptation to depart from God and his commands.</p>
<p>The prophets proclaimed that Ephraim and the other northern tribes would one day be reunited with the southern kingdom of Judah in the messianic kingdom (<a href="?bref=Hos.1.11">Hos 1:11</a>). The division introduced by Jeroboam I would be healed when a king descended from David would rule over Judah, Ephraim, and all the tribes of Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.1-28">Ez 37</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=EphraimPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ephraim (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=EphraimPlace_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ephraim (Place) #1</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>