<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Eshbaal">
  <title>Eshbaal</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ESHBAAL</p>
<p class="fl">King Saul’s fourth son, who became Israel’s king after his father’s death. Eshbaal literally means “man of Baal,” or “Baal exists” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.33">1 Chr 8:33</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.39">9:39</a>). During the period of the judges and the early monarchy, many Hebrew names were compounded with “baal,” a word that can mean “master” or “possessor.” Later generations were reluctant to speak the name “baal,” so “bosheth” (shame) was substituted (cf. <a href="?bref=Hos.2.16-17">Hos 2:16-17</a>). Thus, Eshbaal was altered to Ishbosheth (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.8">2 Sm 2:8</a>), which means “man of shame.” Perhaps later copyists changed the name in the book of Samuel because it was read aloud in synagogue services, whereas Chronicles was not.</p>
<p>After the death of Saul and his older sons, Abner, commander of Saul’s army, installed Ishbosheth as Israel’s king (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.8-9">2 Sm 2:8-9</a>). Judah’s tribe, however, followed King David, who struggled with Ishbosheth for leadership of all the tribes. The conflict lasted a long time, but the house of David gradually overwhelmed the house of Saul (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.1">3:1</a>). Abner deserted Ishbosheth and was murdered by Joab, one of David’s men (v <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.27">27</a>), thus removing an important leader of Israel and causing the people to despair (<a href="?bref=2Sam.4.1">4:1</a>). Soon afterward Ishbosheth was murdered by two of his captains (v <a href="?bref=2Sam.4.7">7</a>). Although David disapproved of the deaths of Abner and Ishbosheth, the last obstacles to his kingship over all the tribes had been removed.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=David_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">David</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=Saul_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Saul #2</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>