<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EternalLife">
  <title>Eternal Life</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ETERNAL LIFE</p>
<p class="fl">Mode of existence referred to in Scripture characterized by either timelessness or immortality; kind of life attributed to God and distributed to believers. The perspective of the biblical writers flowed from an understanding of a living God who existed prior to the world’s creation and who will continue to exist when the end of time arrives. God’s gift to those who are obedient and responsible to him is designated as “eternal life” or some such synonym. John’s Gospel provides the most definitive material on eternal life.</p>
<p>The phrase “eternal life” occurs only once in the Greek version of the OT (<a href="?bref=Dan.12.2">Dn 12:2</a>, with the basic meaning of “the life of the age,” designating the life of the age beyond the resurrection from the dead). The primary meaning of “life” in the OT, however, is the quality of well-being in earthly existence.</p>
<p>In the intertestamental period, the rabbinic distinction between “this age” and “the age which is to come” emphasized that the concept of life in the new age consists of a qualitative, rather than simply a quantitative, distinction from the present age.</p>
<p>The Greek word translated “eternal” is derived from the word for “age” or “eon.” The setting of the NT within the context of Judaism, with its concept of a living God and the consequent promise of “the age which is to come,” gives depth and color to the meaning of the adjective “eternal.” Jesus Christ’s coming as God’s definitive revelation brings the possibility of the qualities of life in the future messianic age into present reality.</p>
<p>The rich young ruler came to Jesus and asked for directions on how to inherit eternal life (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.17">Mk 10:17</a>). He was obviously thinking of resurrection in the age to come. Jesus answered in the same terms (v <a href="?bref=Mark.10.30">30</a>).</p>
<p>In his response to the rich young ruler, Jesus equated the reception of eternal life with entrance into the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.23-25">Mk 10:23-25</a>). The kingdom of God is not simply a future event but is already inaugurated in Jesus’ life, ministry, and teachings. The kingdom is a gift of life available while the follower still lives within the present age. Many of Jesus’ parables emphasize this point (e.g., those in <a href="?bref=Matt.13.1-58">Mt 13</a>). The Beatitudes in the Sermon on the Mount (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.3-12">5:3-12</a>) reinforce the concept of a present blessedness that includes salvation, forgiveness, and righteousness. Thus eternal life is a present blessing available to those who submit to God’s reign and are enjoying the blessing of this new era of salvation before the final consummation at the present age’s end.</p>
<p>The definitive discussion of eternal life comes from John’s Gospel. John’s purpose delineates the crucial significance of the concept: “But these are written that you may believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, and that believing you may have life in his name” (<a href="?bref=John.20.31">Jn 20:31</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The earliest Johannine reference to eternal life is found in <a href="?bref=John.3.15">John 3:15</a>.</p>
<p>John clearly shared in the Jewish expectation of the age to come with its anticipated blessings (e.g., <a href="?bref=John.3.36">Jn 3:36</a>; <a href="?bref=John.4.14">4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.5.29,39">5:29, 39</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.27">6:27</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.25">12:25</a>). Eternal life is defined by the special gifts of the messianic age when it arrives at consummation. Lazarus’s resurrection (ch <a href="?bref=John.11.1-57">11</a>) was a living parable demonstrating the future life available to those who trust in Christ. Martha, before her brother’s actual resurrection, asserted her belief that Lazarus would be raised on the last day (v <a href="?bref=John.11.24">24</a>). Jesus responded that he himself is the resurrection and the life, and that those who believe in him will never die, even if they die physically (vv <a href="?bref=John.11.25-26">25-26</a>).</p>
<p>The central emphasis of John’s Gospel, however, does not lie in the anticipated future but in the present experience of that future life. The life of the age to come is already available in Christ to the believer. The metaphors with which Jesus defined his own mission emphasize the present new life: living water that is a spring of water welling up to eternal life (<a href="?bref=John.4.10-14">Jn 4:10-14</a>); living bread that satisfies the world’s spiritual hunger (<a href="?bref=John.6.35-40">6:35-40</a>); the light of the world who leads his followers into the light of life (<a href="?bref=John.8.12">8:12</a>); the good shepherd who brings abundant life (<a href="?bref=John.10.10">10:10</a>); the life giver who raises the dead (<a href="?bref=John.11.25">11:25</a>); the way, the truth, and the life (<a href="?bref=John.14.6">14:6</a>); and the genuine vine who sustains those who abide in him (<a href="?bref=John.15.5">15:5</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus was very careful to note that the accomplishment of his mission did not rest in his own nature and ability but in the Father who sent him. Jesus’ submission to the Father highlights again the fact that life is a gift of God. Those who believe in the Son of God are recipients of the life that God alone gives—eternal life. Thus the promise of resurrection for all believers, made explicit in Lazarus’s resurrection and guaranteed in Christ’s resurrection as the “firstfruits” (in Pauline terminology, <span class="sc">kjv</span> <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.23">1 Cor 15:23</a>), is the natural consequence of God’s gift (<a href="?bref=John.5.26-29">Jn 5:26-29</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus added further content to the concept of eternal life by connecting it with knowing the true God (<a href="?bref=John.17.3">Jn 17:3</a>). In Greek thought, knowledge referred to the result of either contemplation or mystical ecstasy. In the OT, however, knowledge meant experience, relationship, fellowship, and concern (cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.31.34">Jer 31:34</a>). This connotation of knowledge as intimate relationship is underlined by the usage of the verb form to designate sexual relations between male and female (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.4.1">Gn 4:1</a>). Jesus stated, “I am the good shepherd; I know my own and my own know me, as the Father knows me and I know the Father” (<a href="?bref=John.10.14-15">Jn 10:14-15</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The intimate and mutual relationship of Father and Son is the model for the relationship of the Son and his disciples. This knowledge does not come by education or manipulation of the mind but by revelation through the Son (<a href="?bref=John.1.18">1:18</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=John.14.7">14:7</a>).</p>
<p>A brief survey of the primary elements in the concept of eternal life clearly shows that it is not simply an endless or everlasting life. Although there are no final boundaries to eternal life, the Bible’s primary emphasis is on the quality of life, especially its divine elements. Eternal life is the importation of the qualities of the age to come into the present through the revelation of a faithful God in Christ, and it brings knowledge of God’s relationship with him.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Life_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Life</a>; <a href="?item=NewCreationNewCreature_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New Creation, New Creature</a>; <a href="?item=Regeneration_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Regeneration</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>