<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ethiopia">
  <title>Ethiopia</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ETHIOPIA</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT, Ethiopia was generally referred to as Cush (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.6">Gn 10:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.8">1 Chr 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.11">Is 11:11</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>), which is a transliteration of the only Hebrew word used to describe the land lying to the south of Egypt. The Greek version, however, spoke of this territory as Ethiopia and kept the name Cush for the lists of peoples in <a href="?bref=Gen.10.6-8">Genesis 10:6-8</a> and <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.8-10">1 Chronicles 1:8-10</a>. English translations have generally followed the Greek, except in cases where Cushi appears as a personal name (<a href="?bref=2Sam.18.21-23,31-32">2 Sm 18:21-23, 31-32</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Location">Location</p>
<p class="fl">The Hebrew name <span class="hebrew">Cush</span> is actually an old Egyptian loanword that came into use in the early Middle Kingdom period. At that time it was used of a small area between the second and third cataracts of the Nile. Later on, in the New Kingdom period (c. 1570–1160 <span class="era">BC</span>), it was applied to a larger area that extended some distance to the south. This broader designation corresponds geographically to the modern lands of Nubia and northern Sudan. It is misleading to think that the Ethiopia of Scripture is the same territory as the Ethiopia of modern times, which in an earlier period was called Abyssinia. The name Ethiopia was of Greek origin, and according to some interpreters means “burnt-faced” (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.8.27">Acts 8:27</a>). This tradition has been perpetuated by the Arabic name Beled es Sudan, or “land of the blacks,” from which the designation Sudan comes.</p>
<p>The use of Cush by the OT writers seems to have paralleled the Egyptian geographical terminology in naming an arid land stretching south to Aswan, the Syene of <a href="?bref=Ezek.29.10">Ezekiel 29:10</a>. The borders of Ethiopia were never clearly defined, even by the Egyptians, so the territory may be regarded as extending to some indeterminate point in the Sudan beyond Meroé.</p>
<p>Ethiopia consisted predominantly of desert lying east of the Nile, and the topography of the region made travel hazardous. Even the river itself presented obstacles to navigation in the form of cataracts. Outcroppings of hard stone forced the Nile down narrow channels and produced rough water that swamped boats easily. Such forbidding natural obstacles protected Egypt against invasion from the south but also gave an inhospitable character to Ethiopia. Almost all the land suitable for farming in Egyptian Nubia and part of northern Sudan was inundated, and the Nubians were compelled to move below Aswan to Kom Ombo.</p>
<p>Since the area covered by Nubia is predominantly desert, it is hardly surprising that the rainfall is minimal, except for the upstream areas. The territory around Meroé, which was the capital during the Meroitic period, experiences seasonal rains; an area bordered on the west and north by the Nile and the Atbara, the so-called “island of Meroé,” was apparently quite fertile in antiquity and may have been heavily forested.</p>
<p class="h2" id="BiblicalReferences">Biblical References</p>
<p class="fl">In <a href="?bref=Esth.1.1">Esther 1:1</a> and <a href="?bref=Esth.8.9">8:9</a>, Ethiopia is described as the most distant southwesterly province in the Persian Empire. Its “rivers” were presumably the Nile and the Atbara (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.18.1">Is 18:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.10">Zep 3:10</a>). The products of Cush were referred to in <a href="?bref=Job.28.19">Job 28:19</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.45.14">Isaiah 45:14</a>, which according to Egyptian lists included semiprecious stones, animals, and agricultural products. Some prophets expected exiled Jews in Ethiopia to return (<a href="?bref=Ps.87.4">Ps 87:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.11">Is 11:11</a>), while others foresaw divine judgment coming upon the land (<a href="?bref=Isa.20.3">Is 20:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.30.4">Ez 30:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.12">Zep 2:12</a>). But since Cush was under God’s sovereignty, it could hope for divine blessing as well as punishment—hence, the expectation in <a href="?bref=Ps.68.31">Psalm 68:31</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.45.14">Isaiah 45:14</a>, and <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.10">Zephaniah 3:10</a> that its peoples would be converted to the Hebrew faith. The Ethiopia of <a href="?bref=Acts.8.27">Acts 8:27</a> was the kingdom of Candace (“queen”), who ruled from Meroé, where the capital of Cush had been moved about 300 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CushPlace_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cush (Place)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>