<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Evangelist">
  <title>Evangelist</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EVANGELIST</p>
<p class="fl">NT term referring to one who proclaims the gospel of Jesus Christ. There are only three occurrences of the word in the NT. The apostle Paul exhorted the Ephesian church to walk worthy of their calling (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.1-12">Eph 4:1-12</a>). The exhortation stressed the gifts given to each within the unity of the Spirit. Paul explained that the ascended Christ has given “some as apostles, and some as prophets, and some as evangelists, and some as pastors and teachers” (v <a href="?bref=Eph.4.11">11</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>). Paul was saying that Christ calls persons to these ministries and gives them to the church. The evangelist is one of Christ’s gifts to the church. The meaning of the term indicates that the task of such a person is to function as a spokesperson for the church in proclaiming the gospel to the world. An evangelist is similar to an apostle in function, except that being an apostle involved a personal relationship to Jesus during his earthly ministry (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.21-22">Acts 1:21-22</a>). The evangelist stands in contrast to the pastor/teacher. The former makes the initial proclamation, and the latter provides continuing follow-up ministry that develops maturity in the believer. The reference to Philip the evangelist (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.8">21:8</a>) supports the idea of evangelism as a gifted ministry to which Christ calls some in the church.</p>
<p>More than one gift or ministry may be performed by the same person. Paul charged Timothy with his responsibilities as a pastor and teacher, and also exhorted him to “do the work of an evangelist” (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.5">2 Tm 4:5</a>). Therefore, “evangelist” can refer to a person called to that distinct ministry, and also to a function that may be performed by others.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=SpiritualGifts_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Spiritual Gifts</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>