<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EzekielBookof">
  <title>Ezekiel, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EZEKIEL, Book of</p>
<p class="fl">Prophetic book of the OT, originating in the time of the Babylonian exile.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DateandBackground">Date and Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">Ezekiel was the son of Buzi (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.3">1:3</a>), a member of a priestly family. It is unclear whether he actually served in the temple as a priest, but such was his training. His writings show that he knew the regulations for sacrifices, the rituals, and the people’s expectations of a priest. In exile Ezekiel the priest spoke God’s word about the future of the temple to his fellow exiles. Settled at Tel-abib, on the canal of Kebar, the thousands of deportees eked out a meager existence. They hoped for a speedy return to Judah and a change for the better in the international situation. Their hope was enflamed by the spirited preaching of false prophets, likened to jackals among the ruins (<a href="?bref=Ezek.13.4">13:4</a>). They piously said, “The Lord declares . . . ,” but they were actually self-commissioned (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.13.6">6</a>). They deceived the people with a message of peace at a time when God’s judgment was about to be poured out on his people (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.13.10">10</a>). They had led the people to distrust prophecy to such an extent that a proverb circulated among the people that “the days grow long, and every vision comes to nought” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.12.22">12:22</a>). Much time had passed since visions of God’s judgment had been given to the people, and nothing could be interpreted as a fulfillment of those visions. Ezekiel was called to serve his community by symbolic acts, visions, and verbal messages in order to convince the people that God’s judgment was imminent (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.12.23">23</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="DateandBackground">Date and Background</p>
<p class="fl">The ministry of the prophet Ezekiel can be understood best against the backdrop of his time. If, as the church father Origen believed, the vague reference “in the thirtieth year” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1">1:1</a>) marks the prophet’s age at the time of his first vision, Ezekiel was born during the rule of King Josiah of Judah (c. 640–609 <span class="era">BC</span>). Josiah was the grandson of King Manasseh, whose sacrilegious acts had brought God’s judgment on the kingdom of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.10-15">2 Kgs 21:10-15</a>).</p>
<p>Though Judah’s political situation was perilous, Josiah led the nation in a radical reformation that began with the finding of the “Book of the Law” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.1-20">2 Kgs 22</a>) in the year that Ezekiel was born (c. 621 <span class="era">BC</span>). Idolatry was done away with and the people turned back to God, but God’s judgment on Judah was unchangeable (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.26-27">23:26-27</a>). Josiah erred in trying to make Judah a kingdom with which other states had to reckon. He was threatened when the Egyptian pharaoh Neco passed through Judah on his way to aid the weakened Assyrian kingdom. Josiah marched to meet the Egyptian forces, but his troops were unable to stand against the Egyptians, and he died in battle (v <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.29">29</a>). Egypt took control of Judah, and Pharaoh Neco placed Jehoiakim in power over Jerusalem. Egyptian control did not last long, however, for in 605 <span class="era">BC</span> Egypt and Assyria were defeated by Babylonia’s king Nebuchadnezzar at Carchemish. The Babylonians then pushed south to Jerusalem, and the first deportation of Judean leaders (among them the prophet Daniel) took place.</p>
<p>Jehoiakim was permitted to continue ruling over Judah as a vassal king of Nebuchadnezzar. But his dealings with Egypt brought the emperor’s wrath down upon him. Before the Babylonians could address the Judean situation, Jehoiakim died and his son Jehoiachin was crowned. When the Babylonian forces arrived at the gates of Jerusalem, Jehoiachin and thousands of the aristocracy were taken to Babylon (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.10-17">2 Kgs 24:10-17</a>). Among those deportees was Ezekiel, then about 25 years old.</p>
<p>Although the book says otherwise, many scholars think that Ezekiel lived and taught in Judah for the duration of the siege and the fall of Jerusalem (586 <span class="era">BC</span>). They conclude this from Ezekiel’s familiarity with idolatry in the temple and his vivid descriptions of Jerusalem’s last days (<a href="?bref=Ezek.8.11">Ez 8:11</a>). Others believe that Ezekiel ministered both to the exiled community and to the Judeans living in Judah. Neither interpretation does full justice to the claims of the book itself. Ezekiel was exiled in 597 <span class="era">BC</span>. He was called to bring God’s word to the deportees at Tel-abib; he was granted a vision of the horrible practices in the temple court; and he was familiar with Jerusalem and Judah from having lived there and from reports on affairs in Jerusalem coming to the exiles through messengers. Jeremiah, Ezekiel’s contemporary, was prophesying in Jerusalem, but there is no evidence that Jeremiah and Ezekiel knew of each other’s ministry. If Ezekiel had brought God’s word to Jerusalem during the siege, some reference to Jeremiah might appear in his writings. If Jeremiah was supported by Ezekiel’s ministry in Jerusalem, he probably would have included a positive word for his colleague in his book. The book of Ezekiel plainly says that Ezekiel lived and preached in exile (see <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-3">1:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.24-25">11:24-25</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="fl">The prophecy of Ezekiel is easily outlined by subject matter and chronology. The chronology of the period permits a division before and after 586 <span class="era">BC</span> (the fall of Jerusalem). Chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-24.27">1–24</a> cover the pre-586 ministry of Ezekiel, whereas chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.1-48.35">33–48</a> represent his post-586 ministry. Chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.25.1-32.32">25–32</a> (oracles against the foreign nations) function as a transition between the book’s two major divisions.</p>
<p>The book’s outline according to subject matter divides into four parts: Ezekiel’s call (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-3.21">1:1–3:21</a>); prophecies of judgment against Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.3.22-24.27">3:22–24:27</a>); oracles against the nations (<a href="?bref=Ezek.25.1-32.32">25:1–32:32</a>); and proclamation of hope (<a href="?bref=Ezek.33.1-48.35">33:1–48:35</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Ezekiel’s Call (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-3.21">1:1–3:21</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The prophet’s call in one sense was similar to that of Isaiah and Jeremiah. Isaiah received his mission in a vision of God’s glory in the temple (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-13">Is 6</a>). Jeremiah was called unexpectedly in his youth, and received signs that solemnly set forth the nature of his mission (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.11-15">Jer 1:11-15</a>). The call of Ezekiel combined those two elements. Revelation of God’s glory to the prophet at the same time revealed the nature of the prophet’s mission. Ezekiel’s call contained a full description of God’s glory. Isaiah briefly stated that he saw the Lord enthroned in the temple, and he concentrated on the seraphim representing and magnifying God’s glory. Ezekiel elaborated on the revelation of the Lord’s glory as well as on the ministering angels who went before the Lord as part of his royal entourage. The vision of God’s glory, though difficult to understand, is the key to the book of Ezekiel.</p>
<p>Ezekiel, as a priest, was concerned about the future of the temple. That sacred place had been ordained by God as his home among his people. The glory, presence, and holiness of God were symbolized in the temple (see <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.10-11">1 Kgs 8:10-11</a>). In exile Ezekiel could not serve his people as a priest, for they were far from Jerusalem, the city God had chosen. Against all expectations the Lord revealed himself to Ezekiel in the land of Babylon. In calling Ezekiel to a prophetic ministry, God assured his servant that he had not forsaken his people, even though they had been banished from the Promised Land.</p>
<p>The prophet’s vision began with a storm. As a large cloud approached from the north, Ezekiel saw a brightness surrounding the cloud, four creatures, and four wheels. The combination of creatures and wheels suggests that the Lord appeared in a chariot. God’s chariot is a familiar OT representation of his coming in judgment (see <a href="?bref=Isa.66.15-16">Is 66:15-16</a>). The wheels within wheels and the position of the four living creatures may signify God’s total control over the whole earth, so he could move his “chariot of judgment” in any direction. It is also possible that the living creatures with their four faces, and the wheels full of eyes, may be separate symbols showing that God sees all that happens and thereby knows the plight of the exiles. In the vision the prophet’s attention was drawn to a throne above the heads of the creatures. On the throne was “the appearance of the likeness of the glory of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.28">1:28</a>). In his vision of God’s coming in judgment, Ezekiel received his call to the prophetic ministry: “Son of man, I send you to the people of Israel, to a nation of rebels who have rebelled against me” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.2.3">2:3</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). During a dark hour of Israel’s history, Ezekiel had to prophesy, rebuke his fellow exiles (<a href="?bref=Ezek.3.11">3:11</a>), and be responsible as a watchman over the house of Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.3.17">3:17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.1-9">33:1-9</a>). Symbolic of his mission was a scroll filled with lamentations and woe (<a href="?bref=Ezek.2.9-10">2:9-10</a>), which when eaten became sweet as honey (<a href="?bref=Ezek.3.1-3">3:1-3</a>). Difficult as the mission was, God’s presence and the certain fulfillment of the prophecies sweetened Ezekiel’s task. Such encouragement was intended to take away any fear of the rebellious Israelites (<a href="?bref=Ezek.2.6-7">2:6-7</a>). Instead of being elated with his mission, however, Ezekiel became despondent.</p>
<p>A week later, the word of the Lord came to Ezekiel to remind him of his important role as a watchman (<a href="?bref=Ezek.3.16-17">3:16-17</a>). Ezekiel became responsible for Israel as a nation, not just for individuals. His witness to Israel had the express aim of national repentance (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.3.18-19">18-19</a>).</p>
<p>Ezekiel was confined to his house by God (<a href="?bref=Ezek.3.24-25">3:24-25</a>). The house ministry was to be carried on only with those Israelites who sought God’s will, for the Lord had abandoned those who continued in their apostasy. The prophetic word would not help the apostates (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.3.26">26</a>). The principle of Ezekiel’s ministry is found in <a href="?bref=Ezek.3.27">3:27</a>: “Whenever I give you a message, I will loosen your tongue and let you speak. Then you will say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> says!’ Some of them will listen, but some will ignore you, for they are rebels” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.11.15">Mt 11:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.13.43">13:43</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Prophecies of Judgment against Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.3.22-24.27">3:22–24:27</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Symbolism figures prominently in Ezekiel’s writing. His priestly background and preparation probably suited him to receive and communicate God’s word in symbolic acts and speech. Chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.4.1-17">4</a> and <a href="?bref=Ezek.5.1-17">5</a> contain four symbolic acts: (1) Jerusalem’s siege is portrayed on a brick (<a href="?bref=Ezek.4.1-3">Ez 4:1-3</a>); (2) Israel’s iniquity is represented by Ezekiel’s lying on his sides (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.4.4-8">4-8</a>); (3) Jerusalem’s grief and horror in the last days of the siege are represented by Ezekiel’s food and drink (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.4.9-17">9-17</a>); (4) Jerusalem’s fate is represented by the prophet’s hair being cut off (<a href="?bref=Ezek.5.1-4">5:1-4</a>).</p>
<p>Ezekiel’s instructions were further illuminated by God’s explanation of Israel’s apostasy (<a href="?bref=Ezek.5.6-7">5:6-7</a>) and his judgment on Israel (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.5.8-12">8-12</a>). The judgment will last until the Israelites admit that in covenant faithfulness their Lord has inflicted righteous judgment on them (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.5.13">13</a>).</p>
<p>God would direct his judgment first against the people and the city of Jerusalem. Next in line were the mountains of Israel (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.6.1-14">6</a>) and the land (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.7.1-27">7</a>). God’s wrath included the cities and cultic sites in the hill country of Judah, leaving no protection for the people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.6.3-6">6:3-6</a>). Abominations that were practiced throughout the land caused God’s judgment to fall on the land as well as on the people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.7.2-3,10-11,23">7:2-3, 10-11, 23</a>). But because God is righteous, he judged the people according to their ways of life, desiring that they would once more acknowledge him as their God (<a href="?bref=Ezek.7.27">7:27</a>).</p>
<p>The prophet then (chs <a href="?bref=Ezek.8.1-11.25">8–11</a>) focused on the abominations practiced in Jerusalem, particularly idolatry in the temple courts, which caused the judgment announced in chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-7.27">1–7</a>. An idol had been erected in the inner court (<a href="?bref=Ezek.8.3-5">8:3-5</a>). By the wall of the court, elders of the city were paying homage to the idols that surrounded the court (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.8.11-12">11-12</a>). Closer to the temple, women were weeping for the god Tammuz (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.8.14">14</a>), and men were worshiping the sun (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.8.16">16</a>). In preparation for the ultimate judgment on the land, the prophet placed a mark on the foreheads of the few faithful Israelites so that they would survive (<a href="?bref=Ezek.9.4-6">9:4-6</a>). Then (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.1-22">10</a>), the glory of God, which had filled the temple from the time of Solomon, gradually left: “Then the glory of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> went up from the city and stopped above the mountain to the east” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.11.23">11:23</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The people, now without divine protection, were being handed over to the Babylonians (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.9">9</a>).</p>
<p>The message of doom for Jerusalem contains four elements of hope: restoration of the people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.11.17">11:17</a>), restoration of the land (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.17">17</a>), purification of the people (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.18">18</a>), and renewed fellowship between God and his people (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.19-20">19-20</a>). The prophet develops those four themes in chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.1-48.35">33–48</a>.</p>
<p>The visions of chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.1-22">10</a> and <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.1-25">11</a> made clear that when God removed his presence from Jerusalem, the exile was approaching. Those who were already in Babylon were unwilling to believe that such an extensive devastation of Jerusalem would happen or that the people would all be exiled and the land become desolate.</p>
<p>Ezekiel acted out the certainty of God’s word of judgment by packing his bags and showing the baggage to his fellow exiles. First, he placed the bags in the courtyard outside his modest home. Next, he went out by making a hole through the wall. Finally, the prophet walked about the settlement with his bags in full view. Skeptical observers did not understand Ezekiel and probably thought he was crazy. The believers who saw him understood. His strange actions dramatized how the king’s aides would do all they could to help King Zedekiah escape just before the fall of Jerusalem. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.1-30">Second Kings 25</a> tells how the king and his soldiers left Jerusalem for the wilderness, to be overtaken by the Babylonians at Jericho and brought before Nebuchadnezzar at Riblah. As a captive, Zedekiah witnessed the murder of his sons; then his eyes were put out, and he was sent into exile with the other Judeans (cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.12.13">Ez 12:13</a>). The prophet’s explanation concluded with a word of comfort. Because of his covenant with Abraham, God promised not to destroy the people completely. A remnant who overcame the sword, famine, and pestilence would live to tell the story of God’s judgment (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.12.15-16">15-16</a>).</p>
<p>Ezekiel further illustrated the nation’s plight by eating as though full of fear, depicting the great trauma that all of Judah’s inhabitants would soon undergo.</p>
<p>Both symbolic acts, packing his belongings and eating, emphasized the truthfulness of God’s word. The people needed to face the nature of their God: He is magnificent, and when he speaks, his words are powerful and come to pass. Thus, the devastation of the land and the people’s exile were a fulfillment of God’s word through the prophets. The judgment was meant to produce a recognition of the Lord, repentance, and a return to God. Some in Judah doubted the efficacy of God’s prophecies, saying, “Time passes, making a liar of every prophet” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.12.22">12:22</a>). Others thought God’s word would come true in the distant future (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.12.27">27</a>). The prevailing attitude of distrust in God’s word had been stimulated by the popular preaching of false prophets (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.13.1-23">13</a>). Never commissioned by the Lord, they deceived God’s people by lying and misdirecting them with messages of peace (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.13.8-10">8-10</a>). Wickedness, lying, and deceit were encouraged among the people by such false prophets (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.13.22">22</a>). The magnitude of their sin and their great responsibility for Judah’s fall would be matched by the Lord’s heavy judgment. Yet God would save his people from such evil and will prepare a righteous nation with whom to maintain his covenant (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.13.23">23</a>).</p>
<p>The certainty of the judgment has been connected with the truthfulness of God’s word. Ezekiel’s difficult task of affirming the doom of Jerusalem to stubborn hearers was intensified by the people’s idolatry. Their whole way of life denied the existence of God. They practiced idolatry in their worship, and they had set up idols in their hearts (<a href="?bref=Ezek.14.3">14:3</a>). Before the covenant with God could be restored, they had to be purified from their idolatry. Even so, repentance would not guarantee immunity from judgment. Sword, famine, wild beasts, and plagues would ravage the population (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.14.21">21</a>). After the execution of his judgment, God would take back those survivors who had turned to him for mercy. God would surely accomplish all that he intended for his people’s good (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.14.23">23</a>).</p>
<p>In chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.15.1-17.24">15–17</a> Ezekiel uses three parables to set forth the apostasy, present uselessness, and judgment of Israel. Jerusalem and Judah are compared to a piece of charred wood, an adulterous woman, and a vine.</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Ezek.15.1-8">15</a> reviews Jerusalem’s case. Jerusalem is compared to a piece of wood, both ends of which have been charred with fire, so that the wood is of no value. As the whole piece of wood is burned instead of being saved, so Jerusalem would undergo complete devastation (<a href="?bref=Ezek.15.7-8">15:7-8</a>).</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.1-63">16</a> presents God’s case against Jerusalem from a different perspective, stressing his care for Jerusalem in the past. The beginnings of her history are compared to the birth of a female child, left abandoned by her mother (<a href="?bref=Ezek.16.3-5">16:3-5</a>). God adopted the child and washed and clothed her (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.6-7">6-7</a>). He made a covenant with her (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.8">8</a>), making her his own possession. He generously gave her all the fine things of life (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.9-13">9-13</a>). In the height of her development, Jerusalem’s fame spread to the nations (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.14">14</a>). Her self-reliance made her a spiritual prostitute as she took up the religious practices and way of life of the nations (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.15-34">15-34</a>). The cities of Sodom (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.1-38">Gn 19</a>) and Samaria (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.6">2 Kgs 17:6</a>), known for their immorality, are called Jerusalem’s sisters (<a href="?bref=Ezek.16.46">Ez 16:46</a>). They had been judged by God, but the corruption of those cities was little compared to the lewdness of Jerusalem (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.48-51">48-51</a>). Thus, Jerusalem also would surely fall and become desolate. Yet Ezekiel anticipates the judgment’s final outcome; Jerusalem will be restored to covenantal blessing (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.62-63">62-63</a>) after her repentance.</p>
<p>The third parable (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.17.1-24">17</a>) focuses on God’s sovereignty over political developments. Assyria was no longer a power to be reckoned with. Babylon and Egypt both exercised dominion, although the balance of power was veering in favor of Babylon. Their extension of power is likened to an eagle. Nebuchadnezzar, pictured as “a great eagle with broad wings full of many-colored feathers,” took control over the affairs of Judah by removing Jehoiachin, “the highest branch of a cedar tree,” from office and by exiling him with young leaders of the Judean state (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.3-4">17:3-4</a>). Ezekiel was among them. Nebuchadnezzar let the Judeans control their own affairs under Zedekiah but expected them to be subject to Babylon and not to any other power. But Judah (likened to a vine) tried to ally itself with Pharaoh Hophra of Egypt, “another great eagle with broad wings and full plumage” (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.17.7">7</a>), against Nebuchadnezzar. Zedekiah’s folly in turning to Egypt would cause Nebuchadnezzar to pull up the vine by its roots and make it wither (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.17.9-10">9-10</a>). In explaining the parable, God told the exiles that Judah’s fall was a result of its unfaithfulness to King Nebuchadnezzar, to whom Judah owed allegiance by covenant (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.17.13-18">13-18</a>). Judah’s unfaithfulness thus extended to all of its relationships: religious, cultural, and political. After the exile, God promised, he would restore his people to their land under a Messiah, “a tender shoot” (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.17.22">22</a>). The messianic rule is signified by the young twig, which when planted in the land will become a magnificent cedar, giving shade and protection to the birds. Chapter <a href="?bref=Ezek.17.1-24">17</a> is an inspiring affirmation of the sovereignty of God in human affairs (“All the trees will know that it is I, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, who cuts down the tall tree and helps the short tree to grow tall. It is I who makes the green tree wither and gives new life to the dead tree”—<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.24">17:24</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.18.1-22.31">18–22</a> contain Ezekiel’s oracles to Judah, its leaders, and the exiles. First, he enunciates God’s standard of righteousness: “The person who sins will be the one who dies” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.18.4">18:4</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The people are charging God with injustice, for they believe themselves to be under God’s judgment for the sins of their ancestors (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.18.25-29">25-29</a>). Although the Ten Commandments do say that God may punish “the sins of their parents to the third and the fourth generations” (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.5">Ex 20:5</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>), the prophet vindicates God’s justice, telling the people that they are not being punished merely for their ancestors’ sin. Each person must be directly accountable to God; the sinner will die in wickedness, and the righteous will live by righteousness. A life of faithfulness to God’s moral and civil law will be rewarded (<a href="?bref=Ezek.18.5-9">Ez 18:5-9</a>). Even if one’s father was a sinner, the father’s sin is not transferable (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.18.14-18">14-18</a>). God is ready to forgive any sinner who repents (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.18.27">27</a>). The prophet’s vindication of God’s justice becomes a call to repentance. The sinners in Judah and in exile were thus warned of the consequences of their evil, and were exhorted to return to their God and his standard of right and wrong (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.18.31-32">31-32</a>).</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Ezek.19.1-14">19</a> contains two parables in the form of a lamentation. The first portrays a lioness and her two cubs. The lioness is Hamutal, the wife of King Josiah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.31">2 Kgs 23:31</a>), who bore two sons: Jehoahaz and Zedekiah. Jehoahaz is referred to in <a href="?bref=Ezek.19.3-4">Ezekiel 19:3-4</a> as a cub who grew up and was taken to Egypt (by Pharaoh Neco in 608 <span class="era">BC</span>; see <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.31-34">2 Kgs 23:31-34</a>). Zedekiah succeeded to the throne ten years later. In the lamentation the prophet imaginatively represents Zedekiah as a young cub who is ultimately taken to Babylon as a rebellious ruler (<a href="?bref=Ezek.19.7-9">Ez 19:7-9</a>). The second parable changes the imagery to a vine, representing Israel (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.19.10">10</a>). In its early days God blessed Israel with strong rulers, but now the vine was wilting as Zedekiah irresponsibly led Judah to its last days. Ezekiel’s lamentation stresses the lack of a good candidate for the throne and the lack of life in the vine (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.19.13-14">13-14</a>).</p>
<p>In chapter <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.1-49">20</a> the prophet concludes God’s argument against his people. He reviews the history of Israel’s past, starting with God’s self-revelation in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Ezek.20.5-6">20:5-6</a>). He took to himself a stubborn nation, tied to idolatry (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.8">8</a>) and prone to apostasy (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.13,21">13, 21</a>). Israel wanted to be one of the great nations (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.32">32</a>) instead of a sanctified people (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.12">12</a>). As a result of its spiritual hardness, Israel is dispersed to live among the nations (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.35">35</a>). Yet God had a solemn covenant with Israel, made by oath to the patriarchs Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. On the basis of that covenant, God will reach out with compassion to those who repent of their sinful ways (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.37-44">37-44</a>). In Israel’s judgment and restoration the nations will see the holiness of God, which does not tolerate unfaithfulness in Israel (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.41">41</a>).</p>
<p>Ezekiel’s prophecies alternate between God’s judgment on Israel’s sin and his restoration of Israel, spanning the bridge between Israel’s past and future. In view of the people’s doubts of the coming judgment on Jerusalem, he stresses the necessity of judgment and the need for repentance. Still, the future restoration of a remnant is touched upon here and there as the counterpart of his message of judgment. After announcing the fall of Jerusalem, the prophet shifts from a message of judgment to one of hope.</p>
<p>The prophet returns to the proclamation of judgment in four oracles (<a href="?bref=Ezek.20.45-21.32">20:45–21:32</a>). He speaks against the Negev Desert area (<a href="?bref=Ezek.20.45-49">20:45-49</a>), Jerusalem and the land of Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.21.2-17,20-27">21:2-17, 20-27</a>), and against the Ammonites (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.21.28-32">28-32</a>). God permitted the sword of Nebuchadnezzar to be his instrument of judgment upon the Judeans (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.21.19">19</a>). He would see to the judgment on the Ammonites. The Judeans would recover their previous glory, but the memory of the Ammonites would perish (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.21.27,32">27, 32</a>). The oracle against the Ammonites anticipates a larger treatise on Israel’s other neighbors: Moab, Edom, Philistia, Tyre, Sidon, and Egypt (chs <a href="?bref=Ezek.25.1-29.21">25–29</a>).</p>
<p>Chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.22.1-24.27">22–24</a> contain a renewed series of indictments against Jerusalem. Jerusalem’s religious and civil leadership (the prophets, priests, and princes) are corrupt, and the people have followed their example (<a href="?bref=Ezek.22.25-30">22:25-30</a>). The parable of the two sisters, Oholah and Oholibah, is a variation of the parable of adulterous Jerusalem (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.23.1-49">23</a>; cf. ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.1-63">16</a>). It differs in that the comparison drawn between Jerusalem, soon to be exiled, and Samaria, already in exile, is more explicit in the parable of Oholah and Oholibah. In chapter <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.1-63">16</a> Jerusalem was charged with greater sins than Sodom and Samaria, but was promised restoration. Only the adulterous nature of the two sisters and God’s judgment on them is emphasized in chapter <a href="?bref=Ezek.23.1-49">23</a>, with no word of restoration. This parable is a fitting introduction to that of the boiling pot (ch <a href="?bref=Ezek.24.1-27">24</a>), in which Jerusalem is compared to a rusty pot boiling with water. The Jerusalemites, likened to pieces of meat in the boiling pot, will die in the city. The parable was pronounced on the starting day of Nebuchadnezzar’s siege of Jerusalem. Thus, the exiles were divinely forewarned of God’s intent to destroy the temple (<a href="?bref=Ezek.24.21">24:21</a>) and were prepared for messengers bringing the bad news of Jerusalem’s fall.</p>
<p>Those oracles and parables conclude the first division of the book. Ezekiel has stated God’s case against the rebellious house of Judah in many ways. His metaphors have likened Judah to a burnt piece of wood, to an uprooted vine, to a baby who grew up to be an adulteress, and to Oholibah, the adulterous woman. He has countered arguments against the fulfillment of God’s word and against the justice of God. He has reassured the exiles that God will not leave the righteous and that the future of Israel begins with a righteous remnant. The pendulum of Ezekiel’s writing has swung from judgment to restoration, while the clock was bringing Judah closer to the hour of its fall.</p>
<p class="h3">Oracles against the Nations (<a href="?bref=Ezek.25.1-32.32">25:1–32:32</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Ammon, Moab, and Edom were Israel’s neighbors to the east. Because they were ethnically related to Israel, they were not attacked by the Israelites on their march to the Promised Land. Ammon and Moab were descendants of Lot, Abraham’s nephew, and the Edomites descended from Esau, the brother of Jacob. Although God forbade war with them, relations between Israel and its eastern neighbors were always tense. Israel had been overrun by the Ammonites for a time, and Israel was never successful in controlling the Edomites’ competitive trade relations. Those neighboring nations joined the Babylonian attack against Jerusalem and rejoiced when Jerusalem fell and the temple was devastated (<a href="?bref=Ezek.25.3-12">Ez 25:3-12</a>). They were ready to take over and loot Judah’s cities, and to instigate trouble in a time when Jerusalem was distressed. Therefore, says Ezekiel, God’s judgment will also extend to Ammon, Moab, and Edom (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.25.4-14">4-14</a>).</p>
<p>The Philistines had been Israel’s enemy to the southwest. During the period of the judges and the united monarchy, the Philistines had controlled much of Israel’s territory. King David successfully limited the Philistine threat by confining them to their own territory. But in Ezekiel’s day they were still considered Israel’s “everlasting” enemy (<a href="?bref=Ezek.25.15">25:15</a>), possibly intensified by Philistine support of the Babylonian invasion of Judah.</p>
<p>The city of Tyre had received reports of the overthrow of Jerusalem and was ready to exploit the opportunity for its own advantage (<a href="?bref=Ezek.26.2">26:2</a>). Tyre’s trade position was unrivaled; its ships crossed the seas to exchange goods with many distant lands (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.1-36">Ez 27</a>). But Tyre would soon be broken by the Babylonians, its wealth dried up with the destruction of the fleet and the murder of its sailors (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.26">27:26</a>).</p>
<p>The prince of Tyre is singled out in chapter <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.1-26">28</a>, but verse <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.12">12</a> refers to the “king” of Tyre. Interpreters disagree whether they are one person or two. Those who distinguish between the two understand the prince of Tyre to be the ruler of that city, but they consider the “king” of Tyre to represent Satan (<a href="?bref=Ezek.28.13-15">28:13-15</a>). The Garden of Eden with all its splendor is an appropriate setting for the original glory of an angelic Satan before his fall. But there is no reason within the context to distinguish between the prince and the king of Tyre. Each is said to have exalted himself, and both took authority over men as if they were gods and enjoyed all the splendor and royalty that belong to God. And both prince and king fall from their high position. The passage is a magnificent example of Ezekiel’s literary ability. He draws a glorious picture of the Garden of Eden, reworking the same theme as he depicts the glory and fall of the king of Tyre. Ezekiel presents him as a cherub, in accordance with the local belief that the king was divine. He wore the finest clothing, with nine kinds of precious stones (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.13">13</a>). Though God had elevated him to the royal throne (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.13-14">13-14</a>), the king’s heart turned to materialism and to religious and judicial corruption (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.16-18">16-18</a>). In a sense the king (prince) represents the people of Tyre. They were all guilty of corruption, injustice, and violence. If God judged his covenant people for their perversion of justice and for their sins, his judgment would surely come also on the city of Tyre (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.18-19">18-19</a>). When the Babylonians marched on Tyre, they laboriously built a jetty from the mainland to the city. At the same time Tyrian ships loaded with goods and treasures sailed out across the Mediterranean, so that when Nebuchadnezzar’s troops finally breached the walls, little loot could be taken (<a href="?bref=Ezek.29.18">29:18</a>).</p>
<p>The city of Sidon also cheered Jerusalem’s destruction. Sidon was a port city in Phoenicia, to the north of Tyre. By pestilence and war, the inhabitants of Sidon would learn the justice of Israel’s God.</p>
<p>Six nations (Ammon, Moab, Edom, Philistia, Tyre, and Sidon) scorned Israel at the fall of Jerusalem. Because God had invested his holiness in the temple of Jerusalem and in his people, the temple’s destruction and the people’s exile signified to the nations that Israel’s God was impotent. They did not realize that the reason for Israel’s fate was God’s intolerance of his people’s sin. God’s holiness required the punishment of sin, and it also required vindication for his name (<a href="?bref=Ezek.28.22-23">28:22-23</a>). God was still concerned for his people, that Israel might know he had removed the scorn of their neighbors (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.24">24</a>). In the restoration of Israel the Lord would further manifest his holiness before the nations. Israel would receive back the land, vineyards, and houses, and would enjoy the bounty of the Lord in peace (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.25-26">25-26</a>).</p>
<p>Egypt had convinced the people of Israel and Judah that with its help the Assyrians and the Babylonians could not stand their ground in Palestine. In 722 <span class="era">BC</span> the Assyrian troops took the northern capital of Samaria, and in 586 the Babylonians conquered Jerusalem, while Egypt remained passive. The Egyptians had desired control over Palestine for economic reasons, but not at the expense of their own welfare. Egypt, too, would lose its leadership under God’s judgment (<a href="?bref=Ezek.29.9-16">29:9-16</a>). Reduced to dependence on foreign powers, Egypt would no longer be a stumbling block for Israel. First, Babylonia was permitted to break Egypt’s power (<a href="?bref=Ezek.23.1-32.21">23:1–32:21</a>); later, the Persians, Greeks, and Romans would incorporate Egypt as a province. The fall of Egypt coincided with the fall of several great and small kingdoms: Assyria (<a href="?bref=Ezek.32.22-23">32:22-23</a>), Elam (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.32.24-25">24-25</a>), Meshech and Tubal (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.32.26-28">26-28</a>), Edom (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.32.29">29</a>), and Sidon (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.32.30">30</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Proclamation of Hope (<a href="?bref=Ezek.33.1-48.35">33:1–48:35</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">After the visions of God’s judgment on the surrounding nations, Ezekiel returns to the future hope of Israel. In the first major section of his book he dealt with the reasons for Judah’s exile and the destruction of the temple, alluding often to the future of Israel. But the prophet’s organization of his material included, between prophecies of Israel’s judgment and restoration, the oracles of God’s judgment on Israel’s neighbors who had encouraged and rejoiced in its fall. Throughout its history Israel had allowed foreign nations to influence its religion, culture, and form of government. The reduction of their powers meant Israel, restored to the Promised Land, would be more free for faithfulness to God. Before taking up the theme of the restoration, Ezekiel reviews the emphases of chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-24.27">1–24</a>: (1) He was called to be a watchman over Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.33.1-9">33:1-9</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-3.21">1:1–3:21</a>). (2) Israel had sinned against the Lord and had to receive a righteous judgment (<a href="?bref=Ezek.33.10">33:10</a>). (3) Jerusalem was to be taken by the Babylonians (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.21">21</a>). (4) Israel’s repentance is necessary for restoration (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.11-16">11-16</a>).</p>
<p>Thus far, his ministry had not met with success. The exiles who had heard his messages were full of appreciation for Ezekiel’s rhetorical and literary abilities (<a href="?bref=Ezek.33.32">33:32</a>). They readily accepted Ezekiel as a watchman who warned the people of the impending catastrophe at Jerusalem, and they may have admitted that their sin was the reason for God’s judgment on Israel and Jerusalem. But they were slow in applying the prophetic word to their own lives. God was ready to forgive their sins if they repented, acknowledged him, and demonstrated their renewed spirit by practicing the law of God (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.32">32</a>). Now that the news of Jerusalem had been reported to the exiles (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.21">21</a>), the necessity for the people to act responsibly was even more urgent. The Lord had demonstrated that Ezekiel was a true prophet (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.33">33</a>).</p>
<p>The success of Ezekiel’s ministry was not measured in numbers. He faithfully declared the word of God in word, sign, and parable. The exiles had followed the false hopes proclaimed by false “shepherds” who had fattened themselves at the expense of the flock (<a href="?bref=Ezek.34.2-3">34:2-3</a>). They did not take care of those in need (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.4">4</a>), and they allowed the flock to be scattered (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.5-6">5-6</a>). God promised his people that he would be the faithful shepherd, bring the sheep together, feed them, and care for them (<a href="?bref=Ezek.34.11-15">34:11-15</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.23.1-6">Ps 23</a>). God would also distinguish between the sheep and the goats, to find out whose hearts were right with him, so that the true sheep could be restored to God’s flock (<a href="?bref=Ezek.34.20-22">Ez 34:20-22</a>). God’s promise included the restoration of the land and the restoration of the divinely appointed Davidic dynasty (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.24">24</a>). The renewed fellowship between the Lord and Israel under the messianic ruler would be sealed with a new covenant, the “covenant of peace.” That covenant assured the people of God’s blessing on their labor, bringing them abundant harvests (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.26-27">26-27</a>). The people would not be forced to fight against nature in their pursuits (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.25-28">25-28</a>). They would not have to struggle against other peoples who might try to share in their blessings by force (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.27-29">27-29</a>). The prophetic vision telescoped the events of the restoration of Israel after the exile, the coming of Jesus the Messiah (cf. <a href="?bref=John.10.1-42">Jn 10</a>), and the full restoration of the sin-cursed world.</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.1-31">34</a> is the key to the messages of restoration. The emphases include the outworking of the frequently repeated verse “They will truly be my people, and I will be their God” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.11.20">11:20</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.30">34:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.36.28">36:28</a>). The most significant aspects of the restoration theme include: (1) God’s gracious restoration of his people to covenant blessing (<a href="?bref=Ezek.36.20-36">36:20-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.23-26">37:23-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.25">39:25</a>); (2) God’s restoration of the nation of Israel to the land (<a href="?bref=Ezek.36.1-15,24">36:1-15, 24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.14-23">37:14-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.27">39:27</a>); (3) God’s new covenant, giving his Spirit to his people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.36.25-27">36:25-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.14">37:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.29">39:29</a>), and his blessing on his people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.36.8-12,29-38">36:8-12, 29-38</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.9-10,26">39:9-10, 26</a>), assuring them of victory over their enemies (<a href="?bref=Ezek.35.1-15">35:1-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.36.36">36:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.28">37:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.38.1-39.24">38:1–39:24</a>); (4) God’s appointment of a Davidic king, the Messiah, over his people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.24-25">37:24-25</a>); and (5) God’s temple restored among his people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.26-27">37:26-27</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">The People of God</p>
<p class="fl">The rejection of the exiles did not last forever. Based on the Abrahamic covenant, the Lord promised to bless the faithful remnant and to make of them a new people. The imagery of a valley of dry bones is particularly fitting. The dry bones represent God’s people without hope (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.11">37:11</a>). Ezekiel proclaims to them the good news that God will renew and restore them (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.12">12</a>). The Lord’s purpose for his people is that all the nations may honor his holy name through his people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.39.7,25-27">39:7, 25-27</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">The Land</p>
<p class="fl">The promise also extends to the land, originally given to Abraham and his descendants. The Abrahamic covenant included a messianic element, for through the family of Abraham living in the Promised Land all nations would receive God’s blessing (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.3">Gn 12:3</a>). In a vision Ezekiel saw the boundaries and described the division of the land (<a href="?bref=Ezek.47.1-48.35">Ez 47–48</a>). The royal city of Jerusalem is the central symbol of God’s presence among his people; its name will be “The Lord is there” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.48.8-35">48:8-35</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">The New Covenant</p>
<p class="fl">The Abrahamic covenant is renewed, a gracious covenant that expresses the restored relationship. “Covenant of peace” fittingly describes its nature and benefits. The restless people of God are promised rest from their searching, their enemies, and their toil. The change in relationship is further emphasized by God’s sending of his Spirit, who will add a new dimension to the lifestyle of his people. Obedience to God will no longer be constrained, for God’s Spirit helps his people to do his will. A new heart, controlled by the Spirit of God, is given to the Lord’s people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.36.26-27">36:26-27</a>). The presence of the Spirit also signifies a new life for the people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.14">37:14</a>; see <a href="?bref=John.3.8,16">Jn 3:8, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.38">Acts 2:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.8.2-4,15">Rom 8:2-4, 15</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">The Messiah</p>
<p class="fl">The OT hope of a messianic king is crystallized in Ezekiel’s message. His rule will be everlasting (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.25">Ez 37:25</a>), over all God’s people who have new hearts (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.15-25">15-25</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">The Temple</p>
<p class="fl">As a priest, Ezekiel remained keenly interested in the temple, priesthood, sacrificial regulations, and festivals. A large section of the prophecy’s last division describes the temple’s revived worship (<a href="?bref=Ezek.40.1-46.24">40:1–46:24</a>). His vision of the glory of God, so important in the messages of God’s judgment on Jerusalem (chs <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-28">1</a>, <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.1-11.25">10–11</a>), now assures the remnant that God did not forsake his people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.43.2-5">43:2-5</a>). He will dwell among them, for the temple is a symbol of God’s presence (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.27">37:27</a>). Some interpreters believe that the temple, with its ritual as described in <a href="?bref=Ezek.40.1-46.24">Ezekiel 40–46</a>, will be restored in the messianic era before the last judgment. Others believe the promises about the temple provide a positive symbolic answer to Ezekiel’s greatest concern: whether God will return to be with his people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.48.35">48:35</a>; see <a href="?bref=John.2.21">Jn 2:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.22">Rv 21:22</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="EzekielSTemple"/>
<p>There are various interpretations of chapters <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.1-48.35">34–48</a>. As a watchman to Israel, Ezekiel had a message for the exiled Jewish community. Thus the prophecy’s fulfillment must have begun with the decree of Cyrus I (538 <span class="era">BC</span>) permitting the Jews to return to their land (<a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1-3">Ezr 1:1-3</a>). Two rival schools of interpretation exist on how the prophecy is fulfilled beyond Israel’s restoration to the land. Those who interpret Israel as simply the nation view the modern return of Jewish people to the land of Israel as a continuation of God’s prophetic promise. They believe that God’s plan for Israel is being fulfilled along with, and in addition to, his plan for the Christian church. The fulfillment of those prophecies will be inaugurated by the coming of the messianic king, who will give earthly peace to the Jewish people. The temple worship (<a href="?bref=Ezek.40.1-48.35">Ez 40–48</a>) will be restored in some way during the period of the messianic kingdom. The church will enjoy a small share in all the events centered on the Jews. The promises of Ezekiel’s vision are thus limited to the nation of Israel and must be fulfilled before the coming of a new heaven and earth.</p>
<p>Other interpreters believe that Ezekiel wrote for the benefit of spiritual descendants of Abraham who believe, as Abraham did, in God’s promises (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.6">Gn 15:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.4.11-13">Rom 4:11-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.6-9,29">Gal 3:6-9, 29</a>). All who have faith like Abraham, whether Jews or Gentiles, are regarded as Abraham’s offspring (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.28-29">Gal 3:28-29</a>). Ezekiel’s message thus would include all of God’s gracious work among Christian Gentiles, who have become the recipients of God’s promises and benefits. It is possible, on the basis of <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.10-11">1 Peter 1:10-11</a>, to interpret Ezekiel’s language as a prophetic expression of how God’s grace would come to all those who become reconciled to God through faith in the gospel.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=EzekielPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ezekiel (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=Prophecy_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophecy</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>