<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EzionGeber">
  <title>Ezion-Geber</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EZION-GEBER</p>
<p class="fl">Important port near some significant ruins at the head of the Gulf of Aqaba. Ezion-geber was one of the stations where the Israelites encamped while on their way to the plains of Moab (<a href="?bref=Num.33.35-36">Nm 33:35-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.2.8">Dt 2:8</a>). The city is not mentioned again until Solomon’s time. From this port Solomon and Hiram, king of Tyre, carried on a profitable commercial venture. Solomon’s products included copper (mined in the Arabah at Timna, 15 miles, or 24.1 kilometers, north of Ezion-geber), olive oil, and possibly products bought from Egypt, such as linen, and chariots (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.28-29">1 Kgs 10:28-29</a>). The “ships of Tarshish,” with the ships of Hiram, made a round trip of three years from Ezion-geber to many ports along the coasts of Africa and Arabia and possibly even as far as India (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.22">1 Kgs 10:22</a>). In exchange the fleet brought back gold from Ophir, along with precious stones, almug wood (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.11-12">11-12</a>), silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.22">22</a>). Solomon’s alliance with the Phoenicians of Tyre gave him a port on the Mediterranean (which he himself did not have). The alliance also gave Hiram and the Phoenicians an outlet at Ezion-geber for trading in the Indian Ocean.</p>
<p>With the division of the kingdom after Solomon, the port was under Judah’s control. It was burned and destroyed by Shishak of Egypt in his invasion of Judah in Rehoboam’s fifth year (925 <span class="era">BC</span>). A second city was built on the ruins, but there is no mention of a navy. Jehoshaphat was able to restore the fleet to sail once again, but some storm or other disaster wrecked the ships (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.48">1 Kgs 22:48</a>). In subsequent Judean history, Judah was able to use the port when it was strong, but in its times of weakness, other nations did (e.g., Edom, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.8.20-22">2 Kgs 8:20-22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.6">16:6</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Exodusthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Exodus, The</a>; <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>