<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Fear">
  <title>Fear</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FEAR</p>
<p class="fl">Emotional worry that something bad will happen soon. Often spoken of as the cause of people wanting religion. Yet fear alone can never account for true religion, since men are impelled to draw near unto God, the object of their worship. No one wants to come close to someone they fear.</p>
<p>The biblical conception of fear embraces a much wider dimension than does our common English word, which simply denotes dread or terror. While this meaning forms an essential part of the scriptural picture, it is by no means the primary significance, especially when the fear of God—an awe-inspiring reverence—is referred to.</p>
<p>There is, of course, a legitimate place for the fear of God in the lower, anxious sense. We are told, “It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God” (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.31">Heb 10:31</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Jesus taught that we should fear God because he has the power to punish sin and destroy people (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.4-5">Lk 12:4-5</a>). Fear helps people realize the moral depravity of their souls and their need of divine forgiveness. The first occurrence of such fear may be found in <a href="?bref=Gen.3.1-24">Genesis 3</a>, where Adam and Eve stepped back from the presence of the holy God because they had openly disobeyed his commandment. Their fear was entirely reasonable because they had been severely warned that disobedience would cause a grave judgment. Fear is quite naturally the logical consequence of sin (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.10">Gn 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.4.13-14">4:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.28.1">Prv 28:1</a>). The Bible shows many people who are plagued with profound anxiety (e.g., Cain, Saul, Ahaz, and Pilate). Anxious fear seizes the wicked (<a href="?bref=Job.15.24">Jb 15:24</a>), surprises the hypocrite (<a href="?bref=Isa.33.14">Is 33:14</a>), and consumes evildoers (<a href="?bref=Ps.73.19">Ps 73:19</a>), whose faithless lives are characterized by fear (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.8">Rv 21:8</a>). Pharaoh’s mighty host was virtually paralyzed by fear as God moved against them (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.16">Ex 15:16</a>), and Job’s associate Bildad spoke of men driven to their knees by the judgments of God (<a href="?bref=Job.18.11">Jb 18:11</a>).</p>
<p>Fear has a tendency to either immobilize people or seriously affect their activity. This is especially true of the spiritually uncommitted. Saul’s fear of the people caused him to transgress the commandment of God (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.24">1 Sm 15:24</a>). The parents whose blind son was miraculously healed by Jesus were afraid to support Christ because they feared the Jews (<a href="?bref=John.9.22">Jn 9:22</a>). In the parable of the talents Jesus told of a man whose fear prevented him from doing his reasonable duty (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.25">Mt 25:25</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus Christ, by his atoning death, resurrection, and heavenly intercession for believers, is the unique liberator from fear. The apostle Paul encouraged the Romans (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.15">Rom 8:15</a>) by informing them that in their conversion to Christ they received the Holy Spirit, not as a spirit of fear and bondage, but as the spirit of adoption, whereby they could address God as “Abba” (the Aramaic word commonly used by Jewish children to address their fathers). This is the word by which our Lord Jesus addressed his heavenly Father and which Christians, by virtue of their adoption into the family of God, may also use in speaking to God (<a href="?bref=Gal.4.6">Gal 4:6</a>). Recipients of God’s love have received a dynamic force for casting out their anxieties (<a href="?bref=1Jn.4.18">1 Jn 4:18</a>).</p>
<p>Unjustified fear may harm the efforts of the people of God. God warned Jeremiah not to fear his opponents (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.8">Jer 1:8</a>), or else God might allow him to face calamity (v <a href="?bref=Jer.1.17">17</a>). Similar calls to courage were given to Jeremiah’s contemporary, Ezekiel, and to a great many others (<a href="?bref=Josh.1.7-9">Jos 1:7-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.2.6">Ez 2:6</a>). We realize that even godly people are tempted to fear and may be temporarily overwhelmed (<a href="?bref=Ps.55.5">Ps 55:5</a>). Therefore, God repeatedly counsels his people not to succumb to that temptation (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.12">Is 8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.1,27">Jn 14:1, 27</a>). He tells them to place their anxieties upon the God of their redemption, whose care for his sheep is infinitely great (<a href="?bref=1Pet.5.7">1 Pt 5:7</a>). Faith, then, is the indispensable antecedent of fearlessness as seen in the words of Isaiah: “Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace, whose mind is stayed on thee: because he trusteth in thee” (<a href="?bref=Isa.26.3">Is 26:3</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). The psalmists repeatedly stress the role of faith in conquering fear (<a href="?bref=Ps.37.1">Pss 37:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.46.2">46:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.112.7">112:7</a>).</p>
<p>Genuine faith is expressed in, and animated by, a reverential awe, and this is the basic meaning of the biblical idea of the fear of God. Unless there is personal awareness of the awesome and majestic sovereignty of God, it is impossible to have a meaningful faith existing in one’s heart (<a href="?bref=Ps.5.7">Pss 5:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.7">89:7</a>). Though Christians are to be liberated from the fear of men (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.6">Heb 13:6</a>), death (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.15">2:15</a>), and life in general (<a href="?bref=2Tim.1.6-7">2 Tm 1:6-7</a>), they must never lose their sense of the awesomeness of God. Such awareness not only leads to true wisdom (<a href="?bref=Ps.111.10">Ps 111:10</a>) but also provides direction for the child of God throughout life (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.21">Eph 5:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.12">Phil 2:12</a>). Those who love God learn of wholesome fear by searching the Scriptures (<a href="?bref=Pr.2.3-5">Prv 2:3-5</a>), the Word of God, which the ancient Israelites were commanded to cleave to and obey as evidence of their reverence for God (<a href="?bref=Deut.6.2">Dt 6:2</a>). In <a href="?bref=Acts.10.2">Acts 10:2</a> Cornelius and his family were called “God-fearers” because of their high regard for the God of Israel and because they stood in awe of his person. True reverence for God must invariably express itself in good works and holy living (<a href="?bref=2Cor.7.1">2 Cor 7:1</a>). This holy fear is actually a source of joy (<a href="?bref=Ps.2.11">Ps 2:11</a>) and a veritable fountain of life (<a href="?bref=Pr.14.27">Prv 14:27</a>). The fear of the Lord is more valuable than the greatest material riches (<a href="?bref=Pr.15.16">15:16</a>) because the Lord takes pleasure in those who hold him in such high regard (<a href="?bref=Ps.147.11">Ps 147:11</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>