<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Firstborn">
  <title>Firstborn</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FIRSTBORN</p>
<p class="fl">Term used in the Bible to describe a family’s oldest son or daughter (<a href="?bref=Gen.22.21">Gn 22:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.29.26">29:26</a>). Israel was called God’s firstborn because of that nation’s miraculous beginning and special deliverance out of Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.5,15-16">Gn 17:5, 15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.4.22">Ex 4:22</a>). As God’s firstborn, Israel had unique privileges over all other nations. Gentiles were “blessed” only in relation to their kindness to Israel (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.3">Gn 12:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.19.6">Ex 19:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.5-8">Dt 4:5-8</a>). The prophet Isaiah foresaw a day when Israel would have a double portion of inheritance (<a href="?bref=Isa.61.7">Is 61:7</a>). Thus, being firstborn implies priority or preeminence, as well as an inheritance.</p>
<p>The expression “first-born of the poor,” (<a href="?bref=Isa.14.30">Is 14:30</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) means one who is supremely poor, the poorest of the poor. Another figurative expression, “first-born of death” (<a href="?bref=Job.18.13">Jb 18:13</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), implied that Job’s disease was fatal.</p>
<p>Because God delivered Israel’s firstborn sons from death in Egypt, he expected each firstborn to be sanctified to him (<a href="?bref=Exod.11.4-7">Ex 11:4-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.13.12">13:12</a>). The first male child was a representative of the entire offspring (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.3">Gn 49:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.22.29">Ex 22:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.13">Nm 3:13</a>). The firstborn of all animals used in sacrifice was to be sanctified to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.2,15">Ex 13:2, 15</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="FirstbornandRedemption">Firstborn and Redemption</p>
<p class="fl">The firstborn of every tribe except Levi’s was to be redeemed by a sum not to exceed five shekels (<a href="?bref=Num.18.15-16">Nm 18:15-16</a>). Redemption implied a previous bondage and was to remind Israel of their redemption from bondage in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.2-8">Ex 13:2-8</a>).</p>
<p>The firstborn of ritually clean animals was devoted to the Lord. It was brought to the tabernacle (or later, the temple) within a year from the eighth day after birth. This animal was then sacrificed and its blood sprinkled on the altar. The meat of the sacrificed animal was for the priests (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.13">Ex 13:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.22.30">22:30</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Num.18.17">Nm 18:17</a>). The firstborn of unclean animals could be redeemed with an addition of one-fifth of the value as determined by the priest. If not redeemed, these animals were sold, exchanged, or destroyed by the priests (<a href="?bref=Lev.27.27">Lv 27:27</a>). The colt of an ass was to be redeemed with a lamb (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.13">Ex 13:13</a>). If not redeemed, it was to be killed. Meat from unclean animals was not eaten.</p>
<p class="h2" id="FirstbornandBirthright">Firstborn and Birthright</p>
<p class="fl">The firstborn acted as priest of the family in the father’s absence or death. Esau and Reuben are both examples (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.19,32">Gn 27:19, 32</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.5.1-2">1 Chr 5:1-2</a>). This position of the firstborn ceased when the priesthood was committed to Levi’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Num.3.12-13">Nm 3:12-13</a>). All the firstborn of succeeding generations had to be redeemed. The redemption money became part of the Levites’ yearly income (<a href="?bref=Num.8.17">8:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.18.16">18:16</a>).</p>
<p>A double portion of the family inheritance was the right of the firstborn. This protected the firstborn when there was a polygamous marriage. The son of a favorite wife could not take the place of the first son born of the household (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.17">Dt 21:17</a>).</p>
<p>The title “firstborn” is applied to Christ (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.7">Lk 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.8.29">Rom 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.15,18">Col 1:15, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.1.6">Heb 1:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.1.5">Rv 1:5</a>). It stresses Christ’s preeminence over all because he was the first to rise from the dead. As firstborn, Christ is heir of all things (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.2">Heb 1:2</a>) and the head of the church (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.20-23">Eph 1:20-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.18,24">Col 1:18, 24</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.2.10-12">Heb 2:10-12</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Birthright_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Birthright</a>; <a href="?item=Heir_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Heir</a>; <a href="?item=Inheritance_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Inheritance</a>; <a href="?item=Primogeniture_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Primogeniture</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>