<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Foreigner">
  <title>Foreigner</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FOREIGNER</p>
<p class="fl">Noncitizen or alien, temporary guest, sojourner, or stranger.</p>
<p>The Hebrew word meaning “foreigner” is rendered correctly on all occasions in the <span class="sc">rsv</span>, but the <span class="sc">kjv</span> uses it in its truest sense on only two occasions (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.3">Dt 15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Obad.1.11">Ob 1:11</a>). In most cases the <span class="sc">kjv</span> translates the word as “alien” (<a href="?bref=Deut.14.21">Dt 14:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.19.15">Jb 19:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.69.8">Ps 69:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.5.2">Lam 5:2</a>) or “stranger” (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.13">Gn 15:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.2.22">Ex 2:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.25.35">Lv 25:35</a>). Another Hebrew word means “dweller” (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.35">Lv 25:35</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.29.15">1 Chr 29:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.39.12">Ps 39:12</a>) or “settler.” For the most part, however, it is rendered “foreigner.”</p>
<p>A temporary guest or sojourner was usually someone who wanted to take up temporary residence or had moved from one tribe of people to another, and then attempted to obtain certain privileges or rights belonging to the natives. A whole tribe might be sojourners in Israel. This was the case with the Gibeonites (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.1-27">Jos 9</a>) and the Beerothites (<a href="?bref=2Sam.4.3">2 Sm 4:3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Chr.2.17">2 Chr 2:17</a>). The Israelites themselves were sojourners in the land of Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.13">Gn 15:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.23.4">23:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.26.3">26:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.47.4">47:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.2.22">Ex 2:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.23.9">23:9</a>) and in other lands (<a href="?bref=Ruth.1.1">Ru 1:1</a>).</p>
<p>Foreigners or sojourners had certain rights but also certain limitations while in Israel. They could offer sacrifices (<a href="?bref=Lev.17.8">Lv 17:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.22.18">22:18</a>) but could not enter the sanctuary unless circumcised (<a href="?bref=Ezek.44.9">Ez 44:9</a>). They were allowed to participate in the three great Jewish festivals (<a href="?bref=Deut.16.11,14">Dt 16:11, 14</a>) but could not eat the Passover meal unless circumcised (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.43,48">Ex 12:43, 48</a>). Foreigners were not obliged to follow the Israelite religion, but they shared in some of its benefits (<a href="?bref=Deut.14.29">Dt 14:29</a>). They were not to work on the Sabbath or the Day of Atonement (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.10">Ex 20:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.23.12">23:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.16.29">Lv 16:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.14">Dt 5:14</a>) and could be stoned for reviling or blaspheming God’s name (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.16">Lv 24:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.15.30">Nm 15:30</a>). Foreigners were forbidden to eat blood (<a href="?bref=Lev.17.10-12">Lv 17:10-12</a>) but could eat animals that had died a natural death (<a href="?bref=Deut.14.21">Dt 14:21</a>). Israel’s code of sexual morality also applied to the foreigner (<a href="?bref=Lev.18.26">Lv 18:26</a>). There were prohibitions against Israelites intermarrying with foreigners, but it was nevertheless a common occurrence (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.14">Gn 34:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.12,16">Ex 34:12, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.7.3-4">Dt 7:3-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.23.12">Jos 23:12</a>).</p>
<p>Civil rights were provided for foreigners by the law of Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.49">Ex 12:49</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.24.22">Lv 24:22</a>), and they came under the same legal processes and penalties (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.2">Lv 20:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.24.16,22">24:16, 22</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.1.16">Dt 1:16</a>). They were to be treated politely (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.21">Ex 22:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.23.9">23:9</a>), loved as those under the love of God (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.34">Lv 19:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.10.18-19">Dt 10:18-19</a>), and treated generously (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.10">Lv 19:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.23.22">23:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.19-22">Dt 24:19-22</a>). They could receive asylum in times of trouble (<a href="?bref=Num.35.15">Nm 35:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.20.9">Jos 20:9</a>). Foreign servants were to receive treatment equal to Hebrew servants (<a href="?bref=Deut.24.14">Dt 24:14</a>). A foreigner could not take part in tribal deliberations or become a king (<a href="?bref=Deut.17.15">17:15</a>). The prophet Ezekiel looked forward to the messianic age when the foreigner would share all the blessings of the land with God’s own people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.47.22-23">Ez 47:22-23</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT, “foreigner” is often used metaphorically. On the one hand, the work of Christ allowed all foreigners (i.e., those alienated from Christ) to become members of God’s household (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.11-19">Eph 2:11-19</a>). On the other hand, Christians should consider themselves foreigners in this world (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.13">Heb 11:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.11">1 Pt 2:11</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Barbarian_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Barbarian</a>; <a href="?item=Neighbor_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Neighbor</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>