<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Forgiveness">
  <title>Forgiveness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FORGIVENESS</p>
<p class="fl">Pardon, involving restoration of broken relationships; ceasing to feel resentment for wrongs and offenses. Primarily, forgiveness is an act of God, releasing sinners from judgment and freeing them from the divine penalty of their sin. Since only God is holy, only God can forgive sin (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.7">Mk 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.21">Lk 5:21</a>). Forgiveness is also a human act extended toward one’s neighbor—a manifestation of one’s realization and appropriation of God’s forgiveness. Hence, forgiveness is a uniquely Christian doctrine.</p>
<p>In other religions, forgiveness does not have the same force. In animism, there is no awareness of a personal relationship with God. In Hinduism, all have to pay the inexorable consequences of karma in the wheel of reincarnations. Buddhism likewise knows nothing of a forgiving God. The idea is present in Islam, but there is no personal God and Father. Even in Judaism, forgiveness remains a limited experience, though forgiveness as developed in the NT adds dimension to the teaching of the OT.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ExpressionsofForgivenessintheOldTestament">Expressions of Forgiveness in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The idea of forgiveness is expressed in various metaphors. The command is <span class="hebrew">nasa</span><span class="ital">,</span> to “send away,” as the scapegoat was sent away into the wilderness to bear the sins of the Israelites. It is also rendered “to be merciful” (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.20">Lv 4:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.30,34">1 Kgs 8:30, 34</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.86.5">Pss 86:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.103.3">103:3</a>). The Hebrew word <span class="hebrew">kapar</span> is commonly used of atonement, meaning “to cover up,” as the sacrifice was offered to cover the deficiency of the worshiper (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.36">Ex 29:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.21.8">Dt 21:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.18.23">Jer 18:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.43.20">Ez 43:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.20">45:20</a>). Cognates of <span class="hebrew">salah</span> always refer to God’s act of forgiveness (<a href="?bref=Num.30.5,8,12">Nm 30:5, 8, 12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.86.5">Pss 86:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.130.4">130:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.9.9">Dn 9:9</a>). God lets go of the transgression; he removes it. Another expression is <span class="hebrew">maha</span><span class="ital">,</span> to “wipe away” (<a href="?bref=Ps.51.1,7">Ps 51:1, 7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.43.25">Is 43:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.44.22">44:22</a>).</p>
<p>The OT teaches that God is a forgiving God (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6-7">Ex 34:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.17">Neh 9:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.9.9">Dn 9:9</a>), yet he is just and punishes sin. In many cases, God refuses to forgive when the proper conditions are not met, or when certain serious offenses are committed (<a href="?bref=Deut.29.20">Dt 29:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.4">2 Kgs 24:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.5.7">Jer 5:7</a>). Forgiveness is part of God’s character, but it is never given randomly, for people must also be repentant. The OT (cited here in the <span class="sc">rsv</span>) uses vivid imagery to indicate the magnitude of God’s forgiveness. Sin is cast “into the depths of the sea” (<a href="?bref=Mic.7.19">Mi 7:19</a>), removed “as far as the east is from the west” (<a href="?bref=Ps.103.12">Ps 103:12</a>), hid behind God’s back (<a href="?bref=Isa.38.17">Is 38:17</a>), “remembered no more” (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.34">Jer 31:34</a>). The stain and soil of sin is bleached white (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.18">Is 1:18</a>). Sin, which burdens like a weight, is forever lifted and forgiven.</p>
<p>The dynamic of forgiveness in the OT is thus releasing one from the past. The past acts and deeds of sin are not denied, but there is no longer any bondage. Forgiveness brings freedom.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ForgivenessintheNewTestament">Forgiveness in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the NT, the concept of the unmerited forgiveness of God is intensified by the fact that God forgave our sins when Christ died for us. Each human is an insolvent debtor (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.23-35">Mt 18:23-35</a>) who has no hope of repayment. Sinners all, we cannot keep the law or save ourselves (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.26-27">Mk 10:26-27</a>). This highlights the NT teaching that it is in the person of Christ himself that there is forgiveness. He alone has the power to forgive sins (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.5-10">2:5-10</a>). It is his death that is redemptive (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.28">Mt 26:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.45">Mk 10:45</a>) and his blood that is the basis of a new covenant (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.25">1 Cor 11:25</a>). It is through him that one can enter into the living experience of forgiveness (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.15,22">Heb 9:15, 22</a>). So forgiveness is inseparable from the proclamation of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.38">Acts 13:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.7">Eph 1:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.14">Col 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.12">1 Jn 2:12</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="TheChristianExperienceOfForgiveness"/>
<p>There are other distinctively NT concepts of forgiveness. The Greek word <span class="greek">charizomai</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “to forgive sins,” is distinctively developed by Paul in terms of God’s gracious pardon (<a href="?bref=2Cor.2.7">2 Cor 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.12.13">12:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.32">Eph 4:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.2.13">Col 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.13">3:13</a>). Sin is considered as a debt, and <span class="greek">aphesis</span> denotes the discharge of a debt (“putting it away”—see <a href="?bref=Luke.6.37">Lk 6:37</a>). Forgiveness is also treated as remission, <span class="greek">paresis</span> (“passing over”). God has not executed the full retribution called for by sin (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.16">Acts 14:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.30">17:30</a>); instead, he has shown mercy.</p>
<p>Yet the NT speaks of two limitations to forgiveness. One is the unpardonable sin (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.31-32">Mt 12:31-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.28-30">Mk 3:28-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.10">Lk 12:10</a>). In this regard Christ speaks of those who, like the Pharisees, are so distorted in their moral judgments that they cannot distinguish between acts of Satan and the good deeds of Christ. There is also “the sin against the Holy Spirit” that is “sin unto death” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.5.16">1 Jn 5:16</a>). This sin is not specifically defined, but its essence seems to be consistent rejection of the grace of God.</p>
<p>The ethics of forgiveness in the NT insists not only on penitence as a condition for forgiveness (<a href="?bref=2Cor.7.10">2 Cor 7:10</a>), but also on the need to forgive others (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.14-15">Mt 6:14-15</a>). If in the midst of receiving forgiveness one does not forgive others, it is a clear sign that repentance is not complete. Several times in his parables the Lord insists that the readiness to forgive others is a sign of true repentance (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.23-35">Mt 18:23-35</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.37">Lk 6:37</a>). So Christ taught that to forgive is a duty, and no limits can be set on it. It must be granted without reserve, even to 70 times 7 (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.21-22">Mt 18:21-22</a>). Forgiveness is part of the mutual relationship of believers: since all are dependent upon God’s forgiveness, all are required to forgive one another. “As the Lord has forgiven you, so you also must forgive” (<a href="?bref=Col.3.13">Col 3:13</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Confession_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Confession</a>; <a href="?item=Repentance_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Repentance</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>