<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ZechariahBookof">
  <title>Zechariah, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ZECHARIAH, Book of</p>
<p class="fl">Longest book of the Minor Prophets and the most difficult to understand. One reason for this difficulty is the numerous visions that call for an interpreter. At times an interpreting angel is present to tell what the vision means (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.9-10,19-20">Zec 1:9-10, 19-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.4.1-6">4:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.5.5-6">5:5-6</a>), but at other times, when an interpretation is really needed, there is no angel to give one. The obscure meaning of many passages has spawned numerous theories concerning the date, authorship, unity, and interpretation of this book. One thing that makes the book of Zechariah significant for the Christian is its use in the NT. The last part of Zechariah (chs <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-11.17">9–11</a>) is the most quoted section of the Prophets in the Gospel Passion narratives, and, other than Ezekiel, Zechariah influenced the book of Revelation more than any other OT book.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Date">Date</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurposeandMessage">Purpose and Message</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">The name Zechariah probably means “the Lord remembers” or “the Lord is renowned.” Zechariah is a common name in the OT and NT. At least 30 different people in the OT are named Zechariah. There is a problem in identifying the prophet’s father. In <a href="?bref=Zech.1.1">Zechariah 1:1</a> and <a href="?bref=Zech.1.7">1:7</a>, the prophet is called “the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo,” but in <a href="?bref=Ezra.5.1">Ezra 5:1</a> and <a href="?bref=Ezra.6.14">6:14</a> he is called simply “the son of Iddo.” There was another Zechariah in Isaiah’s time whose father was named Jeberechiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.2">Is 8:2</a>). Another prophet by the name of Zechariah, the son of Jehoiada the priest, lived much earlier during the reign of Joash, king of Judah (835–796 <span class="era">BC</span>). This prophet was stoned to death because he proclaimed that the Lord had forsaken his people because of their sins (<a href="?bref=2Chr.24.20-22">2 Chr 24:20-22</a>). Jesus seemed to refer to this or a similar unrecorded incident, but he calls the prophet the son of Berechiah, the last of the martyrs among the prophets (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.35">Mt 23:35</a>). However, Luke’s account of what Jesus said about Zechariah (<a href="?bref=Luke.11.51">Lk 11:51</a>) does not include the words “the son of Berechiah.” Since Jesus was quoting 2 Chronicles, which was the last book in the Hebrew Bible, he was simply indicating the sweep of time from the first murder (Abel) to the last (Zechariah, the son of Jehoiada). There is no evidence that the prophet of the book of Zechariah was martyred; therefore, the best solution to the problem is to consider Berechiah the father, and Iddo the grandfather, of this prophet.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Date">Date</p>
<p class="fl">The first part of the book of Zechariah (chs <a href="?bref=Zech.1.1-8.56">1–8</a>) is easy to date. The first date is in the first verse, “the eighth month of the second year of Darius.” This was Darius, king of Persia (521–486 <span class="era">BC</span>). The eighth month of Darius’s second year would be October 520 <span class="era">BC</span>. This date seems to be the first time the “word of the Lord” came to Zechariah. The second date in Zechariah is in <a href="?bref=Zech.1.7">1:7</a>: “On the twenty-fourth day of the eleventh month which is the month of Shebat, in the second year of Darius . . .” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). This date would be February 15, 519 <span class="era">BC</span>. The word of the Lord that came to Zechariah on this date seems to include the account of eight night visions, along with some oracles, from an angel who talked with him. The third date in Zechariah is in <a href="?bref=Zech.7.1">7:1</a>: “In the fourth year of King Darius . . . on the fourth day of the ninth month, which is Chislev . . .” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). This date would be the equivalent of December 7, 518 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>There are no dates in <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-14.21">Zechariah 9–14</a>. Zechariah’s name is never mentioned, and neither is Darius or any king. A period of relative peace and stability gives place to war. The temple is standing (<a href="?bref=Zech.11.13">11:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.14.20">14:20</a>), and evidently Greek soldiers are present (<a href="?bref=Zech.9.13">9:13</a>). Any attempt to assign specific dates to <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-14.21">Zechariah 9–14</a> would be speculation.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">The temple in Jerusalem was destroyed by Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon, in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. Nebuchadnezzar made several raids against Jerusalem before and after it fell, taking many captives to Babylon (cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.1-17">2 Kgs 24:1-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.1.1">Dn 1:1</a>). On two occasions, Jeremiah had predicted that captivity would last 70 years (<a href="?bref=Jer.25.11">Jer 25:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.29.10">29:10</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Dan.9.2">Dn 9:2</a>). In the time of Zechariah, the period of 70 years since the fall of Jerusalem was coming to an end (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.12">Zec 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.7.5">7:5</a>). It had been 66 years since Jerusalem fell, when the first “word of the Lord” came to Zechariah in the second year of Darius (520 <span class="era">BC</span>). The Babylonian Empire had fallen to the Persians in 538 <span class="era">BC</span>, and Cyrus the first king of Persia signed a decree permitting all captives to return to their homes (<a href="?bref=2Chr.36.23">2 Chr 36:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1-4">Ezr 1:1-4</a>). Evidently, the first contingent of Jewish captives returned to Jerusalem with Zerubbabel and Joshua the priest about 536 <span class="era">BC</span>. One of the first objectives of the returnees was to rebuild the temple (<a href="?bref=Ezra.1.3">Ezr 1:3</a>), but internal strife and external opposition from the Samaritans prohibited the immediate rebuilding of the temple. After Darius I became king of Persia in 521 <span class="era">BC</span>, a wave of expectation and enthusiasm swept over the Jewish communities in Jerusalem and Babylon. Two prophets, possibly from the Babylonian exiles, Haggai and Zechariah, began preaching so powerfully that work on the second temple began in 520 <span class="era">BC</span> and was finished in 516 <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=Ezra.5.1,14-15">Ezr 5:1, 14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1-2.23">Hg 1–2</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.1.1-8.23">Zec 1–8</a>).</p>
<p>The book of Zechariah opens in the second year of Darius (520 <span class="era">BC</span>). Some of the captives had been back in Jerusalem for 16 years, but nothing was being done about rebuilding the temple. Zechariah’s first message called for the people to repent and not repeat the mistake of their fathers, whose sins and refusal to repent led to the exile and destruction of the temple (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.1-6">Zec 1:1-6</a>). Then a series of eight night visions follows (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.7-6.8">1:7–6:8</a>), assuring the people that the temple would be rebuilt by Zerubbabel (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.16">1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.4.9">4:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.15">6:15</a>). Two verses in Zechariah speak volumes concerning the hardships and difficulties in Jerusalem before the temple was rebuilt: “This is what the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Almighty says: Take heart and finish the task! You have heard what the prophets have been saying about building the Temple of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Almighty ever since the foundation was laid. Before the work on the Temple began, there were no jobs and no wages for either people or animals. No traveler was safe from the enemy, for there were enemies on all sides. I had turned everyone against each other” (<a href="?bref=Zech.8.9-10">8:9-10</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>The first eight chapters of Zechariah are set against the social, political, and religious situations in Jerusalem from 520 to 518 <span class="era">BC</span>. But beginning with chapter <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-17">9</a>, historical moorings are lost. Chapter <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-17">9</a> opens with an oracle against Syria, including Damascus, Tyre, and Sidon, and against Philistia. Each of these places will be conquered and cleansed and will become like a clan in Judah. There is the promise of a new king coming triumphantly to Jerusalem, yet humbly riding on a donkey. His reign will be peaceful and universal. The next oracle speaks of setting the captives free, but this may not refer to the Babylonian captives, because of a reference to the Greeks. <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-12.14">Zechariah 9–12</a> is almost wholly concerned with the future. Some scholars call this part apocalyptic literature. The nations attack Jerusalem and are defeated (chs <a href="?bref=Zech.12.1-14">12</a>, <a href="?bref=Zech.14.1-21">14</a>). The temple is standing (<a href="?bref=Zech.11.13">11:13</a>), but it does not seem to have a place of great prominence in the new Jerusalem and in the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Zech.14.6-9">14:6-9</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeandMessage">Purpose and Message</p>
<p class="fl">The purpose of the book is to reassure and encourage. The restored Jewish community of 520 <span class="era">BC</span> needed the assurance that the temple would be rebuilt, and later groups of God’s people needed to know that ultimately the kingdom of God would come in its fullness. There are three messages in the book of Zechariah: the need for repentance (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.1-5.11">1:1–5:11</a>); the eight night visions (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.7-6.8">1:7–6:8</a>) signifying that the temple would be rebuilt and God’s glory would return to Jerusalem; and the coming kingdom of God (chs <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-14.21">9–14</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="fl">The book of Zechariah may be divided into two main parts: chapters <a href="?bref=Zech.1.1-8.23">1–8</a> and <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-14.21">9–14</a>. The first part is dated between 520 <span class="era">BC</span> and 518 <span class="era">BC</span>. It consists of oracles and visions of Zechariah the son of Berechiah. Mainly prose, its primary concern is to assure the restored Jewish community that the temple will be rebuilt. The second part (chs <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-14.21">9–14</a>) is undated. There are no references to Zechariah. The temple is standing, and much of the language is eschatological and apocalyptic. The second part itself has two parts: chapters <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-11.17">9–11</a> and <a href="?bref=Zech.12.1-14.21">12–14</a>. Chapters <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-17">9</a> and <a href="?bref=Zech.12.1-14">12</a> begin essentially the same way: “The oracle of the word of the Lord.”</p>
<p>The first part of Zechariah (chs <a href="?bref=Zech.1.1-8.23">1–8</a>) has four main sections: superscription and first oracle (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.1-6">1:1-6</a>); eight night visions and related oracles (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.7-6.8">1:7–6:8</a>); the symbolic crowning of Joshua (<a href="?bref=Zech.6.9-15">6:9-15</a>); and the question about fasting and morality (<a href="?bref=Zech.7.1-8.23">7:1–8:23</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Superscription (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.1">1:1</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This section is dated specifically “in the eighth month” of the Babylonian calendar, which was from mid-October to mid-November. The second year of Darius, king of Persia, was 520 <span class="era">BC</span>. The date is important in relating the work of Zechariah to that of Haggai (cf. <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1,15">Hg 1:1, 15</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.1,10,18-20">2:1, 10, 18-20</a>) and to the reconstruction of the temple under Zerubbabel. The first oracle concerns the need for repentance. The first message of Zechariah came between Haggai’s second and third message. He, like Haggai, probably attributed the failure of the crops and other hardships to a failure to rebuild the temple (cf. <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.6-11">Hg 1:6-11</a>). Zechariah calls for the people to repent so that they can persevere with work on the temple.</p>
<p class="h3">The Eight Night Visions and Related Oracles (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.7-6.8">1:7–6:8</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">These visions that Zechariah saw in Jerusalem all seem to have been given on the night of the 24th day of the 11th month (Shebat) in the second year of Darius (mid-January to mid-February 519 <span class="era">BC</span>). Seven of the eight visions have essentially the same form. Four of the visions begin with the words “Then I looked up and saw” (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.18">1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.2.1">2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.5.1">5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.1">6:1</a>). One begins, “In a vision during the night” (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.8">1:8</a>). Another begins, “Then the angel who had been talking with me returned and woke me, as though I had been asleep. ‘What do you see now?’ he asked” (<a href="?bref=Zech.4.1-2">4:1-2</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Still another (the seventh) vision begins, “Then the angel who was talking with me came forward and said . . .” (<a href="?bref=Zech.5.5">5:5</a>). However, the fourth vision is different from the other seven. It begins, “Then he showed me” (<a href="?bref=Zech.3.1">3:1</a>, cf. <a href="?bref=Amos.7.1,4,7">Am 7:1, 4, 7</a>). This message in the third person contains no interpreting angel nor any direct message to Zechariah, as if he were merely an observer. This fourth vision is so different from the other seven that it was not a part of the original series of eight.</p>
<p>An overall pattern to the eight visions is not evident. Some scholars have seen some significance in the fact that the visions move from the evening or night in the first vision to the sunrise in the last vision. Others have detected some relationships in pairs of visions. The first and last visions involve horses and riders or chariots. The second and third visions involve the restoration of Judah and Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.18-21">1:18-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.2.1-5">2:1-5</a>). The fourth and fifth deal with the place of the two leaders in the restored community: Joshua will be cleansed and restored as the high priest (<a href="?bref=Zech.3.1-5">3:1-5</a>) and Zerubbabel the governor will complete the temple (<a href="?bref=Zech.4.1-14">4:1-14</a>). The sixth and seventh visions involve the cleansing of the land. A flying scroll enters the house of every thief and false witness and consumes it (<a href="?bref=Zech.5.1-4">5:1-4</a>). Wickedness personified as a woman will be carried in an ephah (basket) to the land of Shinar (vv <a href="?bref=Zech.5.5-11">5-11</a>). Interspersed in the vision accounts are four oracles (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.14-17">1:14-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.2.8-13">2:8-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.3.6-10">3:6-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.4.8-14">4:8-14</a>). Each of these passages begins with the messenger formula, “Thus says the Lord,” or the expression “Cry out” (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.14,17">1:14, 17</a>). The first oracle assures the people that the temple, the cities, and the choice of Jerusalem will be renewed. The second oracle exhorts any exiles remaining in Babylon to return to Judah and Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Zech.2.7-12">2:7-12</a>). <a href="?bref=Zech.2.12-13">Zechariah 2:12-13</a> are interesting. Verse <a href="?bref=Zech.2.12">12</a> is the only OT reference to Palestine as “the Holy Land,” and verse <a href="?bref=Zech.2.13">13</a> is similar to the call to worship in <a href="?bref=Hab.2.20">Habakkuk 2:20</a>: “Be silent before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, all humanity, for he is springing into action from his holy dwelling” (<a href="?bref=Zech.2.13">Zec 2:13</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The third oracle in the visionary accounts concerns Joshua the high priest as a sign of the coming of God’s servant, the Branch who removes the guilt of the land in a single day (<a href="?bref=Zech.3.6-10">3:6-10</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Symbolic Crowning of Joshua (<a href="?bref=Zech.6.9-15">6:9-15</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Zechariah is told to go into the house of Josiah son of Zephaniah, take silver and gold from some returnees from Babylon, make a crown, and put it on the head of Joshua the priest as a symbol of the royal and priestly king, the Branch, the builder of the temple. After the ceremony the crown is to be hung in the temple as a memorial of those who gave the silver and the gold. The last verse (<a href="?bref=Zech.6.15">6:15</a>) seems to say that just as gold and silver from exiles was used to symbolize the crowning of the coming king of the kingdom, so exiles, “those who are far off,” will also participate in the completion of the temple. Then Zechariah’s hearers will know God sent him to prophesy. This will all take place when and if they will diligently obey the voice of the Lord.</p>
<p class="h3">The Question about Fasting and Morality (<a href="?bref=Zech.7.1-8.23">7:1–8:23</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">A delegation from Bethel (10 miles or 16.1 kilometers north of Jerusalem) came to Jerusalem in the fourth year of Darius (518 <span class="era">BC</span>). Work on the temple had been going on for two years. The purpose of this visit was to entreat the favor of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Zech.7.2">7:2</a>) and to ask the priests and the prophets if they should continue to fast as they had done since the temple was destroyed 70 years earlier (v <a href="?bref=Zech.7.3">3</a>). The Lord told Zechariah to ask why they were fasting—for the Lord or for selfish motives? The answer to the question of fasting seems to be that God desires truth, justice, and covenant-love more than fasting. Zechariah reiterates the message the Lord had already given his people by the former prophets. The last section in the first part of Zechariah is a decalogue of promises (<a href="?bref=Zech.8.1-23">8:1-23</a>). The ten promises begin with the words “Thus says the Lord” or “The word of the Lord came to me.” The last word of God is not judgment but promise, hope, forgiveness, and restoration.</p>
<p class="h3">The Oracles of the Lord (chs <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-12.14">9–12</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The last half of the book of Zechariah (chs <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-14.21">9–14</a>) falls into two nearly equal parts: chapters <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-11.17">9–11</a> (46 verses) and chapters <a href="?bref=Zech.12.1-14.21">12–14</a> (44 verses). Each part begins with the words “An oracle” (<a href="?bref=Zech.9.1">9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.12.1">12:1</a>). Both “oracles” are primarily eschatological. The first part (chs <a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-11.17">9–11</a>) is concerned with the restoration of the tribes to Palestine (<a href="?bref=Zech.9.11-17">9:11-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.10.6-12">10:6-12</a>). In order to accomplish this, the Lord will rid Palestine and Syria of opponents to his rule (<a href="?bref=Zech.9.1-8">9:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.11.1-3">11:1-3</a>), remove the evil shepherds (rulers; <a href="?bref=Zech.10.2b-5">10:2b-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.11.4-17">11:4-17</a>), and the Prince of Peace will come (<a href="?bref=Zech.9.9-10">9:9-10</a>). The last “oracle” of Zechariah (<a href="?bref=Zech.12.1-14.21">12:1–14:21</a>) is also eschatological. This time the concern is primarily that of Jerusalem and Judah. Twice Jerusalem is attacked by the nations (<a href="?bref=Zech.12.1-8">12:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.14.1-5">14:1-5</a>). Each time the Lord fights for Jerusalem, Judah, and the house of David. Jerusalem weeps and mourns for an unidentified martyr (<a href="?bref=Zech.12.10-14">12:10-14</a>). The martyr could be called the “good” shepherd who is killed and his sheep scattered (<a href="?bref=Zech.13.7-9">13:7-9</a>). Jesus referred to this passage in connection with his arrest (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.31">Mt 26:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.27">Mk 14:27</a>). A fountain will be opened for the house of David, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem will be cleansed from sin, idolatry, and false prophets (<a href="?bref=Zech.13.1-6">Zec 13:1-6</a>). The new Jerusalem will remain aloft on its site and the land around it will be turned into a plain (<a href="?bref=Zech.14.10-11">14:10-11</a>). There will be no night nor extreme temperatures in the new Jerusalem. Living waters will flow from Jerusalem, and the Lord will become King of all the earth. Those who fight against Jerusalem will be destroyed, but those who survive will worship the Lord year by year by keeping the Feast of Booths.</p>
<p>The last scene in the book of Zechariah is a picture of the world after Armageddon, a new world cleansed of sin. It will be a time of peace and security. When God comes to reign, everything will become holy. The warhorses will become as holy as the priest’s turban, and the ordinary cooking vessel will be as temple vessels. The Canaanite or trader will be eliminated. There will be no difference between Jew and Gentile, as long as one worships the Lord of Hosts as King.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=PostexilicPeriod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Postexilic Period</a>; <a href="?item=Prophecy_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophecy</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetProphetess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophet, Prophetess</a>; <a href="?item=ZechariahPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Zechariah (Person) #20</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>