<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Zedekiah">
  <title>Zedekiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ZEDEKIAH</p>
<p class="list">1. Judah’s last king and a key political figure in the fateful final decade of the southern kingdom. His reign (597–586 <span class="era">BC</span>) spanned Nebuchadnezzar’s two attacks on Jerusalem, in 597 and 586. The first attack was in reprisal for the rebellion of Josiah’s son, Jehoiakim (609–598 <span class="era">BC</span>), against Nebuchadnezzar; however, by the time his forces captured Jerusalem, Jehoiakim was dead and had been succeeded by his 18-year-old son Jehoiachin. Nebuchadnezzar deposed the young king and deported him to Babylon, along with the elite of the nation: government officials, army officers, and craftsmen. As Jehoiachin’s replacement, Nebuchadnezzar appointed his uncle Mattaniah, a younger brother of Jehoiakim and of the earlier, short-lived King Jehoahaz (609 <span class="era">BC</span>). Mattaniah was thus the third son of Josiah to occupy the throne of Judah. The Babylonian king named him Zedekiah, which means “the Lord is my righteousness.”</p>
<p class="list-text">Zedekiah found himself in a difficult position as Judah’s king. Many evidently still regarded Jehoiachin as the real king (cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.28.1-4">Jer 28:1-4</a>). Certainly the Judeans deported to Babylonia dated events by reference to Jehoiachin (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.27">2 Kgs 25:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.2">Ez 1:2</a>). Though the Babylonians exacted from Zedekiah an oath of loyalty (<a href="?bref=2Chr.36.13">2 Chr 36:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.17.13-18">Ez 17:13-18</a>), evidence suggests that they too viewed Zedekiah’s predecessor as the legitimate king and Zedekiah as regent. They may have been holding him in reserve for possible restoration to power, should events require it.</p>
<p class="list-text">Judah was filled with a false optimism that could hardly have helped the new king. It was confidently expected that the deportation of the leading citizens would be only temporary; prophets were guaranteeing that Babylon’s power would be broken within two years (<a href="?bref=Jer.28.2-4">Jer 28:2-4</a>). They were opposed by a few prophets led by Jeremiah, whose message found little support.</p>
<p class="list-text">Pressure both from within the nation and from without was put on Zedekiah to change his political allegiance. In the fourth year of his reign (593 <span class="era">BC</span>), the neighboring states of Ammon, Moab, Tyre, and Sidon formed a coalition to fight for independence from Babylon. Envoys were sent to Zedekiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.27.1-3">Jer 27:1-3</a>). However, Jeremiah advised the king not to get involved. In the same year, according to <a href="?bref=Jer.51.59">Jeremiah 51:59</a>, Zedekiah visited Babylon. He may have been summoned to affirm his loyalty and to explain his role in the political situation. The planned rebellion did not occur, perhaps because aid from Egypt failed to materialize.</p>
<p class="list-text">Within the Judean court a strong pro-Egyptian party existed. This party saw Egypt as an ally for breaking away from their eastern master, just like the advisers of King Hezekiah a century before (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.31.1-3">Is 31:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.36.6">36:6</a>). Zedekiah, finding it difficult to resist this political pressure, eventually transferred his allegiance to Egypt.</p>
<p class="list-text">Hophra (589–570 <span class="era">BC</span>), Psammetichus’s heir to the Egyptian throne, organized a joint rebellion in the west against Babylon. According to <a href="?bref=Ezek.21.18-32">Ezekiel 21:18-32</a> and <a href="?bref=Ezek.25.12-17">25:12-17</a>, Judah and Ammon supported him, while Edom and Philistia shrewdly abstained. Zedekiah was rebuked by the prophet Ezekiel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.13-18">Ez 17:13-18</a>) for breaking his oath to Nebuchadnezzar (cf. <a href="?bref=2Chr.36.13">2 Chr 36:13</a>) and rebelling against him by sending envoys to Egypt to negotiate for military support.</p>
<p class="list-text">In the face of this western uprising engineered by his Egyptian rival, Nebuchadnezzar was forced to march westward. Setting up headquarters at Riblah in northern Syria, he decided to make Jerusalem his prime target (<a href="?bref=Ezek.21.18-23">Ez 21:18-23</a>). The ensuing siege of Jerusalem was temporarily lifted due to an Egyptian attack but afterward was resumed until the city fell. Zedekiah, fleeing eastward with his troops, was caught near Jericho and taken north to Nebuchadnezzar at Riblah. There he was put on trial for breaking his promises of vassalage. By way of punishment, his sons were killed before his eyes. This tragic sight was the last he ever saw, since his eyes were then put out. He was taken in chains to Babylon, where he eventually died in prison (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.5-7">2 Kgs 25:5-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.39.7">Jer 39:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.52.8-11">52:8-11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.12.13">Ez 12:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Kenaanah’s son and one of the prophets who spoke falsely to kings Ahab of Israel and Jehoshaphat of Judah, telling them that the Lord would give Ahab victory over the Syrians at Ramoth-gilead (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.11">1 Kgs 22:11</a>). After hearing Micaiah’s contrary prediction that Ahab would in fact be killed in the battle, Zedekiah, in anger, struck Micaiah (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.24">24</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Jeconiah’s son and a descendant of David through Solomon’s line (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.16">1 Chr 3:16</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Leading priest who affirmed Nehemiah’s covenant during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.1">Neh 10:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Maaseiah’s son, who, according to Jeremiah, King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon would kill by roasting in fire for his adultery and lying words (<a href="?bref=Jer.29.21-23">Jer 29:21-23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. Hananiah’s son and a prince in Judah during King Jehoiakim’s reign (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.12">Jer 36:12</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>