<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ZephaniahBookof">
  <title>Zephaniah, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ZEPHANIAH, Book of</p>
<p class="fl">One of the books of the Minor Prophets in the OT.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurposeandTeaching">Purpose and Teaching</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">According to the editorial heading (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.1">Zep 1:1</a>), Zephaniah prophesied during the reign of Josiah (640–609 <span class="era">BC</span>). His family tree is given in an unusually full form. Some scholars have suggested that his great-great-grandfather was King Hezekiah (715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>). But remarkably there is no Jewish or Christian tradition to support the suggestion, which there probably would have been if it had been true. His own name, meaning “he whom the Lord protects or hides,” was not uncommon and was a testimony to the keeping power of God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</p>
<p class="fl">Zephaniah probably prophesied around 630 <span class="era">BC</span>. The fall of Nineveh (612 <span class="era">BC</span>) had not yet occurred (<a href="?bref=Zeph.2.13-15">2:13-15</a>). Josiah’s reign falls into two periods, dividing at 622 <span class="era">BC</span>. In that year, while the temple was being cleared of pagan articles, the Book of the Law was found, which gave momentum to Josiah’s religious reforms (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.1-20">2 Kgs 22</a>). The unreformed state of affairs described by Zephaniah (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.4-12">Zep 1:4-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.1-4">3:1-4</a>) points to a date before 622, at least for his denunciations. The prophet addressed Judah, the southern kingdom, and in particular the civil and religious authorities in Jerusalem. He most probably prophesied during the reign of Josiah, who came to the throne at the age of eight.</p>
<p>The negative parts of the book concerning the sin and punishment of Judah—now fulfilled—would serve as a serious warning against disobedience to God. Moreover, the fulfillment of Zephaniah’s prophetic threats would serve to enhance the positive side of the book, confirming the hope of completion in the experience of a fresh generation of God’s people.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">Politically, the Assyrian Empire had spread westward and held Palestine in its grip. The long reign of Manasseh (696–642 <span class="era">BC</span>) had been a period of total subservience to Assyria. Political subservience as an Assyrian vassal meant religious subservience to the gods of Assyria, especially worship of the heavenly bodies (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.5">2 Kgs 21:5</a>). Zephaniah complained of this sin (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.5">Zep 1:5</a>). When the door opened to one foreign religion, others naturally came in. Once the exclusiveness of the worship of the God of Israel was abandoned, Palestinian cults were openly accepted. The Canaanite Baal was blatantly worshiped (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.3">2 Kgs 21:3</a>), as Zephaniah attested (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.4">Zep 1:4</a>). Zephaniah condemned the worshipers of Molech (v <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.5">5</a>), who sacrificed children to the Ammonite god (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.7">1 Kgs 11:7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.10">2 Kgs 23:10</a>). International imperialism meant a weakening of national culture, so that foreign customs were practiced, probably with religious overtones (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.8-9">Zep 1:8-9</a>).</p>
<p>The reign of Josiah brought changes, marking a political and religious turning point. Assyria, preoccupied with troubles on the eastern and northern frontiers and unable to consolidate its acquisitions, became unable to reinforce its authority in the west. This weakness induced Josiah to launch a national liberation movement. He threw off the yoke of Assyria and expanded his sphere of influence northward into the territory of the old northern kingdom. From a religious standpoint, he completely dissociated himself and his country from the religions that prevailed in Judah and recalled the nation to a pure and exclusive faith in the God of Israel. The book of Zephaniah shows that there was at least one person who shared his ideals. His prophetic ministry undoubtedly paved the way for Josiah’s subsequent reformation. He was a contemporary of Jeremiah, at least for the early part of that prophet’s career (Jeremiah began prophesying in 627 <span class="era">BC</span>).</p>
<p>Scholars have suggested that Zephaniah’s prophesying was prompted in part by attacks of the Scythians. The Greek historian Herodotus tells how the barbaric Scythians overran western Asia and reached as far south as the Egyptian frontier at about the time that Zephaniah prophesied. There is now much less inclination to believe Herodotus’s tale and relate Zephaniah’s prophetic ministry to it. There is no objective evidence for Scythian attacks on so large a scale as Herodotus claimed. Probably Zephaniah spoke simply out of a theological necessity, as he himself claimed (e.g., <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.17">1:17</a>). From his inspired standpoint, he foresaw that a clash involving divine intervention and human downfall was unavoidable.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeandTeaching">Purpose and Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">As Zephaniah prophesied in God’s name, he denounced the religious sins of Judah and the corruption rampant among both civil and religious authorities. He foretold the downfall of the nation that actually occurred in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. The moral and religious landslide could only culminate in a political avalanche of destruction that would engulf the nation. This avalanche is called by Zephaniah “the Day of the Lord.” It was not a new term, and the prophet knew that it would arouse terror in the hearts of his hearers. Amos used it, and even in his time it was well established (<a href="?bref=Amos.5.18-20">Am 5:18-20</a>). Isaiah was the first to use the expression in the southern kingdom (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.6-22">Is 2:6-22</a>, see v <a href="?bref=Isa.2.12">12</a>). In this, as in a number of respects, Zephaniah was a latter-day Isaiah called by God to reapply truths earlier prophesied by Isaiah to a later generation.</p>
<p>The theme of the Day of the Lord refers to a time when the Lord would decisively intervene in the world to establish his sovereignty. Hostile elements would be swept aside. The enemies of God, sinners against his moral will, would be exposed and punished. It was associated with judgment upon those who did not acknowledge God’s sovereignty—especially Gentiles, but also sinful Israel. The emphasis on the suffering of God’s people was intended to correct the popular assumption that other nations would be the sole target of divine judgment.</p>
<p>The “day” also would vindicate those who were loyal to God. It guaranteed the rehabilitation of his oppressed supporters. Zephaniah developed this two-sided phenomenon in order to communicate the truth of God to his own generation. It is “a day of the wrath of God” (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.15,18">Zep 1:15, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.2">2:2</a>), when his reaction to human sin would be demonstrated. Its target was not only other nations but Judah as well, both Jerusalem, the capital (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.10-13">1:10-13</a>), and the other cities of Judah.</p>
<p>Zephaniah also had a positive message for the people of Judah. For the prophets, the message of salvation did not cancel the message of doom. Judgment would come first, then salvation would follow. But the period of tribulation could not be avoided. The prophet’s grim descriptions of “the day of wrath” are interpreted as dire warnings and implicit pleas to the people of Judah to abandon their complacent, sinful ways.</p>
<p>Clearly, Zephaniah’s role under God was to reapply earlier truths sadly forgotten by his own generation. Zephaniah was able to foresee God’s judgment of Judah and the world. But he also proclaimed permanent truths concerning the nature of God and his providential relationship to the world and concerning the responsibilities of the people of God.</p>
<p>The importance of the book of Zephaniah for the NT lies in the phraseology about the Day of the Lord. There are a number of allusions to this aspect of his message (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.41">Mt 13:41</a> [<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.3">Zep 1:3</a>]; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.17">Rv 6:17</a> [<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.14">1:14</a>]; <a href="?bref=Rev.14.5">14:5</a> [<a href="?bref=Zeph.3.13">3:13</a>]; <a href="?bref=Rev.16.1">16:1</a> [<a href="?bref=Zeph.3.8">3:8</a>]). These echoes stress Zephaniah’s importance beyond his own time. He contributed to the total biblical picture of a God who intervenes in human history and will establish his kingdom. Zephaniah’s descriptions are a pattern for events that will mark the end of history.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="fl">The heading (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.1">Zep 1:1</a>) introduces Zephaniah, gives the historical setting, and above all stresses his meditation on the divine word.</p>
<p>The first major part of the book is <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.2-2.3">1:2–2:3</a>. It subdivides into four units: verses <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.2-7,8-13,14-18">2-7, 8-13, 14-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.1-3">2:1-3</a>. Verses <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.2-7">2-7</a> include Judah in a forecast of universal destruction. Zephaniah used traditional material to stress that God’s people were by no means exempt, as they often chose to believe (cf. <a href="?bref=Amos.5.18-20">Am 5:18-20</a>). The prophet supported his startling revelation with reasoned statements regarding the religious deviations practiced in Jerusalem. The image of sacrifice was used ironically, portraying Judah as the victim.</p>
<p>The national administration and members of the royal family were guilty (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.8-13">Zep 1:8-13</a>). Superstitions were punctiliously observed, yet basic divine commands against stealing and fraudulent gain went unheeded. Zephaniah saw the enemy attack on the north side of Jerusalem as an illustration of God’s punishment of dishonest traders (cf. <a href="?bref=Amos.8.5-6">Am 8:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.10-11">Mi 6:10-11</a>).</p>
<p>There follows a shocking and terrifying description of the grimness of the coming “Day” (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.14-18">Zep 1:14-18</a>). The prophet stirred up a complacent people who did not want to hear God’s message. He frightened them into reality with a monotonous drumbeat of doom and destruction. Judah would be the demoralized target of God’s wrath. Their wealth had secured luxurious imports but could not prevent divine judgment.</p>
<p>The prophet completed his sermon with an appeal for repentance (<a href="?bref=Zeph.2.1-3">2:1-3</a>). Having emotionally stirred his audience from their apathy, he was able to bring the good news that all was not yet lost. A penitential assembly at the temple and the intercession of the spiritually minded and obedient among God’s people might prevent destruction. God’s punishment of foreign nations is described in the second main part of the book (<a href="?bref=Zeph.2.4-15">2:4-15</a>). Representative states are named to the west, east, south, and north of Judah. In the context of the previous material, it amplifies the universal nature of the Day of the Lord. Like the first part, it subdivides into four passages: verses <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.4-7,8-11,12">2:4-7, 8-11, 12</a>, and <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.13-15">13-15</a>.</p>
<p>The subject of the first passage is the Philistines. In the case of the cities of Gaza and Ekron, there is a play on words typical of Hebrew prophecy. Both names contain doom within their very sound. The Philistines are labeled as trespassers because they were illegal immigrants from Crete into the Promised Land, which was intended for God’s own people.</p>
<p>Zephaniah predicted that Moab and Ammon would suffer attack for their overbearing attitude and their annexation of Judean territory (<a href="?bref=Zeph.2.8-11">2:8-11</a>). God would come to the aid of his covenant people.</p>
<p>The first two main sections have spelled out at length a message of judgment for both Judah and the surrounding nations. This twofold message is now repeated in a much shorter form in the third main section (<a href="?bref=Zeph.3.1-8">3:1-8</a>). Zephaniah criticized Jerusalem in its combined role of political capital and religious center. The responsibility of being God’s representatives rested too lightly on the shoulders of government and temple officials. Civil leaders abused their powers by demanding bribes and even killing their political opponents. Instead of being the shepherds of the people (cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.1-31">Ez 34</a>), they were beasts of prey (cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.22.25-27">Ez 22:25-27</a>). The prophets misused their gifts for their own selfish interests, while the priests broke the strict regulations of the temple. The lessons of history went unheeded; they had not learned caution and reverence. The conclusion is clear: Judah could not escape punishment in the coming Day of the Lord but would suffer with other nations.</p>
<p>The outworking of God’s will for both Judah and the nations is in view in the final main section (<a href="?bref=Zeph.3.9-20">Zep 3:9-20</a>), but this time from a quite different aspect. Punishment was not God’s last word for his own people or even for the nations at large. Ultimately God’s will is not destruction but salvation (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.9">2 Pt 3:9</a>). The section has three parts: <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.9-10,11-13">Zephaniah 3:9-10, 11-13</a>, and <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.14-20">14-20</a>. Verses <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.9-10">9-10</a> deal with the conversion of the nations. This remarkable passage looks forward with divinely guaranteed certainty to the willing submission of Gentiles to the God of Israel. Their turning to God would not be based on human initiative but would originate in the providential activity of God. Lips defiled by worship of pagan gods would be purified and devoted solely to the adoration of the God of Israel. People from remote parts of the earth, here illustrated as the remote south beyond the Ethiopian Nile, would come as suppliants, as if they were scattered Jews returning home.</p>
<p>God’s own people would be marked by a change of heart (<a href="?bref=Zeph.3.11-13">3:11-13</a>). By now they would have been purged of the proud people who put themselves before God in the sphere of politics and religion. They would be a purified people who humbly trusted in God. To them were promised the blessings of paradise.</p>
<p>The last passage speaks of coming joys (<a href="?bref=Zeph.3.14-20">3:14-20</a>). The prophet projects himself into the future, to the time when God’s judgment would be over and the time of salvation had dawned. God’s people would rejoice in the presence of their Lord. Fear and demoralization would be canceled by God’s powerful presence and radiant joy. His joy would infectiously communicate itself to them so that they too would rejoice. Moreover, his joy would be a reaction to the transformation he was working in the lives of his people (v <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.17">17</a>; “he will renew you in his love,” <span class="sc">rsv</span>). A necessary part of this transformation would feature the vindication of God’s suffering people. They would be brought to a position of honor, as the visible representatives of the God of glory. Ultimately, God’s power would be revealed through a people of power.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=Josiah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Josiah #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>