<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Zerubbabel">
  <title>Zerubbabel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ZERUBBABEL</p>
<p class="fl">Babylonian-born Jew who returned to Palestine in 538 <span class="era">BC</span> to serve as governor of Jerusalem under Persian rule. The name presumably means “seed [offspring] of Babylon,” referring to someone born in Babylon.</p>
<p>The exact identity of Zerubbabel’s biological father is uncertain. All biblical references except one mention Shealtiel as his father (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.2,8">Ezr 3:2, 8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.5.2">5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.12.1">Neh 12:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1,12-14">Hg 1:1, 12-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.2,23">2:2, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.1.12-13">Mt 1:12-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.27">Lk 3:27</a>). This would make Zerubbabel the grandson of the Davidic king Jehoiachin. However, <a href="?bref=1Chr.3.19">1 Chronicles 3:19</a> identifies Pedaiah, the brother of Shealtiel, as Zerubbabel’s father.</p>
<p>Two solutions have been proposed. Many scholars have assumed that Shealtiel died before fathering an heir. His brother, Pedaiah, would then have fathered Zerubbabel by Shealtiel’s widow. Hence, Zerubbabel would have retained the name of Shealtiel rather than Pedaiah in accordance with the law of levirate marriage (<a href="?bref=Deut.25.5-10">Dt 25:5-10</a>). This solution is weakened by its lack of textual support; similarly, the Chronicler would hardly have failed to state such an important piece of information if he had been desirous of “correcting” an error pertaining to Zerubbabel’s parentage.</p>
<p>A simpler solution is obtained by reading the Septuagint text of <a href="?bref=1Chr.3.19">1 Chronicles 3:19</a>, which lists Salathiel (Shealtiel) as the father of Zerubbabel. In this way, the single reference to 1 Chronicles may be harmonized with the other verses cited above.</p>
<p>In either case, whether Shealtiel or Pedaiah was Zerubbabel’s biological father, it is clear that Zerubbabel was of Davidic lineage and was viewed by members of the Israelite community as a viable candidate for leading them back to a position of power.</p>
<p>Following the edict of Cyrus in 538 <span class="era">BC</span>, Jews were permitted to return to Palestine and reclaim their former homeland. Zerubbabel was appointed governor, and probably by the decade of 529–520 had started work on the reconstruction of the Jerusalem temple. However, because of several discouraging events, little was accomplished until the year 520 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The writings of Haggai and Zechariah reveal much information about Zerubbabel’s standing in the community. These two prophets evidently viewed Jeshua and Zerubbabel as the two men chosen by God for the task. Accordingly, in many of their oracles, support for one or both men is openly stated (e.g., <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.21-23">Hg 2:21-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.3.8">Zec 3:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.4.6-7">4:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.12">6:12</a>). The prophets viewed Jeshua and Zerubbabel’s work as being messianic. This is most clearly seen in the vision of Zechariah (<a href="?bref=Zech.4.11-14">Zec 4:11-14</a>). In the vision, two olive branches, one on either side of the lampstand, are identified as “the two anointed who stand by the Lord of the whole earth.” As the context clearly shows, none other than Jeshua (or Joshua; named in <a href="?bref=Zech.3.1-9">3:1-9</a>) and Zerubbabel (named in <a href="?bref=Zech.4.6-10">4:6-10</a>) are meant. Because of his association with the rebuilding of the temple in Jerusalem, Zerubbabel had been accorded a place of great honor in Jewish tradition.</p>
<p>Some hold that Zerubbabel was known to the Persians as Sheshbazzar. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Sheshbazzar_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sheshbazzar</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>