<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ZichriZicri">
  <title>Zichri*, Zicri</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ZICHRI*, ZICRI</p>
<p class="list">1. Kohathite Levite and a descendant of Izhar (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.21">Ex 6:21</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. One of Shimei’s sons from Benjamin’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.19">1 Chr 8:19</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. One of Shashak’s sons from Benjamin’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.23">1 Chr 8:23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. One of Jeroham’s sons from Benjamin’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.27">1 Chr 8:27</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Ancestor of Mattaniah. Mattaniah returned with Zerubbabel to Israel following the exile (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.15">1 Chr 9:15</a>); Zicri is probably identifiable with Zabdi in <a href="?bref=Neh.11.17">Nehemiah 11:17</a>.</p>
<p class="list">6. Descendant of Eliezer, the son of Moses. His son, Shelomoth, was in charge of the treasuries of the dedicated gifts (<a href="?bref=1Chr.26.25">1 Chr 26:25</a>).</p>
<p class="list">7. Father of Eliezer, the chief officer of the Reubenites during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.16">1 Chr 27:16</a>).</p>
<p class="list">8. Father of Amasiah, a volunteer in charge of 200,000 men during Jehoshaphat’s reign (<a href="?bref=2Chr.17.16">2 Chr 17:16</a>).</p>
<p class="list">9. Father of Elishaphat, a participant in the conspiracy against Athaliah led by Jehoiada (<a href="?bref=2Chr.23.1">2 Chr 23:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Mighty man of Ephraim who participated in Pekah’s subjugation of Judah. Zicri killed Ahaz’s son Maaseiah, Azrikam the commander of the palace, and Elkanah the king’s deputy (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.7">2 Chr 28:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Father of Joel, overseer of the Benjaminites who returned to Jerusalem following the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.9">Neh 11:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. Levite who served as a priest and the head of the clan of Abijah during the days of Joiakim the high priest (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.17">Neh 12:17</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>