<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Salvation">
  <title>Salvation</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SALVATION</p>
<p class="fl">God’s way of providing people deliverance from sin and death. Scripture reveals God but it also reveals his plan to save the human race. In that sense, salvation is a major theme in both the OT and NT.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The concept of salvation is represented by various terms and situations in both Testaments. Among several Hebrew words that mean “deliver” or “save,” the Hebrew verb <span class="hebrew">yasha‘</span> and derivatives are most frequently translated by English versions as “save” or “salvation.” Frequency in the English Bible depends upon the version considered. For example, in the OT “salvation” is found 74 times in the <span class="sc">nlt</span>, 80 times in the <span class="sc">niv</span>, 90 times in the <span class="sc">rsv</span>, 111 times in the <span class="sc">nasb</span>, and 119 times in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>. Salvation is not used as a technical term in the OT and is ascribed to both individuals and God. Leaders like Samson (<a href="?bref=Judg.13.5">Jgs 13:5</a>) or David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.6">2 Sm 8:6</a>) are used of the Lord to bring deliverance to God’s people.</p>
<p>Israel’s concept of salvation was rooted in the historical experience of the exodus. This momentous occasion was an opportunity to witness the salvation of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.13">Ex 14:13</a>) firsthand. Poets (<a href="?bref=Ps.106.8">Ps 106:8</a>) and prophets (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.3">Is 43:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.13.4">Hos 13:4</a>) later reiterated God’s salvation when recalling the exodus experience. Israel’s understanding of salvation was worked out in historical instances like Sennacherib’s attack on Jerusalem in 701 <span class="era">BC</span>, when the Lord declared that he would save the city for his name’s sake (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.34">2 Kgs 19:34</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.30,35">18:30, 35</a>). Israel’s opportunity to see God’s salvation through various leaders and situations corroborated this understanding of God as the God of salvation.</p>
<p>Israel’s response to God’s deliverance was primarily praise, as evidenced so often in the psalms (<a href="?bref=Ps.3.8">Pss 3:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.9.14">9:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.21.1">21:1</a>) and earlier poetic passages (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.2">Ex 15:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.1">1 Sm 2:1</a>). In addition, they directed petitions and pleas for help to the Lord for his salvation—whether from enemies (<a href="?bref=Ps.35.3">Pss 35:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.38.22">38:22</a>), sickness (<a href="?bref=Ps.69.29">69:29</a>), or battle (<a href="?bref=Ps.140.7">140:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.144.10-11">144:10-11</a>)—and in faith expected his deliverance (<a href="?bref=Ps.35.9">35:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.65.5">65:5</a>).</p>
<p>The prophets emphasized the eschatological (end-time) aspect of salvation. God’s ability to save was revealed by his great works in the past, which thus promoted the anticipation of his work of deliverance in the future. This future hope was for the nation of Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.17">Is 45:17</a>) but anticipated universal deliverance (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.6">49:6</a>). The prophets looked forward to deliverance and return from exile in Babylon (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.25-26">Is 49:25-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.46.27">Jer 46:27</a>), yet they also spoke of an abiding future salvation (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.17">Is 45:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.51.6-8">51:6-8</a>). The messianic hope is indicated in passages that speak of an individual who will bring God’s salvation. Isaiah speaks of the Servant who brings salvation to the ends of the earth (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.6">49:6</a>), while Jeremiah writes of deliverance by God’s righteous Branch (<a href="?bref=Jer.23.5-6">Jer 23:5-6</a>). The mention of the king who brings salvation in <a href="?bref=Zech.9.9">Zechariah 9:9</a> reflects this messianic theme and is applied to Jesus Christ in <a href="?bref=Matt.21.4-5">Matthew 21:4-5</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In classical Greek the verb <span class="greek">sozo</span> (“to save”) and noun <span class="greek">soteria</span> (“salvation”) are used for the concept of “rescue,” “deliverance” or “salvation,” and even “well-being” or “health.” The Septuagint most frequently uses <span class="greek">sozo</span> to render the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">yasha‘</span> (“to save”), and the NT primarily employs <span class="greek">sozo</span> and its derivatives for the idea of salvation.</p>
<p>These Greek terms are generally used theologically in the NT, but examples of nontheological usage occur. In <a href="?bref=Acts.27.1-44">Acts 27</a>, these words refer to the threat and deliverance of the soldiers, sailors, and prisoners from shipwreck (vv <a href="?bref=Acts.27.20,31">20, 31</a>), as well as their well-being (v <a href="?bref=Acts.27.34">34</a>).</p>
<p>In the Gospels “salvation” is clearly connected with the OT concept of salvation; it is applied to the coming of Christ in Zechariah’s prophecy (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.69,71">Lk 1:69, 71</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.106.10">Pss 106:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.132.17">132:17</a>) and in Simeon’s hymn of praise (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.30">Lk 2:30</a>). While <span class="greek">soteria</span> does not occur frequently in the Gospels, the concept of salvation is implied in Jesus’ statement about entrance into the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.24-26">Mt 19:24-26</a>) and his miracles of healing (<a href="?bref=Luke.17.19">Lk 17:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.18.42">18:42</a>).</p>
<p>The NT teaches that salvation has its source in Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=2Tim.2.10">2 Tm 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.5.9">Heb 5:9</a>), who is the “author” and mediator of salvation (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.10">Heb 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.25">7:25</a>). Salvation is God’s work (<a href="?bref=1Thes.5.9">1 Thes 5:9</a>) and is offered by his grace (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.8-9">Eph 2:8-9</a>). The message of salvation is contained in the Scriptures (<a href="?bref=2Tim.3.15">2 Tm 3:15</a>) and is carried by those who proclaim the word of truth (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.13">Eph 1:13</a>). The appropriate response is repentance (<a href="?bref=2Cor.7.10">2 Cor 7:10</a>) and faith (<a href="?bref=2Tim.3.15">2 Tm 3:15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.9">1 Pt 1:9</a>). This was the preaching of the early church as it proclaimed the Savior Jesus (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.12">Acts 4:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.23-26">13:23-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.16.30-31">16:30-31</a>). Paul especially proclaimed the universality of God’s offer of salvation (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">Rom 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.2.11">Ti 2:11</a>). His desire was for Jews to be saved (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.1">Rom 10:1</a>), though he primarily preached the message of salvation to the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.11-13">11:11-13</a>).</p>
<p>Within the Scriptures there are many other terms associated with the concept of salvation. The new birth speaks of being made alive in Christ (“born again,” <a href="?bref=John.3.3">Jn 3:3</a>). Justification envisions one’s legal standing before God, while redemption speaks more of the means of salvation—the payment of a price to bring one back to God. Reconciliation speaks of a change in relationship and propitiation, which evokes the OT sacrificial system and points to the turning away of God’s wrath. These terms and others share some common ground with the biblical concept of salvation, but all point to the person and work of Jesus Christ the Savior.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=JustificationJustified_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Justification, Justified</a>; <a href="?item=Reconciliation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Reconciliation</a>; <a href="?item=RedeemerRedemption_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Redeemer, Redemption</a>; <a href="?item=Savior_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Savior</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>