<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SecondComingofChrist">
  <title>Second Coming of Christ*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SECOND COMING OF CHRIST*</p>
<p class="fl">The return of Jesus Christ to earth to complete the work of salvation.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TermsUsed">Terms Used</p>
<p class="fl">The doctrine is expressed by verbs such as “come,” “descend,” “appear,” and “is revealed” with Christ as the subject (e.g., “I will come again,” <a href="?bref=John.14.3">Jn 14:3</a>; “the Lord himself will descend,” <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.16">1 Thes 4:16</a>; “when he appears,” <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.28">1 Jn 2:28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.2">3:2</a>; “the day when the Son of man is revealed,” <a href="?bref=Luke.17.30">Lk 17:30</a>; “when the Lord Jesus is revealed from heaven,” <a href="?bref=2Thes.1.7">2 Thes 1:7</a>). It is expressed also by a variety of nouns, principally by “coming” (which is the regular translation of the Greek word <span class="greek">parousia</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “presence,” “visit,” “arrival,” “advent,” especially of a royal or distinguished person) but also by “appearing” (as in <a href="?bref=2Tim.4.8">2 Tm 4:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.2.13">Ti 2:13</a>), “revealing,” or “revelation” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.7">1 Cor 1:7</a>). These different verbs and nouns point to the same event but highlight different aspects of it, especially the manifestation of God’s glory in Christ when he comes. The time of this event is repeatedly referred to as “the Day,” sometimes absolutely (as in <a href="?bref=Rom.13.12">Rom 13:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.3.13">1 Cor 3:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.25">Heb 10:25</a>), more often with a qualification, such as “the day of Christ” (<a href="?bref=Phil.1.10">Phil 1:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.16">2:16</a>), “the day of the Lord” (<a href="?bref=1Thes.5.2">1 Thes 5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.2">2 Thes 2:2</a>), “the day of the Lord Jesus” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.5.5">1 Cor 5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.14">2 Cor 1:14</a>), “the day of Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=Phil.1.6">Phil 1:6</a>), and “the day of our Lord Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.8">1 Cor 1:8</a>). When such expressions are used, there is often some reference to the judgment to be passed at the coming of Christ: his day is “the day of judgment” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.4.17">1 Jn 4:17</a>) or “the day of wrath” (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.5">Rom 2:5</a>). For the people of God, however, it is “the day of redemption” (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.30">Eph 4:30</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheProclamationoftheNewTestament">The Proclamation of the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">That the second coming of Christ was an essential element in the gospel as preached in the apostolic age is clear from many NT writings (quoted below from the <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>The origin of the Second Coming is found in the teachings of Jesus before his death. Speaking of himself as the Son of Man, Jesus said, “The day when the Son of man is revealed” (<a href="?bref=Luke.17.30">Lk 17:30</a>) he will come “in clouds with great power and glory” (<a href="?bref=Mark.13.26">Mk 13:26</a>). This language is derived from the OT, especially from Daniel’s vision in which “one like a son of man” is brought “with the clouds of heaven” to receive everlasting dominion from the Ancient of Days (<a href="?bref=Dan.7.13-14">Dn 7:13-14</a>). A cloud or clouds regularly enveloped the divine glory in the OT (as in <a href="?bref=Exod.40.34">Ex 40:34</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.10-11">1 Kgs 8:10-11</a>); their mention in connection with the coming of the Son of Man indicates that, when he comes, the glory of God will be manifested in him. Jesus’ last reference to his second coming came at his trial before the Jewish authorities when, asked by the high priest to say whether or not he was “the Christ, the Son of the Blessed,” he replied, “I am; and you will see the Son of man seated at the right hand of Power, and coming with the clouds of heaven” (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.61-62">Mk 14:61-62</a>).</p>
<p>After the Gospels, the rest of the NT affirms the eventuality of Christ’s second coming. The record of Acts begins with the angels’ assurance at the ascension of Christ that “this Jesus, who was taken up from you into heaven, will come in the same way as you saw him go into heaven” (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.11">Acts 1:11</a>). The summaries of apostolic addresses that the book contains make repeated references to Jesus as “the one ordained by God to be judge of the living and the dead” (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.42">10:42</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.17.31">17:31</a>).</p>
<p>Writing to his converts in Thessalonica (c. <span class="era">AD</span> 51) a few weeks after they first heard and believed the gospel, Paul reminds them how they had “turned to God from idols, to serve a living and true God, and to wait for his Son from heaven, whom he raised from the dead, Jesus who delivers us from the wrath to come” (<a href="?bref=1Thes.1.9-10">1 Thes 1:9-10</a>). Here Jesus’ expected deliverance of his people from end-time judgment is put on the same plane as his historical resurrection; the Christian way of life embraces both serving God and waiting for Christ. This note of waiting for Christ is repeated and amplified several times in this short letter. A few years later Paul uses similar language when writing to his converts in Corinth (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.18.1-18">Acts 18:1-18</a>): “You are not lacking in any spiritual gift, as you wait for the revealing of our Lord Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.7">1 Cor 1:7</a>). And in what may have been his last letter he speaks of “the crown of righteousness” that the Lord will award him “on that Day, and not only to me,” he adds, “but also to all who have loved his appearing” (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.8">2 Tm 4:8</a>). To love his appearing and to wait for him are two different ways of expressing the same attitude.</p>
<p>The writer to the Hebrews encourages his readers with the assurance that in a little while “the coming one shall come and shall not tarry” (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.37">Heb 10:37</a>). James says that “the coming of the Lord is at hand” (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.8">Jas 5:8</a>). Peter speaks of the time “when the chief Shepherd is manifested” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.5.4">1 Pt 5:4</a>). The Revelation to John ends with the risen Lord’s promise, “Surely I am coming soon,” and the church’s response, “Amen. Come, Lord Jesus!” (<a href="?bref=Rev.22.20">Rv 22:20</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheSecondComingandtheResurrection">The Second Coming and the Resurrection</p>
<p class="fl">In 1 Thessalonians, written not more than 20 years after the death and resurrection of Christ, his coming again is presented by way of comfort and encouragement to those whose Christian friends had died. Paul had been compelled to leave Thessalonica before he had time to give his converts there as much teaching as they required, and when some of their number died shortly after his departure, their friends wondered if they would suffer some serious disadvantage at the Second Coming, in contrast to those who would still be alive to greet the returning Lord. No, says Paul, “those who have fallen asleep” will suffer no disadvantage. On the contrary, the first thing to happen when “the Lord himself will descend from heaven” is that “the dead in Christ will rise.” Only after that will those who survive until then be caught away to join them and be forever “with the Lord” (<a href="?bref=1Thes.4.15-17">1 Thes 4:15-17</a>). Fuller information on the same subject is given in 1 Corinthians, written about five years later. There the resurrection of believers is the full harvest that was inaugurated by the resurrection of Christ: “Christ the first fruits, then at his coming those who belong to Christ” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.23">1 Cor 15:23</a>). An additional revelation is imparted: not only will each believer who has died be raised in a “spiritual body” (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.44">44</a>) but also those who are still alive will be “changed” so as to have bodies suitable for life in resurrection. For dead and living believers alike, Paul proclaimed that “as we have borne the image of the man of dust [i.e., Adam; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.2.7">Gn 2:7</a>], we shall also bear the image of the man of heaven [i.e., the risen Christ]” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.49">1 Cor 15:49</a>). To the same effect, Paul writes (a few years later still) in <a href="?bref=Phil.3.20-21">Philippians 3:20-21</a> that from heaven “we await a Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ, who will change our lowly body to be like his glorious body.” A deeper unveiling of what this will involve is made in <a href="?bref=Rom.8.18-23">Romans 8:18-23</a>, where the resurrection of the people of Christ is the catalyst for the liberation and glorious renewal of all creation.</p>
<p class="h3">The Second Coming and Judgment</p>
<p class="fl">The association of judgment with the Second Coming arises in Jesus’ teaching in the Gospels. The association is equally plain in the epistles of the NT. Paul, in particular, put the subject on a personal level. He forbade premature judgment of fellow Christians: “Do not pronounce judgment before the time, before the Lord comes” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.4.5">1 Cor 4:5</a>). The Lord will conduct an investigation that will bring to light the hidden motives of the heart. Paul knew that his own apostolic work would be assessed on “the day of Christ” (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.16">Phil 2:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.2.19">1 Thes 2:19</a>). Elsewhere, Paul urges his converts to bear in mind that they, with himself, must appear before the divine tribunal, variously called “the judgment seat of God” (where “each of us shall give account of himself,” <a href="?bref=Rom.14.10-12">Rom 14:10-12</a>) or “the judgment seat of Christ” (where each will “receive good or evil, according to what he has done in the body,” <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.10">2 Cor 5:10</a>). It seems clear that this judgment is to take place at the second coming of Christ, who will then “judge the living and the dead” (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.1">2 Tm 4:1</a>). Because Paul was writing to Christians, he tended to concentrate on the judgment or assessment that the believers would experience at the Lord’s return. But he also made it plain that the same coming would bring judgment to those who opposed the Christian faith (<a href="?bref=2Thes.1.6-10">2 Thes 1:6-10</a>). This is made explicit in <a href="?bref=Acts.17.31">Acts 17:31</a>, where Paul told the Athenians that God “has fixed a day on which he will judge the world in righteousness by a man whom he has appointed.”</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DayoftheLord_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Day of the Lord</a>; <a href="?item=Eschatology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eschatology</a>; <a href="?item=Judgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judgment</a>; <a href="?item=JudgmentSeat_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judgment Seat</a>; <a href="?item=LastDays_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Last Days</a>; <a href="?item=Rapture_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Rapture</a>; <a href="?item=Resurrection_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Resurrection</a>; <a href="?item=RevelationBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Revelation, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=Tribulation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tribulation</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>