<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Seraiah">
  <title>Seraiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SERAIAH</p>
<p class="list"> 1. Royal secretary of King David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.17">2 Sm 8:17</a>); alternately called Sheva in <a href="?bref=2Sam.20.25">2 Samuel 20:25</a>, Shisha in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.3">1 Kings 4:3</a>, and Shavsha in <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.16">1 Chronicles 18:16</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Chief priest in Jerusalem at the time of its destruction by the Babylonians in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. He was taken by Nebuzaradan, the captain of the guard, to Nebuchadnezzar at Riblah, where he was put to death (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.18">2 Kgs 25:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.52.24">Jer 52:24</a>). <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.14">First Chronicles 6:14</a> records Seraiah as the son of Azariah, the father of Jehozadak and a descendant of Levi through Aaron’s line.</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Son of Tanhumeth the Netophathite and one of the captains of the Judean forces who sought clemency from Nebuchadnezzar under Gedaliah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.23">2 Kgs 25:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.40.8">Jer 40:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Judahite, the son of Kenaz, the brother of Othniel and Joab’s father (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.13-14">1 Chr 4:13-14</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Simeonite, the son of Asiel and Joshibiah’s father (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.35">1 Chr 4:35</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. One of the men who returned with Zerubbabel to Judah following the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.2">Ezr 2:2</a>); called Azariah in <a href="?bref=Neh.7.7">Nehemiah 7:7</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Azariah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Azariah #23</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Father of Ezra the scribe. Ezra returned to Jerusalem during the reign of King Artaxerxes I of Persia (464–424 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.1">Ezr 7:1</a>). He is perhaps identical with #2 above, in which case Jehozadak would be Ezra’s brother.</p>
<p class="list"> 8. One of the priests who set his seal on the covenant of Ezra (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.2">Neh 10:2</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Son of Hilkiah and a priest living in Jerusalem during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.11">Neh 11:11</a>); called Azariah in <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.11">1 Chronicles 9:11</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Azariah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Azariah #10</a>.</p>
<p class="list">10. One of the leaders of the priests who returned with Zerubbabel and Jeshua to Judah after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.1">Neh 12:1</a>). His house in the next generation was headed by Meraiah. He is perhaps identical with #6 above.</p>
<p class="list">11. Son of Azriel who, with Jerahmeel and Shelemiah, was ordered by King Jehoiakim of Judah (609–598 <span class="era">BC</span>) to capture Baruch and Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.26">Jer 36:26</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. Son of Neriah and the official who accompanied King Zedekiah of Judah (597–586 <span class="era">BC</span>) to Babylon. Seraiah was to relay Jeremiah’s message against Babylon (<a href="?bref=Jer.51.59-61">Jer 51:59-61</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>