<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ServantoftheLord">
  <title>Servant of the Lord</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SERVANT OF THE LORD</p>
<p class="fl">Title applied to a variety of persons in the Bible. The basic term, “servant,” covers a range of meanings. Used some 800 times in the OT alone, “servant” refers to a slave, to an officer close to the king, or to the chosen leader of God’s people.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Isa.41.8-9">Isaiah 41:8-9</a> defines this highest servanthood as something granted by God’s grace: “But you, Israel, my servant, Jacob whom I have chosen . . . ; you whom I took from the ends of the earth, and called from its farthest corners, saying to you, ‘You are my servant. . . . ’ ” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). This title is thus applicable to heroes of faith and action—to the patriarchs (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.24">Gn 26:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.25">Ez 28:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.25">37:25</a>), to Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.31">Ex 14:31</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.53,56">1 Kgs 8:53, 56</a>), to David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.26-29">2 Sm 7:26-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.33.21-26">Jer 33:21-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.24">Ez 37:24</a>) and his descendants (as Hezekiah, Eliakim, Zerubbabel—<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.23">Hg 2:23</a>), to the prophets (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.10">2 Kgs 10:10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.25">14:25</a>), and to other faithful Israelites, such as Joshua and Caleb (<a href="?bref=Num.14.24">Nm 14:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.29">Jos 24:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.2.8">Jgs 2:8</a>).</p>
<p>Prophets other than Isaiah employ this term, but only Zechariah joins him in giving an apparently messianic prediction to this name. <a href="?bref=Zech.3.8">Zechariah 3:8</a> says, “Hear now, O Joshua the high priest, you and your friends who sit before you, for they are men of good omen: behold, I will bring my servant the Branch” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). Some would see Zerubbabel as the individual in view here (cf. <a href="?bref=Zech.6.12">Zec 6:12</a>); however, the use of “Branch” is decidedly messianic in Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.1">Is 11:1</a>) and Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.33.15">Jer 33:15</a>).</p>
<p>“<span class="ital">The</span> servant of the Lord,” in specialized biblical usage, points to the Messiah while also alluding to Isaiah’s central message. Though Isaiah, with others, employs “servant” with a range of significations, he composed some passages known as the Servant Songs. These distinctive sections of his book are distinguishable in content, but they cannot be extracted from the surrounding context without disrupting the flow of prophecy. Isaiah’s focus is on the future Messiah-servant. None can question the NT’s unanimous messianic interpretation of Isaiah’s servant, nor its application of this understanding to Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>A “servant Christology” pervades Acts (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.13,26">Acts 3:13, 26</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.27,30">4:27, 30</a>), and 1 Peter, with numerous allusions in the Gospels. Jesus himself quotes <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">Isaiah 53</a> explicitly only in <a href="?bref=Luke.22.37">Luke 22:37</a>, but he seems to allude to it in <a href="?bref=Mark.10.45,14">Mark 10:45, 14:24</a>, and possibly <a href="?bref=Mark.9.12">9:12</a>. Peter not only emphasizes vicarious, redemptive suffering (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.21-25">1 Pt 2:21-25</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.18">3:18</a>) but seems to highlight the theme of <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">Isaiah 53</a> in summing up OT prophecy (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.11">1:11</a>) as predicting “the sufferings of Christ and the glories that would follow.” Paul includes these elements (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.3">1 Cor 15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.6-11">Phil 2:6-11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.4.25">Rom 4:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.19">5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.21">2 Cor 5:21</a>), and John’s “Lamb of God” title derives from <a href="?bref=Isa.53.7">Isaiah 53:7</a> no less than from the entire sacrificial system.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Christology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Christology</a>; <a href="?item=IsaiahBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Isaiah, Book of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>