<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shaphan">
  <title>Shaphan</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHAPHAN</p>
<p class="list">1. Son of Azaliah and the father of Ahikam, Elasah, and Gemariah. He and his household favored Josiah’s reforms, supported the prophet Jeremiah, and complied with Babylonian hegemony.</p>
<p class="list-text">Shaphan served as the royal secretary to Josiah, king of Judah (640–609 <span class="era">BC</span>). He read the Book of the Law to the king after it was found by the high priest Hilkiah in the sanctuary of Jerusalem. Later, Josiah sent him with a small delegation to hear the words of the prophetess Huldah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.3-14">2 Kgs 22:3-14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.8-28">2 Chr 34:8-28</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Shaphan’s sons were mentioned among the political leaders of Judah during the days of its desolation by Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon (605–586 <span class="era">BC</span>). Ahikam assisted with the repair of the sanctuary and protected Jeremiah from the men who sought his death during the reign of King Jehoiakim (609–598 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.12">2 Kgs 22:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.26.24">Jer 26:24</a>). Elasah delivered a message from King Zedekiah of Judah (597–586 <span class="era">BC</span>) to Nebuchadnezzar in Babylon (<a href="?bref=Jer.29.3">Jer 29:3</a>). Gemariah was the prince of Judah from whose chamber Baruch read the scroll of Jeremiah to the people (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.10-12">36:10-12</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Shaphan was the grandfather of Micaiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.11-13">Jer 36:11-13</a>) and Gedaliah. Gedaliah was appointed governor of Judah by Nebuchadnezzar (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.22">2 Kgs 25:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.40.5-11">Jer 40:5-11</a>) and ordered to protect Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.39.14">Jer 39:14</a>). Gedaliah was later murdered by a mob led by Ishmael (<a href="?bref=Jer.41.2">41:2</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Father of Jaazaniah and, in Ezekiel’s vision, a leader of idolatrous practices in Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.8.11">Ez 8:11</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>