<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ShecaniahShechaniah">
  <title>Shecaniah, Shechaniah*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHECANIAH, SHECHANIAH*</p>
<p class="list">1. Descendant of David through the line of Zerubbabel living in postexilic Palestine (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.21-22">1 Chr 3:21-22</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Levite and the head of the 10th of 24 divisions of priests formed during the reign of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.24.11">1 Chr 24:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. One of six priests serving under Kore during the reign of King Hezekiah of Judah (715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>). Shecaniah assisted with the distribution of the temple offerings among his fellow priests living in the priestly cities (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.15">2 Chr 31:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Father of Hattush, who returned with Ezra to Judah following the Babylonian captivity during the reign of King Artaxerxes I of Persia (464–424 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.8.3">Ezr 8:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Son of Jahaziel who returned with Ezra to Judah during the reign of King Artaxerxes I of Persia (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.5">Ezr 8:5</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. Son of Jehiel in the house of Elam, who urged Ezra to command the sons of Israel to divorce the foreign women they had married (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.2">Ezr 10:2</a>).</p>
<p class="list">7. Father of Shemaiah. Shemaiah, the keeper of the East Gate, helped Nehemiah rebuild a section of the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.29">Neh 3:29</a>).</p>
<p class="list">8. Father-in-law of Tobiah the Ammonite and the son of Arah (<a href="?bref=Neh.6.18">Neh 6:18</a>).</p>
<p class="list">9. Head of a priestly family who returned to Judah with Zerubbabel following the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.3">Neh 12:3</a>). Shecaniah is perhaps identical with Shebaniah in verse <a href="?bref=Neh.12.14">14</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Shebaniah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shebaniah #3</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>