<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shekinah">
  <title>Shekinah*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHEKINAH*</p>
<p class="fl">Transliteration of a Hebrew word meaning “the one who dwells” or “that which dwells.” The term enters Christian theology from its use in the Targums and rabbinic literature to describe the immanent presence in the world of the transcendent Deity. Although the word is not itself used in either Testament, it clearly originates in OT passages that describe God as dwelling among a people or in a particular place (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.27">Gn 9:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.25.8">Ex 25:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.29.45-46">29:45-46</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.5.3">Nm 5:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.13">1 Kgs 6:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.68.16-18">Pss 68:16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.74.2">74:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.8.18">Is 8:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.43.7-9">Ez 43:7-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.3.17,21">Jl 3:17, 21</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.2.10-11">Zec 2:10-11</a>); God, whose dwelling is in heaven, also dwells on earth. The term is also applied to the “shekinah glory,” the visible pillar of fire and smoke that dwelled in the midst of Israel at Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.16-18">Ex 19:16-18</a>), in the wilderness (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.34-38">40:34-38</a>), and in the temple (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.13">1 Kgs 6:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.10-13">8:10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.6.1-2">2 Chr 6:1-2</a>).</p>
<p>The NT frequently alludes to the concept of the shekinah, even though the term itself is not used. God’s presence in the NT is frequently associated with light and glory (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.9">Lk 2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.29">9:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.3-6">Acts 9:3-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.22.6-11">22:6-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.12-16">26:12-16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.1.16-18">2 Pt 1:16-18</a>). John’s Gospel emphasizes both the concept of glory and the concept of dwelling. When the Word became flesh, he dwelt among men who beheld his glory (<a href="?bref=John.1.14">Jn 1:14</a>). The Spirit of God remained on him (v <a href="?bref=John.1.32">32</a>) and would be with his followers forever (<a href="?bref=John.14.16">14:16</a>). He would abide in those who abide in Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.15.4-10">15:4-10</a>). The same themes of dwelling in Christ and of his dwelling in his people occur repeatedly also in John’s letters (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.6,14,24,27-28">1 Jn 2:6, 14, 24, 27-28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.6,14-15,24">3:6, 14-15, 24</a>; <a href="?bref=2Jn.1.9">2 Jn 1:9</a>).</p>
<p>Paul also identifies Christ as the shekinah of God. All the fullness of the Godhead dwells in him bodily (<a href="?bref=Col.1.19">Col 1:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.2.9">2:9</a>). The dwelling of Christ in the church constitutes the saints as the people of God (<a href="?bref=Col.1.15-23">1:15-23</a>). Paul’s message was the “gospel of the glory of Christ,” for God had caused light to shine to give “knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Christ” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.4-6">2 Cor 4:4-6</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Finally, the writer of Hebrews sees Christ as “the radiance of God’s glory and the exact representation of his being” (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.3">Heb 1:3</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Glory_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Glory</a>; <a href="?item=PillarofFireandCloud_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Pillar of Fire and Cloud</a>; <a href="?item=Theophany_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Theophany</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>