<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shem">
  <title>Shem</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHEM</p>
<p class="fl">Eldest son of Noah (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.32">Gn 5:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.6.10">6:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.7.13">7:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.9.18,23,26-27">9:18, 23, 26-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.11.10">11:10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.4,17-27">1 Chr 1:4, 17-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.36">Lk 3:36</a>) and the ancestor of the Semitic peoples (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.1,21-31">Gn 10:1, 21-31</a>). Shem lived 600 years (<a href="?bref=Gen.11.10-11">11:10-11</a>). In Hebrew, Shem means “name,” perhaps implying that Noah expected this son’s name to become great.</p>
<p>After their deliverance from the great Flood, Shem and Japheth acted with respect and dignity toward their drunken father Noah on an occasion when their brother Ham dishonored him (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.20-29">Gn 9:20-29</a>). Because of this act, Noah later pronounced a curse on Canaan, the son of Ham, and a blessing on both Shem and Japheth.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Gen.11.10-27">Genesis 11:10-27</a>, the line of descent for the promised seed, which was to crush Satan (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Gn 3:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.5.1-32">5:1-32</a>), is traced through Shem to Abraham, and ultimately through Judah and David to Christ (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.3.36">Lk 3:36</a>). The blessing of Noah on Shem is thus to be taken as an indication that the line of Shem will be the line through which the seed of <a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Genesis 3:15</a> will come. This is the first time in the Bible that God is called the God of some particular individual or group of people. The statement that Canaan would be a servant to Shem was fulfilled centuries later when the Israelites, who descended from Shem, entered the land of Canaan and subdued the inhabitants of the land (cf. <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.20-21">1 Kgs 9:20-21</a>).</p>
<p>Noah also said that Japheth would be enlarged and dwell in the tents of Shem (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.27">Gn 9:27</a>), the latter of which would seem to imply sustenance and protection. After Japheth would be greatly increased in numbers, the Japhethites would be brought into contact with Shem and would share in the blessings and promises of the Semitic faith. Many scholars see fulfillment of this prophecy in the opening of the gospel to the Gentiles during the NT era of the establishment of the church.</p>
<p>In the “table of nations” recorded in <a href="?bref=Gen.10.1-32">Genesis 10</a>, five descendants of Shem are mentioned (Elam, Asshur, Arphaxad, Lud, and Aram). Receiving particular emphasis among these descendants is Eber from the line of Arphaxad, whose line is traced to Abraham in <a href="?bref=Gen.11.16-27">Genesis 11:16-27</a>.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Abraham_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Abraham</a>; <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>; <a href="?item=Nations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Nations</a>; <a href="?item=Noah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Noah #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>