<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shephatiah">
  <title>Shephatiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHEPHATIAH</p>
<p class="list">1. One of six sons born to David during his seven-year reign at Hebron. Shephatiah’s mother was Abital, one of David’s wives (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.4">2 Sm 3:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.3.3">1 Chr 3:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Benjaminite and the father of Meshullam, a returnee to Jerusalem after the Babylonian captivity (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.8">1 Chr 9:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Haruphite from Benjamin’s tribe and one of the men of military prowess who came to David’s support at Ziklag (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.5">1 Chr 12:5</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Son of Maacah and chief official of the Simeonites during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.16">1 Chr 27:16</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. One of the seven sons of King Jehoshaphat of Judah (872–848 <span class="era">BC</span>) and the brother of Jehoram who became sole regent (853–841 <span class="era">BC</span>) after his father’s death (<a href="?bref=2Chr.21.1-2">2 Chr 21:1-2</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. Forefather of 372 descendants who returned with Zerubbabel to Judah following the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.4">Ezr 2:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.9">Neh 7:9</a>). Later, 81 members of Shephatiah’s house accompanied Ezra back to Palestine during the reign of King Artaxerxes I of Persia (464–424 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.8.8">Ezr 8:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list">7. Founder of a household of Solomon’s servants that returned with Zerubbabel to Judah after the Babylonian captivity (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.57">Ezr 2:57</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.59">Neh 7:59</a>).</p>
<p class="list">8. Descendant of Perez and an ancestor of a Judahite family living in Jerusalem during the postexilic period (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.4">Neh 11:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">9. Son of Mattan and a prince of Judah during the reign of King Zedekiah (597–586 <span class="era">BC</span>). Annoyed with Jeremiah’s prophecies of doom for Jerusalem, Shephatiah (with Gedaliah, Jucal, and Pashhur) tried to put him to death. With Zedekiah’s permission, they hoped to achieve their ends by imprisoning Jeremiah in a cistern (<a href="?bref=Jer.38.1">Jer 38:1</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>