<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Sheshbazzar">
  <title>Sheshbazzar</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHESHBAZZAR</p>
<p class="fl">Jewish leader who found favor with Cyrus the Great, king of Persia. In the first year of his reign, Cyrus issued a decree that the temple in Jerusalem should be rebuilt (<a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1-4">Ezr 1:1-4</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ezra.6.1-5">6:1-5</a>). He appointed Sheshbazzar governor of Judah (<a href="?bref=Ezra.5.14">Ezr 5:14</a>) and handed over to him the gold and silver vessels that Nebuchadnezzar had carried off when he took Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Ezra.1.7-9">1:7-9</a>). Sheshbazzar fulfilled this commission by taking the vessels to Jerusalem with the returning exiles (v <a href="?bref=Ezra.1.9">9</a>) and beginning the restoration of the temple (<a href="?bref=Ezra.5.16">5:16</a>).</p>
<p>Sheshbazzar is mentioned in the Bible only four times, all in the book of Ezra (<a href="?bref=Ezra.1.8-9">1:8-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.5.14-16">5:14-16</a>). For many years it was commonly held that Sheshbazzar was another name for Zerubbabel. Both were of the royal line; Sheshbazzar is called “the prince of Judah,” which may mean that he was heir apparent to the throne. Since his genealogy is not given, he may be represented in that listing by some other name, either Zerubbabel or Shenazzar (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.18-19">1 Chr 3:18-19</a>). In the record of people who returned to Jerusalem, Sheshbazzar’s name does not appear. The name of Zerubbabel is at the head of this list, where one would expect Sheshbazzar’s to be; both were governors of the province of Judah. Zerubbabel is associated with the laying of the foundation of the temple (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.8-11">Ezr 3:8-11</a>), but that work is attributed to Sheshbazzar in <a href="?bref=Ezra.5.16">5:16</a>, in accordance with chapter <a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1-11">1</a>. It is evident that the name Sheshbazzar is found only in connection with the Persians, for chapter <a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1-11">1</a> relates his dealings with Cyrus, and in chapter <a href="?bref=Ezra.5.1-17">5</a> the two occurrences of his name are in a letter written by the Persian official, Tattenai. One may conclude that the Persians knew him as Sheshbazzar, but the Jews called him Zerubbabel. Both names are Akkadian, so there is no parallel here to the renaming of Jewish captives in Babylon (<a href="?bref=Dan.1.7">Dn 1:7</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>