<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shiloh">
  <title>Shiloh</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHILOH</p>
<p class="fl">Town identified with Tell Seilun, located 10 miles (16.1 kilometers) northeast of Bethel, 12 miles (19.3 kilometers) southeast of Shechem, and 3 miles (4.8 kilometers) east of the road between Shechem and Jerusalem, precisely fitting the description of its location in <a href="?bref=Judg.21.19">Judges 21:19</a>. In addition to the continuity of the name of the site and its fitting the biblical requirements for location, excavation results agree with the history of Shiloh as far as it is known from the Bible and confirm the identification.</p>
<p>The town is not mentioned in any prebiblical sources. Excavations show that Shiloh flourished as a fortified town in the early second millennium.</p>
<p>The site was abandoned and resettled in the early Israelite period. The Bible provides no information as to how the site passed into Israelite hands. Joshua established the tabernacle there (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.1">Jos 18:1</a>), and Shiloh became the center of religious life during the period of the judges. There Joshua cast lots to apportion the inheritance of land to seven of the tribes (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.1-19.51">18:1–19:51</a>) and to designate the Levitical cities (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.1-42">21:1-42</a>). A dispute regarding an altar erected by the two and a half tribes that settled in Transjordan was settled at Shiloh (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.9-34">22:9-34</a>). Some Benjaminites abducted women from there during a religious festival (<a href="?bref=Judg.21.1-25">Jgs 21</a>). Elkanah and Hannah often traveled to the tabernacle at Shiloh, where Hannah vowed to give her child to the service of the Lord (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.3,9,24">1 Sm 1:3, 9, 24</a>). The sons of Eli who ministered there had dishonored their office and were rejected, so the Lord appeared to Samuel (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.14">1 Sm 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.3.21">3:21</a>). When the ark was taken from Shiloh to a battle with the Philistines, news of its loss to the Philistines reached Eli and brought about his death (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.1-18">1 Sm 4:1-18</a>). The ark was never returned to Shiloh; the psalmist records that God had “abandoned the tabernacle of Shiloh, the tent he had set up among men” (<a href="?bref=Ps.78.60">Ps 78:60</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>).</p>
<p>The town of Shiloh would presumably have suffered some destruction at the time of the fall of the northern kingdom in 722 <span class="era">BC</span>. The sudden scarcity of ceramic remains in the Iron III period suggests that the site was largely abandoned around 600 <span class="era">BC</span>. After the destruction of the temple in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>, people came from Shiloh to offer sacrifices in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Jer.41.5">Jer 41:5</a>). Shilonites were possibly also among the first returnees from the Babylonian captivity (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.5">1 Chr 9:5</a>). The site was resettled around 300 <span class="era">BC</span> and flourished through the Roman period. It is mentioned by Eusebius and Jerome and in Talmudic sources. It lost much of its importance after the Islamic conquests.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="IsShilohAMessianicName"/>
  </body>
</item>