<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shimei">
  <title>Shimei</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHIMEI</p>
<p class="list">1. Son of Gershon, the grandson of Levi, and the brother of Libni (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.17">Ex 6:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.18">Nm 3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.17">1 Chr 6:17</a>). He was the father of four sons and the founder of the Shimeite family (<a href="?bref=Num.3.21">Nm 3:21</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.7,10">1 Chr 23:7, 10</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.12.13">Zech 12:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Benjaminite, and the son of Gera from the house of Saul. He met King David at the village of Bahurim during the king’s journey from Jerusalem to Mahanaim. Here Shimei bitterly opposed David, cursing him for the ruin of Saul’s house (<a href="?bref=2Sam.16.5-13">2 Sm 16:5-13</a>). Later, Shimei repented of his shameful behavior, entreated David’s forgiveness, and received the king’s pardon (<a href="?bref=2Sam.19.16-23">19:16-23</a>). After David’s death, King Solomon ordered Shimei to settle in Jerusalem and never to leave the city for any reason. Shimei disobeyed the decree and was killed (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.8,36-44">1 Kgs 2:8, 36-44</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Brother of David and the father of Jonathan (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.21">2 Sm 21:21</a>); alternately called Shammah in <a href="?bref=1Sam.16.9">1 Samuel 16:9</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Shammah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shammah #2</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 4. One of David’s court officials who did not support Adonijah’s attempt to set himself up as king (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.8">1 Kgs 1:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Benjaminite, the son of Ela and one of King Solomon’s officials who oversaw the royal household (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.18">1 Kgs 4:18</a>); perhaps identical with #4 above.</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Judahite, the son of Pedaiah, the brother of Zerubbabel, and a descendant of David through Solomon’s line (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.19">1 Chr 3:19</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Simeonite, the son of Zaccur and the father of 16 sons and 6 daughters (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.26-27">1 Chr 4:26-27</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Reubenite, the son of Gog and the father of Micah (<a href="?bref=1Chr.5.4">1 Chr 5:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Son of Libni, the father of Uzzah, and a descendant of Levi through Merari’s line (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.29">1 Chr 6:29</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Gershonite Levite, the son of Jahath, the father of Zimmah, and an ancestor of Asaph who served as a leader of the musicians in the sanctuary during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.42">1 Chr 6:42</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Benjaminite, the father of nine sons and a head of his father’s house (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.21">1 Chr 8:21</a>); alternately called Shema in verse <a href="?bref=1Chr.8.13">13</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=ShemaPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shema (Person) #3</a>.</p>
<p class="list">12. Gershonite Levite, and the father of three sons in the house of Ladan (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.9">1 Chr 23:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">13. Son of Jeduthun and the leader of the 10th of 24 divisions of musicians trained for service in the sanctuary during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.25.3,17">1 Chr 25:3, 17</a>).</p>
<p class="list">14. Ramathite, and a member of King David’s staff who had charge of David’s vineyards (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.27">1 Chr 27:27</a>).</p>
<p class="list">15. Son of Heman, the brother of Jehuel, and one of the Levites selected to cleanse the house of the Lord during King Hezekiah’s reign (715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.14">2 Chr 29:14</a>).</p>
<p class="list">16. Levite, and the brother of Conaniah appointed by King Hezekiah of Judah to oversee the administration of the temple contributions in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.12-13">2 Chr 31:12-13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">17–19. Three men, a Levite, Hashum’s son, and Binnui’s son, who were encouraged by Ezra to divorce their foreign wives during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.23,33,38">Ezr 10:23, 33, 38</a>)</p>
<p class="list">20. Son of Kish and grandfather of Mordecai (<a href="?bref=Esth.2.5">Est 2:5</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>