<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shunem">
  <title>Shunem</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHUNEM</p>
<p class="fl">Village of Issachar’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.18">Jos 19:18</a>) strategically located in the Jezreel Valley. Shunem (modern Sulem) is about three and a half miles (5.6 kilometers) north of Jezreel, situated on the outer hills of Mt Moreh. Both Shunem and Jezreel guard the eastern approach to the Jezreel Valley from Beth-shan through the valley of Harod. This strategic location explains the appearance of Shunem on city lists of various foreign invaders: the lists of Thutmose III (15th century <span class="era">BC</span>); the Amarna Letters (15th century <span class="era">BC</span>), which mention it in conjunction with Megiddo; and the tenth-century <span class="era">BC</span> record at Karnak of the Egyptian Shishak, who listed Shunem’s importance.</p>
<p>The Philistines used Shunem to launch their siege of the Israelite forces at Jezreel (<a href="?bref=1Sam.28.1-31.13">1 Sm 28–31</a>). Because Shunem was on a well-used route, Elijah frequented the town and even resided there (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.8">2 Kgs 4:8</a>). Later, Elijah raised a woman’s son from death (vv <a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.32-37">32-37</a>). During the latter years of the reign of David, a beautiful woman from Shunem named Abishag was summoned to care for the ailing king (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.3,15">1 Kgs 1:3, 15</a>). After David’s death, Abishag appears in the story of the rivalry between Adonijah (David’s eldest son) and Solomon. Adonijah requests Abishag for his own, once Solomon gains the throne, but the king views his brother’s interest as presumption—and a possible attempt at his throne (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.13-25">2:13-25</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Abishag_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Abishag</a>; <a href="?item=Shulammite_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shulammite</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>