<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Sihon">
  <title>Sihon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SIHON</p>
<p class="fl">King of the Amorites who ruled in Heshbon, about 14 miles (22.5 kilometers) east of the north end of the Dead Sea. His defeat by Israel under Moses, together with that of Og, king of Bashan, is frequently mentioned in OT prose and poetry, in narrative and song (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.4">Dt 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.2.26-37">2:26-37</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.46">4:46</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.29.7">29:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.31.4">31:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.2.10">Jos 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.9.10">9:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.2-6">12:2-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.13.10-12">13:10-12</a>). In the eyes of the sacred writers, this dual defeat is so significant that it can be ranked with the exodus as one of the singular manifestations of God’s saving intervention on behalf of his people (<a href="?bref=Ps.135.11">Pss 135:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.136.19-20">136:19-20</a>), and as evidence of his everlasting love for them. In the postexilic period this event is recalled in prayer as a pleading ground for God’s continuing mercy to the returned exiles (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.22">Neh 9:22</a>).</p>
<p>Before Israel’s arrival in Transjordan, Sihon had conquered Moab’s territory as far south as the Arnon River (<a href="?bref=Num.21.26">Nm 21:26</a>). This conquest gives rise to a piece of ancient poetry that is incorporated into sacred Scripture (vv <a href="?bref=Num.21.27-30">27-30</a>). Sihon’s realm extends from the Arnon on the south to the Jabbok on the north, with the Jordan as its western boundary. It also includes the Jordan Valley as far as the Sea of Kinnereth (<a href="?bref=Josh.12.2-3">Jos 12:2-3</a>), comprising part of the region known as Gilead. On the east it extends toward the desert and touches on Ammonite land.</p>
<p>Sihon’s refusal to grant Israel passage through his domain is similar to that of Edom (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.21.23">Nm 21:23</a> with <a href="?bref=Num.20.20">20:20</a>). However, Sihon exhibits overt hostility toward Israel. Sihon was defeated and killed at Jahaz; his country was occupied by Israel. Subsequently, it was distributed to the tribes of Gad and Reuben (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.32.33-38">Nm 32:33-38</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.13.10">Jos 13:10</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>