<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SlaveSlavery">
  <title>Slave, Slavery</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SLAVE, SLAVERY</p>
<p class="fl">Person owned as property by another, and the relationship that bound the owner and the slave. Slavery was widespread in the ancient Near East, although the economy was not dependent upon it. By Roman times, slavery was so extensive that in the early Christian period one out of every two people was a slave. From at least 3000 <span class="era">BC</span>, captives in war were the primary source of slaves (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.21">Gn 14:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.31.9">Nm 31:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.20.14">Dt 20:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.5.30">Jgs 5:30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.4.9">1 Sm 4:9</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.5.2">2 Kgs 5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.28.8">2 Chr 28:8</a>).</p>
<p>Slaves could be purchased locally from other owners or from foreign traveling merchants who sold slaves along with cloth, bronzeware, and other goods (<a href="?bref=Joel.3.4-8">Jl 3:4-8</a>). Joseph was sold by Midianites and Ishmaelites to an Egyptian (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.36">Gn 37:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.39.1">39:1</a>) in this manner. Debt was the basic cause for many families being reduced to slavery; an entire family could be subject to slavery (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.1">2 Kgs 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.5.5-8">Neh 5:5-8</a>). The law code of Hammurabi stipulated a maximum of three years of slavery for the family (Section 117), as opposed to a maximum of six years under Hebrew law (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.18">Dt 15:18</a>). Voluntary slavery was widespread as a means of escape from abject poverty and starvation (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.47-48">Lv 25:47-48</a>). Selling a kidnapped person into slavery, the crime of Joseph’s brothers (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.27-28">Gn 37:27-28</a>), was a capital offense under the law code of Hammurabi (Section 14) and the Mosaic law (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.11">Ex 21:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.7">Dt 24:7</a>).</p>
<p>In Sumerian society, slaves had legal rights, could borrow money, and could engage in business. As the normal price for a slave was probably less than that for a strong donkey, the slave always had the hope that he could save sufficient money to purchase his freedom. Slaves performed tedious labor on farms and in households, though some gifted individuals occupied executive positions in households. Despite provisions in ancient law, the release of slaves was not always honored on schedule. A Hebrew who voluntarily entered slavery was normally released the next jubilee year, and theoretically no Hebrew could be enslaved for life (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.2">Ex 21:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.25.10-13">Lv 25:10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.15.12-14">Dt 15:12-14</a>).</p>
<p>The Israelites made a deliberate attempt to safeguard the slave from brutality by a master or overseer. By law, a maimed slave had to be released (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.26-27">Ex 21:26-27</a>). The few Hebrew slaves in a household frequently toiled alongside their masters in the fields, and they and household slaves often had a reasonable and secure existence, compared with the threat of starvation and destitution of the poorest free men.</p>
<p>In Greek and especially in Roman times, when the number of slaves increased dramatically, household slaves remained the best treated. Many became servants and confidants; some even established good businesses to their own and their masters’ benefit.</p>
<p>Information from Ur, Nuzi, and the book of Genesis shows that where a wife was childless, the female slave could bear the master’s child (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.2-4">Gn 16:2-4</a>). Legally a Hebrew master could agree to marry a young female slave, have his own son marry her, or establish her as a concubine. If subsequently she was discarded, or if the agreement was not fulfilled, she would be released from her slavery (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.7-11">Ex 21:7-11</a>). Conquered people were required to perform forced labor for the state (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.31">2 Sm 12:31</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.15,21-23">1 Kgs 9:15, 21-23</a>), including the Israelites themselves in Lebanon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.13-18">1 Kgs 5:13-18</a>). Captured in war, the Midianites (<a href="?bref=Num.31.28-30,47">Nm 31:28-30, 47</a>) and Gibeonites (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.23-25">Jos 9:23-25</a>) were made slaves to serve the temple. The practice continued through the reigns of David and Solomon (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.58">Ezr 2:58</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.8.20">8:20</a>). Nehemiah records that foreign slaves helped make repairs on the walls of Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.26,31">Neh 3:26, 31</a>).</p>
<p>The NT attitude toward slavery indicates that the status of a slave was more like that of a servant and that the institution of slavery generally was declining. There was no strong opposition to slavery from Jesus or the apostles, but an admonition that slaves and servants should serve their masters faithfully and that masters should treat their slaves humanely and fairly (<a href="?bref=Eph.6.9">Eph 6:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.4.1">Col 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.6.2">1 Tm 6:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.16">Phlm 1:16</a>). Paul never preached against slavery, but he personally tried to attain freedom for the slave Onesimus from his Christian master, Philemon (see the discussion on this in Philemon, Letter to).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BondBondage_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bond, Bondage</a>; <a href="?item=Liberty_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Liberty</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="SlaveANameAdoptedByChristianServants"/>
  </body>
</item>