<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Sleep">
  <title>Sleep</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SLEEP</p>
<p class="fl">Sleep is spoken of in three ways in the Bible: (a) to speak of natural sleep, (b) to refer to moral or spiritual inactivity, and (c) to refer to death.</p>
<p class="h2" id="NaturalSleep">Natural Sleep</p>
<p class="fl">The sleep that the human body needs is seen as a precious gift of God (<a href="?bref=Ps.4.8">Pss 4:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.127.2">127:2</a>). Sleep may be withheld, as God chooses and to serve his purposes (<a href="?bref=Esth.6.1">Est 6:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.6.18">Dn 6:18</a>). God may also, to fulfill his purposes, give people deep sleep (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.21">Gn 2:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.15.12">15:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.26.12">1 Sm 26:12</a>), and during a person’s sleep, God may make his will known by a dream or vision (e.g., <a href="?bref=Gen.28.11-16">Gn 28:11-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.4.13-17">Jb 4:13-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.1.20-24">Mt 1:20-24</a>).</p>
<p>Several statements in the book of Proverbs rebuke the lack of discipline of life shown in the undue love of sleep. For example, one proverb says, “If you love sleep, you will end in poverty. Keep your eyes open, and there will be plenty to eat!” (<a href="?bref=Pr.20.13">Prv 20:13</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>; see also <a href="?bref=Pr.6.9-11">6:9-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.10.5">10:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.24.32-34">24:32-34</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="MoralorSpiritualInactivity">Moral or Spiritual Inactivity</p>
<p class="fl">In a figurative way, sleep is used as a symbol of laziness, carelessness, or inactivity. <a href="?bref=Isa.56.10">Isaiah 56:10</a> speaks of those who failed in their responsibility as leaders of God’s people: “They love to lie there, love to sleep, to dream” (<span class="sc">tlb</span>). In the NT those who are the Lord’s servants are called to watch and to be sure that when their Master comes he will not find them sleeping (<a href="?bref=Mark.13.35-37">Mk 13:35-37</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Matt.25.1-13">Mt 25:1-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.26.40-46">26:40-46</a>). Likewise, the challenge to maintain spiritual alertness and to refrain from sleep comes in a number of places in the epistles: “Awake, O sleeper, and arise from the dead, and Christ shall give you light” (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.14">Eph 5:14</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>); “So be on your guard, not asleep like the others. Watch for his return and stay sober” (<a href="?bref=1Thes.5.6">1 Thes 5:6</a>, <span class="sc">tlb</span>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Death">Death</p>
<p class="fl">Very frequently, the Bible speaks of death as sleep. Commonly in the OT, when a person dies, he is said to go to sleep with his fathers (e.g., <a href="?bref=Deut.31.16">Dt 31:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.7.12">2 Sm 7:12</a>). Jesus spoke of death as sleep (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.24">Mt 9:24</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.11">Jn 11:11</a>). So did the apostle Paul (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.30">1 Cor 11:30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.20,51">15:20, 51</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.13-14">1 Thes 4:13-14</a>). In some of these references, it would seem that it is the temporary nature of death that is the reason why it is spoken of as sleep. Even in <a href="?bref=Dan.12.2">Daniel 12:2</a> it is said that death is a sleep, until the dead “rise up, some to everlasting life and some to shame and everlasting contempt” (<span class="sc">tlb</span>). This is made more specific in many passages in the NT. When, however, we consider the full teaching of the Bible on the meaning of death for the Christian, we need to give full weight to such passages as <a href="?bref=Luke.23.43">Luke 23:43</a>, <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.8">2 Corinthians 5:8</a>, and <a href="?bref=Phil.1.23">Philippians 1:23</a>, and especially <a href="?bref=1Thes.5.13-14">1 Thessalonians 5:13-14</a>. In the first of these Jesus says to the dying thief on the cross, “Today you will be with me in paradise,” and in the second Paul speaks of death for him as going to “be with Christ.”</p>
  </body>
</item>