<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SodomandGomorrah">
  <title>Sodom and Gomorrah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SODOM AND GOMORRAH</p>
<p class="fl">Two of the “cities of the plain [valley]” referred to in <a href="?bref=Gen.13.12">Genesis 13:12</a>. There were five cities—Sodom, Gomorrah, Admah, Zeboiim, and Bela or Zoar (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.2">Gn 14:2</a>)—all situated in the valley of Siddim (i.e., the Salt Sea). Of these, Sodom is mentioned most frequently in Genesis—36 times in all, of which 16 references are to Sodom alone. Sodom became known in biblical literature as the supreme example of a wicked city, and its destruction (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.24">19:24</a>) was used as a warning of God’s judgment in other biblical writings (<a href="?bref=Deut.29.23">Dt 29:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.9-10">Is 1:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.14">Jer 23:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.49.18">49:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.4.6">Lam 4:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.4.11">Am 4:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.9">Zep 2:9</a>). The story of Sodom’s destruction found its place also in the NT (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.15">Mt 10:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.12">Lk 10:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.17.29">17:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.9.29">Rom 9:29</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.6">2 Pt 2:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jude.1.7">Jude 1:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.11.8">Rv 11:8</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="PossibleLocationofSodomandGomorrah"/>
<p>The primary story of Sodom and Gomorrah occurs in <a href="?bref=Gen.18.1-33">Genesis 18</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.19.1-38">19</a>, although the biblical interest in the city begins in chapter <a href="?bref=Gen.13.1-18">13</a> with the decision of Lot, Abraham’s nephew, to settle in the Jordan Valley, in the vicinity of Sodom, among people who were notorious sinners. It becomes clear that one of Sodom’s most grievous sins was sexual perversion, especially homosexuality. Lot’s offer of his virgin daughters to the men of Sodom to turn their attention away from his heavenly visitors is an indication of the demoralizing influence of the city.</p>
<p>Four rulers from the East descended on the region of Sodom and Gomorrah sometime after Lot settled there and subdued the area. They returned 14 years later to quell a rebellion (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.1-5">Gn 14:1-5</a>). Among their captives was Lot, who was (subsequently) rescued by Abraham. The evil of Sodom and Gomorrah was so great that the Lord determined to destroy them. Abraham pleaded for mercy for them if ten righteous men could be found (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.20-33">18:20-33</a>). The two heavenly visitors who went from Abraham to Sodom found Lot sitting in the gate of Sodom (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.1">19:1</a>), revealed God’s intentions to him, and persuaded Lot and his wife and two daughters to flee the city. Then the Lord rained brimstone and fire on Sodom and Gomorrah. The next morning Abraham saw the smoke from the destroyed cities rising like the smoke of a furnace.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CitiesofthePlain_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cities of the Plain</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>