<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SolomonPerson">
  <title>Solomon (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SOLOMON (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Third king over Israel, the second son of David and Bathsheba, who reigned 40 years (970–930 <span class="era">BC</span>). His alternative name was Jedidiah, “beloved of the Lord.”</p>
<p class="h2" id="AppointedtotheThrone">Appointed to the Throne</p>
<p class="fl">Once Amnon and Absalom were no longer in competition for the throne, the two most likely remaining candidates were Solomon and Adonijah, although the kingship had been assured to the former (<a href="?bref=1Chr.22.9-10">1 Chr 22:9-10</a>). Near the end of David’s life, Adonijah contested the choice of Solomon and took steps to become king. With the help of Joab, general of the army, and Abiathar the priest, he was proclaimed the monarch. Solomon was not invited and neither were Nathan the prophet or Benaiah. Nathan brought word of this plot to Bathsheba, who in turn quizzed David as to his intentions. David then ordered Solomon to be proclaimed king over Israel; he was anointed by Zadok amidst the blowing of the trumpets and the shout of the people: “Long live King Solomon” (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.34">1 Kgs 1:34</a>). Adonijah realized his claim had collapsed and asked for mercy, promising to be faithful to the new king.</p>
<p>Solomon moved swiftly to establish his hold on the government (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.1-2.46">1 Kgs 1–2</a>). When Adonijah asked to marry Abishag, David’s companion in his old age (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.1-4">1:1-4</a>), Solomon refused and ordered his death because of possible claims to the throne (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.22-25">2:22-25</a>). In addition, because Abiathar had joined with Adonijah, he was removed from his service as priest and sent back to Anathoth. Joab fled to the altar and there took hold of its horns and refused to let go. The king ordered his death at the hand of Benaiah, who then became commander-in-chief of the armies. Another contender, Shimei, of the house of Saul, was also executed.</p>
<p>One of Solomon’s earliest recorded acts as king was to go to the high place at Gibeon and sacrifice 1,000 burnt offerings. On the following night, the Lord appeared to the king in a dream, asking as to his fondest wish. Solomon asked for wisdom to judge Israel, and God was pleased with the request (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.3.1-28">1 Kgs 3</a>). Israel’s king was given his wish, along with the gifts of long life, riches, and fame.</p>
<p class="h2" id="SolomonsAccomplishments">Solomon’s Accomplishments</p>
<p class="h3">His Government</p>
<p class="fl">David’s efforts had brought about a union of the 12 tribes, but Solomon established an organized state with many officials to help him (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.1-34">1 Kgs 4</a>). The entire country was divided into 12 major districts; each district was to ensure the provisions of the king’s court for one month each year. The system was equitable and designed to distribute the tax burden over the entire country.</p>
<p class="h3">His Buildings</p>
<p class="fl">One of Solomon’s earliest building attempts was to construct the temple. David had wanted to build the temple, but this task was left to Solomon, the man of peace. Hiram, king of Tyre, provided cedar trees from Mt Lebanon for the temple (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.1-12">1 Kgs 5:1-12</a>), and in return he was given an appropriate amount of food. In order to provide the necessary labor for these building projects, the Canaanites became slaves (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.20-21">9:20-21</a>). Israelites likewise were compelled to work in groups of 10,000, every third month (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.13-18">5:13-18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.2.17-18">2 Chr 2:17-18</a>). The workers for the temple alone comprised 80,000 stonecutters, 70,000 common laborers, and 3,600 foremen.</p>
<p>It took seven years to finish the temple, which by modern standards was a rather small building: 90 feet (27.4 meters) long, 30 feet (9.1 meters) wide, and 45 feet (13.7 meters) high. Nevertheless, the gold covering for both walls and furniture made it quite expensive.</p>
<p>In the 11th year of Solomon’s reign, the dedication of the temple was celebrated in a great convocation (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.38">1 Kgs 6:38</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.1-5">8:1-5</a>). The presence of the Lord filled the temple, and Solomon then offered his great dedicatory prayer (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.23-53">8:23-53</a>), marking it as one of the great peaks of his devotion to the Lord. Afterward, he offered up 22,000 oxen and 120,000 sheep as well as other offerings. The people were full of joy because David had so great a successor.</p>
<p>Solomon built other buildings: the House of the Forest of Lebanon, the Hall of Pillars, a hall for his throne, and a house for the daughter of Pharaoh (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.2-8">1 Kgs 7:2-8</a>). Thirteen years were involved in the building of his own house, large enough to take care of his wives and concubines as well as the servants. A great fortress was also built, Millo, which was used to protect the temple (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.24">9:24</a>), as well as other store and fortified cities.</p>
<p class="h3">His Trade with Other Nations</p>
<p class="fl">The king had an agreement with Hiram, king of Tyre, to pay yearly for cedar trees, stonecutters, and other buildings; for 125,000 bushels (4.4 million liters) of wheat; and for 115,000 gallons (435,275 liters) of olive oil (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.11">1 Kgs 5:11</a>). In addition, Hiram received 20 cities in Galilee to cover all indebtedness. Contrary to the instruction not to trade in horses (<a href="?bref=Deut.17.16">Dt 17:16</a>), Solomon bought horses and chariots from the Egyptians, and some of these in turn were sold to the Hittites and Arameans at a profit (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.28-29">1 Kgs 10:28-29</a>).</p>
<p>Furthermore, Solomon engaged in sea trade. Ships built at shipyards at Ezion-geber sailed to ports on the Red Sea and Indian Ocean. The mariners collected gold, ivory, and peacocks. From Ophir, the traders brought back 420 talents of gold, a considerable fortune.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HisWisdom">His Wisdom</p>
<p class="fl">Solomon wrote 3,000 proverbs and 1,005 songs (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.32">1 Kgs 4:32</a>). Most of the book of Proverbs is attributed to him (<a href="?bref=Pr.25.1">Prv 25:1</a>), as well as Ecclesiastes, Song of Songs, and <a href="?bref=Ps.72.1-20">Psalms 72</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.127.1-5">127</a>. His obituary notice mentions his literary accomplishments in the book of the acts of Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.41">1 Kgs 11:41</a>).</p>
<p>The queen of Sheba came to see and hear if the reports of Solomon’s fame and wisdom were correct. After viewing all he had in Jerusalem and hearing his wisdom, her final response was to bless the Lord God of Israel, who raised up such a wise person to sit upon such a magnificent throne (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.1-29">1 Kgs 10</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="HisFall">His Fall</p>
<p class="fl">Solomon made many misjudgments during his reign, and one of them was his excessive taxation of the people. His worst blunder was adding more and more wives to his harem, accommodating their religious preferences with pagan shrines (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.1-8">1 Kgs 11:1-8</a>). The Lord plagued Solomon, permitting Israel to be attacked on all sides. Although the kingdom was not damaged during Solomon’s day, his son experienced its division. There is no record that Solomon repented, but it is quite possible that the book of Ecclesiastes does reveal his realization of his wrong decisions.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>; <a href="?item=EcclesiastesBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ecclesiastes, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=King_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">King, Kingship</a>; <a href="?item=ProverbsBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Proverbs, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=SongofSolomon_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Song of Solomon</a>; <a href="?item=Wisdom_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wisdom</a>; <a href="?item=WisdomLiterature_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wisdom Literature</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>