<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Spain">
  <title>Spain</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SPAIN</p>
<p class="fl">Name of the most westerly peninsula in southwestern Europe. Biblical references to the peninsula note the role of the Phoenicians, whose far-flung Carthaginian Empire reached into Spain. The Romans expelled the Carthaginians from Spain as early as 206 <span class="era">BC</span>, but they did not conquer the local tribes until 25 <span class="era">BC</span>. Only by then had the Romans gained control of the whole region (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.8.3">1 Macc 8:3</a>).</p>
<p>The Phoenician traders of Tyre extended their commercial empire to Spain or historic Iberia as early as 1100 <span class="era">BC</span>. From Carthage on the North African coast, which was a center of the Phoenician Empire, a series of colonial thrusts followed the trading contacts. The Carthaginians established many settlements on the Spanish coast during the flourishing of their republic. These included Carthago Nova (now Cartagena) and Malacca (now Malaga). Later, they took Tartessus and absorbed much of the peninsula into their empire. From this base in Spain, the Carthaginians sought to expand their empire into Europe. The Romans met the Carthaginian challenge. After beating Hannibal back in his attack on Italy in the Second Punic War (218–201 <span class="era">BC</span>), the Romans extended their territory by overcoming the Carthaginians on the Spanish peninsula. Finally, under Augustus, the Romans made Spain part of the empire. At that time the Romans built a magnificent road system circling and crossing the whole Spanish peninsula.</p>
<p>Roman civilization had a deep and lasting influence on Spain. Three emperors—Trajan, Hadrian, and the first Theodosius—were born in Spain. Several scholars and writers of note in Roman culture came from Spain. These included the two Senecas, Martial, Prudentius, Lucan, Quintialian, Pomponius, and Mela.</p>
<p>In the apostle Paul’s scheme for reaching the uttermost regions of the civilized world with the good news of Jesus Christ, he probably realized the potential of converts in Spain. The chief evidence that Paul included Spain in his strategic planning is in <a href="?bref=Rom.15.24,28">Romans 15:24, 28</a>. In that letter Paul clearly sets forth his message to Romans and Gentiles throughout the empire. To follow up on this letter, he planned to visit Rome and then make his way to Spain. Testimony of Paul actually visiting Spain comes only from a vague reference after his death. Clement of Rome, an early Christian writer at the end of the first century <span class="era">AD</span>, stated that Paul went to “the limits of the West” (1 Clement 1:5). Although most Romans considered Spain as the western limit of their empire, this vague phrase does not give sufficient evidence for a Pauline visit. Yet clearly Paul saw Spain as a strategic place for mission work; thus, it stands to reason that he himself, or others whom he designated, planted the Christian church in Spain during the first century <span class="era">AD</span>.</p>
  </body>
</item>