<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Susa">
  <title>Susa</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SUSA</p>
<p class="fl">Capital of the non-Semitic people and district of Elam. Susa (modern Shush) is located in southwest Iran, about 150 miles (241.4 kilometers) north of the Persian Gulf and due east of the well-known city of Babylon. French archaeologists began excavating the site in 1884, discovering that it was occupied as long ago as about 4000 <span class="era">BC</span>. Its importance in the OT derives mainly from the fact that it was incorporated into the Persian Empire, founded by Cyrus in 550 <span class="era">BC</span>. It became a royal city along with Ecbatana (the other main city in Elam), Babylon, and Persepolis. This was the great period of importance for Susa, although it had known an earlier golden age in the 12th century <span class="era">BC</span>. (The first copy of the law code of Hammurabi ever found was discovered at Susa, dated in the 12th century <span class="era">BC</span>.)</p>
<p>The center of Persian Susa was an acropolis or citadel that rose above the city as a rectangular platform surrounded by a massive wall. This was the royal quarter within which the palace stood. The palace was the winter residence of the Persian kings.</p>
<p>Nehemiah was a cupbearer at the palace of Susa in the reign of Artaxerxes I (<a href="?bref=Neh.1.1,11">Neh 1:1, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.2.1">2:1</a>). In <a href="?bref=Esth.1.2">Esther 1:2</a> and <a href="?bref=Esth.2.8">2:8</a> the young Jewess Esther was introduced to the court of King Ahasuerus, who was evidently the Persian king Xerxes (485–465 <span class="era">BC</span>). Most of the action of the book takes place in Susa (cf. <a href="?bref=Esth.3.15">Est 3:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.8.14-15">8:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.9.6-18">9:6-18</a>).</p>
<p>According to <a href="?bref=Dan.8.2">Daniel 8:2</a>, the place of Daniel’s vision is Susa. Probably Daniel is not to be regarded as having been there literally, but rather he was spiritually transported there in the vision. Chronologically, Daniel’s vision is set at the end of the Babylonian period, just before the Persian conquest (<a href="?bref=Dan.8.1">Dn 8:1</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Dan.7.1">7:1</a>). At this time Susa controlled the Medians and was not subject to Babylon.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PersiaPersians_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Persia, Persians</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>