<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="FamilyLifeandRelations">
  <title>Family Life and Relations</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FAMILY LIFE AND RELATIONS</p>
<p class="fl">In Bible times, the family comprised members of a household, including not only parents and children, along with other relatives and concubines, but also servants, travelers, aliens, and anyone else who happened to be within the house and was therefore under the protection of the head of the family. The family of Jacob, for example, comprised three generations (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.8-26">Gn 46:8-26</a>). Biblically, the term “family” is interchangeable with “house,” and “founding a house” can refer to setting up a separate dwelling as well as establishing a family. In the broader sense, “house” may refer to an entire nation (“house of Israel”). The heads of families returning from Babylon in the postexilic period controlled sometimes several hundred family members (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.1-14">Ezr 8:1-14</a>). The family was a smaller part of a clan and tribe. In nomadic times the responsibilities and allegiances centered on the larger family group.</p>
<p>Those who belonged to the clan knew that they had to work for common interests and accept responsibility for the whole group. All members of the family were to be protected and assisted in time of need.</p>
<p>As the life of the Israelites became more settled, families (in the wider sense of the term) lived in villages surrounded by fields of wheat, barley, and flax, with areas of grazing land for sheep and goats. Each group of villages consisted of an intermarried, interdependent family group, such as that of the Danites of Zorah and Eshtaol (<a href="?bref=Judg.18.11">Jgs 18:11</a>). The hard life of those days demanded a sharing of work and the loyal cooperation of the entire family for survival.</p>
<p>As crafts and trades developed, along with a more sedentary lifestyle, sons learned their fathers’ skills and continued the family trade. Consequently, the whole village might follow a particular craft (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.14">1 Chr 4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.11.35">Neh 11:35</a>). By specializing in such trades, however, the villagers became less self-sufficient, depending more on farmers for food and on other specialized villages for the production of cloth or pottery (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.21-23">1 Chr 4:21-23</a>).</p>
<p>With the growth of cities, related groups lived together in specific areas. Many members of the tribes of Benjamin and Judah were listed in the census of Jerusalem by Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.4-8">Neh 11:4-8</a>), and by the writer of Chronicles (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.3-9">1 Chr 9:3-9</a>). One consequence of life in the cities was the fragmentation of the family group. As the bonds of the wider family were loosened, the unit consisted increasingly of a husband and wife with their children, living in one house. The size of houses that have been excavated precludes the idea of any larger family unit as the norm in OT societies.</p>
<p>During the kingdom period, King David’s sons Amnon and Absalom set up their own separate houses (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.7-8,20">2 Sm 13:7-8, 20</a>). At that time there were few slaves in Hebrew society, but they also were considered members of the family. As bonds of the wider family loosened, and the master of the household lost a degree of authority, the society became one in which the king was sovereign and all the people were his subjects.</p>
<p>The early kings of Israel promoted such a change in order to establish a central ruling authority for the entire country. The king’s subjects fell broadly into the categories of employers and employees, corresponding to the rich and poor of society. By the eighth century <span class="era">BC</span>, members of the wider family no longer worked for the communal good under the authority of the clan’s head; rather, individuals worked primarily for the good of their own immediate family. Hence one’s labor and devotion were focused more narrowly, and the greatest beneficiary was the king, the personal symbol of the nation.</p>
<p>Emphasis on the smaller family unit increased, and old duties that had been willingly accepted by the wider groups in former times came to be neglected. People did not always help relatives in times of need, and they frequently had to be reminded of their obligations, particularly toward widows and orphans (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.17">Is 1:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.7.6">Jer 7:6</a>). Family feuds also declined because members no longer felt responsible to take vengeance as a way to uphold the honor of the clan (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.27">2 Sm 3:27</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.16.8">16:8</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.26">2 Kgs 9:26</a>). Nevertheless, Nehemiah expected Israelites to fight for their family honor (<a href="?bref=Neh.4.14">Neh 4:14</a>). In NT times, the family was such a unit that it could be sold for a debt incurred by one of its members (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.25">Mt 18:25</a>).</p>
<p>The Hebrew religion’s emphasis on family participation in certain celebrations strengthened the small unit. The Passover, for example, was always celebrated as a family thanksgiving meal (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.3-4,46">Ex 12:3-4, 46</a>). The prophet Samuel’s parents made a traditional annual pilgrimage to the shrine at Shiloh (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.19">1 Sm 2:19</a>). In modern times, a young Jewish boy’s arrival at the threshold of manhood is celebrated with the Bar Mitzvah ceremony. Being so honored in the midst of a religious family preserves the ancient Hebrew tradition of family participation in religious ceremonies.</p>
<p>In his preaching Jesus used the family as a symbol for the relationship of God to his people (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.14">Mt 19:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.9">23:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.21">Lk 8:21</a>). From the cross he handed over responsibility for the care of his mother to his disciple John (<a href="?bref=John.19.27">Jn 19:27</a>).</p>
<p>In NT times, the communion meals in the Jerusalem church took place by households (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.46">Acts 2:46</a>). Early Christian meetings were held in the homes of believers because of opposition by the authorities. The book of Acts contains examples of entire families being converted to Christianity (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.24,44-48">Acts 10:24, 44-48</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.16.15,31-32">16:15, 31-32</a>). Timothy learned the gospel from his grandmother and mother (<a href="?bref=2Tim.1.5">2 Tm 1:5</a>).</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#StatusofFamilyMembers">Status of Family Members</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#MaritalSecurity">Marital Security</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PositionofChildren">Position of Children</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheRightsofChildren">The Rights of Children</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DailyLifeoftheHebrewFamily">Daily Life of the Hebrew Family</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#InNewTestamentTimes">In New Testament Times</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="StatusofFamilyMembers">Status of Family Members</p>
<p class="fl">From nomadic times, a father’s authority held the family group together in their encampment, and he became the symbol of their security. In ancient patriarchal societies, the father was an absolute master who had the power of life and death over family members, ruling with unchallenged authority. Although he had extensive responsibilities for those under his care, his power was awesome and his status unquestioned.</p>
<p>A man’s possessions included his wife, servants, slaves, and animals (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.17">Ex 20:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.21">Dt 5:21</a>). In fact, the phrase “to marry a wife” comes from a Hebrew root meaning “to become the master of a wife.” A husband was as much the master of his wife as he was of his home or his fields. Consequently, the wife addressed him in a subservient manner, as a slave would address a master (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.12">Gn 18:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.19.26">Jgs 19:26</a>). This low status for a woman extended to a daughter’s position in the ancient household. Females were always under the authority of a male relative: first, the father; then a husband. If a woman became a widow, she was subject to her husband’s nearest male relative, who became her “redeemer.” The bride price (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.18,27">Gn 29:18, 27</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.22.16-17">Ex 22:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.18.25">1 Sm 18:25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.14">2 Sm 3:14</a>) paid by her husband was not exactly a purchase of the woman from her father, but the exchange of money did stigmatize her. The amount of a bride price depended on the father’s status (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.12">Gn 34:12</a>). The usual price was probably 20 to 30 shekels of silver. The bride received gifts of jewelry, ornaments, and clothing from her future husband, and she occasionally enjoyed some sort of financial or material return from the bride price for her own use (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.19">Jos 15:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.1.15">Jgs 1:15</a>). When her father or husband died, the money frequently reverted to her.</p>
<p>An engaged woman was considered her fiancé’s property just as much as if she were already married to him (<a href="?bref=Deut.22.23-27">Dt 22:23-27</a>). The woman left her own family at marriage, to live with and become part of her new husband’s family. Normally, any succeeding marriages would be with members of that family.</p>
<p>Despite the low legal status of the mother of the family, her life was not as bad as one might suppose. She was the legal wife, not an unpaid servant, and she frequently took a strong role as adviser to her husband in family affairs. Her most important function, aside from childbearing, was organization of the household, of which she was generally the respected manager. Even though the wife might have been acquired through capture in war (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.10-14">Dt 21:10-14</a>), she could not be sold as a slave or daughter could (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.7">Ex 21:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.5.5">Neh 5:5</a>).</p>
<p>Nevertheless, her position was precarious, in that she could be disowned or divorced by her husband as the result of a simple renunciation: “She is no longer my wife, and I am no longer her husband.” Perhaps he had found fault with her culinary skills, or possibly he was casting his eyes on another woman. In any event, a husband knew that if his wife did not obey even a signal or a glance, he was within his rights to obtain a divorce (cf. <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.25.26">Ecclus 25:26</a>). The wife, however, obtained a certain degree of protection in the letter of repudiation, by which her freedom was formally restored. Under Jewish tradition, a wife could not divorce her husband.</p>
<p>In matters of domestic protocol, the Hebrew wife was not introduced to her husband’s guests, a tradition that subsequently led to considerable embarrassment for Abraham’s wife, Sarah, and for Rebekah (<a href="?bref=Gen.20.16">Gn 20:16</a>). A woman normally remained veiled in public (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.65">24:65</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.38.14">38:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.47.2">Is 47:2</a>).</p>
<p>The imagery in <a href="?bref=Pr.19.13">Proverbs 19:13</a> and <a href="?bref=Pr.27.15">27:15</a> draws a vigorous comparison between a contentious woman and water dripping from a leaky roof. The OT leaves little doubt about the type of behavior expected from a woman. She was expected to be charming, soft-spoken, discreet, and calm (<a href="?bref=Pr.9.13">Prv 9:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.11.16,22">11:16, 22</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.21.9">21:9</a>). She was also to be responsible, well-organized, intelligent, thoughtful, reverent, and a good manager of both the household and the family purse (<a href="?bref=Pr.31.10-31">31:10-31</a>). A woman should also be pious and beautiful, and in NT tradition, submissive to her husband, as befitted a woman adorned with the priceless jewel of a gentle and quiet spirit (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.4-5">Ti 2:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.1-6">1 Pt 3:1-6</a>).</p>
<p>The actions of a few women whose roles in life do not seem to fit the pattern of the meek, passive female pictured above, are recorded in the Bible and the Apocrypha. The books of Judith and Esther recount heroic tales of how national fortunes were saved by women. Deborah and Jael were renowned heroines (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.1-5.31">Jgs 4–5</a>), and the kingdom of Judah was ruled by a vicious woman, Athaliah, for several years (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.1-21">2 Kgs 11</a>). The women who stepped to the forefront of public life were exceptional and few in number. Judith was a rich widow, an unusual thing in Israel.</p>
<p class="h2" id="MaritalSecurity">Marital Security</p>
<p class="fl">The security of a wife’s position improved considerably when she produced her first child, particularly if it was a son. A woman’s primary duty to her husband and his family was procreation (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.28">Gn 1:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.9.1">9:1</a>), and until she gave birth to a son, she feared displacement by a second wife or a concubine. Polygamous marriages were by no means rare, especially in wealthy families. They resulted in two ill-defined family groups, controlled by the mothers but under the overall authority of fathers; there were inevitable jealousies and frictions.</p>
<p>The legal status of a woman was consistently poor in Bible times. With no evidence at all, a husband could accuse his wife of adultery, and she was compelled to face a trial by ordeal. She had to abase herself by taking an oath, eating dust and a cereal offering, and drinking bitter water. A priest, meanwhile, made pronouncements regarding the dire results that would come to her if she were guilty: she would become an outcast with no hope of survival. But if she maintained her serenity, and if her thigh did not rot nor her abdomen swell, she was considered to have “proved” her innocence. In such an event she would go free, and her husband bore no blame whatsoever for his false accusation (<a href="?bref=Num.5.12-31">Nm 5:12-31</a>).</p>
<p>If a woman took a vow, it was legal only as long as her father or husband approved it. If she became a widow, the vow still remained in force and could be used against her (<a href="?bref=Num.30.3-15">Nm 30:3-15</a>).</p>
<p>A woman in Israel was always under the protection of a male, be it her father, grandfather, great-grandfather, brother, husband, or some other member of her husband’s family. She had few legal rights and, in contrast to Babylonian traditions, could not inherit at her husband’s death. It is small wonder that widows were classed with orphans and the poor. A childless widow could on occasion return to her father’s family (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.11">Gn 38:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.22.13">Lv 22:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.1.8">Ru 1:8</a>), thus becoming subject again to the authority of her father. A Hebrew widow could also remain with her late husband’s family. She would then come under the protection of her “redeemer,” a male relative of her husband’s family who assumed responsibility for her. If a husband died leaving a woman childless, it was the responsibility of the husband’s brother to marry her. The first son born of such a union was then regarded as the heir of the first husband.</p>
<p>It was normal for a brother to accept the obligation for such a marriage (levirate). It could be refused on various grounds, but such refusal was considered dishonorable, for it was a man’s duty to perpetuate his brother’s name and to safeguard the family fortune.</p>
<p>A redeemer’s responsibilities were considerable. In addition to the marriage, he was perhaps involved in avenging the family reputation, and he had to ensure that family property increased and remained within family control.</p>
<p>If an Israelite fell into debt and was forced to sell himself into slavery, he would normally be “redeemed” by one of his relatives (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.47-49">Lv 25:47-49</a>). If in his penury an Israelite had to sell his land or his house, the redeemer had the right of first refusal over all other prospective purchasers. It was as much his duty as his right to prevent family property from passing into the hands of strangers (v <a href="?bref=Lev.25.25">25</a>). The prophet Jeremiah bought his cousin Hanamel’s field under similar circumstances (<a href="?bref=Jer.32.6-15">Jer 32:6-15</a>).</p>
<p>The most familiar OT story of a childless widow, her “redeemer,” and their levirate marriage is recorded in the book of Ruth. One of Naomi’s two sons married Ruth. When Ruth was widowed, her impoverished mother-in-law, Naomi, left her home in Moab and returned to Bethlehem to sell some of the family property. Although a close relative was prepared to buy the land and keep it in the family, he was not ready to marry Ruth as well (<a href="?bref=Ruth.3.12">Ru 3:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.4">4:4</a>). He knew that a son of that union would be deemed a son of the deceased, bearing the dead husband’s name, and thus ultimately inheriting the land (<a href="?bref=Ruth.4.4-6">4:4-6</a>). The next relative in order of kinship was Boaz, who became Ruth’s “redeemer.” He was prepared to accept the double obligation of purchasing the land and marrying Ruth (<a href="?bref=Ruth.4.9-10">4:9-10</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="PositionofChildren">Position of Children</p>
<p class="fl">Children were generally well loved, but their childhood was short and they were often regarded as laborers for the house or fields. According to the law of primogeniture, the eldest son received a double portion of the estate as his birthright (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.17">Dt 21:17</a>). Thus, he was assured of the position of family head. Even during his father’s lifetime, the eldest son took precedence over his brothers and sisters (<a href="?bref=Gen.43.33">Gn 43:33</a>). Where twins were born, the first to emerge from the womb was considered the elder, with all the attendant privileges (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.24-26">25:24-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.38.27-30">38:27-30</a>).</p>
<p>For a serious offense, the eldest son could lose the right of primogeniture (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.22">Gn 35:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.49.3-4">49:3-4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.5.1">1 Chr 5:1</a>), or it could be surrendered voluntarily, as Esau did by selling his birthright to his brother Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.29-34">Gn 25:29-34</a>). There was a law protecting the eldest son from his father’s favoritism for a younger brother (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.15-17">Dt 21:15-17</a>). Nevertheless, King David gave his kingdom to Solomon, his youngest son (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.15">1 Kgs 2:15</a>).</p>
<p>In a family with no sons, a daughter could inherit property (<a href="?bref=Num.27.8">Nm 27:8</a>). Frequently, parents consulted neither sons nor daughters when marriage partners were arranged for them. Marriage was often an alliance or contract between two families, and thus the wishes and concerns of individuals were considered unimportant. Love matches were few, although occasionally a son would marry in defiance of his parents, as Esau did (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.34-35">Gn 26:34-35</a>). Although it was rare for young people to express their feelings and preferences about marriage in an open fashion, Saul’s daughter, Michal, made known her love for David (<a href="?bref=1Sam.18.20">1 Sm 18:20</a>).</p>
<p>There is no record of legal adoption among the Hebrews, but it was practiced from ancient times in Mesopotamia. It was especially useful as a means of ensuring a childless couple that their land would be tilled and that they would be cared for in their old age. All examples of adoption mentioned in the OT took place outside the land of Israel (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.10">Ex 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.20">1 Kgs 11:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.2.7,15">Est 2:7, 15</a>) and are not examples of true adoption as a lifetime member of a family.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheRightsofChildren">The Rights of Children</p>
<p class="fl">The nature of patriarchal society made for unfortunate distinctions between male and female children. The position of a daughter, who could be sold into slavery or sold to be the concubine of a man and then possibly sold again (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.7-11">Ex 21:7-11</a>), was certainly inferior to that of a son. In the patriarchal period, however, both a son and a daughter could be put to death for disobeying the head of the family. One’s children could also be sacrificed in worship rituals (see <a href="?bref=Gen.22.1-24">Gn 22</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.11.1-40">Jgs 11</a>). It is probable that infant sacrifice was practiced by nations neighboring Israel, including Canaan and Ammon.</p>
<p>The rights of children were improved considerably with the promulgation of the code of Mosaic law. A father was no longer permitted to put his child to death without referring the case to the elders (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.18-21">Dt 21:18-21</a>). Both sons and daughters could be brought before such authorities and accused of being disobedient, gluttonous, or drunkards. A father’s absolute authority even extended to his married son and family if they were living under his roof. The law also prohibited children from being held responsible for the crimes of their parents (<a href="?bref=Deut.24.16">Dt 24:16</a>). In King David’s time a person convicted by the community had the right of appeal to the king (<a href="?bref=2Sam.14.4-11">2 Sm 14:4-11</a>).</p>
<p>In Hebrew families both parents were held in high respect. Honor had to be given to both mother and father (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.12">Ex 20:12</a>), and the law condemned offenses against either parent (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.17">21:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.20.9">Lv 20:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.21.18">Dt 21:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.27.16">27:16</a>). Respect due to the mother is a recurrent theme in the Wisdom Literature (<a href="?bref=Pr.19.26">Prv 19:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.20">20:20</a>; cf. <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.3.1-16">Ecclus 3:1-16</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="DailyLifeoftheHebrewFamily">Daily Life of the Hebrew Family</p>
<p class="fl">In the everyday affairs of a Hebrew household, it was the father’s responsibility to maintain the family fortune and to be the provider. He might work in the fields, most probably with crops of flax, barley, or wheat. Or he would work at a trade, possibly as a weaver, builder, potter, dyer, fuller, or a worker in copper or bronze. If he lived near the shore, he might be a fisherman.</p>
<p>The father was also responsible for the religious well-being of the family. It was his duty to take over his sons’ education from the mother at an early age, teaching them the tenets of Hebrew religion (<a href="?bref=Exod.10.2">Ex 10:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.12.26">12:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.9">Dt 4:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.6.7">6:7</a>). He also explained all the facets of the law and the interwoven history of the nation.</p>
<p>The father was the disciplinarian of the family, with the rod being used to drive home the lessons taught (<a href="?bref=Pr.13.24">Prv 13:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.22.15">22:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.29.15-17">29:15-17</a>). Though children were loved and valued, they were not pampered (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.30.9-12">Ecclus 30:9-12</a>). In postexilic times education also took place within the precincts of the synagogue, and shortly before the time of Christ, a general elementary education was introduced. It was also imperative that a father teach his sons a trade, normally his own, for a man without a trade either starved or became a thief. Another important paternal responsibility was to provide wives for male offspring in the household.</p>
<p>The mother was responsible for her sons’ and daughters’ early education (<a href="?bref=Pr.1.8">Prv 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.6.20">6:20</a>), teaching them religious songs and prayers as soon as they could talk. A father took over the education of his sons, but the mother continued with the daughters, training them to spin, weave, cook, clean, trim the lamps, and generally to become competent in all the household duties (<a href="?bref=Pr.31.13-31">31:13-31</a>).</p>
<p>With little furniture, keeping a house clean meant sweeping the floors to keep them free from dust and dirt. Cooking was at once simple and difficult. It was simple in that much of the food was cooked in the form of a soup or stew, or else made into a cake and cooked on a griddle. It was difficult in that the corn had to be ground by hand and bread was baked daily.</p>
<p>A mother was expected to take wool, card it, spin it, and often weave and make clothes for her family. In addition, she would help her husband in the fields at harvesttime. Because many families had one or more olive trees, a few grapevines, and fig trees, the mother would also assist in picking the fruit. She would sometimes work at the press when the olives or grapes were being processed. Frequently the treading of grapes in the family vat would be done together by husband and wife. Drawing water from the well was considered a menial task and was generally the wife’s responsibility, although sometimes it was assigned to the children (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.15-16">Gn 24:15-16</a>).</p>
<p>As in all societies, there was a time when children laughed and played together (<a href="?bref=Zech.8.5">Zec 8:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.11.16">Mt 11:16</a>), although childhood and adolescence were not recognized as specific stages of development. Children were considered as sucklings if under three, but were regarded as boys or girls when they were able to take care of themselves. A small child sat on his mother’s lap and was played with (<a href="?bref=Isa.66.12">Is 66:12</a>). There is no evidence of organized sports for children. Toys, including whistles, rattles, dolls, and miniature cooking utensils, have been excavated at Palestinian sites.</p>
<p>As soon as a boy was old enough, he took his place in the family and accepted his appointed task. Among other things, children were expected to gather fuel (<a href="?bref=Jer.7.18">Jer 7:18</a>). Young boys and girls tended the flocks. The sheep had to be protected from marauding wild beasts, guarded against their own folly when they wandered near crevices, steered toward good pasture and water, and carried home when sick or injured (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.6">Gn 29:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.2.16">Ex 2:16</a>). The care of cattle was also the responsibility of children (<a href="?bref=1Sam.16.11">1 Sm 16:11</a>). Of necessity, boys were trained in the various arts of war.</p>
<p>Children sometimes joined their fathers in the fields, and their presence was always welcome. From earliest times, boys in particular would watch their fathers until they too picked up a tool or implement to try their skill; girls watched and learned from their mothers. Young children frequently listened to the talk of the elders at the city gates or in the villages. A visit to a sanctuary at festival time was a family affair, furnishing an ideal learning experience. As a child, Jesus accompanied his parents, Mary and Joseph, to the temple in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.42-47">Lk 2:42-47</a>).</p>
<p>Young girls were surprisingly free to go about their appointed tasks. They were not secluded or veiled and could visit uninhibited with friends and neighbors (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.1">Gn 34:1</a>). They were also able to converse with men without embarrassment (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.15-25">24:15-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.29.11-12">29:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.9.11-13">1 Sm 9:11-13</a>).</p>
<p>Mealtimes were strictly family times. It is doubtful whether a meal comparable to a breakfast was eaten, and a farmer would probably have a light lunch in the fields. The main meal of the day was prepared by the mother, and it would be eaten in the early evening. Although the variety of food available was limited, its preparation was time-consuming.</p>
<p>Feast times were periods of great religious significance and were also the days when family members participated in the symbolic rituals of their faith. Among the Israelites several kinds of food were fundamental to their religious ritual. Family unity and the national religion were molded together by special meals in the home.</p>
<p>Daylight played an important part in the daily habits of the people in antiquity. Although oil lamps were readily available in later periods, it was customary to rise with the sun and go to bed relatively soon after dark. The wife would probably be up before sunrise and might continue her labor after dark.</p>
<p class="h2" id="InNewTestamentTimes">In New Testament Times</p>
<p class="fl">By NT times, for those who followed the Greek and Roman style, life became more elegant. Despite that, the status of many family members did not change substantially. Wealthier families had more slaves, and the children were more likely to have formal education, sometimes spending less effort on family chores. Even in Roman times, however, the father still had a legal right to accept or reject his child.</p>
<p>The status of the woman had definitely improved by the NT period. A Roman matron was highly respected and exerted a strong influence over her husband. She was not sequestered in a particular section of the house, as a Greek woman was, but managed and supervised tasks in any part of her home. She helped her husband in business, had her own place in theaters, games, and religious festivals, and sometimes managed her own property. Palestinian women began to enjoy a new status and dignity as the result of Jesus’ attitude toward women and its influence on the early Christian church.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Education_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Education</a>; <a href="?item=MarriageMarriageCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Marriage, Marriage Customs</a>; <a href="?item=SexSexuality_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sex, Sexuality</a>; <a href="?item=Widow_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Widow</a>; <a href="?item=Woman_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Woman</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>