<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="FeastsandFestivalsofIsrael">
  <title>Feasts and Festivals of Israel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FEASTS AND FESTIVALS OF ISRAEL</p>
<p class="fl">Occasions of public or private rejoicing to commemorate some significant event or personage. The element of celebration has a special meaning in the cycle of religious occasions and the rites and ceremonies associated with these particular days. While the idea of a feast commonly implies a banquet with plenteous food and drink, this element is not indispensable. Sometimes there is only a token amount, as in the celebration of Holy Communion.</p>
<include_items src="../Charts/Charts.xml" name="AnnualFeastsAndFestivalsOfIsrael"/>
<p>In contemporary usage “festival” usually refers to activities extending over a period of time, while “feast” indicates one part of the celebration, often a meal. However, in religious usage, both ancient and modern, the two words are used interchangeably. The ancient Hebrews employed the words <span class="hebrew">mo’ed</span> (“seasons”) and <span class="hebrew">hag</span> for their great public celebrations, while feasts of a more private nature were commonly described by the term <span class="hebrew">mishteh</span><span class="ital">.</span> The majority of English translations of Scripture do not differentiate between these words.</p>
<p class="h2" id="FeastsandTheirFunctions">Feasts and Their Functions</p>
<p class="fl">Each festival places great emphasis on community participation and on the continuity of social or religious tradition, especially where the celebrations are elements of a regular civil or religious calendar. Without community backing, even in a family celebration, no festival can be successful. When there is communal participation, a festival can reinforce the individual and community memory of specific occasions, and can perpetuate that store of recollection over years and generations. Such shared memory has a cohesive effect upon a cooperating community, large or small, and serves to establish the traditions by which the group lives. If the festival commemorates a particular event or celebrates some lofty ideal, that theme becomes more firmly embedded in the minds of the participants by being associated repeatedly with the rites and ceremonies performed. The feasts of the ancient Hebrews had this positive function. The great festivals of their religious calendar commemorated specific occasions when God had reached out in power to intervene for his people or had provided for them in their distress. By celebrating these feasts on a regular basis, the Hebrews continually affirmed that their God had directed their destiny. Their repeated rehearsal of God’s help and love for them reminded them that he was still able to sustain them. Especially in times of hardship, it pointed to the reality of God’s presence and activity among them. Faith sustained by this means furnished an invaluable spiritual dimension to the life of the nation and provided a sense of continuity under divine provision and guidance. Only when corrupt or pagan elements were introduced into festive occasions did this important ingredient of national life begin to lose its vitality.</p>
<p class="h2" id="OldTestamentFestivals">Old Testament Festivals</p>
<p class="h3">General Festivals</p>
<p class="fl">These occasions were surprisingly numerous in Israel, considering the rather austere mode of life reflected in much of the OT. No doubt such celebrations offset or compensated for the hardships and insecurities of existence in the ancient Near East, and the Israelites made the most of every opportunity. A wedding was one of the most obvious occasions for celebration, and it is not surprising that a feast was prepared for the marriage of Rachel and Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.22">Gn 29:22</a>) in which the whole neighborhood participated. Just how long this particular feast lasted is unknown, but some marriage festivals continued for a week, as in the case of the marriage between Samson and the woman of Timnah (<a href="?bref=Judg.14.17">Jgs 14:17</a>). Wine that makes glad man’s heart (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.15">Ps 104:15</a>) was consumed freely on such occasions.</p>
<p>Birthdays were often observed in a festive spirit, especially where a royal person was concerned (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.20">Gn 40:20</a>). Solomon’s dream was commemorated with a feast provided for his servants (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.3.15">1 Kgs 3:15</a>), and when the temple was dedicated, the occasion was celebrated for a full week (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.65">8:65</a>). Kings and queens held feasts periodically to mark certain occasions or to express goodwill (cf. <a href="?bref=Esth.1.3">Est 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.2.18">2:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.5.4,14">5:4, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.7.2,7">7:2, 7</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.5.1">Dn 5:1</a>). Herdsmen traditionally made a feast for the shearing of the first sheep (<a href="?bref=Deut.18.4">Dt 18:4</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Preexilic Festivals</p>
<p class="fl">In addition to the general festivals, which were frequently of a secular nature, communal feasts were prescribed for the Israelites that had a specifically spiritual significance. They were meant to emphasize the activity of God on behalf of his people and to remind them that continued divine blessing depended upon their obedience to his will. The catalog of festivals in <a href="?bref=Lev.23.2">Leviticus 23:2</a> began with an injunction to observe the Sabbath. The seventh day, in which God ceased from creating (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.3">Gn 2:3</a>), was holy, though it is difficult to determine the extent to which it was kept until the time of Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.8-11">Ex 20:8-11</a>). From that time on, Sabbath observance stressed refraining from all work so as to commemorate properly God’s own rest from creative activity (<a href="?bref=Exod.31.17">31:17</a>) and his deliverance of his people from bondage in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Deut.5.12-15">Dt 5:12-15</a>). Sabbath celebration was the sign of a special relationship between God and the Israelites. During this 24-hour period, even trivial tasks like making a fire (<a href="?bref=Exod.35.3">Ex 35:3</a>) or gathering wood (<a href="?bref=Num.15.32-33">Nm 15:32-33</a>) were prohibited on pain of death. Journeys of any distance also came under the Sabbath ban (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.29">Ex 16:29</a>). Special offerings were part of the observance (<a href="?bref=Num.28.9-10">Nm 28:9-10</a>), and the bread of the Presence was replaced in the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.5-8">Lv 24:5-8</a>). Despite the restrictions on activity, the Sabbath was meant to symbolize a time of happiness and security in the presence of God (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.58.13-14">Is 58:13-14</a>), since its observance would bring blessing to the individual and to the whole land.</p>
<p class="h4">Festival of the New Moon</p>
<p class="fl">The new moon was a monthly celebration based on the lunar calendar. It was especially appropriate for an agricultural people, since everyone could tell when the moon was new. Special offerings were prescribed for this festival, consisting of a burnt sacrifice, a grain offering, and a drink offering (<a href="?bref=Num.28.11-15">Nm 28:11-15</a>). In addition, a male goat was sacrificed to God as a sin offering, and trumpet blasts were sounded over the sacrificial offerings as a memorial before God (<a href="?bref=Num.10.10">10:10</a>). The sacrifices prescribed for the new moon festival were significantly greater than those required in <a href="?bref=Num.28.9-10">Numbers 28:9-10</a> for the weekly Sabbath.</p>
<p>This lunar feast was popular throughout Israelite history. During the monarchy, the Levites were required to assist the Aaronic priests at the new moon festival, as well as on the Sabbath (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.29-31">1 Chr 23:29-31</a>). The preexilic prophets may well have taken advantage of the large gatherings to give guidance to the people or proclaim prophetic oracles (cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.23">2 Kgs 4:23</a>), though to what extent this was done is uncertain. Not everyone found the period of rest and celebration valuable, however, and Amos (<a href="?bref=Amos.8.5">Am 8:5</a>) complained about those avaricious Israelites who felt that such observances interfered with the business of making a living. The feast could not be observed when the Judeans were in exile in Babylonia (cf. <a href="?bref=Hos.2.11">Hos 2:11</a>), but under Ezra and Nehemiah, its observance was restored (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.33">Neh 10:33</a>). In <a href="?bref=Isa.66.22-23">Isaiah 66:22-23</a> it was related to Israel’s final destiny and was an accepted part of the ordinances for Ezekiel’s ideal temple (<a href="?bref=Ezek.45.17">Ez 45:17</a>).</p>
<p>The purpose of the festival was to enhance the unity of national life by reminding the Israelites that God’s covenant with their ancestors was permanent and still binding upon the nation. It also stressed the loving nature and providence of a God who could begin such a relationship and carry out his promises with complete faithfulness (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.104.19">Ps 104:19</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">The Festival of Trumpets</p>
<p class="fl">The Festival of Trumpets was celebrated on the first day of the seventh new moon. This month, subsequently named Tishri, was especially holy, and for this reason was governed by certain regulations different from those of ordinary new moon festivals. The trumpets were blown on the first day (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.24">Lv 23:24</a>) as the animal and cereal sacrifices were offered. From <a href="?bref=Num.29.2-6">Numbers 29:2-6</a> it appears that the offerings required for this particular feast exceeded those prescribed for normal Sabbath sacrifice, but were somewhat less than those required for the regular new moon festival (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.28.11">Nm 28:11</a>). This feast was to be observed as a day of solemn rest and as a holy convocation, and the trumpets were sounded as a triumphant memorial to God’s great provision for his people through the Sinai covenant.</p>
<p>The seventh month was particularly sacred, partly because of its place in the hallowed cycle of sevens, but also because the Day of Atonement (or Yom Kippur) and the Feast of Tabernacles, or Booths (Shelters), occurred during this period. The latter feast followed the Day of Atonement by some five days (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.33">Lv 23:33</a>), and its joyful character served to offset somewhat the solemnity of the annual penitential occasion when the nation confessed its collective sins and saw them banished symbolically into the wilderness as the scapegoat was driven from the congregation.</p>
<p class="h4">The Sabbatical Year</p>
<p class="fl">Another festival closely connected with the institution of the Sabbath was the sabbatical year. At the end of each cycle of six years, the following 12 months were observed as a “sabbath of rest for the land.” During this interval, the ground was to lie fallow (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.11">Ex 23:11</a>) without any form of cultivation, and whatever sprouted and grew from it naturally was assigned to the poor and needy (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.6">Lv 25:6</a>). This provision for the land itself constituted one of the most important ecological principles of Scripture. Like God’s people, the land was holy, and just as they needed to have regular intervals of rest from daily work in order to regain their energy and spiritual vitality through worship, so the ground needed to rest and recuperate from the strain of constant cultivation. The festival reminded the Israelites that the land on which they lived had been given to them by God in fulfillment of his covenant undertaking to provide richly for their physical needs (cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.8.7-10">Dt 8:7-10</a>). To keep the Israelites from experiencing any shortages or other hardships during the Year of Sabbath, God promised that in the year immediately preceding the sabbatical period, the land would bear fruit to suffice for the next three years (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.21">Lv 25:21</a>). This assurance was based upon the experience of the wilderness wanderings, when on the sixth day of the week sufficient manna appeared to last through the Sabbath (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.5">Ex 16:5</a>).</p>
<p>In this festival period, God’s absolute claim over the land was reaffirmed (cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.25.23">Lv 25:23</a>), and the faith of the nation in God’s ability to provide for future needs was reinforced. The provisions that freed the land for a year from agricultural bondage were paralleled in the seventh year of rest by those requiring liberation of slaves and debtors. These underprivileged members of society were to be released from their obligations of servitude. As a result, men and women who had become slaves for one reason or another were given personal liberty (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.2-6">Ex 21:2-6</a>), and under proclamation of the Lord’s release, the provisions applying to debt were rescinded (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.1-6">Dt 15:1-6</a>). The sabbatical year seems to have been a regular part of preexilic Israelite life, although some abuses were noted in <a href="?bref=Jer.34.8-22">Jeremiah 34:8-22</a>. There the prophet took advantage of the opportunity presented to instruct the people in the nature and purpose of the sabbatical year ordinance. He also warned the wayward Judeans that because they had disobeyed the commands of God in denying proper liberty to their slaves, they would have their own freedom taken away in a far more serious manner by being carried captive to Babylonia after seeing their land destroyed. The lesson was not lost upon those who returned from exile, for under the administration of Nehemiah, the Jews bound themselves by a covenant to observe the principle of the sabbatical year (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.31">Neh 10:31</a>). This undertaking evidently took its impetus from the reading of the law of Moses at the Feast of Booths (Shelters), which coincidentally occurred at the beginning of the sabbatical year (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.13-18">Neh 8:13-18</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">Jubilee</p>
<p class="fl">Still another feast based on the principle of the sabbath was the Year of Jubilee, or Pentecostal year (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.8-55">Lv 25:8-55</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.27.17-24">27:17-24</a>). As the sabbatical year was related to the concept of the seventh day, so the Pentecostal (50th) year marked the completion of a cycle of seven sabbatical years. The commencement of a jubilee year was proclaimed on the Day of Atonement throughout the land by means of trumpet blasts (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.9">Lv 25:9</a>). The activities that took place during the Pentecostal year were similar to those prescribed for the sabbatical year. A special feature was that land that had been sold during the preceding 49 years was returned to its original owners, a procedure that sometimes involved financial adjustments. To prevent abuse of the process through opportunism or speculation, the Hebrews were instructed to deal fairly and honestly with one another in the fear of God, who was the real owner of the land (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.14-17">Lv 25:14-17</a>). As with the sabbatical year, God promised to make provision before the jubilee year so that no one would suffer hardship. It was during the Year of Jubilee that those who were slaves in Hebrew households were given their liberty, so that everyone in the land would commence a new cycle of sabbatical years on the same footing, as free persons under God.</p>
<p class="h3">Seasonal Festivals</p>
<p class="fl">Three annual festivals that followed the seasons of the year rather than phases of the moon furnished important occasions for commemorating God’s power and provision in national life. These festivals were designated by the term <span class="hebrew">hag</span><span class="ital">,</span> indicating a festival usually observed by some sort of pilgrimage. These three festivals were prescribed in <a href="?bref=Exod.23.14-17">Exodus 23:14-17</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.16.16">Deuteronomy 16:16</a>, and consisted of the Feast of Passover and Unleavened Bread, the Feast of Weeks (Pentecost), and the Festival of Booths (Tabernacles). On these occasions, all the males of Israel were commanded to make pilgrimage to the sanctuary and celebrate these festivals (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.14">Ex 12:14</a>). The Passover and the Feast of Unleavened Bread were originally separate ordinances, but since the latter always followed immediately upon the Passover rite, they naturally blended into a single festival.</p>
<p class="h4">Passover</p>
<p class="fl">The Passover was of supreme theological significance for the Israelites, since it marked one of the most momentous acts of divine intervention in their history, the beginning of their deliverance from bondage in Egypt when, in the final plague, God destroyed the firstborn of the Egyptians but spared those Israelites whose homes had blood smeared on the doorposts (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.11-30">Ex 12:11-30</a>). God commanded that the day was to be observed as a memorial feast (v <a href="?bref=Exod.12.14">14</a>), and the next Passover celebration occurred in the Sinai Desert (<a href="?bref=Num.9.1-5">Nm 9:1-5</a>). In the Hebrew calendar the Passover festival came in the first month, called Abib in <a href="?bref=Deut.16.1">Deuteronomy 16:1</a>, but known after the exile as Nisan (cf. <a href="?bref=Neh.2.1">Neh 2:1</a>). The Passover rite took place the 14th evening (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.5">Lv 23:5</a>), and this was followed by a seven-day period during which nothing leavened was to be eaten. The principle for removing all leaven from bread was similar to that underlying the draining of blood from animal flesh. Both leaven and blood had quickening power and were to be kept separate as an offering to God. The first and seventh days of this period were marked by a holy assembly, during which the only work permitted was the preparation of food (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.16">Ex 12:16</a>). This period when unleavened bread was eaten was described as a festival because it opened the seven-week period of grain harvest (<a href="?bref=Deut.16.9">Dt 16:9</a>). During this feast, special burnt sacrifices were offered, followed with a sheaf of newly harvested barley at the Feast of Firstfruits. By NT times the festivals of Passover and Unleavened Bread were well-attended celebrations and were known as the “days of unleavened bread” (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.1">Lk 22:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.12.3">Acts 12:3</a>). The theme of Israel’s deliverance from the power of Egypt by divine intervention assured the Israelites that God was always ready to act on behalf of a faithful and obedient covenant people. It also reminded them that they had once been slaves (<a href="?bref=Deut.16.12">Dt 16:12</a>). In Israelite life the early Passover and Unleavened Bread observances were comparatively simple in character, but during the monarchy more elaborate Passover rituals came into use (cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.21-23">2 Kgs 23:21-23</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.35.1-19">2 Chr 35:1-19</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">Pentecost</p>
<p class="fl">The second great festival, Pentecost (or Weeks) lasted one day only and was observed on the 50th day after the newly harvested barley sheaf had been waved before the Lord at the end of the Feast of Unleavened Bread (<a href="?bref=Deut.16.9-12">Dt 16:9-12</a>). The festival marked the end of the barley harvest and the beginning of the wheat harvest, the beginning of the period when firstfruits could be offered (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.23.16">Ex 23:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.22">34:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.28.26">Nm 28:26</a>). The feast day was marked by the presentation of two wheat-flour loaves along with sacrifices of seven lambs, two rams, and a bull (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.15-20">Lv 23:15-20</a>). Freewill gifts to God were presented to reflect gratitude for his blessings, and the entire occasion was one of communal rejoicing (<a href="?bref=Deut.16.10-11">Dt 16:10-11</a>). Since Pentecost was essentially a harvest festival (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.16">Ex 23:16</a>), the Israelites were called on to recognize that they depended entirely upon God for their material prosperity. In <a href="?bref=Deut.26.1-19">Deuteronomy 26</a>, specific instructions were given for the ritual of presenting firstfruits from the harvest. It comprised a great confession of faith set within the framework of Israel’s history, and it recounted God’s deliverance of the nation from Egyptian oppression and his provision of a land that could amply supply the needs of his people.</p>
<p class="h4">Festival of Tabernacles</p>
<p class="fl">This festival, known variously as the Feast of Booths, Tabernacles, Shelters (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.34">Lv 23:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.16.13">Dt 16:13</a>), or Ingathering (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.22">Ex 34:22</a>), was the third great occasion that all Hebrew males were required to observe annually. It began on the 15th day of the seventh month (Tishri), shortly after the observance of the Day of Atonement, which fell on the 10th day. The Feast of Booths lasted for one week and involved pilgrimage. It was associated initially with the end of the year (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.22">Ex 34:22</a>), when the agricultural work had been completed. The first day was marked by a symbolic cessation from all activity, after which burnt offerings were presented to the Lord. The eighth day was also one on which the congregation of Israel abstained from manual work and again offered burnt sacrifices. <a href="?bref=Lev.23.39-43">Leviticus 23:39-43</a> furnished details for the rituals that gave the festival its special name of booths or shelters or tabernacles. The fruit of “goodly trees” was to be gathered on the first day of the feast, along with palm fronds, willow branches, and boughs from trees in full leaf. From these, rough shelters or booths were to be constructed in which the people lived for the week of the feast. Every seventh year the observances were marked by a public recital of the covenant provisions to which the Israelites under Moses had committed themselves, a procedure designed to keep fresh in their minds the obligations as well as the blessings of the covenant relationship. A particularly significant observance of the Feast of Tabernacles took place in the time of Ezra, when the Judean community returned from Babylon—a celebration of a kind unknown for centuries (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.13-18">Neh 8:13-18</a>). From the context it appears that observance of the feast had lapsed during the monarchy. The feast at Shiloh where Hannah was mistaken for a drunken woman and the feast referred to in <a href="?bref=Judg.21.19">Judges 21:19</a> were evidently the Feast of Booths. In a prophetic vision in which he saw all nations coming to Jerusalem to observe the Festival of Booths, Zechariah warned that those who did not continue this tradition could expect hardship and shortages of food (<a href="?bref=Zech.14.16-19">Zec 14:16-19</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Postexilic Festivals</p>
<p class="fl">There are a few minor festivals that were created in the period after the Jews returned from exile; some of these festivals had their origin in specific historical occasions.</p>
<p class="h4">The Festival of Purim</p>
<p class="fl">The Festival of Purim, also known as the Festival of Lots, was a joyful occasion occurring on the 14th day of the 12th month (Adar). It celebrated the way in which Esther and Mordecai were used by God to deliver his people in the Persian Empire from extermination by Haman (<a href="?bref=Esth.9.21,24-28">Est 9:21, 24-28</a>). The feast was observed on the 14th day of Adar by those living in villages, and on the 15th by the inhabitants of walled towns and cities. The explanation of the name of the festival is given in <a href="?bref=Esth.9.24-26">Esther 9:24-26</a>, and its observance reminded the Hebrews of God’s ability to save them during a time of anti-Semitic activity in Persia. The deliverance memorialized in this festival has consoled the Jews on other occasions when they have suffered persecution. Traditionally the scroll of Esther was read aloud in the synagogue on the evening before the feast, and there was a great outcry, especially among the children present, whenever the names of the hated Haman and his sons were mentioned.</p>
<p class="h4">Festival of the Dedication of the Temple</p>
<p class="fl">Another joyous festival that lasted for eight days was the Feast of the Dedication of the Temple (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.4.52-59">1 Macc 4:52-59</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Macc.10.6-8">2 Macc 10:6-8</a>), familiar to modern readers as Hanukkah, or the Festival of Lights. The specific dedication that prompted the feast occurred in 164 <span class="era">BC</span>, when Judas Maccabeus reconsecrated the temple in Jerusalem after it had been defiled by Antiochus IV Epiphanes. The celebrations commenced on the 25th day of the ninth month (Kislev) and were marked at night by blazing lights and lanterns. The stories of brave opposition by the Maccabees to the crushing forces of paganism were recounted, and the feast was one of praise to God for his marvelous deliverance of the Jews during the Maccabean period.</p>
<p class="h2" id="NewTestamentFestivals">New Testament Festivals</p>
<p class="fl">In Christ’s time the Sabbath was observed rigorously and was the occasion for synagogue worship (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.4.16">Lk 4:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.14">Acts 13:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.4">18:4</a>). Pharisaic law prohibited all work, and Jesus came into conflict with the authorities periodically for breaches of the Sabbath regulations (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.12.1-4">Mt 12:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.1-5">Mk 3:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.10-17">Lk 13:10-17</a>). In the primitive church, worship occurred on “the first day of the week” (i.e., Sunday) to commemorate Christ’s resurrection. The early Christians initially participated in Jewish ceremonies (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.20.16">Acts 20:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.8">1 Cor 16:8</a>). It was during the Feast of Pentecost, after Christ’s resurrection and ascension, that the Spirit was poured out (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.1-4">Acts 2:1-4</a>), fulfilling <a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-32">Joel 2:28-32</a> and commencing the history of the Christian church as such.</p>
<p>The Passover and Feast of Unleavened Bread were of great significance in the life of Christ (cf. <a href="?bref=John.4.45">Jn 4:45</a>; <a href="?bref=John.5.1">5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.4">6:4</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.1-26">12:1-26</a>), for the occasion was a very popular one in NT times (cf. <a href="?bref=John.12.20">12:20</a>). On the Passover, Pilate had instituted the custom of clemency to a prisoner nominated by the populace (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.15">Mt 27:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.15.6">Mk 15:6</a>). Jesus participated actively in the Passover rituals (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.2.42">Lk 2:42</a>; <a href="?bref=John.2.13">Jn 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.4">6:4</a>). The Last Supper with his disciples occurred just prior to the Passover (<a href="?bref=John.13.1">Jn 13:1</a>), when Judas Iscariot betrayed Jesus to the Pharisees (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.4-6">Lk 22:4-6</a>). The breaking of bread and the drinking of wine at that Passover celebration (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.22-25">Mk 14:22-25</a>) were related directly to Christ’s forthcoming death on the cross in a sacramental manner. Christ’s disciples were instructed to observe this rite as a memorial of his suffering and death for human sin (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.24-26">1 Cor 11:24-26</a>) and as a proclamation of the power of the cross until the Lord returns in glory. Some scholars have suggested that Christ was actually hanging on the cross when the Passover lamb was being slaughtered, and if that chronology is correct, it would represent Jesus graphically as the “Lamb of God, who takes away the sin of the world” (<a href="?bref=John.1.29">Jn 1:29</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Jesus was also present once when the Feast of Tabernacles was celebrated (<a href="?bref=John.7.10">7:10</a>). In his day water was carried in procession from the pool of Siloam as an offering to God, and the ceremony most probably prompted Christ’s discourse on living water and eternal life (vv <a href="?bref=John.7.37-39">37-39</a>). On at least one occasion Jesus was in Jerusalem when the Festival of Lights occurred (<a href="?bref=John.10.22">Jn 10:22</a>) and narrowly missed death by stoning.</p>
<p>Jesus was entertained occasionally at private feasts (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.5.29">Lk 5:29</a>), and once remedied an emergency situation when the wine ran out at a wedding ceremony (<a href="?bref=John.2.8-10">Jn 2:8-10</a>). He was critical of the Pharisees for securing the chief seats at feasts (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.6">Mt 23:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.39">Mk 12:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.46">Lk 20:46</a>) and taught that festivals ought to benefit the poor (<a href="?bref=Luke.14.13">Lk 14:13</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="SymbolismofFeasts">Symbolism of Feasts</p>
<p class="fl">Many aspects of the ancient Hebrew feasts were interpreted symbolically in the early church. Paul regarded the earliest Hebrew Christians as the firstfruits of the Israel of God (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.16">Rom 11:16</a>). In <a href="?bref=Rom.8.23">Romans 8:23</a>, the Holy Spirit as possessed by Christians was regarded as only a token of what was to come, and as such was the firstfruit of the Spirit. Christians themselves were described in <a href="?bref=Jas.1.18">James 1:18</a> as the firstfruits of God’s creatures who were brought forth by the Word of Truth. The resurrection of Jesus was considered by Paul to be the firstfruits of those who slept (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.20,23">1 Cor 15:20, 23</a>). In an allusion to OT festivals, Paul spoke of the Sabbaths, new moons, and feasts as merely being a shadow of good things to come (<a href="?bref=Col.2.16-17">Col 2:16-17</a>). The Passover was used figuratively to emphasize that Christ our Passover Lamb had been sacrificed for us. Believers were urged to keep the feast with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth, and not with the old leaven of malice and evil (<a href="?bref=1Cor.5.7-8">1 Cor 5:7-8</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CalendarsAncientandModern_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Calendars, Ancient and Modern</a>; <a href="?item=OfferingsandSacrifices_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Offerings and Sacrifices</a>; <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>