<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Foreknowledge">
  <title>Foreknowledge*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FOREKNOWLEDGE*</p>
<p class="fl">Knowledge of things or events before they exist or happen.</p>
<p>In the NT the Greek equivalent of “foreknowledge” appears only seven times. It refers to the Christian’s advance warning about false teachers (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.17">2 Pt 3:17</a>); the Jews’ previous knowledge of Paul’s early life (<a href="?bref=Acts.26.4-5">Acts 26:4-5</a>); God’s previous knowledge of the death of Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.23">Acts 2:23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.18-20">1 Pt 1:18-20</a>); and knowledge of his people (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.2">Rom 11:2</a>) and of the church (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.28-30">Rom 8:28-30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.1-2">1 Pt 1:1-2</a>).</p>
<p>The concept of foreknowledge does, however, appear throughout the Bible in other ways. First, the allinclusiveness of the knowledge of God is clearly taught. God’s understanding is unlimited (<a href="?bref=Ps.147.5">Ps 147:5</a>). He knows every heart and thought (<a href="?bref=1Chr.28.9">1 Chr 28:9</a>). <a href="?bref=Ps.139.1-24">Psalm 139</a> provides an extended poetic description of God’s knowledge of all human thoughts, words, and actions. This knowledge extends to the flight of a sparrow and the number of hairs on the head (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.29-30">Mt 10:29-30</a>). From such limitless knowledge, it may be inferred that God also knows the future events of human history.</p>
<p>In addition, Scripture directly teaches that God is aware of events before they happen. This sets him apart from heathen idols, who lack the ability to foresee the future (<a href="?bref=Isa.44.6-8">Is 44:6-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.45.21">45:21</a>). It is God’s foreknowledge that provides the basis for the predictions of the prophets. God announced to Adam and Eve that the seed of the woman would certainly defeat the serpent and his seed (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Gn 3:15</a>). Promises of future blessing were given to Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.3">12:3</a>). God said to Moses, “I know that the king of Egypt will not let you go” (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.19">Ex 3:19</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The coming glory of the Messiah was declared by the OT prophets (see, e.g., <a href="?bref=Isa.9.1-7">Is 9:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.5-6">Jer 23:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.20-31">Ez 34:20-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.3.4-5">Hos 3:4-5</a>). In <a href="?bref=Dan.7.1-28">Daniel 7</a>, God revealed the rise and fall of future world empires and the establishment of the kingdom of God (see also <a href="?bref=Dan.2.31-45">Dn 2:31-45</a>). In many places the NT sees Christ’s ministry and the establishment of the Christian church as fulfillment of predictions made beforehand by the OT prophets (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.22">Mt 1:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.4.14">4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.8.17">8:17</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.38-41">Jn 12:38-41</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.17-21">Acts 2:17-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.3.22-25">3:22-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.8">Gal 3:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.5.6">Heb 5:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.10-12">1 Pt 1:10-12</a>).</p>
<p>For many of the early Greek philosophers, fate rigidly controlled all future events, including not only the events of human history but also the fortunes of the gods. Occasionally, a future event might be known by the gods and revealed to people, and such foreseen events could in no way be altered. This view is, of course, far different from the biblical view of the personal Creator who knows the future and guides history according to his own purpose.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the question of the relationship between God’s foreknowledge and human freedom has occupied the attention of theologians and philosophers over the centuries. It is sometimes argued that if God knows what will happen in the future, then it must happen. Therefore, it makes no difference at all what choice a person makes, since it could not have been otherwise.</p>
<p>The theologians of the early church emphatically denied that foreknowledge implies any predetermination of events. Justin Martyr, for example, said, “What we say about future events being foretold, we do not say it as though they come about by fatal necessity.” In other words, this means that just because God knows what is going to happen before it happens does not necessarily mean that he has <span class="ital">caused</span> it to happen.</p>
<p>Other theologians, fearing that foreknowledge destroys human freedom and responsibility, insist that God does not know future events either certainly or completely. Modern process theology, for example, conceives of God as growing and developing along with nature and man. This God, it is argued, can at most know only those events that have already taken place. Hence the future remains open and uncertain for God as well as for man. An older theologian, Adam Clarke, suggested that although God can know all future events, he chooses not to know some events beforehand.</p>
<p>Augustine denied foreknowledge for a different reason. He argued that God lives in eternity where all things are present. For God, then, there is no past or future. Hence he would not know things before they happened, since he would see all events from the vantage point of an eternal “now.” Augustine, of course, did not deny God’s knowledge of all things, even of things that are still in the future as far as we are concerned.</p>
<p>Because of the clear biblical teaching regarding God’s foreknowledge, evangelical theologians have generally held that God has complete knowledge of all future events. There is a further distinction, however. The followers of Calvin insist that God knows all events precisely because he sovereignly determines what is to happen in human history right down to the tiniest detail. Here foreknowledge is closely tied to, if not identified with, foreordination. At the same time, most Calvinistic theologians assert that human beings are nonetheless responsible for their choices—not victims of a blind fate. It is also generally held that God is not the author of sin. Rather, sin is the result of the rebellion of angels and men against a holy and righteous God.</p>
<p>Evangelicals in the Arminian tradition, on the other hand, distinguish foreknowledge from the foreordination of events. While salvation of the world, and human history in broad outline, are predetermined by God, it is argued that individual response to God is not so predetermined. Hence, God can foreknow an event without directly decreeing that event to take place.</p>
<p>While evangelical Christians differ in their descriptions of the relationship between the eternal all-knowing God and the events of human history, it should be kept in mind that Scripture teaches both God’s foreknowledge of all things and the responsibility of humans for their choices.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ElectElection_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Elect, Election</a>; <a href="?item=Foreordination_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Foreordination</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>