<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Fornication">
  <title>Fornication*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FORNICATION*</p>
<p class="fl">Unchastity, sexual immorality. The word “fornication” is used in the Scriptures to mean several different things.</p>
<p>Its general meaning refers to every kind of illegal sexual intercourse, that is, any intercourse except that between a husband and wife. For example, in <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.1">1 Corinthians 5:1</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) the word is used twice to refer to a sin that was being tolerated by the church: a man apparently was cohabitating with his stepmother. In a list of terrible sins in <a href="?bref=Rom.1.29">Romans 1:29</a>, the apostle Paul included fornication, apparently intending the term to mean all acts of sexual immorality (<span class="sc">kjv</span>). In 1 Corinthians the context suggests that Paul used the word in reference to all sorts of illicit sexual activity (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.13,18">6:13, 18</a>). In <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.2">1 Corinthians 7:2</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) Paul used the plural Greek word for “fornications” to imply the various ways in which the sin may manifest itself. He thus gave a reason why people in Corinth should marry and live together properly. One of the sins included in the word’s general sense is adultery.</p>
<p>“Fornication” also has a more limited sense of immoral sexual activity between unmarried people. Such a meaning is implied in those biblical lists where both fornication and adultery come together. Jesus’ list of the defiling sins that proceed out of a person’s heart includes “fornication” and “adultery” (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.19">Mt 15:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.7.21">Mk 7:21</a>). Paul’s list of those sinners who will not inherit the kingdom of God also contains both fornicators and adulterers (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.9">1 Cor 6:9</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>).</p>
<p>“Fornication” in <a href="?bref=Matt.5.32">Matthew 5:32</a> and <a href="?bref=Matt.19.9">19:9</a> (as translated by the <span class="sc">kjv</span>) is usually taken by biblical students today to refer specifically to adultery (see <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The translation of <span class="greek">porneia</span> has to do with interpretation rather than translation. Scholars disagree as to whether Jesus’ exceptive phrase relative to divorce has to do with fornication in a general or limited sense. He might have meant adultery alone, or he might have been including it generally with other sexual sins.</p>
<p>A figurative use of the word “fornication” appears in both the OT and NT. Originating in descriptions of Israel and the church as the Lord’s wife or the bride, apostasy from God and idolatry are called fornication (see, e.g., <a href="?bref=Jer.2.1-37">Jer 2</a>). <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.1-63">Ezekiel 16</a> uses unfaithfulness to marriage vows as a symbol of Jerusalem’s wayward relationship with God. Jerusalem had become an “unfaithful wife” to him. The first three chapters of Hosea use the relationship of the prophet Hosea and his unfaithful wife, Gomer, as an illustration of how the nation of Israel had become guilty of fornication against its “husband,” the Lord, by going after other gods. In the book of Revelation the figurative use of “fornication” and “impure passion” is ascribed to Babylon the great, the mother of harlots (<a href="?bref=Rev.14.8">Rv 14:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.2-4">17:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.18.3">18:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.2">19:2</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Adultery_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Adultery</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>