<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Fullness">
  <title>Fullness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FULLNESS</p>
<p class="fl">Common translation of the Greek term <span class="greek">pleroma</span><span class="ital">.</span> The word carries various shades of meaning that must be determined by observing its use in context.</p>
<p class="h2">General Usage</p>
<p class="fl">In Greek usage outside the NT, the word means “that which fills.” It is found in reference to the cargo or crew that fills a ship, the people that make up a crowd, and the years that fill a person’s life. The philosopher Aristotle used the term to denote the population that fills a city. That sense is used in Matthew’s and Mark’s Gospels of a patch that fills up a hole in an old garment (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.16">Mt 9:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.2.21">Mk 2:21</a>), and in Mark of the pieces of fish that fill a basket (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.43">Mk 6:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.20">8:20</a>).</p>
<p class="h2">“Earth” Expressions</p>
<p class="fl">In several instances in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> the term is found in the phrase “the earth and its fullness” (<a href="?bref=Ps.24.1">Pss 24:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.50.12">50:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.11">89:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.26">1 Cor 10:26</a>) or “the sea and its fullness” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.16.32">1 Chr 16:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.96.11-12">Ps 96:11-12</a>), meaning “contents.” Beyond its obvious quantitative sense, the meaning in these expressions may reflect a qualitative character: the contents of the earth are good and special. The Hebrew mind viewed the created order as a reflection of the Creator (<a href="?bref=Ps.8.5-6">Pss 8:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.19.1-6">19:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.24">Jer 23:24</a>). Accordingly, whenever people entered into relationship with anything God had created, whether in work or meals or relationships, they also entered objectively into relationship with God, who had given those things. Thus, the Jews heard with horror the prophetic announcement of God’s intention to bring destruction upon “the land and all that fills it” (<a href="?bref=Jer.8.16">Jer 8:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.47.2">47:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.12.19">Ez 12:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.19.7">19:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.30.12">30:12</a>).</p>
<p class="h2">The Apostle Paul’s Usage</p>
<p class="fl">The origin of Paul’s understanding and use of “fullness” as a significant theological term has been debated. It is held by some that the word was a technical term used by the Gnostics in reference to a realm of spiritual beings that bridged the space between the true God and an “evil” earth. Subsequently, false teachers came to view Christ as one among many deities who lived in that “fullness.” In order to correct the misunderstanding, Paul borrowed the term from his opponents and applied it to Christ. Jesus is not just one of the beings between God and humanity, Paul taught; rather, he is all there is (“the fullness”) between God and humanity (<a href="?bref=Col.1.15-20">Col 1:15-20</a>).</p>
<p>Against that view it is argued that Paul used the term in several contexts where that interpretation is obviously inadequate (<a href="?bref=Rom.13.10">Rom 13:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.22-23">Eph 1:22-23</a>). In addition, it is likely that Paul, with his Pharisaic Jewish background, would understand the term in light of its OT usage. Thus, Paul’s use of the term may be better understood as not borrowed from his opponents.</p>
<p>Paul used the term four times in the book of Romans. It can be rendered “full inclusion” in reference to the total number of Jews (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.12">Rom 11:12</a>) or Gentiles (v <a href="?bref=Rom.11.25">25</a>) who will come to God. In verse <a href="?bref=Rom.11.12">12</a>, however, the term is set in opposition to the “failure” and “trespass” of the Jews, who feel that righteousness is a matter of their Jewish heritage rather than faith. It may be that Paul used the term in reference to “complete obedience to God’s will.” Thus, in essence Paul said, “If their disobedience means this much good for the world, think of what their obedience will mean.” It is in this active sense that “fullness” is used in <a href="?bref=Rom.13.10">Romans 13:10</a>. Love brings to realization all that the law intends. Similarly, Paul desires that his own life be a full expression of the gospel of Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.29">15:29</a>).</p>
<p>In the book of Ephesians, the church is referred to as the “fullness of Christ” (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.22-23">Eph 1:22-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.13">4:13</a>), and “the fullness of God” (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.19">3:19</a>). A variety of interpretations have been offered for this phrase: the church is filled, made complete or whole by Christ; the church possesses the attributes of Christ; the church is the agent through which Christ does all his work. The church is full of Christ in that it is the complete, continuing expression of his words and works (compare <a href="?bref=Col.2.10">Col 2:10</a>). In the book of Colossians, Paul used the term in reference to Christ; in him dwells the “fullness of God” (<a href="?bref=Col.1.19">1:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.2.9">2:9</a>). These passages are often interpreted as proclaiming the equality of Christ with God. All of God’s attributes are contained in Christ. All that God is, Christ is.</p>
<p class="h2">The Apostle John’s Usage</p>
<p class="fl">The prologue to John’s Gospel states that the “fullness of Christ” is received by all believers (<a href="?bref=John.1.16">1:16</a>). The exact nature of this fullness is defined in verse <a href="?bref=John.1.14">14</a>: “And the Word became flesh and dwelt among us, full of grace and truth.” The Greek word for “fullness” here indicates plenitude and totality. The Gnostics used the word to describe the totality of all deities. John, as with Paul, used the word to describe Christ as the fullness, the plenitude of God, for all the fullness of the Godhead dwells in him bodily (see <a href="?bref=Col.1.19">Col 1:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.2.9">2:9</a>).</p>
<p>Since all of God’s fullness dwells in Christ, every spiritual reality is found in Christ. In Christ, believers lack nothing. Of course, no single believer could receive all that Christ is; it takes the body of Christ to appropriate Christ’s fullness and to express it (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.23">Eph 1:23</a>). Nevertheless, each believer receives in measure the same content of that fullness. Christ is continually full; he never is depleted. No matter how much the believers receive of him, he keeps on giving. Believers do not need to seek any other source but Christ.</p>
  </body>
</item>