<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Furnace">
  <title>Furnace</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FURNACE</p>
<p class="fl">Brick or stone structure varying in size and shape, depending on whether it was to be used domestically or commercially. A typical furnace consisted of a firebox, a flue, a chamber for the material to be heated, and an opening to give the refiner access from the outside. Common uses of the furnace were to smelt ore, melt ore for casting, heat ore for forging, fire ceramic materials, fire bricks, and make lime.</p>
<p>Various types of furnaces are mentioned in Scripture. The potter’s kiln was used to make lime and to fire and glaze pottery (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.28">Gn 19:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.9.8,10">Ex 9:8, 10</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.19.18">19:18</a>). It was commonly made of limestone, was dome-shaped, had a chimney for smoke to escape, and a hole at the bottom for fuel. Such a furnace emitted a thick, dark column of smoke.</p>
<p>Larger furnaces used for smelting ore were seldom employed by the Hebrews, except possibly in the time of King Solomon. The Hebrews, however, knew of this type of furnace, probably from its extensive use in Lebanon. Most OT references to such furnaces are figurative (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.20">Dt 4:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.51">1 Kgs 8:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.17.3">Prv 17:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.27.21">27:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.48.10">Is 48:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.11.4">Jer 11:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.22.18-22">Ez 22:18-22</a>). This kind of large, ore-smelting furnace is central in the story of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, the three Jewish men whom King Nebuchadnezzar threw into the fiery furnace for refusing to bow down and worship his golden idol (<a href="?bref=Dan.3.1-30">Dn 3</a>).</p>
<p>The most common use of “furnace” in the Bible is to provide a figurative description of God’s discipline or punishment and his refining of character (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.20">Dt 4:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.51">1 Kgs 8:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.48.10">Is 48:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.27-30">Jer 6:27-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.22.18-22">Ez 22:18-22</a>). In the NT “furnace” is used as a symbol for hell (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.42,50">Mt 13:42, 50</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.9.2">Rv 9:2</a>). The refining image is used to refer to the trials of life that prepare a person for life after death (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.12">Jas 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.7">1 Pt 1:7</a>). In John’s vision, the one who is like the Son of Man has “feet like unto fine brass, as if they burned in a furnace” (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.15">Rv 1:15</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). This reference to refined brass, an extremely hard metal, is symbolic of Christ’s power to conquer his enemies.</p>
  </body>
</item>