<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Oath">
  <title>Oath</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OATH</p>
<p class="fl">Solemn vow or promise to fulfill a pledge. There are two terms in Hebrew that mean “oath”: <span class="hebrew">‘ala</span> and <span class="hebrew">sebu’a</span><span class="ital">.</span> The latter, more general term in ancient times meant to enter into a solemn (even magical) relationship with the number seven, although ancient connections are lost. Even so, when Abraham and Abimelech entered into an oath at Beersheba (the well of seven, or the well of the oath), Abraham set aside seven ewe lambs as a witness to the fact that he had dug a well (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.22-31">Gn 21:22-31</a>). The former term <span class="hebrew">‘ala</span><span class="ital">,</span> often translated “oath,” properly means “curse.” At times the two terms are used together (<a href="?bref=Num.5.21">Nm 5:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.10.29">Neh 10:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.9.11">Dn 9:11</a>). Any breach of one’s undertaking affirmed by an oath would be attended by a curse. The Lord affirmed that he had established a covenant and a curse with Israel—that is, a breach of covenant would be followed by a curse (<a href="?bref=Deut.29.14-29">Dt 29:14ff</a>.).</p>
<p>An oath was taken to confirm an agreement or, in a political situation, to confirm a treaty. Both in Israel and among its neighbors, God (or the gods) would act as the guarantor(s) of the agreement and his name (or their names) was invoked for this purpose. When Jacob and Laban made an agreement, they erected a heap of stones as a witness (<a href="?bref=Gen.31.53">Gn 31:53</a>). If either party transgressed the terms, it was a heinous sin. For this reason one of the Ten Commandments dealt with empty affirmations: “Do not misuse the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God. The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will not let you go unpunished if you misuse his name” (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.7">Ex 20:7</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The people of Israel were forbidden to swear their oaths by false gods (<a href="?bref=Jer.12.16">Jer 12:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.14">Am 8:14</a>). To breach an international treaty, where the oath was taken in the Lord’s name, merited death (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.16-17">Ez 17:16-17</a>). It was one of the complaints of Hosea that the people of his day swore falsely when they made a covenant (<a href="?bref=Hos.10.4">Hos 10:4</a>). Judgment would attend such wanton disregard of the solemnity of an oath. Certain civil situations in Israel called for an oath (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.10-11">Ex 22:10-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.5.1">Lv 5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.3">6:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.5.11-28">Nm 5:11-28</a>). This practice provided a pattern for the Israelite covenantal oath of allegiance between God and his people.</p>
<p>Christ taught that oaths were binding (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.33">Mt 5:33</a>). In the kingdom of God oaths would become unnecessary (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.5.34-37">34-37</a>). At his trial before Caiaphas, Jesus heard an imprecatory oath from the high priest (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.63-65">26:63-65</a>), and Paul swore by an oath on occasion (<a href="?bref=2Cor.1.23">2 Cor 1:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.20">Gal 1:20</a>). God himself was bound by his own oath (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.13-18">Heb 6:13-18</a>) to keep his promise to the patriarchs (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.24">Gn 50:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.19-37,49">Pss 89:19-37, 49</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.110.1-4">110:1-4</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Covenant_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Covenant</a>; <a href="?item=VowVows_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Vows</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>