<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ObedEdom">
  <title>Obed-Edom</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OBED-EDOM</p>
<p class="list">1. Man under whose care David placed the ark of the covenant when he was transferring it from Gibeah to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=2Sam.6.10-12">2 Sm 6:10-12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.13.5-14">1 Chr 13:5-14</a>). He is called a Gittite, which indicates that his birthplace was Gath. This was not the Philistine city of Gath but the Levitical town in the territory of Dan known as Gath-rimmon (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.45">Jos 19:45</a>). It is likely that Obed-edom was a Levite and therefore qualified to care for the ark of the covenant. Uzzah’s rash action in steadying the ark when the oxen stumbled brought upon him immediate death. David’s consternation and fear at this turn of events led him to reconsider his intention of bringing the ark to Jerusalem. Apparently Obed-edom’s home was nearby and it was convenient to leave the ark in his care. When David was informed after three months that the Lord had greatly blessed Obed-edom, he realized that the judgment that fell on Uzzah was incurred because the ark was carried contrary to the method prescribed in the Law (<a href="?bref=Num.4.15">Nm 4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.7.9">7:9</a>) and not because the Lord was angry with Uzzah. He ordered that the ark be taken from Obed-edom’s home and carried to Jerusalem in the proper manner (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.25-28">1 Chr 15:25-28</a>). Apparently Obed-edom was rewarded for his faithful service by being appointed a gatekeeper for the ark in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.24">15:24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.26.4,8,15">26:4, 8, 15</a>). But some scholars believe that Obed-edom the gatekeeper was a man other than the one referred to above.</p>
<p class="list">2. Levitical musician who ministered before the ark (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.21">1 Chr 15:21</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.16.5,38">16:5, 38</a>). He was the son of Jeduthun, one of David’s chief singers. Some scholars think that the musician and singer were different men.</p>
<p class="list">3. Levitical guardian of the sacred vessels of the temple taken hostage by Joash (<a href="?bref=2Chr.25.24">2 Chr 25:24</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>