<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="OffendOffense">
  <title>Offend, Offense</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OFFEND, OFFENSE</p>
<p class="fl">Words used two ways in the Bible: doing what is wrong oneself, or causing someone else to do wrong or to stumble.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DoingWrong">Doing Wrong</p>
<p class="fl">In both the Hebrew of the OT and the Greek of the NT there are several words for sin or wrongdoing having a variety of different translations. With the word “offend” or “offense,” the emphasis is on the sin being against a person or against the law, an offense against either God or man.</p>
<p>Sin is fundamentally an offense against God. For example, the people of Edom had grievously offended in taking vengeance on Judah, and so the hand of the Lord was against them in judgment (<a href="?bref=Ezek.25.12-13">Ez 25:12-13</a>). Israel commited an offense in their worship of Baal (<a href="?bref=Hos.13.1">Hos 13:1</a>). The breaking of God’s law is spoken of as an “offense committed” (<a href="?bref=Deut.19.15">Dt 19:15</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.22.26">22:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.25.2">25:2</a>). In the NT, James (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.10">Jas 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.3.2">3:2</a>) speaks of offenses against God and against his law.</p>
<p>There are many passages in the Bible addressing one man’s offense against another: for example, Abraham’s against Abimelech (<a href="?bref=Gen.20.9">Gn 20:9</a>), or Pharaoh’s chief butler and chief baker against their master (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.1">40:1</a>). Sometimes it is an alleged offense and no actual wrong has been done (e.g., <a href="?bref=Gen.31.36">Gn 31:36</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.14">2 Kgs 18:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.37.18">Jer 37:18</a>). Paul, in his defense before the Roman governor Festus, said, “Neither against the law of the Jews, nor against the temple, nor against Caesar have I offended at all” (<a href="?bref=Acts.25.8">Acts 25:8</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Finally, the Bible speaks about dealing with real offenses against God and people. Offenses should be acknowledged and confessed (<a href="?bref=Hos.5.15">Hos 5:15</a>). One’s proper resolution before God is “I will not offend any more” (<a href="?bref=Job.34.31">Jb 34:31</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). One needs to make amends for offenses (<a href="?bref=Eccl.10.4">Eccl 10:4</a>) and to forgive the offenses of others (<a href="?bref=Pr.17.9">Prv 17:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.19.11">19:11</a>). Jesus Christ died for our offenses (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.25">Rom 4:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.15-21">5:15-21</a>), so that in turning to him there is forgiveness for all sins.</p>
<p class="h2" id="CausingAnothertoSin">Causing Another to Sin</p>
<p class="fl">The noun “offense” and the verb “offend” are also used in reference to a person being caused to stumble or to do what is wrong. There are three ways in which this may happen:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. There may be something in the individual that causes him or her to stumble. Jesus expressed the seriousness of this, and though speaking metaphorically, he indicated the strenuous steps of prevention (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.29-30">Mt 5:29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.18.8-9">18:8-9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. There may be something in a person that causes offense to others. Jesus said, “Woe unto the world because of offences! for it must needs be that offences come; but woe to that man by whom the offence cometh!” (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.7">Mt 18:7</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). There are, in fact, many NT passages that insist that one should live so as not to cause others to stumble (<a href="?bref=Rom.14.13">Rom 14:13</a>). The apostle Paul says, “Don’t tear apart the work of God over what you eat. Remember, there is nothing wrong with these things in themselves. But it is wrong to eat anything if it makes another person stumble. Don’t eat meat or drink wine or do anything else if it might cause another Christian to stumble” (<a href="?bref=Rom.14.20-21">Rom 14:20-21</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.32">1 Cor 10:32</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.6.3">2 Cor 6:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. However, people may be offended at the truth through no fault of the person who presents it. Isaiah speaks of God as “a stone that causes people to stumble and a rock that makes them fall” (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.14">Is 8:14</a>) in that people would not always accept his demands and the way of faith in him. The NT takes these same words and applies them to the offense of the gospel of Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.32-33">Rom 9:32-33</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.8">1 Pt 2:8</a>). In the time of his ministry there were those who were offended at Jesus—at his lowly birth (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.57">Mt 13:57</a>), at what he said and did (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.12">15:12</a>), or because of the cost of following him (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.21">13:21</a>). Even disciples were capable of being offended and turning aside (<a href="?bref=John.6.61">Jn 6:61</a>). In the end all were offended and fled from him (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.31,56">Mt 26:31, 56</a>). Finally, the apostle Paul spoke of the offense in the preaching of the cross of Christ. He could have chosen to preach a popular message and avoided persecution, a “message that doesn’t offend anyone” (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.11">Gal 5:11</a>). He chose rather to preach the cross even though it was a stumbling block to Jews and folly to Gentiles (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.23">1 Cor 1:23</a>).</p>
<p class="sp"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Sin_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sin</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>