<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Oil">
  <title>Oil</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OIL</p>
<p class="fl">Substance most commonly produced from the olive berry, although the word could also apply to oil of myrrh (<a href="?bref=Esth.2.12">Est 2:12</a>). Oil was used primarily in cooking, but additionally as a cosmetic for anointing the body, for medicinal purposes, as a source of light, for anointing kings and priests, and in religious offerings.</p>
<p>The growth of olive trees was widespread, and the Israelites took advantage of this major crop to establish a thriving trade in oil with Tyre and Egypt. Like precious metals and animals, oil became an established medium of exchange. Solomon used it as part of the payment to Hiram for construction expenses connected with the temple (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.11">1 Kgs 5:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.17">Ez 27:17</a>).</p>
<p>Because oil was essential for everyday life, it was an effective and acceptable medium of barter. Oil was used in the preparation of most food (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.17.12-16">1 Kgs 17:12-16</a>). The common cake or patty of grain, which formed the basis of the noon meal, would be cooked on a griddle with a little oil.</p>
<p>As a cosmetic, oil was used for anointing the body after a bath (<a href="?bref=Ruth.3.3">Ru 3:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.12.20">2 Sm 12:20</a>). It was frequently used on festive occasions, and at Egyptian banquets the heads of both the guests and the female entertainers were anointed. In the NT, the anointing of the sick is mentioned (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.14">Jas 5:14</a>). Olive oil could also be taken internally as a medicine for the relief of gastric disorders. It had a soothing effect and was also used as a mild laxative. It was applied externally as an ointment for bruises, burns, cuts, and abrasions (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.6">Is 1:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.13">Mk 6:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.34">Lk 10:34</a>).</p>
<p>As soon as the sun set, the only source of light was the oil lamp. Often the small portable one could be placed easily on a shelf, but in large homes, palaces, synagogues, or temples, the lamp could rest on a tall metal base like a standard lamp. The wick of flax (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.3">Is 42:3</a>) or hemp was placed in the oil that gave out a flame until it was extinguished or the supply of fuel ran out. Torches were used in the streets both to light the way and for additional security. They added immeasurably to the festive atmosphere of evening processions. Torches were an essential part of the wedding procession, and normally those carrying the torches brought a quantity of oil in a container in case there was a delay and their supply was exhausted. This scene is vividly portrayed in Jesus’ parable of the wise and foolish virgins (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.1-13">Mt 25:1-13</a>).</p>
<p>In other ceremonial events, oil had a special meaning when used for the anointing of kings (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.1">1 Sm 10:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.39">1 Kgs 1:39</a>) and priests (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.7">Ex 29:7</a>). It was symbolic of the office and of the recognition of God’s blessing on the officeholder.</p>
<p>Quantities of oil were used in the temple. It was donated as part of the firstfruit offering (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.29">Ex 22:29</a>) and was also subject to tithing (<a href="?bref=Deut.12.17">Dt 12:17</a>). Oil was frequently used for the ceremonial aspect of temple life or as part of the offering. The grain offering was mixed with oil (<a href="?bref=Lev.8.26">Lv 8:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.7.19">Nm 7:19</a>), and the oil in the lamp that burned in the sanctuary constantly needed replenishing (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.2">Lv 24:2</a>). The daily sacrifice required the use of oil (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.40">Ex 29:40</a>), although the sin offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.11">Lv 5:11</a>) and the jealousy offering (<a href="?bref=Num.5.15">Nm 5:15</a>) specifically did not use oil.</p>
<p>A pestle and mortar, or a stone press, pressed oil from the olives (<a href="?bref=Exod.27.20">Ex 27:20</a>). Where the latter was used, the pulp initially produced by the press was often trodden out or subjected to further extensive pressing. Stone presses were set up to process the quantities of berries available at the Mt of Olives. The word for “oil press” was <span class="ital">gatt-semen,</span> hence the name Gethsemane.</p>
<p>Oil was symbolically associated with joy, festivity, ceremony, honor, light, and health (both spiritual and physical), while its absence spelled sorrow (<a href="?bref=Joel.1.10">Jl 1:10</a>) and the withdrawal of all that is good in life.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Anoint_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Anoint</a>; <a href="?item=FoodandFoodPreparation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Food and Food Preparation</a>; <a href="?item=MedicineandMedicalPractice_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Medicine and Medical Practice</a>; <a href="?item=Ointment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ointment</a>; <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants</a> (<a href="?item=OliveOliveTree_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Olive, Olive Tree</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>