<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="OlivesMountof">
  <title>Olives, Mount of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OLIVES, Mount of</p>
<p class="fl">Prominent ridge running north-south in the Judean mountains, lying due east of Jerusalem and the Kidron Valley. Three summits with two intervening valleys distinguish the mountain. The northern summit is Mt Scopus. To its south is a small saddle through which the ancient Roman road to Jericho passed. The central hill is the traditional Mt of Olives (2,684 feet, or 818.1 meters) standing across from the temple platform (the <span class="ital">Haram esh-Sherif</span>). Here Constantine built the great Church of the Ascension dedicated to his mother, Helena. Another saddle to the south contains the modern road to Bethany. The southern hill, overlooking Jebusite Jerusalem and the city of David, is called the “Mt of Offense” since here Solomon built temples for his foreign wives. Beneath it is the Arab village of Silwan and the confluence of the Kidron and Hinnom valleys.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfTheMountOfOlives"/>
<p>The Mt of Olives gained its name from its extensive olive groves, which were renowned in antiquity (<a href="?bref=Zech.14.4">Zec 14:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.11.1">Mk 11:1</a>). Its western face collects rainfall from the Mediterranean, which, together with decomposed limestone, makes for fertile orchards. The eastern side marks the boundary of the arid Judean wilderness. Bethany and Bethphage are two NT villages hugging these eastern slopes.</p>
<p>In the OT the Mt of Olives is first mentioned when David fled from Absalom’s conspiracy. He departed from Jerusalem, went up the Mt of Olives in the east, and continued on toward the Rift Valley (<a href="?bref=2Sam.15.30">2 Sm 15:30</a>). Solomon chose this mountain for the construction of “high places” for the foreign deities of Sidon, Moab (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.7">1 Kgs 11:7</a>), and Ammon—each of which was later destroyed by Josiah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.13">2 Kgs 23:13</a>). Ezekiel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.11.23">Ez 11:23</a>) records the vision of the glory of God departing from the temple and resting on the Mt of Olives. The most famous description appears in Zechariah’s apocalyptic vision (<a href="?bref=Zech.14.1-5">Zec 14:1-5</a>): “On that day [the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>’s] feet will stand on the Mount of Olives, which faces Jerusalem on the east. And the Mount of Olives will split apart, making a wide valley running from east to west, for half the mountain will move toward the north and half toward the south” (v <a href="?bref=Zech.14.4">4</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>In the NT Jesus appears at the Mt of Olives during Passion week. The only exceptions are the Bethany stories when Jesus visits Mary and Martha (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.38-42">Lk 10:38-42</a>) and raises Lazarus from the dead (<a href="?bref=John.11.17-44">Jn 11:17-44</a>). On his triumphant entry to Jerusalem, Jesus came from Jericho, crossed the mountain from the east, and then descended into the Kidron Valley (<a href="?bref=Mark.11.1-10">Mk 11:1-10</a>). On his descent he paused and wept over the city (<a href="?bref=Luke.19.41-44">Lk 19:41-44</a>).</p>
<p>During his final week, Jesus taught on the Mt of Olives (<a href="?bref=Mark.13.1-37">Mk 13</a>) and spent his evenings there (<a href="?bref=Luke.21.37">Lk 21:37</a>, although this may refer to Bethany). Following the Last Supper, Jesus came to this mountain for prayer (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.26">Mk 14:26</a>). In a garden near an olive oil press (“Gethsemane”), he was arrested (v <a href="?bref=Mark.14.32">32</a>). The final event of Christ on earth, his ascension, was viewed from the mount by his followers (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.12">Acts 1:12</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="AReveredSiteTheMountOfOlives"/>
  </body>
</item>