<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Omri">
  <title>Omri</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OMRI</p>
<p class="list">1. King of Israel who first appears in Scripture as general of the army during the reign of Elah, king of Israel. In 885 <span class="era">BC</span> Elah sent Omri to besiege the Philistine fortress of Gibbethon. During the siege, Zimri, another military leader, launched a coup against Elah, killed him, and immediately wiped out all of Elah’s male relatives. When Omri heard of the assassination, he had the army declare him king and marched to the capital at Tirzah to deal with Zimri. When Zimri saw that the siege of Tirzah was going to be successful, he set fire to the king’s palace and died in the flames after only seven days on the throne.</p>
<p class="list-text">But Omri’s rule over Israel was not yet established. Tibni seized control of part of the state and held it for about four years. Finally, Omri was able to crush Tibni and extend his power over all Israel. He established Israel’s fourth ruling dynasty, which was destined to continue through three more generations after his own. His reign lasted a total of 12 years (885–874 <span class="era">BC</span>), including the years of sovereignty disputed with Tibni.</p>
<p class="h2-list">International Developments</p>
<p class="list-text-fl">To the northeast of Israel, the Arameans of Syria were building a strong state with its capital at Damascus. A few years before Omri took the throne, Asa of Judah had sought the help of Syria against Baasha of Israel. Soon Syria would become a threat to both Hebrew kingdoms.</p>
<p class="list-text">Farther east, Assyria was growing in strength under the leadership of Ashurnasirpal II (883–859 <span class="era">BC</span>), the founder of the empire. He marched into Phoenicia, but Israel was spared Assyrian attack until the days of Omri’s son Ahab.</p>
<p class="h2-list">Omri’s Reign</p>
<p class="list-text-fl">Since the purpose of Scripture is not to provide a political, military, or even social history of Israel or the countries surrounding it, administrations of the kings of Israel and Judah are often very briefly treated. For a fuller picture, it is necessary to turn to nonbiblical sources. From Assyrian records, it is evident that Omri must have been an impressive ruler. Generations later, Assyrians still spoke of Israel as the “land of Omri.”</p>
<p class="list-text">Perceptive leader that he was, Omri recognized that the nations needed a capital that was centrally located and militarily defensible. He settled on the site of Samaria, the third and most significant capital of the realm (Shechem and Tirzah had previously served as capitals). Located seven miles (11.3 kilometers) northwest of Shechem on the main road leading to Galilee and Phoenicia, it perched on a free-standing hill that rose some 300 to 400 feet (91.4–121.9 meters) above the surrounding plain. Thus it could be quite easily defended; it had a prosperous hinterland to supply it with food and taxes; and it was conveniently located on a main road. Omri bought the hill from Shemer and named the city after its owner. Then he leveled the top of the hill and built the palace compound. He also built a 33-foot- (10.1-meter-) thick wall around the summit of the hill.</p>
<p class="list-text">Omri’s expansionist activities are not mentioned in 1 Kings, but Scripture is supplemented by discovery of the Moabite Stone in 1868 at Dibon, east of the Jordan River. On this stela, Mesha, king of Moab, tells that Omri conquered Moab. Israel had continued to subjugate the land in the days of Ahab, but during his days, Mesha successfully rebelled against Israel (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.4">2 Kgs 3:4</a>). That Omri could mount a successful war against Moab soon after becoming king shows that he was a capable ruler, because previously the kingdom of Israel had been greatly weakened by insurrection and political instability.</p>
<p class="list-text">Omri also reestablished the friendly relations with Phoenicia that had been initiated in the days of David and Solomon. Presumably, he made a full alliance with King Ethbaal of Tyre and then sealed it with the marriage of his son Ahab to the Phoenician princess Jezebel. Such an alliance would have been mutually beneficial, for it would have brought cedar, beautifully crafted goods, and Phoenician architectural and technical expertise to Israel, and it would have provided Israelite grain and olive oil to Phoenicia. Moreover, it would have linked their forces against the threat of the rising power of Assyria.</p>
<p class="list-text">This pact was destined to corrupt Israel, however, for it brought Baal worship into the land. Probably this is what the writer of Kings had in mind when he said that Omri “did worse” than the other kings of Israel before him (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.25">1 Kgs 16:25</a>) because he practiced the idolatrous ways of Jeroboam. Baal worship was regarded as more degrading than the calf worship Jeroboam had introduced. Omri, and his son Ahab after him, subscribed to both.</p>
<p class="list-text">Omri was one of the most powerful kings of Israel, building its new capital, winning for the state a reputation for prowess, and setting a course for future kings to follow. But unfortunately that course was morally corrupt; the introduction of Baal worship was one of the terrible results of Omri’s alliance with Tyre.</p>
<p class="list">2. One of Beker’s sons from Benjamin’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.7.8">1 Chr 7:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Descendant of Perez, son of Judah (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.4">1 Chr 9:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Son of Michael, prince of the tribe of Issachar during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.18">1 Chr 27:18</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>