<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Overseer">
  <title>Overseer</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">OVERSEER</p>
<p class="fl">Word appearing 12 times in the OT (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) and once in the NT. The <span class="sc">niv</span> uses it at least six times in the NT to translate the word <span class="greek">episkopos</span><span class="ital">,</span> which is derived from “peer” or “watch over.” In the OT “overseer” is used to translate three words, which literally mean (1) one with authority who visits, (2) the preeminent one, or (3) the head writer.</p>
<p>Joseph was given authority to watch over and administer all aspects of Potiphar’s house (<a href="?bref=Gen.39.4-5">Gn 39:4-5</a>), advising Pharaoh to appoint 50 men to regulate and watch over the abundant harvest for seven years (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.34">41:34</a>). Solomon appointed 3,600 overseers (“supervisors,” <span class="sc">nasb</span>) to make the people work (<a href="?bref=2Chr.2.18">2 Chr 2:18</a>). In Josiah’s time of temple renovation, there were overseers over all the workmen in every job (<a href="?bref=2Chr.34.13,17">34:13, 17</a>). Nehemiah appointed men to oversee the rebuilding of the wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.9,14">Neh 11:9, 14</a>), to oversee the Levites (v <a href="?bref=Neh.11.22">22</a>), and to be in charge of the Levitical singers (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.42">12:42</a>).</p>
<p>The word “overseer” speaks of the highest person of authority who exercised oversight over others. Included in this authoritative oversight was the idea of watching, directing, and protecting the master’s interests. The NT carries these ideas also in regard to men appointed to serve the church on behalf of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.28">Acts 20:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.1.1">Phil 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.3.1-2">1 Tm 3:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.7">Ti 1:7</a>). Jesus Christ himself is the great Overseer (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.25">1 Pt 2:25</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Bishop_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bishop</a>; <a href="?item=Elder_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Elder</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>