<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BaalIdol">
  <title>Baal (Idol)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BAAL (I<span class="lc">dol</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Name of the most prominent Canaanite deity. As the god of fertility in the Canaanite pantheon (roster of gods), Baal’s sphere of influence included agriculture, animal husbandry, and human sexuality. The word Baal occurs in the OT in combination with other terms, such as place-names (Baal-peor, <a href="?bref=Hos.9.10">Hos 9:10</a>; Baal-hermon, <a href="?bref=Judg.3.3">Jgs 3:3</a>), or with other adjuncts as in Baal-berith (Baal of the covenant, <a href="?bref=Judg.8.33">Jgs 8:33</a>). Use of the name in connection with a local place-name may indicate a local cult of Baal worship.</p>
<p>Baal worship became prominent in the northern kingdom of Israel during the days of King Ahab (ninth century <span class="era">BC</span>) when he married Jezebel of Tyre, a city in Phoenicia (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.29-33">1 Kgs 16:29-33</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.19-40">18:19-40</a>). It later infiltrated the kingdom of Judah when Athaliah, daughter of Ahab and Jezebel, married King Jehoram of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.8.17-18,24-26">2 Kgs 8:17-18, 24-26</a>). Places for worship of Baal were often high places in the hills consisting of an altar and a sacred tree, stone, or pillar (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.5">2 Kgs 23:5</a>). The predominantly urban Phoenicians built temples to Baal; while Athaliah was queen of Judah, even Jerusalem had one (<a href="?bref=2Chr.23.12-17">2 Chr 23:12-17</a>).</p>
<p>In the Ugaritic epic material, Baal is pictured as descending into the netherworld, the domain of the god Mot. That descent was evidently part of a cycle intended to coincide with the cycle of seasons. In order to bring Baal up from the realm of Mot and thus ensure initiation of the fertile rainy season, the Canaanites engaged in orgiastic worship that included human sacrifice as well as sexual rites (<a href="?bref=Jer.7.31">Jer 7:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.19.4-6">19:4-6</a>). Sacred prostitutes evidently participated in the autumnal religious ritual. The worship of Baal was strongly condemned in the OT (<a href="?bref=Judg.2.12-14">Jgs 2:12-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.3.7-8">3:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.19.1-15">Jer 19</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CanaaniteDeitiesandReligion_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Canaanite Deities and Religion</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>