<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Backsliding">
  <title>Backsliding</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BACKSLIDING</p>
<p class="fl">To wane in religious commitment, to become less arduous in piety or less upright in morals. The principal Hebrew word for backsliding means “turning back” or “turning away.” The people of Israel repeatedly turned from God and engaged in the sin and idolatry of their pagan neighbors. In the language of the OT, backsliding Israel lusted after abominations and forsook the Lord and his commandments (<a href="?bref=Ezra.9.10">Ezr 9:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.4">Is 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.21">Ez 11:21</a>). They violated the sacred covenant by worshiping idols and practicing harlotry (<a href="?bref=Ps.78.10">Ps 78:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.11">Jer 2:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.4.10">Hos 4:10</a>). The people forgot God’s mighty works on their behalf, ignored his counsel, and rejected his instruction (<a href="?bref=Ps.78.11">Pss 78:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.107.11">107:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.30.9">Is 30:9</a>). Hard-hearted and rebellious, they delighted themselves in all sorts of perversions (<a href="?bref=Jer.3.21">Jer 3:21</a>). Religious leaders entrusted with the spiritual care of the nation were instrumental in leading the people astray (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.16">Is 9:16</a>). The priests proved themselves faithless shepherds (<a href="?bref=Jer.50.6">Jer 50:6</a>).</p>
<p>Grieved by the spiritual defection of his chosen people, God declared that “backsliding Israel committed adultery” (<a href="?bref=Jer.3.8">Jer 3:8</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). Through Hosea, the Lord lamented the fact that “Israel slideth back as a backsliding heifer” (<a href="?bref=Hos.4.16">Hos 4:16</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). Jeremiah confessed, “Our backslidings are many, we have sinned against thee” (<a href="?bref=Jer.14.7">Jer 14:7</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="TheConceptOfBackslidingInTheNewTestament"/>
  </body>
</item>