<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BaptismofJesus">
  <title>Baptism of Jesus*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BAPTISM OF JESUS*</p>
<p class="fl">Major event in Jesus’ life, which marked the beginning of his ministry. The fact that John the Baptist baptized Jesus is disputed by very few scholars today, but the purpose and significance of Jesus’ baptism remain controversial.</p>
<p>The Gospel accounts agree that John’s baptism was a baptism of repentance (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.6-10">Mt 3:6-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.4-5">Mk 1:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.3-14">Lk 3:3-14</a>). He proclaimed that the kingdom of heaven was at hand and that God’s people should prepare for the Lord’s coming by a renewal of faith toward God. For John, that meant repentance, confession of sins, and practicing righteousness. That being so, why was Jesus baptized? If Jesus was sinless, as the NT proclaims (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.21">2 Cor 5:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.15">Heb 4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.22">1 Pt 2:22</a>), why did he submit to a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness of sins? The Gospels provide the answers.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGospelofMark">The Gospel of Mark</p>
<p class="fl">Mark presents the baptism of Jesus as a necessary preparation for his period of temptation and ministry. At his baptism Jesus received the Father’s approval and the bestowal of the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.9-11">1:9-11</a>). Mark’s focus on Jesus’ special relation to the Father, “You are my beloved Son, and I am fully pleased with you” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.11">1:11</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>), brings together two important OT references. Jesus’ messiahship is presented in a radically new way, in which the ruling Messiah (<a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Ps 2:7</a>) is also the Suffering Servant of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.1">Is 42:1</a>). Popular Jewish belief expected a ruling Messiah who would establish the kingdom of God, not a Messiah who would suffer for the people. Mark intended to show that in Jesus alone had God’s appointed time for the fulfillment of his purpose come.</p>
<p>The statement that the heavens opened at the baptism of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.10">Mk 1:10</a>) may proclaim the arrival of the “end times” (the time of fulfillment and the establishment of God’s kingdom). A then-current Jewish interpretation of <a href="?bref=Isa.64.1">Isaiah 64:1</a> held that in the last days God would open the heavens and come down to his people. In Jewish thought the rending of the heavens was also associated with hearing God’s voice and the bestowal of God’s Spirit.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGospelofMatthew">The Gospel of Matthew</p>
<p class="fl">Matthew’s account of Jesus’ baptism has more detail than Mark’s. It begins by noting John’s reluctance to baptize Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.14">3:14</a>). John was persuaded only after Jesus explained to him that the act was “fitting for us to fulfil all righteousness” (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.15">3:15</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Although the full meaning of those words is uncertain, they at least suggest that Jesus’ baptism was necessary to accomplish God’s will. In both the Old and New Testaments (<a href="?bref=Ps.98.2-3">Ps 98:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.17">Rom 1:17</a>) God’s righteousness is seen in his salvation for his people. That is why the Messiah can be called “The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Is Our Righteousness” (<a href="?bref=Jer.23.6">Jer 23:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1-5">Is 11:1-5</a>). Jesus told John that his baptism was necessary to do God’s will in bringing about salvation for his people. Thus the Father’s declaration at Jesus’ baptism is presented in the form of a public announcement, emphasizing that Jesus was God’s anointed Servant about to begin his ministry as the bringer of the Lord’s salvation.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGospelofLuke">The Gospel of Luke</p>
<p class="fl">Luke passes over Jesus’ baptism quickly, placing it alongside the baptism of others who came to John (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.21-22">3:21-22</a>). The context in Luke also sheds some light on the purpose of Jesus’ baptism. Luke, unlike Matthew, places the genealogy of Jesus after his baptism and just before his ministry begins. The parallel to Moses, whose genealogy occurs just before his primary work begins (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.14-25">Ex 6:14-25</a>), seems more than coincidental. It is probably intended to illustrate Jesus’ role in bringing deliverance (salvation) to God’s people just as Moses did in the OT. At his baptism, by the descent of the Holy Spirit upon him, Jesus was equipped to do the mission God had called him to do. Following his temptation (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.1-13">Lk 4:1-13</a>), Jesus entered the synagogue and declared to the people that he had been anointed by the Spirit to proclaim good news (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.16-21">4:16-21</a>). That anointing came at Jesus’ baptism (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.10.37-38">Acts 10:37-38</a>).</p>
<p>In his Gospel account, Luke tried to identify Jesus with the common people—for example, in the birth story (with Jesus born in a stable and visited by lowly shepherds, <a href="?bref=Luke.2.8-20">Lk 2:8-20</a>) and through placing the genealogy (stressing Jesus’ relation to all of humanity, <a href="?bref=Luke.3.38">3:38</a>) right after the baptism. Thus, Luke saw the baptism as Jesus’ first step in identifying himself with those he had come to save.</p>
<p>In the OT the Messiah was always inseparable from the people he represented (see especially <a href="?bref=Jer.30.21">Jer 30:21</a> and <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.1-46.24">Ez 45–46</a>). Although the “servant” in Isaiah is sometimes viewed corporately (<a href="?bref=Isa.44.1">Is 44:1</a>) and sometimes individually (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.3">53:3</a>), he is always viewed as the representative <span class="ital">of the people</span> to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.5-26">49:5-26</a>), as well as the servant <span class="ital">of the Lord.</span></p>
<p>Evidently Luke, along with Mark and Matthew, was trying to show that Jesus, as the divine representative of the people, had identified himself with them in his baptism.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGospelofJohn">The Gospel of John</p>
<p class="fl">The fourth Gospel does not say that Jesus was baptized but does say that John the Baptist saw the Spirit descend upon Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.1.32-34">Jn 1:32-34</a>). The account emphasizes that Jesus went to John during John’s preaching and baptizing ministry; John recognized that Jesus was the Christ, that God’s Spirit was upon him, and that he was the Son of God. John also recognized that Jesus, unlike himself, baptized with the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=John.1.29-36">1:29-36</a>).</p>
<p>John the Baptist described Jesus as the “Lamb of God who takes away the sin of the world” (<a href="?bref=John.1.29">1:29</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The closest OT parallel to that statement comes from a “servant of the Lord” passage (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.6-7">Is 53:6-7</a>). It is possible that “Lamb of God” could be an alternate translation of the Aramaic term “servant of God.”</p>
<p>The sense of Jesus as the one who bears the sins of the people is obviously in view in the fourth Gospel. That Jesus was the promised representative and deliverer of the people was understood by John the Baptist and conveyed by the Gospel writer.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Conclusion">Conclusion</p>
<p class="fl">In the four Gospels it is clear that the Holy Spirit came upon Jesus at his baptism to enable him to do the work of God. All four Gospel writers saw that Jesus had been anointed by God to accomplish his mission of bringing salvation to the people. Those ideas provide a key to understanding why Jesus was baptized. On that occasion at the beginning of his ministry, God anointed Jesus with the Holy Spirit to do his mediating work between God and the people. At his baptism Jesus was identified as the one who would bear the people’s sins; Jesus was baptized to identify himself with sinful people.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=JesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>