<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Barnabas">
  <title>Barnabas</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BARNABAS</p>
<p class="fl">Name given by the apostles to an early convert to Christianity in Jerusalem. Formerly called Joseph, Barnabas probably earned his new name through effective preaching and teaching.</p>
<p>Sources for the life of Barnabas are limited to passages in the book of Acts and Paul’s letters. The apocryphal Epistle of Barnabas is almost certainly a mid-second-century composition and therefore not from the hand of Barnabas. The apocryphal Acts of Barnabas is from the fifth century and not useful in establishing reliable information on the person of Barnabas. Tertullian assigned to him the authorship of Hebrews, but internal evidence speaks against this view.</p>
<p>A native of Cyprus, Barnabas was a Jew of the Diaspora. His priestly family background gave him a special interest in Jerusalem. He probably came to live in the Holy City. It is possible that he may even have become acquainted with Jesus in Jerusalem, but his conversion to Christianity probably resulted from the apostles’ preaching soon after the resurrection of Christ.</p>
<p>Barnabas first appears as a property owner named Joseph (<span class="sc">kjv</span> Joses) in the book of Acts who sold a field and gave the money to the Christian community (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.36-37">Acts 4:36-37</a>). When persecution of Hellenistic Christians broke out in Jerusalem, Barnabas remained in the city though others of similar background fled (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.1-8">8:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.19-22">11:19-22</a>). His good reputation in Jerusalem may have influenced the apostles to select him as Paul’s companion for missionary work.</p>
<p>As many of the scattered Christians gravitated to Antioch of Syria, the Jerusalem church sent Barnabas to help in the growing work (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.19-26">Acts 11:19-26</a>). The writer of Acts said of Barnabas, “He was a good man, full of the Holy Spirit and of faith” (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.24">11:24</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Barnabas recruited Paul, now a Christian, to help in Antioch, and the two men worked in the church for a year, teaching a large company of Christians (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.26">11:26</a>). When famine hit Jerusalem, Barnabas and Paul were sent with relief funds. On their return to Antioch, John Mark went with them (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.25">12:25</a>).</p>
<p>Barnabas was commissioned with Paul to preach beyond the boundaries of Antioch (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.2-3">Acts 13:2-3</a>). The placing of Barnabas’s name before Saul (Paul) may indicate the priority of Barnabas at this time. They went to Cyprus and to several key centers in Asia Minor. At Lystra the citizens identified Barnabas with the mythical god Zeus, and Paul with Hermes (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.8-12">14:8-12</a>).</p>
<p>At a Jerusalem council, Barnabas and Paul reported on their mission to the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.1-41">Acts 15</a>). Following that council, as the two men planned another mission, a serious disagreement arose that led to their separating (vv <a href="?bref=Acts.15.36-41">36-41</a>). Barnabas wanted to take his cousin John Mark (<a href="?bref=Col.4.10">Col 4:10</a>), but Paul refused on the grounds that Mark had deserted them on the earlier mission (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.13">Acts 13:13</a>). Barnabas left for Cyprus with John Mark, and Paul went to Syria and Cilicia with Silas. After that separation the focus shifted from Barnabas to Paul.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Apocrypha_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Apocrypha (Barnabas, Epistle of)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>