<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BatheBathing">
  <title>Bathe, Bathing</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BATHE, BATHING</p>
<p class="fl">To cleanse as with water; to wash oneself. In the Bible the terms “bathing” and “washing” translate, often interchangeably, a number of different words. One OT passage uses one Hebrew word for cleaning clothes, another for washing other objects, including the body (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.8-12">Lv 15:8-12</a>).</p>
<p>Israel’s dry climate and scarcity of water discouraged bathing except where a stream or pool was available (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.5.10">2 Kgs 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=John.9.7">Jn 9:7</a>). Yet people still washed babies at birth (<a href="?bref=Ezek.16.4">Ez 16:4</a>), dead bodies in preparation for burial (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.37">Acts 9:37</a>), and sheep for their shearing (<a href="?bref=Song.6.6">Sg 6:6</a>). Frequent bathing of the whole body was probably reserved for the rich (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.5">Ex 2:5</a>), but the prevalence of dust made frequent washing of the face, hands, and feet necessary (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.4">Gn 18:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.19.2">19:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.24.32">24:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.43.24">43:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.19.21">Jgs 19:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.5.3">Sg 5:3</a>). Good grooming for the privileged demanded washing of one’s body before anointing with oil (<a href="?bref=Ruth.3.3">Ru 3:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.12.20">2 Sm 12:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.23.41">Ez 23:41</a>). A good host provided water for a guest’s feet (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.4">Gn 18:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.19.21">Jgs 19:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.44">Lk 7:44</a>; <a href="?bref=John.13.4-5">Jn 13:4-5</a>). To wash someone’s feet was the task of a servant. For anyone else to do so was a sign of humility (<a href="?bref=1Sam.25.41">1 Sm 25:41</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.44-47">Lk 7:44-47</a>; <a href="?bref=John.13.3-16">Jn 13:3-16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.5.10">1 Tm 5:10</a>).</p>
<p>Most biblical references to washing or bathing deal with ritual cleansing. Priests and Levites were required to wash their clothes and faces, and sometimes bodies, before approaching the altar and on ceremonial occasions (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.4">Ex 29:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.30.19-21">30:19-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.40.7,12,30-32">40:7, 12, 30-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.8.21">Nm 8:21</a>). Before a slain animal was sacrificed, its legs and intestines were washed (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.9,13">Lv 1:9, 13</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.21">8:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.9.14">9:14</a>). Anyone who was once unclean (e.g., a leper who was healed or someone who had experienced a genital discharge) had to wash his or her clothes and bathe to be ritually pure (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.8-10">Lv 14:8-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.15.5-11,21-27">15:5-11, 21-27</a>). Any garment that became polluted had to be ceremonially cleansed (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.27">Lv 6:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.13.54">13:54</a>).</p>
<p>“Washing” is also used figuratively for a cleansing from sin (<a href="?bref=Ps.51.2">Ps 51:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.16">Is 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.4.4">4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.22">Jer 2:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.4.14">4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.11">1 Cor 6:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.22">Heb 10:22</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>