<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Beggar">
  <title>Beggar</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BEGGAR</p>
<p class="fl">One who asks for charity, especially one who lives by begging, a mendicant.</p>
<p>Biblical references to begging are limited to such Hebrew verbs as “to seek” or “to ask,” and, as a noun, to “the poor and needy”; in the NT, Greek terms refer to being “poor” or “miserable,” and to those who “ask for more.” Professional beggars were unknown in Moses’ time, since the law made ample provision for taking care of the poor.</p>
<p>Earliest legislation (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.11">Dt 15:11</a>) mandated the care of those who were poor. There were regulations such as the Sabbath year, the year of remission to those indebted (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.1-55">Lv 25</a>). In that year the produce of the land was left to the poor and destitute (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.11">Ex 23:11</a>), and all debts were canceled (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.1">Dt 15:1</a>). The duty of lending liberally to the poor was promoted (vv <a href="?bref=Deut.15.7-11">7-11</a>), and hired laborers were protected (<a href="?bref=Deut.24.14-15">24:14-15</a>). The purpose was that “there should be no more poor among you” (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.4">15:4</a>). Indeed, in the early days of Israelite settlement, all Israelites enjoyed a comparable standard of living.</p>
<p>In excavations at Tirsah near Nablus, the size and arrangements of houses of the tenth century <span class="era">BC</span> are all about the same. By the eighth century <span class="era">BC</span>, there is a striking contrast, with houses on the same site clearly divided into the town’s richer and poorer quarters. The social revolution between those two centuries was associated with the rise of the Israelite monarchy and growth of a class of officials who gained private profits from their positions. The prophets condemned the fact that wealth was ill-gotten and badly distributed in their day (e.g., <a href="?bref=Isa.5.8">Is 5:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.12.8">Hos 12:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.4-7">Am 8:4-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.2.2">Mi 2:2</a>). The prophet Amos denounced creditors who felt no pity for the poor (<a href="?bref=Amos.2.6-8">Am 2:6-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.6">8:6</a>). Yet, throughout the OT, there is essentially no reference to beggars. During the intertestamental period, however, almsgiving became an important religious duty.</p>
<p>In the NT, begging seems to be prevalent. In the ministry of Jesus, references are made to a blind beggar (<a href="?bref=John.9.8-9">Jn 9:8-9</a>), to blind Bartimaeus (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.46-52">Mk 10:46-52</a>), and to Lazarus, a godly beggar who is contrasted with a rich man (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.19-31">Lk 16:19-31</a>). The apostles Peter and John encountered a crippled beggar by the “Beautiful,” or Nicanor, Gate in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.1-11">Acts 3:1-11</a>). Jesus rebuked an ostentatious show of almsgiving (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.1-4">Mt 6:1-4</a>) but stressed the importance of giving to the poor from right motives (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.42-48">Mt 5:42-48</a>). By the time of Jesus, Jerusalem had become a center for beggars, probably because almsgiving in the Holy City was then regarded as particularly meritorious. Begging in Jerusalem was concentrated around the holy places. The pool of Beth-zatha was a place of healing, and the sick, blind, lame, and paralyzed lay there to beg as well as to get into the waters for healing (<a href="?bref=John.5.2-9">Jn 5:2-9</a>).</p>
<p>In the early Christian community, the first organization of officers was made to provide for a fair distribution of funds to the poor (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.32-35">Acts 4:32-35</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.6.1-6">6:1-6</a>). On the first day of each week, some portion of each Christian’s income was to be allotted to the needy (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.27-30">11:27-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.25-27">Rom 15:25-27</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.1-4">1 Cor 16:1-4</a>). Possibly the poverty of Palestine was made worse by heavy Roman taxation; tax gatherers as well as beggars are prominent in the Gospel narratives. It has also been suggested that the rise of the Zealots was closely associated with the social factor of poverty; the revolutionary Zealots were largely comprised of society’s “dregs,” according to the Jewish historian Josephus. In <span class="era">AD</span> 66 the Zealots burned the Jerusalem archives, no doubt intending to destroy the records of their debts kept there. Josephus reports that before the Roman destruction of Jerusalem, gangs of beggars were terrorizing the whole city. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Alms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Alms</a>; <a href="?item=Poorthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Poor, The</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>