<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BenjaminTribeof">
  <title>Benjamin, Tribe of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BENJAMIN, T<span class="lc">ribe of</span></p>
<p class="fl">One of the smallest of the 12 tribes of Israel, made up of descendants of Jacob’s youngest son (<a href="?bref=Num.1.36">Nm 1:36</a>). In the OT the tribe is often referred to as simply “Benjamin.” Though small, the tribe of Benjamin played an important role in Israelite history, particularly in their conduct as great warriors (<a href="?bref=Judg.20.13-16">Jgs 20:13-16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.12.1-2">1 Chr 12:1-2</a>).</p>
<p>At the Israelite conquest of Canaan, after the tribes of Judah and Ephraim had received their territory, the first lot came to Benjamin. The tribe was allotted territory between Judah and Ephraim, a strip of land between Mt Ephraim and the Judean hills. The southern boundary with Judah was clearly defined: through the valley of Hinnom immediately south of Jerusalem to a point north of the Dead Sea. Its eastern limit was the Jordan, and its northern boundary with Ephraim ran from the Jordan to Bethel to Ataroth-addar south of Lower Beth-horon (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.11-20">Jos 18:11-20</a>).</p>
<p>Benjamin’s territory extended about 28 miles (45.1 kilometers) from west to east and 12 miles (19.3 kilometers) north to south. It was hilly country, strategically located to control key passes, but with fertile hill basins. Among its hill settlements were the important towns of Jerusalem, Jericho, Bethel, Gibeon, Gibeah, and Mizpeh (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.21-28">Jos 18:21-28</a>). Not all of its towns were immediately taken from their previous possessors; Jerusalem, for example, was in the hands of the Jebusites until David’s time. The environment bred a hardy race of highlanders, well described in Jacob’s blessing of Benjamin as “a wolf that prowls” (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.27">Gn 49:27</a>).</p>
<p>Ehud of Benjamin was one of the early judges in Canaan, a “deliverer” of the Israelites who killed Eglon, king of Moab (<a href="?bref=Judg.3.15">Jgs 3:15</a>). Members of the tribe later helped Deborah and Barak defeat Sisera (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.14">5:14</a>). The tribe continued to produce great men: political leaders (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.21">1 Chr 27:21</a>), captains in Saul’s army (<a href="?bref=2Sam.4.2">2 Sm 4:2</a>) and David’s army (<a href="?bref=2Sam.23.29">23:29</a>), skilled archers (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.40">1 Chr 8:40</a>), and overseers in Solomon’s labor force (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.18">1 Kgs 4:18</a>).</p>
<p>Less noble traits were also shown by Benjamin’s descendants. Palti, a Benjaminite, was one of the scouts making a bad report when the 12 spies returned from the land of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Num.13.1-2,9,31-33">Nm 13:1-2, 9, 31-33</a>). The tribe as a whole displayed disobedience and lack of consistent courage by failing to clear their inheritance of Canaanites (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.21">Jgs 1:21</a>). Following the custom of the day, the whole tribe defended the lewd treatment and murder of a concubine from another tribe by a few of their members (chs <a href="?bref=Judg.19.1-20.48">19–20</a>). That act of gross immorality united the other tribes against them, and the tribe of Benjamin was almost decimated. To keep the tribe from dying out, the other tribes allowed the Benjaminites to take captive several hundred women who then became their wives (<a href="?bref=Judg.21.1-25">Jgs 21</a>).</p>
<p>Benjamin’s tribe proved to be dependable in various ways. During the exodus from Egypt, it took its place in the organization (<a href="?bref=Num.1.11">Nm 1:11</a>) and the army (<a href="?bref=Num.2.22">2:22</a>) and made its tribal offerings (<a href="?bref=Num.7.60">7:60</a>). It demonstrated remarkable loyalty to the throne, initially to Saul and his family (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.8-31">2 Sm 2:8-31</a>). Later David received its faithful support, as did his descendants, for Benjamin remained with Judah, loyal to Solomon’s son Rehoboam when Jeroboam led a secession (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.21-24">1 Kgs 12:21-24</a>).</p>
<p>Other men of Benjamin (often called Benjaminites) spoken of in the OT include Cush, of whom David sang (<a href="?bref=Ps.7.1-17">Ps 7</a> superscription); Jeremiah the prophet, who, though a Levite, lived within Benjamin’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.1">Jer 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.32.8">32:8</a>); and Mordecai, uncle and adviser to Queen Esther (<a href="?bref=Esth.2.5">Est 2:5</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT the apostle Paul made no apologies for his ancestry, twice referring to himself as a Hebrew of Benjamin’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.1">Rom 11:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.3.5">Phil 3:5</a>). In his sermon at Antioch of Pisidia, Paul also mentioned Benjamin as the tribe of King Saul, in his brief account of Israel’s history (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.21">Acts 13:21</a>). In one other NT reference Benjamin is named with the other 11 tribes in John’s apocalyptic vision (<a href="?bref=Rev.7.8">Rv 7:8</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=BenjaminPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Benjamin (Person) #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>