<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BethShemesh">
  <title>Beth-Shemesh</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BETH-SHEMESH</p>
<p class="list">1. Canaanite city on the northern border of Judah’s territory (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.10">Jos 15:10</a>) and the southern border of Dan’s (before that tribe migrated north). Beth-shemesh means “the house of Shamash,” the Canaanite sun god. As Ir-shemesh, it was included in the list of cities of Dan (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.41">19:41</a>). Beth-shemesh was one of the towns of Judah granted to the Levites (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.16">Jos 21:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.59">1 Chr 6:59</a>). Its inhabitants were called Beth-shemites (<a href="?bref=1Sam.6.14,18">1 Sm 6:14, 18</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). When the Philistines decided to dispose of the captured ark of the covenant because plagues were breaking out in their cities, they took it to Beth-shemesh. The area was also the scene of a great victory of King Joash (Jehoash) of Israel over King Amaziah of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.25.21-23">2 Chr 25:21-23</a>). About a century later, Beth-shemesh was captured from King Ahaz of Judah by the Philistines (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.16-20">28:16-20</a>). After that, the settlement fell into decline and was finally destroyed by Nebuchadnezzar in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Canaanite city allotted to Issachar’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.22">Jos 19:22</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Fortified Canaanite city allotted to Naphtali’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.38">Jos 19:38</a>). The inhabitants of this Beth-shemesh were not driven out by the Israelites (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.33">Jgs 1:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. KJV reference to the Egyptian city of Heliopolis (or On), where the sun was worshiped (<a href="?bref=Jer.43.13">Jer 43:13</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Heliopolis_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Heliopolis</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfBethShemesh"/>
</body>
</item>