<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BethHoron">
  <title>Beth-Horon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BETH-HORON</p>
<p class="fl">Canaanite place-name perhaps meaning “the house of Hauron,” the god of the underworld. Beth-horon was a dual settlement 10 and 12 miles (16.1 and 19.3 kilometers) northwest of Jerusalem. Located on the boundary between the tribal territories of Ephraim and Benjamin (<a href="?bref=Josh.16.3,5">Jos 16:3, 5</a>), the twin settlements controlled the valley of Aijalon, one of the most important ancient routes between the Mediterranean coast and the interior hill country. The upper town controlled a strategic pass. Ephraim’s “Beth-horon with its pasture lands” was assigned to the Levite family of Kohath (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.22">Jos 21:22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.68">1 Chr 6:68</a>).</p>
<p>Many armies marched through the Aijalon Valley. Amorites pursued by Joshua’s army fled past Beth-horon after being defeated at Gibeon on “the day the sun stood still” (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.1-14">Jos 10:1-14</a>). A band of Philistines approached it to make war with Saul (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.18">1 Sm 13:18</a>). The Egyptian army of Shishak passed by Beth-horon (according to his Karnak inscription). Syrian armies under Seron (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.3.13-24">1 Macc 3:13-24</a>) and Nicanor (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.7.39-43">7:39-43</a>) were defeated by Judas Maccabeus at Beth-horon. The Romans under Cestius were nearly annihilated there by the Jews, according to Jewish historian Josephus.</p>
<p>Beth-horon was probably destroyed and rebuilt more than once. Sheerah, Beriah’s daughter and Ephraim’s granddaughter, is credited with building both lower and upper Beth-horon (<a href="?bref=1Chr.7.24">1 Chr 7:24</a>). King Solomon fortified both Beth-horons after raids in the vicinity by an Egyptian pharaoh (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.15-17">1 Kgs 9:15-17</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.8.5">2 Chr 8:5</a>). In the intertestamental period Beth-horon was fortified by the Syrian general Bacchides after a battle with Jonathan Maccabeus (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.9.50">1 Macc 9:50</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>