<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BibleInspirationofthe">
  <title>Bible*, Inspiration of the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BIBLE*, I<span class="lc">nspiration of the</span></p>
<p class="fl">Theological term for the influence God exerted on the writers of Scripture, enabling them to transmit his revelations in writing.</p>
<p>The Bible itself tells us that it is an inspired text. It says, “All scripture is given by inspiration of God” (<a href="?bref=2Tim.3.16">2 Tm 3:16</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). A translation closer to the original language (Greek) would be, “All Scripture is God-breathed” (<span class="sc">niv</span>). This tells us that every word of the Bible was breathed out from God. The words of the Bible came from God and were written by men. The apostle Peter affirmed this when he said that “no prophecy of Scripture came about by the prophet’s own interpretation. For prophecy never had its origin in the will of man, but men spoke from God as they were carried along by the Holy Spirit” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.1.20-21">2 Pt 1:20-21</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>).</p>
<p>“Men spoke from God.” This short sentence is the key to understanding how the Bible came into being. Thousands of years ago, God chose certain men—such as Moses, David, Isaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, and Daniel—to receive his words and write them down. What they wrote became books, or sections, of the OT. Nearly 2,000 years ago, God chose other men—such as Matthew, Mark, Luke, John, and Paul—to communicate his new message, the message of salvation through Jesus Christ. What they wrote became books, or sections, of the NT.</p>
<p>God gave his words to these men in many different ways. Certain writers of the OT received messages directly from God. Moses was given the Ten Commandments inscribed on a stone when he was in God’s presence on Mt Sinai. When David was composing his psalms to God, he received divine inspiration to foretell certain events that would occur 1,000 years later in Jesus Christ’s life. God told his prophets—such as Isaiah and Jeremiah—exactly what to say; therefore, when they gave a message, it was God’s word, not their own. This is why many OT prophets often said, “Thus says the Lord.” (This statement appears over 2,000 times in the OT.) To other prophets, such as Ezekiel and Daniel, God communicated his message through visions and dreams. They recorded exactly what they saw, whether they understood it or not. And other OT writers, such as Samuel and Ezra, were directed by God to record events in the history of Israel.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="AntilegomenaTheBooksThatDidnTMakeIt"/>
<p>Four hundred years after the last book of the OT (Malachi) was written, God’s Son, Jesus Christ, came to earth. In his talks, he affirmed the divine authorship of the OT writings (see <a href="?bref=Matt.5.17-19">Mt 5:17-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.16.17">Lk 16:17</a>; <a href="?bref=John.10.35">Jn 10:35</a>). Furthermore, he often pointed to certain passages in the OT as having predicted certain events in his life (see <a href="?bref=Luke.24.27,44">Lk 24:27, 44</a>). The NT writers also affirmed the divine inspiration of the OT text. It was the apostle Paul who was directed by God to write, “All Scripture is God-inspired.” Quite specifically, he was speaking of the OT. And, as was already noted, Peter said that the OT prophets were motivated by the Holy Spirit to speak from God.</p>
<p>The NT is also a God-inspired book. Before Jesus left this earth and returned to his Father, he told the disciples that he would send the Holy Spirit to them. He told them that one of the functions of the Holy Spirit would be to remind them of all the things that Jesus had said and then to guide them into more truth (see <a href="?bref=John.14.26">Jn 14:26</a>; <a href="?bref=John.15.26">15:26</a>; <a href="?bref=John.16.13-15">16:13-15</a>). Those who wrote the Gospels were helped by the Holy Spirit to remember Jesus’ exact words, and those who wrote other parts of the NT were guided by the Spirit as they wrote.</p>
<p>The inspiration for writing the Gospels didn’t begin when the authors set pen to papyrus; the inspiration began when the disciples Matthew, Peter (for whom Mark wrote), and John were enlightened by their encounters with Jesus Christ, the Son of God. The apostles’ experiences with him altered their lives forever, imprinting on their souls unforgettable images of the revealed God-man, Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>This is what John was speaking of in the prologue to his Gospel when he declared, “The Word became flesh and lived among us, and we have seen his glory” (<a href="?bref=John.1.14">1:14</a>, paraphrased). The “we” refers to those eyewitnesses of Jesus’ glory—the apostles who lived with Jesus for over three years. This reminiscence is expanded upon in John’s prologue to his first epistle, where he says “we have heard him, touched him, seen him, and looked upon him” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.1-2">1 Jn 1:1-2</a>, paraphrased). In both the Gospel and the Epistle, the verbs are in the perfect tense, denoting a past action with a present, abiding effect. Those past encounters with Jesus were never forgotten by John; they lived with him and stayed with him as an inspiring spirit until the day—many years later—he wrote of them in his Gospel. The same could be said for Matthew, who wrote an important Gospel, and Peter, who was really the author behind Mark’s composition. Luke was not an eyewitness, but he based his Gospel on the accounts of those who were (see <a href="?bref=Luke.1.1-4">Lk 1:1-4</a>).</p>
<p>The inspiration for the writing of the Epistles can also be traced to the writers’ encounters with the living Christ. The most prominent epistle writer, Paul, repeatedly claims that his inspiration and subsequent commission came from his encounter with the risen Christ (see, for example, <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.8-10">1 Cor 15:8-10</a>). Peter also claims that his writings were based upon his experiences with the living Christ (see <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.1">1 Pt 5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.1.16-18">2 Pt 1:16-18</a>). And so does John, who claims to have experienced the God-man visibly, audibly, and palpably (see <a href="?bref=1Jn.1.1-4">1 Jn 1:1-4</a>). James and Jude make no such claim directly, but since they were the brothers of Jesus who became converts when they saw the risen Christ (this is certain for James—see <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.7">1 Cor 15:7</a>—and presumed for Jude—see <a href="?bref=Acts.1.14">Acts 1:14</a>), they too drew their inspiration from their encounters with the living Christ. Thus, all the epistle writers (with the possible exception of the one who wrote Hebrews, who is unknown) knew the living Christ. This is the relationship that qualified them to write those books that became part of the NT canon. This made them distinct from all others, no matter how good their writings were.</p>
<p>The writers of the NT epistles were inspired by the Spirit when they wrote. Speaking for all the apostles, Paul indicated that the NT apostles were taught by the Holy Spirit what to say. The writers of the NT did not speak with words “taught by human wisdom,” but with “words taught by the Holy Spirit” (see <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.10-13">1 Cor 2:10-13</a>). What they wrote was Spirit-taught. For example, when the apostle John saw that Jesus Christ had come to give eternal life to men, the Spirit helped him express this truth in many different ways. Thus, the reader of John’s Gospel sees different phrases about Jesus giving life: “in him was life,” “a well of living water springing up into eternal life,” “the bread of life,” “the light of life,” “the resurrection and the life,” etc. (see <a href="?bref=John.1.4">Jn 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=John.4.14">4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.48">6:48</a>; <a href="?bref=John.8.12">8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.25">11:25</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.6">14:6</a>). When the apostle Paul contemplated the fullness of Christ’s deity, he was inspired by the Spirit to use such phrasing as “in him dwells all the fullness of the Godhead bodily,” “in him are hid all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge,” and “the unsearchable riches of Christ” (see <a href="?bref=Col.2.3,9">Col 2:3, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.3.8">Eph 3:8</a>).</p>
<p>As the Spirit taught the writers, they used their own vocabulary and writing style to express the thought of the Spirit. As such, the Scriptures came as the result of divine and human cooperation. The Scriptures were not mechanically inspired—as if God used the men as machines through whom he dictated the divine utterance. Rather, the Scriptures were inspired by God, then written by men. The Bible, therefore, is both fully divine and fully human.</p>
  </body>
</item>