<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Birthright">
  <title>Birthright</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BIRTHRIGHT</p>
<p class="fl">Right or privilege belonging to the firstborn son in a Hebrew family. The eldest son ranked highest after the father and in the father’s absence had the father’s authority and responsibility, as illustrated by Reuben’s relationship to his younger brothers (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.19-22,28-30">Gn 37:19-22, 28-30</a>). However, because he later committed incest, Reuben forfeited his birthright (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.1-4">Gn 49:1-4</a>). Next in line were Simeon, Levi, and Judah (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.31-35">Gn 29:31-35</a>), but Jacob, their father, passed over Simeon and Levi because of their lack of character (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.5-7">Gn 49:5-7</a>). Although he praised Judah (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.8-10">Gn 49:8-10</a>), Jacob gave the birthright to his favorite son, Joseph (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.22-26">Gn 49:22-26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.5.1-2">1 Chr 5:1-2</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.37.2-4">Gn 37:2-4</a>).</p>
<p>Tablets recovered from Nuzi in Mesopotamia have shown that the birthright could be exchanged among members of the same family (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.25.19-34">Gn 25:19-34</a>). The holder of the birthright appears to have been in possession of the “teraphim,” or household idols (<a href="?bref=Gen.31.19,32,34">31:19, 32, 34</a>), which were small terra-cotta images, presumably of the particular deity worshiped locally. These tokens would reinforce the position and authority of the firstborn.</p>
<p>The birthright meant not only the honor of family leadership but also an inheritance of twice the amount received by every other son. In polygamous Israelite society the birthright belonged to the actual firstborn of the father and could not be transferred to the son of a favorite wife without just cause (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.15-17">Dt 21:15-17</a>). However, the birthright did not belong to the firstborn son if his mother was a concubine or slave (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.9-13">Gn 21:9-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.11.1-2">Jgs 11:1-2</a>). The rights of the firstborn son of a king included the right of succession to the throne (<a href="?bref=2Chr.21.1-3">2 Chr 21:1-3</a>). When King Rehoboam of Judah violated custom by making his favorite son, Abijah, his successor, he had to pay off his other sons to avoid trouble (<a href="?bref=2Chr.11.18-23">11:18-23</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.12.16">12:16</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT, reference is made to the OT account of Esau, the son of the patriarch Isaac, who impulsively traded his birthright for a bowl of lentil stew (<a href="?bref=Heb.12.16-17">Heb 12:16-17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.25.19-34">Gn 25:19-34</a>). Christians are warned not to throw away their inheritance of spiritual blessing from God the way Esau lost his birthright and his father’s blessing (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.1-46">Gn 27</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Inheritance_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Inheritance</a>; <a href="?item=Heir_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Heir</a>; <a href="?item=Firstborn_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Firstborn</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="AnEternalInheritance"/>
  </body>
</item>