<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Bishop">
  <title>Bishop*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BISHOP*</p>
<p class="fl">Official in the church whose qualifications are listed in <a href="?bref=1Tim.3.2-7">1 Timothy 3:2-7</a> and <a href="?bref=Titus.1.6-9">Titus 1:6-9</a>. The Greek word from which the English title “bishop” and the adjective “episcopal” are derived is often translated in modern versions as “elder,” “overseer,” “shepherd,” or “guardian,” corresponding closely to the current term “pastor.” Jesus is called “the Shepherd and Bishop of your souls” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.25">1 Pt 2:25</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>).</p>
<p>In the NT, “bishop,” and “elder” refer to the same office, as shown by the apostle Paul’s telling Titus to appoint “elders in every town” and then referring to those same individuals as “bishops” (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.5,7">Ti 1:5, 7</a>). While at Miletus, Paul summoned the elders from the church at Ephesus and then addressed them as “overseers” or “guardians” (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.17,28">Acts 20:17, 28</a>). In his letter to Philippi, Paul greeted the “bishops and deacons” (<a href="?bref=Phil.1.1">Phil 1:1</a>). The fact that there were numerous bishops at Philippi, as well as in Ephesus, shows that the episcopal office had not yet developed into what it later became: a single bishop governing one or more churches.</p>
<p>Bishops obviously had positions of authority, but the duties of the office are not clearly defined in the NT. One task was to combat heresy (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.9">Ti 1:9</a>) and to teach and expound the Scriptures (<a href="?bref=1Tim.3.2">1 Tm 3:2</a>). In addition, there is some evidence that a primary concern was with economic matters and the care of the poor, as well as with a general overseeing of the congregation. The lists of qualifications in Paul’s letters to Timothy and Titus indicate that a bishop was considered a leader in the congregation and a representative to the non-Christian world. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Elder_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Elder</a>; <a href="?item=Pastor_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Pastor</a>; <a href="?item=Presbyter_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Presbyter</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>