<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BloodFlowof">
  <title>Blood*, Flow of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BLOOD*, F<span class="lc">low of</span></p>
<p class="list">1. Vaginal discharge such as that during menstruation. <a href="?bref=Lev.15.1-33">Leviticus 15</a> contains social and sanitary laws that God gave to Moses concerning genital discharges. A woman with vaginal bleeding was considered ceremonially unclean during bleeding and for seven days afterward. She could not go to the tabernacle or temple for worship while unclean or mingle with crowds in the street or market. Anyone touching her or her clothes, bed, chair, and the like was also ceremonially unclean (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.19-28">Lv 15:19-28</a>). Sexual intercourse was not allowed while the woman was ceremonially unclean. Seven days after her bleeding stopped, a woman would present to the priest two turtledoves or young pigeons as offerings to atone for the time of her uncleanness (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.29-30">Lv 15:29-30</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Jesus’ miraculous healing of a woman who had been hemorrhaging (slowly or intermittently) for 12 years was recorded in three of the four Gospels (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.20-22">Mt 9:20-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.5.25-34">Mk 5:25-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.43-48">Lk 8:43-48</a>). If her bleeding was vaginal, the years of ceremonial uncleanness and separation must have been particularly distressing for her. Besides being anxious and uncomfortable, she would also have been unable to bear children. Further, she had “suffered a great deal from many doctors” and “had spent everything she had to pay for them, but she had gotten no better” (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.26">Mk 5:26</a>). In despair she ignored the rules about uncleanness and made her way through a crowd to touch Jesus. When she touched him, the bleeding stopped immediately and permanently.</p>
<p class="list">2. Bloody stools. The “bloody flux” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) from which Publius’s father suffered was some form of dysentery (<a href="?bref=Acts.28.8">Acts 28:8</a>).</p>
<p class="sp"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=MedicineandMedicalPractice_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Medicine and Medical Practice</a>; <a href="?item=Hemorrhage_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hemorrhage</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>