<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Bone">
  <title>Bone</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BONE</p>
<p class="fl">One of the separate parts of the human or animal skeleton. After death, bones retain their form long after the soft tissues have decomposed, so bones are often associated with dead bodies or with death itself. The Israelites were concerned about proper respect for the bodies of the dead (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.25">Gn 50:25</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.31.11-13">1 Sm 31:11-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.14-18">2 Kgs 23:14-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.14-16">Ez 39:14-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.2.1">Am 2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.22">Heb 11:22</a>).</p>
<p>A valley of “old, dry bones” symbolized the people of Israel, who were without hope until the Spirit of the Lord would put life back into them (<a href="?bref=Ezek.37.1-14">Ez 37:1-14</a>). In a living body, however, bones are living tissue, and Ezekiel knew that broken bones could heal (<a href="?bref=Ezek.30.21">30:21</a>). Intact bones were a requirement for an unblemished lamb for the Passover (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.46">Ex 12:46</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.9.11-12">Nm 9:11-12</a>). Thus, the NT states that when Jesus Christ, the “Lamb of God” (<a href="?bref=John.1.36">Jn 1:36</a>), was crucified, contrary to Roman practice, his legs were not broken (<a href="?bref=Ps.34.20">Ps 34:20</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.30-37">Jn 19:30-37</a>).</p>
<p>Some references to bones in the Bible (<a href="?bref=Job.2.5">Jb 2:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.19.20">19:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.30.30">30:30</a>) carry the connotation of deep feelings, as in the phrase “I feel it in my bones.” Other references are metaphorical expressions of close kinship, “flesh and bone” (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.23">Gn 2:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.29.14">29:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.9.2">Jgs 9:2</a>) being equivalent to the expression “one’s own flesh and blood.”</p>
  </body>
</item>