<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Book">
  <title>Book</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BOOK</p>
<p class="fl">A set of written sheets or a scroll—whether composed of wood, parchment, papyrus, or paper—containing records or a literary composition. With respect to the Bible, each individual composition is called a “book” because that was what the document was before it became part of the biblical collection. As such, the Bible has 66 books—such as Genesis, Isaiah, Matthew, and Revelation.</p>
<p>The most important book to the ancient Hebrews was the Book of the Law (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.8">2 Kgs 22:8</a>), because it came from God to Moses (<a href="?bref=Josh.23.6">Jos 23:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.26">Mk 12:26</a>) and contained the record of the Mosaic covenant (e.g., <a href="?bref=Exod.20.1-26">Ex 20</a>). God instructed Joshua to meditate on it day and night (<a href="?bref=Josh.1.8">Jos 1:8</a>). The prophets appealed to it constantly, particularly to Deuteronomy. The discovery of the Book of the Law during the renovation of the temple in Josiah’s reign led to important religious reforms (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.8-13">2 Kgs 22:8-13</a>).</p>
<p>Some books specifically labeled as biblical source materials are the Book of the Wars of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Num.21.14">Nm 21:14</a>), the Book of Jashar (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.13">Jos 10:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.1.18">2 Sm 1:18</a>), the Book of the Acts of Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.41">1 Kgs 11:41</a>), and the Book of the Chronicles of the Kings of Judah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.29">14:29</a>). A number of prophetic works are cited in the books of Chronicles as sources for the material recorded in those books. Some of these are the Chronicles of Samuel the Seer, the Chronicles of Nathan the Prophet, the Chronicles of Gad the Seer (<a href="?bref=1Chr.29.29">1 Chr 29:29</a>), and the Prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite (<a href="?bref=2Chr.9.29">2 Chr 9:29</a>). The fact that prophetic sources were used for Chronicles demonstrates that the Hebrew people regarded their history as the record of God’s activity. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Writing_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Writing</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>