<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BreadofthePresence">
  <title>Bread of the Presence</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BREAD OF THE PRESENCE</p>
<p class="fl">Loaves of bread placed on a special table in the sanctuary or Holy Place of the tabernacle and later in the temple. Two other terms in the OT are used to describe the “bread of the Presence,” which means bread that has been set before the Lord’s face (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.23,30">Ex 25:23, 30</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.35.13">35:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.39.36">39:36</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.48">1 Kgs 7:48</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.4.19">2 Chr 4:19</a>). The term “showbread” (<span class="sc">kjv</span> “shewbread”) refers to the arrangement of the bread in rows on the table (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.32">1 Chr 9:32</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.29">23:29</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.28.16">28:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.2.4">2 Chr 2:4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.13.11">13:11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.18">29:18</a>).</p>
<p>Although the table of showbread, the altar of incense, and the golden lampstand were not in the Holy of Holies, they were nevertheless considered to be in the presence of God. As an offering placed before the presence of God, the loaves were considered holy and could be eaten only by priests. Later in Israel’s history, provision for offering the bread of the Presence as well as other temple services was financed by a tax of one-third shekel upon all citizens (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.32-33">Neh 10:32-33</a>).</p>
<p>The bread of the Presence consisted of 12 very large loaves, each made of one-fifth ephah of fine flour. Since an ephah was just over a bushel, two and a half bushels (30.3 liters) of finely ground wheat were required to make the 12 loaves. They were sprinkled with frankincense, arranged in two rows, the one leaning against the other, and placed on the table of showbread (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.5-9">Lv 24:5-9</a>). Arranged in that way, the bread became an “offering of food” to the Lord. The loaves were changed weekly on the Sabbath day.</p>
<p>The bread of the Presence is featured in one incident recalled in the NT. The tabernacle was at Nob when David was fleeing from the presence of King Saul. David went to Ahimelech, the priest, in search of food (<a href="?bref=1Sam.21.1-6">1 Sm 21:1-6</a>). Ahimelech had only the showbread, which he agreed to share with David’s men, provided they had been sexually continent for a period of time before their eating. Jesus later referred to the incident as a parallel to his own ministry of supplying the needs of those who followed him (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.1-8">Mt 12:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.2.25-26">Mk 2:25-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.1-5">Lk 6:1-5</a>). As God’s anointed, David and his men were permitted to eat the holy bread. Likewise Jesus, God’s anointed one, provided for the needs of others in spite of the Sabbath regulations.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>