<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BronzeSerpentBronzeSnake">
  <title>Bronze Serpent, Bronze Snake</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BRONZE SERPENT, BRONZE SNAKE</p>
<p class="fl">Piece of sculpture that God commanded Moses to make when the Israelites were being bitten by “fiery serpents” (<a href="?bref=Num.21.4-9">Nm 21:4-9</a>). The serpents had been sent as a judgment because the people were grumbling against God and against Moses. When the people repented, God ordered the replica made; those who looked at it were healed.</p>
<p>Some connect the theological meaning of the scene with an episode in which Moses’ rod became a serpent, swallowed up the serpent-rods of the Pharaoh’s magicians, and then became a rod again (<a href="?bref=Exod.7.8-12">Ex 7:8-12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.4.2-5,28-30">4:2-5, 28-30</a>). The serpent was a deified figure in both the Egyptian and Canaanite religions. Therefore, the triumph of God’s serpent figure typified the superiority of the Lord over the pagan gods. In <a href="?bref=Num.21.1-35">Numbers 21</a>, however, such a realization must have been secondary. That event was the last of a number of “apostasies” in the wilderness (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.9">1 Cor 10:9</a>), all of which included four elements: complaints against God, judgment, repentance, and forgiveness or deliverance. The major theological theme is not the Lord’s superiority but his provision of salvation. The stress was not on a magical formula for healing, but rather on the serpent as a symbol of salvation offered to all who would focus on it.</p>
<p>The bronze serpent appears again in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.4">2 Kings 18:4</a>. In the intervening centuries it had become an idolatrous object, and King Hezekiah (716–686 <span class="era">BC</span>) of the southern kingdom of Judah abolished it in his reform movement. The final reference to it in pre-Christian literature is in the apocryphal book Wisdom of Solomon, which supports the above interpretation: salvation came not through the serpent but through God’s provision. “He who turned towards it was healed, not by what he saw, but by you, the Savior of all” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.16.7">Wisd of Sol 16:7</a>).</p>
<p>Against this background, Christ said that he, like Moses’ serpent, must be lifted up (<a href="?bref=John.3.14">Jn 3:14</a>). The “lifting up” of the “Son of Man” is a definite reference to Christ’s death and has two foci. One is a “death as salvation” theme, seen in the Mosaic serpent imagery and the divine imperative “must” (in Jn referring to the necessity of God’s ordained plan of salvation). The other is a “death as exaltation” theme, seen in the verb itself (containing the idea of majesty) and in John’s stress on the glory of Jesus’ earthly ministry and of his resurrected status.</p>
  </body>
</item>