<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Brother">
  <title>Brother</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">BROTHER</p>
<p class="fl">Man or boy in his relationship to the other children of his parents; also a close male friend or fellow member of the same race, creed, profession, organization, and the like; a kinsman.</p>
<p>In the OT the Hebrew word translated “brother” describes the relationship between male children who have at least one parent in common. Joseph and Benjamin were children of Jacob and Rachel (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.24">Gn 35:24</a>), but the other sons born to Jacob are also called Joseph’s brothers (<a href="?bref=Gen.42.6">42:6</a>). The love Joseph had for Benjamin is not always found between brothers. Cain killed his brother Abel (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.8">4:8</a>), and Esau hated his brother, Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.41">27:41</a>). A brother may be a bad influence (<a href="?bref=Deut.13.6-7">Dt 13:6-7</a>), but ideally he is one who helps in times of need (<a href="?bref=Pr.17.17">Prv 17:17</a>). The law of levirate marriage required that if a man died leaving a childless widow, the man’s brother had to raise up children through her to perpetuate the family name (<a href="?bref=Deut.25.5">Dt 25:5</a>).</p>
<p>David spoke affectionately of his “brother” Jonathan, although they were not related (<a href="?bref=2Sam.1.26">2 Sm 1:26</a>). A fellow Israelite could be called brother. The relationship required certain obligations: money could not be loaned to a brother at interest, and a brother could not be enslaved (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.35-43">Lv 25:35-43</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT the Greek word is used to describe natural brothers, such as Andrew and Peter (<a href="?bref=John.1.41">Jn 1:41</a>). Four brothers of Jesus are named (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>). (The Roman Catholic view is that they were really Jesus’ cousins, but the Greek language has several words for cousin, and the word “brother” is used here; thus, it refers either to children or foster children of Mary and Joseph.) Jesus’ brothers did not believe in him at first (<a href="?bref=John.7.5">Jn 7:5</a>), but after the resurrection they were meeting with the Christian community (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.14">Acts 1:14</a>). Jesus taught that his disciples had one Father (God) and were therefore brothers (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.8-9">Mt 23:8-9</a>), and he graciously identified himself with the disciples as their brother (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.10">28:10</a>).</p>
<p>Early in the history of the church it became customary for Christians to address one another as brother (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.17">Acts 9:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.1">Col 1:1</a>); on two occasions the Christian community is called “the brotherhood” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.17">1 Pt 2:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.9">5:9</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Specific duties and responsibilities accompany Christian brotherhood. A Christian’s love for his brother will be demonstrated in the restraint of sexual passions (<a href="?bref=1Thes.4.6">1 Thes 4:6</a>), provision of material goods when needed (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.15-16">Jas 2:15-16</a>), and determination not to offend (<a href="?bref=Rom.14.13">Rom 14:13</a>). A Christian must not “go to law” against a brother (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.5-6">1 Cor 6:5-6</a>), but brothers must resolve their problems either personally or within the church group (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.15-17">Mt 18:15-17</a>). The relationship between Christians is significant because a Christian cannot offer worship to God if he is out of harmony with his brother (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.23-24">Mt 5:23-24</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=FamilyLifeandRelations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Family Life and Relations</a>; <a href="?item=BrothersandSisters_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Brothers (and Sisters)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>