<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Earth">
  <title>Earth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EARTH</p>
<p class="fl">Term used for our inhabited planet; the world, as distinguished from heaven and hell; land; soil; and in several other ways. Biblical usage is as broad as modern usage.</p>
<p>One Hebrew word translated “earth” is also used generically for “man,” or Adam (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.7,19">Gn 2:7, 19</a>). That word refers to reddish soil from which Adam’s body was made. Another Hebrew word translated “earth” or “land” can refer to a country (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.21">21:21</a>). A word translated “dust” can mean simply earth or dry ground (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.19">3:19</a>). In the NT one Greek word translated “earth” can refer to a land or country (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.45">Mt 27:45</a>). The Greek word from which “ecumenical” is derived refers to the whole inhabited earth (<a href="?bref=Luke.21.26">Lk 21:26</a>) or the Roman Empire of those days (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.1">2:1</a>).</p>
<p>In the beginning “God called the dry land Earth, and the waters that were gathered together he called Seas. . . . And God said, ‘Let the earth put forth vegetation’” (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.10-11">Gn 1:10-11</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). In some passages “the earth” is used in essentially the modern sense for the whole planet (<a href="?bref=Job.1.7">Jb 1:7</a>), hanging in empty space (<a href="?bref=Job.26.7">26:7</a>). References to the earth’s four corners (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.12">Is 11:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.7.2">Ez 7:2</a>) allude to the points of a compass, not to the earth’s shape. The circle of the earth probably refers to the circumference of the horizon (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.22">Is 40:22</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Job.38.13">Jb 38:13</a>). The earth is sometimes pictured as supported on pillars (<a href="?bref=Job.9.6">Jb 9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.75.3">Ps 75:3</a>) or foundations (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.5">Ps 104:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.8.29">Prv 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.24.18">Is 24:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.31.37">Jer 31:37</a>). Since many of the biblical usages are found in figurative passages of poetry or prophecy, they reveal little about the Hebrews’ cosmological understanding.</p>
<p>“Earth” sometimes refers to the soil or ground that a farmer works (cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.5.17">2 Kgs 5:17</a>). According to the Bible, the original condition of the earth (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.6">Gn 2:6</a>) was affected by the curse of human sinfulness (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.17-19">3:17-19</a>). (Modern ecologists seem to agree that the earth suffers because of human greed and arrogance.) After Abel’s blood was spilled on the ground, Cain’s difficulty in making the soil produce for him was a constant reminder that he had murdered his brother (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.8-12">4:8-12</a>).</p>
<p>The Israelites were instructed to let the land rest every seventh year (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.10-12">Ex 23:10-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.25.4-5">Lv 25:4-5</a>), allowing the soil to replenish nutrients used up by crops. After seven such “sabbath years,” in the 50th “jubilee year” the land reverted back to original family holdings (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.10-17">Lv 25:10-17</a>). That provision not only reminded the people of God’s ultimate ownership but kept potential “land barons” from amassing huge estates.</p>
<p>The Mosaic law instructed the Israelites that the land’s condition would be a spiritual barometer of their relationship with God. Drought or lack of productivity was a sign that the relationship had been broken (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.1-46">Lv 26</a>; Dt 28). Israel was warned that their wickedness could become so great that the Lord would evict them from his land (cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.26.37">Lv 26:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.28.64">Dt 28:64</a>). Even if that happened, however, God would eventually restore his people so they could again be “wedded” to the land (<a href="?bref=Isa.62.4">Is 62:4</a>).</p>
<p>Many passages point to a “coming age,” when the earth will be set free from its “bondage to decay,” a deliverance for which the whole creation is said to be “groaning” in anticipation (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.19-23">Rom 8:19-23</a>). The Bible pictures a period of prodigious renewal of the earth’s fertility (Ez 47; <a href="?bref=Joel.3.18">Jl 3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.9.13-15">Am 9:13-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.14.6-9">Zec 14:6-9</a>). One day, however, “the heavens will pass away with a loud noise, and the elements will be dissolved with fire, and the earth and the works that are upon it will be burned up” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.10">2 Pt 3:10</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Yet in the apostle John’s apocalyptic vision, he saw “a new heaven and a new earth, for the old heaven and the old earth had disappeared” (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.1">Rv 21:1</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=NewHeavensandNewEarth_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New Heavens and New Earth</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>