<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EdomEdomites">
  <title>Edom, Edomites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EDOM, EDOMITES</p>
<p class="fl">Land and its inhabitants found on the high plateau to the south and southeast of the Dead Sea. The biblical term Edom, meaning “red,” denotes either the name of the land or the name of Esau, in remembrance of the red pottage or stew for which he exchanged his birthright (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.30">Gn 25:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.36.1,8,19">36:1, 8, 19</a>). The country of Edom was also known as Seir (<a href="?bref=Gen.32.3">Gn 32:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.36.30">36:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.24.18">Nm 24:18</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Geography">Geography</p>
<p class="fl">The northern boundary of Edom was the Wadi Zered, the “Brook of the Willows” (<a href="?bref=Isa.15.7">Is 15:7</a>). In ancient geological times, the area was elevated considerably, exposing dark-red sandstone cliffs along the western side where the land falls steeply into the Arabah - the southern extension of the deep depression in which the Dead Sea and the Jordan Valley lie. The Edom Plateau rises to over 5,000 feet (1,523.9 meters), reaching over 5,600 feet (1,706.8 meters) in places. The area divides into two unequal parts. The region of Punon forms something of a valley between the smaller northern part and the longer southern part. The northern section is not quite so high, though in a limited area near Radhadiyeh it reaches 5,300 feet (1,615.4 meters). The southern section is longer and generally higher, being over 5,000 feet (1,523.9 meters) throughout the central ridge and touching 5,687 feet (1,733.3 meters) at one point. To the east, the escarpment does not fall below 4,000 feet (1,219.1 meters), except in the north. The desert lies beyond and limits expansion eastward. To the west, the land falls away rather steeply into the Arabah. The extent of Edom to the west varied from time to time. Gaining access to the Negev of southern Judah was relatively easy in this area, and Edomite occasionally intruded. The southern border was marked by a wide limestone cliff at the southern edge of the plateau. This ran eastward from Ain Gharandal in the Arabah. Beyond this barrier to the south lay rocky, uninhabitable desert, through which merchants must have journeyed to the port at Ezion-geber for trade.</p>
<p>The land of Edom was, on the whole, inhospitable, though there were areas where farming could be undertaken, particularly to the northeast. Here herds of animals could be grazed. Edom’s wealth, however, came largely from the caravan trade that came up from the south and brought goods from India and South Arabia to the Mediterranean coast and Egypt. The important King’s Highway (<a href="?bref=Num.21.22">Nm 21:22</a>) passed through Edom on its way north.</p>
<p class="h2" id="History">History</p>
<p class="fl">Biblically, the name Edom does not appear in the genealogy in <a href="?bref=Gen.10.1-32">Genesis 10</a>. It first appears in the story of Esau in <a href="?bref=Gen.25.30">Genesis 25:30</a>. Esau was called Edom from the red color of the pottage for which he sold his birthright to his brother, Jacob. In <a href="?bref=Gen.36.1-43">Genesis 36</a> there is reference to an Edomite kingdom at a time well before the appearance of an Israelite kingdom, though it is possible that the “chiefs” of Edom were tribal chieftains or non-dynastic leaders like the Israelite judges.</p>
<p>The earliest nonbiblical references come from Egypt and seem to confirm this. Amarna Letter 288 (early 14th century <span class="era">BC</span>) refers to the “lands of Seir,” and the crossing of the Shashu tribes of Edom into Egypt is mentioned by Seti II (1214–1208 <span class="era">BC</span>) and Ramses III (1198–1166 <span class="era">BC</span>). There are no Egyptian references to towns or rulers, only to tribal Bedouin from Seir-Edom. There is some evidence that Ramses II was in Transjordan about 1280–1270 <span class="era">BC</span>, but there is no clear evidence that there was a centralized government before the 13th century <span class="era">BC</span>. Rather, the land was occupied mainly by seminomadic people. From then on, permanent settlements began to appear, a fact that has relevance for the date of the exodus. The Song of Moses in <a href="?bref=Exod.15.1-27">Exodus 15</a> refers to the “chiefs of Edom.” By the time of the exodus, there appears to have been a kingdom of Edom (<a href="?bref=Num.20.14,18,20-23">Nm 20:14, 18, 20-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.33.37">33:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.34.3">34:3</a>). The Israelites walked along Edom on their journey to the Promised Land (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.4">Jgs 5:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.11.17-18">11:17-18</a>).</p>
<p>At the time of the rise of the Israelite monarchy, Saul fought successfully against Edom (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.47">1 Sm 14:47</a>). Doeg the Edomite was the chief of Saul’s herdsmen (<a href="?bref=1Sam.21.7">21:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.22.9,18-22">22:9, 18-22</a>). At the beginning of the 10th century <span class="era">BC</span>, David defeated Edom in the Valley of Salt and killed many Edomites (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.13">2 Sm 8:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.12">1 Chr 18:12</a>). Thereafter, David placed garrisons in Edom, and the Edomites became his subjects (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.14">2 Sm 8:14</a>). It is not clear whether David saw in these people a military threat or whether he was interested in the supply of copper from their land and the potential wealth that would flow from the caravan traffic passing through Edom. David’s successes resulted in the flight of a certain Hadad, who was “of the royal house of Edom” to Egypt (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.14-17">1 Kgs 11:14-17</a>), where he married a member of the Egyptian royal family (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.18-20">18-20</a>). On David’s death, Hadad returned to Edom, where he became king. It would seem that a monarchical form of government had developed by David’s time. Solomon continued to exert influence in Edom. He had access to the port of Ezion-geber (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.26">9:26</a>).</p>
<p>The biblical records provide no information about Edom from the end of Solomon’s reign until the days of Jehoshaphat of Judah (872–848 <span class="era">BC</span>). Jehoshaphat was able to occupy the port of Ezion-geber, although his ships were wrecked there, possibly by the Edomites (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.48">1 Kgs 22:48</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.20.36-37">2 Chr 20:36-37</a>). Israel combined with Judah and Edom in an unsuccessful campaign against King Mesha of Moab (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.4-27">2 Kgs 3:4-27</a>). Edom was able to throw off Judah’s authority under King Jehoram (853–841 <span class="era">BC</span>) and set up a king of its own (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.8.20-22">8:20-22</a>). It remained independent until the days of King Amaziah of Judah (796–767 <span class="era">BC</span>), who conquered Edom as far south as Sela, defeating a large army of the Edomites in the Valley of Salt (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.7">2 Kgs 14:7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.25.11-13">2 Chr 25:11-13</a>). This gave Judah control of the copper mines in the Punon area. King Uzziah of Judah (792–740 <span class="era">BC</span>) was able to push his control south to Elath (near Ezion-geber; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.22">2 Kgs 14:22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.26.1-2">2 Chr 26:1-2</a>). Before the end of the eighth century <span class="era">BC</span>, in the days of Ahaz (735–715 <span class="era">BC</span>), Edom defeated Judah and recovered Elath (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.6">2 Kgs 16:6</a>). Thereafter, Judah lost control over Edom.</p>
<p>During the eighth century <span class="era">BC</span>, the Assyrians began to move into Transjordan. About 800 <span class="era">BC</span> Adad-nirari III (810–782 <span class="era">BC</span>) claimed to have conquered several of these western states and to have imposed the payment of tribute. Then Tiglath-pileser III (745–727 <span class="era">BC</span>) received tribute from Qaus-malaku of Edom. Sargon II (722–705 <span class="era">BC</span>) spoke of an unnamed ruler of Edom who was involved in the rebellion of Ashdod in 713 <span class="era">BC</span>. Sennacherib (705–681 <span class="era">BC</span>) spoke of a certain Aiarammu, who brought gifts from Edom. Esarhaddon (681–669 <span class="era">BC</span>) referred to Qaus-gabri, king of Edom, who came to Nineveh with 22 vassals to swear allegiance. Under Ashurbanipal (669–627 <span class="era">BC</span>), Edom appears on Assyrian records. Thereafter, Assyria itself was defeated by the Babylonians. Under Babylonian rule, Edom seemed to be a submissive vassal. However, in 594, it joined other small nations in discussing rebellion (<a href="?bref=Jer.27.1-22">Jer 27</a>). When Nebuchadnezzar attacked these, however, Moab and Edom were not involved. In the overthrow of Jerusalem in 586, Edom remained neutral and even allowed some refugees from Judah to shelter there for a time (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.11">40:11</a>). The prophet Obadiah punished Edom for not assisting Judah at the time of the Babylonian invasion (<a href="?bref=Obad.1.11">Ob 1:11</a>). Instead, they raided Judah, handed over captives to Babylon, and possessed lands in the Negev area to the south (<a href="?bref=Ezek.35.1-15">Ez 35</a>).</p>
<p>A long history of enmity existed between Judah and Edom, and several prophets spoke unfavorably about Edom (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.14">Is 11:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.5-17">34:5-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.32.29">Ez 32:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.3.19">Jl 3:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.1.11-12">Am 1:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.1.2-4">Mal 1:2-4</a>). In the sixth century <span class="era">BC</span>, Edom entered a period of decline. Several cities were abandoned. At the same time Edomite colonies west of the Arabah in the southern hill country of Judah emerged, and by Roman times there was a province of Idumea, which was the descendant of the Persian province of Edom, with its administrative center at Lachish. In the old Edomite homeland, Arab groups began to move in. Finally, ancient Edom became the home of the Nabateans.</p>
  </body>
</item>