<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Eleazar">
  <title>Eleazar</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ELEAZAR</p>
<p class="list">1. Third of Aaron’s four sons (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.23">Ex 6:23</a>). Eleazar (“God has helped”) was consecrated as a priest with his brothers and Aaron in the Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.1">Ex 28:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.2,13">Lv 8:2, 13</a>). When his brothers Nadab and Abihu were killed by God as they offered “unholy fire” to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.1-7">Lv 10:1-7</a>), Eleazar and Ithamar took leading positions as Aaron’s sons (<a href="?bref=Num.3.1-4">Nm 3:1-4</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Eleazar is described as “chief of the leaders of the Levites” (<a href="?bref=Num.3.32">Nm 3:32</a>). Under his supervision were the sanctuary and its vessels (<a href="?bref=Num.4.16">4:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.16.37-39">16:37-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.19.3-4">19:3-4</a>). Eleazar was installed as high priest by Moses when Aaron died on Mt Hor (<a href="?bref=Num.20.25-28">Nm 20:25-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.10.6">Dt 10:6</a>). He was then considered Moses’ assistant (<a href="?bref=Num.26.1-3,63">Nm 26:1-3, 63</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.27.2,21">27:2, 21</a>). Joshua was commissioned by Moses in the presence of Eleazar (<a href="?bref=Num.27.18-23">27:18-23</a>). In the conquest of Canaan, Joshua and Eleazar served together as leaders. It was Eleazar’s function as Joshua’s counselor to inquire of the Lord (v <a href="?bref=Num.27.21">21</a>). He also had his share in the census taking at Shittim. He took part in the partitioning of Canaan, the east bank (<a href="?bref=Num.34.17">34:17</a>), and the west bank (<a href="?bref=Josh.14.1">Jos 14:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.17.4">17:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.19.51">19:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.1">21:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">When Eleazar died, he was highly regarded and memorialized in the land of Ephraim (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.33">Jos 24:33</a>); his son Phinehas followed him as high priest.</p>
<p class="list-text">In the oversight of the priests, 16 divisions were assigned to Eleazar’s descendants and eight to Ithamar’s (<a href="?bref=1Chr.24.1-31">1 Chr 24</a>). The ancestry of the prominent priests Zadok and Ezra is traced to Eleazar (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.3-15,50-53">1 Chr 6:3-15, 50-53</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.24.3">24:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.1-5">Ezr 7:1-5</a>). In King Solomon’s time the priests of Zadok replaced Abiathar, a descendant of Ithamar (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.26-27,35">1 Kgs 2:26-27, 35</a>). The descendants of Eleazar would be the only ones permitted to minister in Ezekiel’s ideal temple (<a href="?bref=Ezek.44.15">Ez 44:15</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Aaron_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Aaron</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Abinadab’s son, charged with caring for the ark by the people of Kiriath-jearim, when it was brought from Beth-shemesh and placed in the “house of Abinadab on the hill” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.1">1 Sm 7:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Dodo’s son, one of the three mighty men whose exploits against the Philistines gained him great fame (<a href="?bref=2Sam.23.9">2 Sm 23:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.11.12">1 Chr 11:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Merarite Levite, son of Mahli. Eleazar died without sons, so his daughters were married to their first cousins (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.21-22">1 Chr 23:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.24.28">24:28</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Priest descended from Phinehas. This Eleazar helped inventory the temple treasure on returning from the exile with Ezra (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.33">Ezr 8:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. Parosh’s son, listed with others who divorced their foreign wives in the reform under Ezra (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.25">Ezr 10:25</a>).</p>
<p class="list">7. Priest in attendance at the dedication of the rebuilt walls of Jerusalem following the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.42">Neh 12:42</a>).</p>
<p class="list">8. Person in the lineage of Joseph, husband of Mary (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.15">Mt 1:15</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>