<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ElectElection">
  <title>Elect, Election</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ELECT, ELECTION</p>
<p class="fl">In modern English, terms referring to the selection of a leader or representative by a group of people. An element of choice is involved, since usually there are several candidates out of whom one must be chosen.</p>
<p>When the verb “elect” is used theologically in the Bible, it usually has God as its subject. In the OT it is used for God’s choice of Israel to be his people (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.13.17">Acts 13:17</a>). Israel became God’s people, not because they decided to belong to him, but because he took the initiative and chose them. Nor did God’s choice rest on any particular virtues that his people exemplified, but rather on his promise to their forefather Abraham (<a href="?bref=Deut.7.7-8">Dt 7:7-8</a>). God also chose their leaders, such as Saul and David (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.24">1 Sm 10:24</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.6.21">2 Sm 6:21</a>), apart from any popular vote by the people. The word indicates God’s authority in deciding what shall happen, independent of human choice.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="TheMysteryOfElection"/>
<p>The same thoughts are found in the NT. God’s people are described as his “elect” or “chosen ones,” a term used by Jesus when speaking of the future time when the Son of Man will come and gather together God’s people (<a href="?bref=Mark.13.20,27">Mk 13:20, 27</a>). He will vindicate them for their sufferings and for their patience in waiting for his coming (<a href="?bref=Luke.18.7">Lk 18:7</a>). In <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Peter 2:9</a>, God’s people are called a “chosen [elect] nation.” This phrase was originally used of the people of Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.20">Is 43:20</a>), and it brings out the fact that the people of God in the OT and the Christian church in the NT stand in continuity with each other. The promises made to Israel are now fulfilled in the church.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Rom.9.1-11.36">Romans 9–11</a> Paul discusses the problem of why the people of Israel as a nation have rejected the gospel, while the Gentiles have accepted it. He states that in the present time there is a “remnant” of Israel as a result of God’s gracious choice of them. This group is “the elect.” They are the chosen people who have obtained what was meant for Israel as a whole, while the greater mass of the people have failed to obtain it because they were “hardened” as a result of their sin (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.5-7">Rom 11:5-7</a>).</p>
<p>Nevertheless, God’s choice of Israel to be his people has not been canceled. Most Jewish people have aligned themselves against the gospel, so that the Gentiles may come in and receive God’s blessings in their place. However, they still are loved by God, and God will not go back on his original calling of them (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.28">Rom 11:28</a>). Consequently, Paul is confident that eventually, the people of Israel will return to God.</p>
<p>The word translated “elect” is generally found in the plural and refers either to the members of God’s people as a whole or to those in a particular local church (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.33">Rom 8:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.12">Col 3:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.4">1 Thes 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.10">2 Tm 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.1">Ti 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.1-2">1 Pt 1:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.1.10">2 Pt 1:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.14">Rv 17:14</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.16.13">Rom 16:13</a> and <a href="?bref=2Jn.1.13">2 Jn 1:13</a>, which have the singular form). The use of the plural may partly be explained by the fact that most of the NT letters are addressed to groups of people rather than to individuals. More probably, however, the point is that God’s election is concerned with the creation of a collective people rather than the calling of isolated individuals.</p>
<p>The word “election” emphasizes that membership of God’s people is due to God’s initiative, prior to all human response, made before time began (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.4">Eph 1:4</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=John.15.16,19">Jn 15:16, 19</a>). It is God who has called men and women to be his people, and those who respond are elect. God’s call does not depend on any virtues or merits of humankind. Indeed, he chooses the foolish things by worldly standards to shame the wise, the weak to confound the strong, and the lowly and insignificant to bring to nothing those who think that they are something (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.27-28">1 Cor 1:27-28</a>). The effect of election is to leave no reason whatever for humans to boast about their achievements and position. Whatever the elect are, they owe it entirely to God, and they cannot boast or compare themselves with other people.</p>
<p>God’s elect are a privileged people. Since they now have God to uphold them, no one can bring any accusation against them that might lead to God’s condemnation (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.33">Rom 8:33</a>). They constitute a royal priesthood; they are God’s servants with the right of access to him (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Pt 2:9</a>). It is for their sake that the apostles endured hardship and suffering, so that they might enjoy future salvation and eternal glory (<a href="?bref=2Tim.2.10">2 Tm 2:10</a>).</p>
<p>The elect are distinguished by their faith in God (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.1">Ti 1:1</a>), and they are called to show the character that God’s people should have (<a href="?bref=Col.3.12">Col 3:12</a>). They must make their calling and election sure; that is, they must show that they belong to God by the quality of their lives (<a href="?bref=2Pet.1.10">2 Pt 1:10</a>). They must continue being faithful to the One who called them (<a href="?bref=Rev.17.14">Rv 17:14</a>).</p>
<p>The relationship between God’s call and human response is explained in <a href="?bref=Matt.22.14">Matthew 22:14</a>: “For many are called, but few are chosen.” Although God calls many through the gospel, only some of those respond to the call and become his elect people. The text does not explain the mystery of why only some become God’s people. Certainly, when a person does respond to God’s call, it is because the gospel comes to him or her “in power and in the Holy Spirit and with full conviction” (<a href="?bref=1Thes.1.4-5">1 Thes 1:4-5</a>). When men and women refuse the gospel, it is because they have become hardened as a result of sin and their trust in their own works. Scripture does not go beyond that point in explanation, and neither should Christians.</p>
<p>“Election” can also be used of God’s choice of people to serve him. Jesus chose the 12 disciples out of the larger company of those who followed him (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.13">Lk 6:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.2">Acts 1:2</a>). The same thought reappears in John’s Gospel; Jesus commented that although he chose the Twelve, one of them turned out to be a devil (<a href="?bref=John.6.70">Jn 6:70</a>; <a href="?bref=John.13.18">13:18</a>). When a replacement was needed for Judas, the church prayed to Jesus and asked him to show them which of the two available candidates he would choose to fill the gap in the Twelve (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.24">Acts 1:24</a>). Peter attributes his evangelism among the Gentiles to God’s election of him for that purpose (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.7">15:7</a>). Similarly, Paul was an elected instrument for God’s mission to the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.15">9:15</a>). The initiative in Christian mission rests with God, who elects people to serve him in particular ways.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Foreknowledge_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Foreknowledge</a>; <a href="?item=Foreordination_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Foreordination</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>