<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ExaltationofChrist">
  <title>Exaltation of Christ*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EXALTATION OF CHRIST*</p>
<p class="fl">The glory and authority that Jesus attained after finishing his earthly work of suffering and death. It is both the completion of his redemptive sacrifice and the reward for fully obeying the Father's will. The exaltation includes Jesus' resurrection, ascension, and enthronement in heaven, as taught in the Bible.</p>
<p>During his earthly ministry, Jesus predicted not only that he would suffer, die, and be buried (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.28">Mt 20:28</a>; <a href="?bref=John.3.14">Jn 3:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.51">6:51</a>; <a href="?bref=John.10.11">10:11</a>; etc.) but also that he would thereafter be exalted by the power of the Father to heavenly dominion and glory (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.26">Lk 24:26</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.5">Jn 17:5</a>). This humiliation-exaltation pattern was plainly indicated by Jesus on the occasion of his encounter with a delegation of proselytes who sought to meet with the Lord (<a href="?bref=John.12.20-36">Jn 12:20-36</a>). Jesus far exceeded the expectations of these Greeks by declaring that fellowship with his Father would be extended to the Gentiles in consequence of his imminent passion and resurrection. By affirming, “The hour has come for the Son of man to be glorified” (<a href="?bref=John.12.23">Jn 12:23</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), Jesus indicated that he would receive honor and splendor at his exaltation to the presence of the Father in heaven. Jesus’ teaching in respect to his exaltation to heaven provided the foundation for the church’s more explicit teaching on the subject.</p>
<p>The resurrection, the initial event in the exaltation of Jesus, is one of the central affirmations of NT teaching (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.24,32">Acts 2:24, 32</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.3.15">3:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.10">4:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.4">Rom 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.4">1 Cor 15:4</a>). From apostolic times Christians have consistently affirmed that at a particular moment in time and in a given place its founder literally passed from a state of death to a state of endless life. The absolute uniqueness of Christ’s exaltation via bodily resurrection from the dead sets Christianity in a class by itself among the religions of the world. A reading of the NT plainly indicates that Jesus openly predicted that death was unable to defeat him. To the skeptical Jews who demanded from Jesus a sign of the authority by which he purged the temple, the Lord answered: “Destroy this temple, and in three days I will raise it up” (<a href="?bref=John.2.19">Jn 2:19</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). After Peter’s crucial confession of Christ’s divine sonship at Caesarea Philippi, Jesus gave to his followers a more detailed account of the divine plan whereby he would be raised from the dead on the third day (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.21">Mt 16:21</a>). To the disciples who assembled in Galilee shortly after his transfiguration, Jesus spoke plainly of his forthcoming exaltation: “The Son of man is to be delivered into the hands of men, and they will kill him, and he will be raised on the third day” (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.22-23">17:22-23</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). In the NT, the apostolic teaching about Christ’s death is almost always accompanied by an emphasis upon the certainty of his physical resurrection after three days.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the NT writers were careful to spell out the profound theological significance of Christ’s exaltation in resurrection: (1) it demonstrates Christ’s certain power over death and the grave (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.24">Acts 2:24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.54-56">1 Cor 15:54-56</a>); (2) it confirms the validity of Christ’s teachings, particularly his claims to divine Sonship (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.36">Acts 2:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.4">Rom 1:4</a>); (3) it represents God’s ultimate vindication of his obedient, suffering servant (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.8-9">Phil 2:8-9</a>); (4) it is the means of the justification (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.25">Rom 4:25</a>) and regeneration (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.3">1 Pt 1:3</a>) of the believer; and (5) it is the guarantee of the future resurrection of the Christian (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.5">Rom 6:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.22-24">1 Cor 15:22-24</a>). The effective cause of Christ’s resurrection is declared to be, on one hand, God (<a href="?bref=Ps.16.10">Ps 16:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.32">Acts 2:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.19-20">Eph 1:19-20</a>) and, on the other hand, our Lord himself (<a href="?bref=John.2.19">Jn 2:19</a>; <a href="?bref=John.10.17-18">10:17-18</a>).</p>
<p>The ascension represents the second phase of the exaltation of Christ. According to the two NT historical accounts (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.50-51">Lk 24:50-51</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.9-11">Acts 1:9-11</a>), 40 days after his death Jesus left his disciples for the last time and ascended into heaven. Jesus, who several times in John’s Gospel specifically refers to his ascension (<a href="?bref=John.3.13">Jn 3:13</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.62">6:62</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.12">14:12</a>; <a href="?bref=John.20.17">20:17</a>), regarded the place to which he would depart as an actual locality in the heavenly realm (<a href="?bref=John.14.2">14:2</a>). In his reflection upon this second stage of the exaltation suggested in <a href="?bref=Ps.68.18">Psalm 68:18</a>, the apostle Paul associates the ascension with Christ’s triumph over his foes and the giving of spiritual gifts to the church (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.8">Eph 4:8</a>). The victor triumphantly returned to his Father’s throne in order to bless his people. In what may be part of an early Christian hymn, Paul explains what he regards as the supreme “mystery” of the Christian faith, namely, that Christ Jesus who “was manifested in the flesh” was at the close of his life “taken up into glory” (<a href="?bref=1Tim.3.16">1 Tm 3:16</a>).</p>
<p>Alone among the writings of the NT, the Epistle to the Hebrews associates Christ’s ascension with his high priestly ministry in the heavenly sanctuary. He who steadfastly withstood every earthly trial, having “passed through the heavens,” is fully able to empathize with his people and impart grace to the tempted and distraught (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.14-16">Heb 4:14ff</a>.). Employing the symbolism of the ancient Hebrew sanctuary, the writer conceptualizes the Ascension as the event whereby Christ enters into the inner shrine behind the curtain (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.19">6:19</a>), bringing with him his own blood (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.12">9:12</a>), to the end that he might appear in the presence of God on our behalf (v <a href="?bref=Heb.9.24">24</a>).</p>
<p>The NT thus attributes considerable theological significance to this phase of Christ’s exaltation. By virtue of his exaltation to the Father, Christ (1) demonstrated his defeat of every earthly enemy (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.8">Eph 4:8</a>); (2) sent the promised Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=John.16.7">Jn 16:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.33">Acts 2:33</a>), which awaited his glorification (<a href="?bref=John.7.39">Jn 7:39</a>); and (3) formally undertook his heavenly priestly ministry (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.20">Heb 6:20</a>).</p>
<p>The third stage of Christ’s exaltation is his heavenly enthronement at the right hand of the Father. Following his passion, death, resurrection, and ascension to the heavenly realm, Christ is represented in Scripture as having taken his seat at the Father’s right hand. The biblical phrase “right hand of God” (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.55-56">Acts 7:55-56</a>), which has been preserved in many later Christian creeds and confessions, is an anthropomorphism that figuratively describes Christ’s universal dominion, authority, and power in the presence of the Father. This aspect of Christ’s exaltation represents the fulfillment of his prayer recorded in <a href="?bref=John.17.5">John 17:5</a>: “Now, Father, glorify me in your own presence with the glory I had with you before the world was made.”</p>
<p>In the OT the description of God seated on the throne of the universe is a sign of his sovereignty (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.19">1 Kgs 22:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.99.1">Ps 99:1</a>), majesty (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-4">Is 6:1-4</a>) and holiness (<a href="?bref=Ps.47.8">Ps 47:8</a>). That one should be invited to take a seat on the right hand of the sovereign in Eastern cultures was a token of extraordinary honor and authority (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.19">1 Kgs 2:19</a>). The fact that the exalted Christ would be accorded this particular privilege was anticipated in the Scriptures of the OT (see <a href="?bref=Ps.8.5">Ps 8:5</a>, quoted in <a href="?bref=Heb.2.8">Heb 2:8</a>; and see <a href="?bref=Ps.110.1">Ps 110:1</a>).</p>
<p>The Epistle to the Hebrews, which shows unusual interest in the doctrine of Christ’s exaltation, represents Christ’s heavenly enthronement both as the sequel to his completed earthly sacrifice and as the commencement of his ministry as High Priest in the sanctuary on high. Affirming the superiority of Christ as High Priest of the new covenant, <a href="?bref=Heb.8.1-2">Hebrews 8:1-2</a> portrays Christ as seated at the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in heaven, a minister in the heavenlies. Christ’s enthronement affirms not only the finality of his earthly work of self-sacrifice but also his newly acquired status as mediator of the new and better covenant. <a href="?bref=Heb.10.11-18">Hebrews 10:11-18</a> highlights the difference between the ineffective sacrifices of the legal priests who <span class="ital">stand</span> in the performance of their ritual sacrifices and the effective single sacrifice of Christ, who is now <span class="ital">seated</span> at the right hand of God as intercessor for the saints.</p>
  </body>
</item>