<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Abimelech">
  <title>Abimelech</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ABIMELECH</p>
<p class="fl">Royal title for Philistine rulers, similar to the designation “pharaoh” among the Egyptians and “agag” among the Amalekites.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. King of Gerar in Abraham’s time. At Gerar, a city a few miles south of Gaza, Abraham presented his wife as his sister out of fear for his life (<a href="?bref=Gen.20.1-18">Gn 20:1-18</a>), as he had once done in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.10-20">Gn 12:10-20</a>). Because of this, Sarah was taken into Abimelech’s harem. But Abimelech was warned by God in a dream not to come near her on pain of death because she was a married woman, so she was restored to her husband. The same Abimelech and Abraham later entered into a treaty to clarify water rights in the Negev Desert at Beersheba (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.22-34">Gn 21:22-34</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. King of Gerar in Isaac’s time. Isaac, too, passed off his wife, Rebekah, as his sister at Gerar. Abimelech, perhaps remembering the near judgment on his predecessor, acted decisively to protect Rebekah’s integrity. He proclaimed a death penalty on any who touched her or her husband (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.1-11">Gn 26:1-11</a>). Abimelech asked Isaac to leave Philistine territory because of overcrowding and continuing dispute over water (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.12-22">Gn 26:12-22</a>). Eventually, at Beersheba, Isaac and Abimelech ended their hostility by renewing the treaty made by Abraham and the earlier Abimelech (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.26-33">Gn 26:26-33</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Gideon’s son by a concubine in Shechem (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.31">Jgs 8:31</a>). After his father’s death, Abimelech conspired with his mother’s family to assassinate his 70 half brothers. Only one of them, Jotham, escaped (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.1-5">Jgs 9:1-5</a>). In Abimelech’s third year of rule, he cruelly suppressed a rebellion (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.22-49">Jgs 9:22-49</a>). Eventually his skull was crushed by a millstone thrown down by a woman on a tower. Abimelech ordered his armor bearer to kill him with a sword so that no one could say he had been killed by a woman (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.53-57">Jgs 9:53-57</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Achish, king of the Philistine city of Gath (<a href="?bref=1Sam.21.10-15">1 Sm 21:10-15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Abiathar’s son, a priest associated with Zadok in David’s time (<a href="?bref=1Chr.18.16">1 Chr 18:16</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>