<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AdamPerson">
  <title>Adam (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ADAM (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">First man and father of the human race. Adam’s role in biblical history is important not only in OT considerations but also in understanding the meaning of salvation and the person and work of Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>The creation of Adam and the first woman, Eve, is recited in two accounts in the book of Genesis. The intent of the first account (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.26-31">1:26-31</a>) is to present the first pair in their relationship to God and to the rest of the created order. It teaches that with regard to God the first humans were created male and female in God’s image with his specific mandate to populate and rule over the earth. With regard to the rest of creation the first humans were, on one hand, part of it, being created on the same day as other land animals; on the other hand, they were distinctly above it, being the culmination of the creation process and sole bearers of God’s image.</p>
<p>The intent of the second account is much more specific (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.4-3.24">2:4–3:24</a>); it seeks to explain the origin of the present human condition of sin and death and to set the stage for the drama of redemption. The story treats in detail aspects of Adam’s creation omitted from the first story. For example, it tells of the formation of Adam from the dust of the ground and of his receiving the breath of life from God (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.7">2:7</a>). It recounts the planting of the Garden and the responsibility given to Adam to cultivate it (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.8-15">2:8-15</a>). God’s instruction to Adam that the fruit of every tree in the Garden was his for food, except one, is carefully recorded, as well as the solemn warning that the fruit of the “tree of the knowledge of good and evil” was never to be eaten, under the pain of death (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.16-17">2:16-17</a>). Adam’s loneliness after naming the animals and not finding a suitable companion is also described, thus introducing the creation of the first woman (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.18-22">2:18-22</a>). The creation of Eve from Adam’s rib poignantly portrays the essential unity of spirit and purpose of the sexes intended by God.</p>
<p>The story does not end on such a positive note, however. It moves on to record the great deception Satan played upon Eve through the serpent. By clever insinuations and distortion of God’s original commandment (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.3.1">3:1</a> with <a href="?bref=Gen.2.16-17">2:16-17</a>), the serpent tricked Eve into eating the forbidden fruit and sharing it with Adam. Eve seems to have eaten because she was deceived (<a href="?bref=1Tim.2.14">1 Tm 2:14</a>), Adam out of a willful and conscious rebellion. Ironically, the two beings originally created in God’s image and likeness believed that they could become “like” God by disobeying him (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.5">Gn 3:5</a>).</p>
<p>The effects of their disobedience were immediate, though not at all what Adam had expected. For the first time a barrier of shame disrupted the unity of man and woman (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.7">3:7</a>). More important, a barrier of real moral guilt was erected between the first couple and God. The story relates that when God came looking for Adam after his rebellion, he was hiding among the trees, already aware of his separation from God (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.8">3:8</a>). When God questioned him, Adam threw the blame on Eve and, by implication, back on God: “It was the woman you gave me who brought me the fruit” (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.12">3:12</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Eve in turn blamed the serpent (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.13">3:13</a>).</p>
<p>According to the story in Genesis, God held all three responsible and informed each one of the calamitous consequences of their rebellion (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.14-19">3:14-19</a>). The two great mandates, originally signs of pure blessing, became mixed with curse and pain—the earth could now be populated only through the woman’s birth pangs and could be subdued only by the man’s labor and perspiration (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.16-18">3:16-18</a>). Further, the unity of man and woman would be strained by man’s subjugation of her, or possibly by the beginning of a struggle for dominance between them (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.16">3:16b</a> can be taken both ways). Finally, God pronounced the ultimate consequence: as he had originally warned, Adam and Eve were to die. Someday the breath of life would be taken from them, and their bodies would return to the dust from which they were made (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.19">3:19</a>). That very day they also experienced a “spiritual” death; they were separated from God, the giver of life, and from the tree of life, the symbol of eternal life (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.22">3:22</a>). God sent them out of Eden, and there was no way back. The entrance to paradise was blocked by the cherubim and flaming sword (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.23-24">3:23-24</a>). Only God could restore what they had lost.</p>
<p>The story is not devoid of hope. God was merciful even then. He made them garments of skin to cover their bodies and promised that someday the power of Satan behind the serpent would be crushed by the woman’s “seed” (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Gn 3:15</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.16.20">Rom 16:20</a>). Many scholars consider that promise to be the first biblical mention of redemption.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheSignificanceofAdam">The Significance of Adam</p>
<p class="fl">Adam’s significance is based upon several assumptions, the first being that he was a historical individual. That assumption was made by many OT writers (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.25">Gn 4:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.5.1-5">5:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.1">1 Chr 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.6.7">Hos 6:7</a>). The NT writers agreed (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.38">Lk 3:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.14">Rom 5:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.22,45">1 Cor 15:22, 45</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.2.13-14">1 Tm 2:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jude.1.14">Jude 1:14</a>). Equally essential to Adam’s significance is a second assumption, that he was more than an individual. To begin with, the Hebrew word <span class="hebrew">adam</span> (more correctly <span class="hebrew">’a–dha–m</span>) is not merely a proper name. Even in the Genesis story it is not used as a name until <a href="?bref=Gen.4.25">Genesis 4:25</a>. The word is one of several Hebrew words meaning “man” and is the generic term for “human race.” In the vast majority of cases it refers either to a male individual (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.2">Lv 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.14.15">Jos 14:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.29">Neh 9:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.56.2">Is 56:2</a>) or to humanity in general (<a href="?bref=Exod.4.11">Ex 4:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.12.3">Nm 12:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.16.29">16:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.28">Dt 4:28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.31">1 Kgs 4:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.7.20">Jb 7:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.14.1">14:1</a>). The generic, collective sense of the word <span class="hebrew">adam</span> is also behind the phrase “children (or sons) of men” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.14">2 Sm 7:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.11.4">Pss 11:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.12.1">12:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.14.2">14:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.53.2">53:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.90.3">90:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.1.13">Eccl 1:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.2.3">2:3</a>). That phrase, literally “sons of <span class="hebrew">adam</span><span class="ital">,”</span> simply means “men” or “human beings,” and when it is used the entire human race is in view. Indeed, the universalistic human connotation of the word <span class="hebrew">adam</span> indicates a concern in the OT going far beyond Israel’s nationalistic hopes and its God—to all the earth’s people and the Lord of all nations (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.5-7">Gn 9:5-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.24">Dt 5:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.8.3">8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.38-39">1 Kgs 8:38-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.8.4">Pss 8:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.48">89:48</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.107.8-31">107:8-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.12.14">Prv 12:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.8">Mi 6:8</a>).</p>
<p>It is no accident, then, that the first man was named “Adam” or “Man.” The name intimates that to speak about Adam is somehow also to speak about the entire human race. Such usage can perhaps best be understood through the ancient concept of corporate personality and representation familiar to the Hebrews and other Near Eastern peoples. Modern thinking emphasizes the individual; existence of the social group and all social relationships has been seen as secondary to, and dependent upon, the existence and desire of the individual. The Hebrew understanding was quite different. Though the separate personality of the individual was appreciated (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.29-30">Jer 31:29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.18.4">Ez 18:4</a>), there was a strong tendency to see the social group (family, tribe, nation) as a single organism with a corporate identity of its own. Likewise the group representative was seen as the embodiment or personification of the corporate personality of the group. Within the representative the essential qualities and characteristics of the social group resided in such a way that the actions and decisions of the representative were binding on the entire group. If the group was a family, the father was usually considered the corporate representative; for good or for ill his family, and sometimes his descendants, received the results of his actions (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.1-8">Gn 17:1-8</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.20.1-9,18">Gn 20:1-9, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.20.5-6">Ex 20:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.7.24-25">Jos 7:24-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.11.28">Rom 11:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.1-10">Heb 7:1-10</a>).</p>
<p>As the original man and father of humankind, in whose image all succeeding generations would be born (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.3">Gn 5:3</a>), Adam was the corporate representative of humanity. The creation accounts themselves give the impression that the mandates of <a href="?bref=Gen.1.26-30">Genesis 1:26-30</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.9.1,7">Gn 9:1, 7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.8.5-7">Pss 8:5-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.104.14">104:14</a>) as well as the curses of <a href="?bref=Gen.3.16-19">Genesis 3:16-19</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.90.3">Ps 90:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.12.7">Eccl 12:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.13.8">Is 13:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.21.3">21:3</a>) were meant not only for Adam (and Eve) but, through him, for the entire race.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Rom.5.12-21">Romans 5:12-21</a> the apostle Paul contrasted the death and condemnation brought upon humanity by Adam’s disobedience with the life and justification given to humanity through Christ’s obedience. More explicitly, in <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45-50">1 Corinthians 15:45-50</a> (<span class="sc">rsv</span>), Paul called Christ the “last Adam,” “second man,” and the “man of heaven” in juxtaposition to the “first Adam,” the “first man,” and the “man of dust.”</p>
<p>For Paul, the human race was divided into two groups in the persons of Adam and Christ. Those who remain “incorporated” in Adam are the “old” humanity, bearing the image of the “man of dust” and partaking of his sin and alienation from God and Creation (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.12-19">Rom 5:12-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.8.20-22">8:20-22</a>). But those who are incorporated into Christ by faith become Christ’s “body” (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.4-5">Rom 12:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.12-13,27">1 Cor 12:12-13, 27</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.22-23">Eph 1:22-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.18">Col 1:18</a>); they are recreated in Christ’s image (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.29">Rom 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.49">1 Cor 15:49</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.18">2 Cor 3:18</a>); they become one “new man” (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.15">Eph 2:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.24">4:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.9-10">Col 3:9-10</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>); and they partake of the new creation (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.17">2 Cor 5:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.6.15">Gal 6:15</a>). The old barriers raised by Adam are removed by Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.1">Rom 5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.19">2 Cor 5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.27-28">Gal 3:27-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.2.14-16">Eph 2:14-16</a>). For Paul, the functional similarity of Adam and Christ as representatives meant that Christ had restored what Adam had lost.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Eve_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eve</a>; <a href="?item=ManOldandNew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Man, Old and New</a>; <a href="?item=NewCreationNewCreature_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New Creation, New Creature</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>