<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ahaz">
  <title>Ahaz</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AHAZ</p>
<p class="list">1. King of Judah (735–715 <span class="era">BC</span>) who was especially remembered for his apostasy. The name Ahaz (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.9">Mt 1:9</a>) is a shortened form of Ahaziah or Jehoahaz. The three main accounts of Ahaz (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.1-20">2 Kgs 16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.28.1-27">2 Chr 28</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.7.1-25">Is 7</a>) treat him as one of the most evil rulers of the southern kingdom of Judah. Consequently, his burial was relatively dishonorable (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.27">2 Chr 28:27</a>). He was succeeded by his son Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.1">2 Kgs 18:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">There is little agreement on the chronology of this section of the OT. The chronological system that seems to have the fewest problems would place Ahaz’s accession in 735 <span class="era">BC</span>. If he first came to the throne as co-regent with his father, Jotham, from 735 to 732 <span class="era">BC</span>, his entire reign covered a span of approximately 20 years, ending in 715 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="list-text">Ahaz reigned over Judah during a critical time in the history of the ancient Near East. The Assyrians were pushing westward, threatening the Syro-Palestinian area. Pekah, king of Israel, and Rezin, king of Syria, adopted a policy of resistance against the Assyrians and invaded Judah in order to effect a solid coalition by deposing Ahaz.</p>
<p class="list-text">Blatantly revealing a lack of trust in God, Ahaz appealed to Tiglath-pileser III, the Assyrian king, for help. That appeal brought the wrath of the prophet Isaiah upon Ahaz. The ensuing encounter (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.1-25">Is 7</a>) led to Isaiah’s prediction of the birth of Immanuel as a sign of the dissolution of the countries of Israel and Syria. Those two kingdoms were ultimately destroyed by Tiglath-pileser in a campaign that lasted about two years (734–732 <span class="era">BC</span>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="AhazSLackOfFaith"/>
<p class="list-text">Before the two kingdoms to the north were conquered by Assyria, their invasion of Judah caused great turmoil (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.8">2 Chr 28:8</a>). The invaders not only carried off much spoil but also attempted to depopulate portions of Judah by taking 200,000 people captive to Samaria. That attempt was protested by a prophet in Samaria named Obed, who condemned the act of slavery and ordered the captives returned (v <a href="?bref=2Chr.28.9">9</a>). He was joined by several leaders of Israel (v <a href="?bref=2Chr.28.12">12</a>), who succeeded in having the captives returned to Jericho with provisions from the spoil that had been taken.</p>
<p class="list-text">During that time, the kingdom of Judah may have been threatened from the south as well. The Edomites, who had long been under the domination of Judah, may have taken advantage of Judah’s growing internal weakness to assert their independence. The Masoretic Text of the OT refers to an invasion of the seaport town of Elath on the Red Sea by Aram, the Hebrew name for Syria (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.6">2 Kgs 16:6</a>). The name Aram is quite similar to the name Edom in Hebrew, however, so many scholars think that invasion was actually by Edomites.</p>
<p class="list-text">By virtue of the alliance he had made, Ahaz placed his country in a dangerous position of dependence on Assyria. The kingdom of Judah became essentially a vassal state under the tacit control of Tiglath-pileser. Ahaz went to Damascus, the capital of fallen Syria, to appear before Tiglath-pileser, possibly to assure his allegiance to the king to whom his nation had become tributary (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.10">2 Kgs 16:10</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">While in Damascus, Ahaz saw an Assyrian altar, a model of which he sent back to Judah. Under the direction of Uriah the priest, a similar altar was built in Jerusalem, replacing the original bronze altar. Several other alterations were made in the temple by Ahaz, all indicating his turning away from Jewish religion.</p>
<p class="list-text">The “dial of Ahaz” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.11">2 Kgs 20:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.38.8">Is 38:8</a>) later figured in a sign given to his son Hezekiah; the Hebrew word actually refers to a flight of stairs, no doubt built by Ahaz and used to tell time by the movement of a shadow across it.</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=King_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">King</a>; <a href="?item=KingsBooksofFirstandSecond_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Kings, Books of First and Second</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=Sundial_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sundial</a>; <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Micah’s son and Jehoaddah’s father, a descendant of Saul, otherwise unknown (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.35-36">1 Chr 8:35-36</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>