<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Aijalon">
  <title>Aijalon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AIJALON</p>
<p class="list">1. City located in a valley 15 miles (24 kilometers) northwest of Jerusalem (at modern Yalo) and originally allotted to Dan’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.42">Jos 19:42</a>). Aijalon was designated as one of four levitical cities in Dan’s area (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.24">Jos 21:24</a>) and was later made a city of refuge by Ephraim’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.69">1 Chr 6:69</a>). Dan’s tribe had by then migrated north, having been unable to occupy its southerly allotment, including Aijalon (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.34-36">Jgs 1:34-36</a>). Near Aijalon, Saul and Jonathan won a victory over the Philistines (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.31">1 Sm 14:31</a>). Members of Benjamin’s tribe occupied it at one time (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.13">1 Chr 8:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">When the kingdom was divided after Solomon’s death, Aijalon, on the northwest border of the southern kingdom, was fortified by King Rehoboam (<a href="?bref=2Chr.11.10">2 Chr 11:10</a>). It was one of 65 cities claimed to have been conquered by the Egyptian pharaoh Shishak, who invaded Palestine around 924 <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=2Chr.12.2-12">2 Chr 12:2-12</a>). Much later, Aijalon was lost to the Philistines during the reign of Ahaz (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.18">2 Chr 28:18</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The valley of Aijalon was part of the geographical setting of Joshua’s battle to control Gibeon (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.12">Jos 10:12</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). To make the Israelite victory complete, God answered Joshua’s prayer to “let the sun stand still over Gibeon, and the moon over the valley of Aijalon” (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.12">Jos 10:12</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CitiesofRefuge_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cities of Refuge</a>; <a href="?item=LeviticalCities_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Levitical Cities</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. City in the territory of Zebulun, burial place of the judge Elon (<a href="?bref=Judg.12.12">Jgs 12:12</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>