<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AmalekAmalekites">
  <title>Amalek, Amalekites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AMALEK, AMALEKITES</p>
<p class="fl">Amalek was the son of Eliphaz (Esau’s son) by his concubine, Timna (<a href="?bref=Gen.36.12">Gn 36:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.36">1 Chr 1:36</a>). Descendants of this tribal chief of Edom were known as Amalekites. They settled in the Negev Desert and became allies of the Edomites, Ammonites, Moabites, Ishmaelites, and Midianites. The Amalekites were notable enemies of Israel. Amalek inherited the fraternal feud that had begun with his grandfather Esau’s antagonism toward Jacob. Since Jacob was one of the progenitors of Israel, the conflict between Amalek and Israel had both a theological and political basis.</p>
<p>The territory of the nomadic Amalekites in the Negev ranged at times from south of Beersheba to the southeast as far as Elath and Ezion-geber. They undoubtedly raided westward into the coastal plain, eastward into the Arabah wastelands, and possibly over into Arabia. In the Negev they blocked the path of the Israelites during the exodus (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.8-16">Ex 17:8-16</a>).</p>
<p>Israel’s first encounter with the warriors of Amalek came at Rephidim near Sinai. Moses stood on top of a hill and held up the rod of God until Israel won the battle, then built an altar and named it “The Lord Is My Banner” (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.1,8-16">Ex 17:1, 8-16</a>). The Amalekites attacked stragglers during Israel’s desert wanderings (<a href="?bref=Deut.25.17-18">Dt 25:17-18</a>). After reaching the boundary of the Promised Land but rejecting Caleb and Joshua’s report of it, the unbelieving and disheartened Israelites attacked the Amalekites and were defeated (<a href="?bref=Num.14.39-45">Nm 14:39-45</a>).</p>
<p>When Balaam was summoned by King Balak of Moab to curse Israel, he turned his curse upon Moab and in his last oracle predicted the end of Amalek’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Num.24.20">Nm 24:20</a>). Moses, in his farewell speech, reminded the children of Israel that they had been harassed by Amalek’s descendants and should blot out all remembrance of the name Amalek (<a href="?bref=Deut.25.17-19">Dt 25:17-19</a>).</p>
<p>During the period of the judges Amalekites continued to occupy their traditional area and became associated with the Kenites (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.5-6">1 Sm 15:5-6</a>), descendants of Moses’ father-in-law, who settled in the Negev south of Arad (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.16">Jgs 1:16</a>). The Amalekites, still associated with other nomadic tribes (Moabites, Ammonites, Midianites), were rallied by Eglon, king of Moab, to defeat Israel and seize Jericho (<a href="?bref=Judg.3.12-14">Jgs 3:12-14</a>). The Song of Deborah cites Amalek as one of a coalition of tribes against Israel (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.14">Jgs 5:14</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). The name is omitted in a number of modern translations, and in others translated as “into the valley” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). However, Amalekite harassment is referred to in other passages of the time of Deborah and Barak (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.3,33">Jgs 6:3, 33</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.7.12">7:12</a>). Gideon defeated the coalition (<a href="?bref=Judg.7.12-25">Jgs 7:12-25</a>), but there is no evidence that the Amalekites were driven out of the Negev.</p>
<p>According to 1 Samuel, Saul sent his armies out against the Amalekites (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.47-48">14:47-48</a>) and received a command from God to destroy them and all their possessions (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.1-3">15:1-3</a>). He did attack their city (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.4-7">15:4-7</a>) but did not kill their king, Agag (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.8">15:8</a>). Saul distributed the choicest Amalekite livestock to his men (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.9">15:9</a>), for which the Lord condemned him and sent Samuel to tell him that his kingship was ended because of his sin (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.10-31">15:10-31</a>). Samuel then slaughtered Agag (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.32-35">15:32-35</a>). A remnant of Amalekites must have escaped, since they appeared again as David’s foes while he was still a young warrior (<a href="?bref=1Sam.27.8">27:8</a>). He rescued his two wives carried off by Amalekites and killed most of the raiding party (<a href="?bref=1Sam.30.1-20">30:1-20</a>). The Amalekites were Israel’s sworn enemies throughout King David’s reign (<a href="?bref=2Sam.1.1">2 Sm 1:1</a>). They are listed among the enemies of Israel (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.12">2 Sm 8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.11">1 Chr 18:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.83.7">Ps 83:7</a>). Destruction of the few surviving Amalekites came several hundred years after David during the reign of Hezekiah of the southern kingdom of Judah (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.41-43">1 Chr 4:41-43</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>