<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Amariah">
  <title>Amariah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AMARIAH</p>
<p class="fl">Common OT name, meaning “the Lord has spoken” or “the Lord has promised.”</p>
<p class="list-space"> 1. Son of Meraioth in the line of Aaron’s son Eleazer (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.7,52">1 Chr 6:7, 52</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 2. High priest, Azariah’s son and Ahitub’s father (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.11">1 Chr 6:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.3">Ezr 7:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Hebron’s second son and Kohath’s grandson from Levi’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.19">1 Chr 23:19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.24.23">24:23</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Chief priest during the reign of Jehoshaphat of the southern kingdom of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.19.11">2 Chr 19:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Levite who served faithfully under King Hezekiah of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.14-15">2 Chr 31:14-15</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. One of Binnui’s sons, who obeyed Ezra’s exhortation to divorce his pagan wife after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.42">Ezr 10:42</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Priest who returned from Babylon with Zerubbabel (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.2,13">Neh 12:2, 13</a>) and who, with Nehemiah and others, signed Ezra’s covenant of faithfulness to God after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.3">Neh 10:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Shephatiah’s son, a descendant of Judah and ancestor of Athaiah. Amariah lived in Jerusalem after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.4">Neh 11:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Hezekiah’s son and ancestor of the prophet Zephaniah (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.1">Zep 1:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Person mentioned in the Ezra genealogies of <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Esd.8.2">1 Esdras 8:2</a> and <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Esd.1.2">2 Esdras 1:2</a>. In the first list he is Uzzi’s son and Ahitub’s father. In the second he is Azariah’s son and Eli’s father. He may be the same as Amariah #1 or #2 above, since both sources list him as Ahitub’s father.</p>
  </body>
</item>