<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Amorites">
  <title>Amorites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AMORITES</p>
<p class="fl">Semitic people found throughout the Fertile Crescent of the Near East at the beginning of the second millennium <span class="era">BC</span>. Amorites are first mentioned in the Bible as descendants of Canaan in a list of ancient peoples (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.16">Gn 10:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.13-16">1 Chr 1:13-16</a>). Some of these nomadic people seem to have migrated from the Syrian Desert into Mesopotamia, others into Palestine.</p>
<p>Akkadian cuneiform inscriptions mention a relatively uncivilized people called <span class="ital">Amurru</span> (translation of the Sumerian <span class="ital">Mar-tu</span>), perhaps named for a storm god. They overran the Sumerians and eventually most of Mesopotamia. The city of Mari, on the upper Euphrates River, fell to them about 2000 <span class="era">BC</span>; Eshunna a short time later; Babylon by 1830 <span class="era">BC</span>; and finally Assur around 1750 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>Farther to the west, Amorites had been in Palestine and Syria as early as the third millennium <span class="era">BC</span>. Egyptian texts of the early part of the 19th century <span class="era">BC</span> show that additional waves of Amorite nomads were entering Canaan at that time. Many of their names are similar to the Amorite names from upper Mesopotamia. In fact, many names from the Mari tablets are identical with or similar to names in the patriarchal accounts in Genesis. People named Jacob, Abraham, Levi, and Ishmael were known at Mari, and names similar to Gad and Dan have been found there. Benjamin was known as the name of a tribe. Nahor was found to be the name of a city near Haran. According to Genesis, Abraham lived in Haran many years before going to Canaan. Jacob spent 20 years there and married two women from Haran.</p>
<p>Amorites appear prominently in the OT as major obstacles to the occupation of Canaan (the Promised Land) by the Israelites after the exodus. Calling Moses to lead Israel out of Egypt, the Lord spoke of Canaan, then occupied by Amorites and others, as a good land (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.8,17">Ex 3:8, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.13.5">13:5</a>). When the Israelites were in the wilderness, God promised to destroy those nations (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.23">Ex 23:23</a>) and drive them out of the land (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.2">Ex 33:2</a>). The Hebrew people were warned not to make covenants with any of them, to intermarry with them, or to tolerate their idol worship (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.11-17">Ex 34:11-17</a>).</p>
<p>Spies sent into the land found Amalekites in the south; Hittites, Jebusites, and Amorites in the northern mountains and to the west of the Jordan River; and Canaanites by the sea and along the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Num.13.25-29">Nm 13:25-29</a>). At that time there were Amorites east of the Jordan as well (<a href="?bref=Num.21.13">Nm 21:13</a>).</p>
<p>God had instructed Israel to go up from Horeb and conquer the mountain Amorites on the west side of the Jordan all the way to the Mediterranean Sea (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.7">Dt 1:7</a>). When they arrived at Kadesh-barnea they were at the foot of those mountains (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.19-20">Dt 1:19-20</a>). But the people murmured and complained that God had brought them from Egypt only to be slaughtered by the Amorites. From the spies’ reports, they pictured the Amorites as an awesome people, greater and taller than the Israelites (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.26-28">Dt 1:26-28</a>). At first they refused to trust God enough to go in, so God told them to turn around and head back into the wilderness. Then they changed their minds, stubbornly attacked the Amorites against God’s command, and were badly beaten (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.34-44">Dt 1:34-44</a>). Finally, after 38 additional years in the wilderness, the Israelites once again faced the Amorites, but this time on the east side of the Dead Sea (<a href="?bref=Num.21.13">Nm 21:13</a>). The Amorite king, Sihon, refused to let them pass through his land. The Israelites were drawn up at the Arnon River, which flows into the Dead Sea about two-thirds of the way up its eastern shore.</p>
<p>Transjordan was controlled by two Amorite kings, Sihon and Og. Israel had to face Sihon first. His city, Heshbon, lay due east of the north end of the Dead Sea (<a href="?bref=Num.21.21-26">Nm 21:21-26</a>). Sihon himself had taken this land from the Moabites. Moses knew of Sihon’s reputation and quoted a poem that boasted of Sihon’s victory over Moab (<a href="?bref=Num.21.27-30">Nm 21:27-30</a>). Nevertheless, the Israelites defeated Sihon and devastated his kingdom from Dibon, four miles (6.4 kilometers) north of the Arnon, to Medeba, seven miles (11.2 kilometers) south of Heshbon. King Og, farther to the north, received the same treatment (<a href="?bref=Num.21.31-35">Nm 21:31-35</a>). King Balak of Moab heard of the Israelite victories and was terrified (<a href="?bref=Num.22.2-3">Nm 22:2-3</a>).</p>
<p>Moses reminded the people that by relying on God’s promises they had taken all of the land of the Amorites east of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.24-3.10">Dt 2:24–3:10</a>). The conquered territory was given to the tribes of Gad and Reuben and to the half-tribe of Manasseh (<a href="?bref=Num.32.33">Nm 32:33</a>). Then, 40 years after the exodus began, Israel was standing on the east side of the Jordan, having dispossessed the two great Amorite nations there (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.1-4">Dt 1:1-4</a>). But there were other Amorite kingdoms in the hills west of the Jordan, along with other nations (<a href="?bref=Deut.7.1-2">Dt 7:1-2</a>). They were to be destroyed in the same way Sihon and Og had been defeated (<a href="?bref=Deut.31.3-6">Dt 31:3-6</a>).</p>
<p>So famous was the victory of Israel east of the Jordan that Rahab and others in Jericho, west of the Jordan, knew of it and were frightened (<a href="?bref=Josh.2.8-11">Jos 2:8-11</a>). The Israelites crossed the Jordan and took Jericho but were defeated at the smaller city of Ai in the hill country west of Jericho. They immediately assumed that they would be wiped out by the Amorites in those hills (<a href="?bref=Josh.7.7">Jos 7:7</a>).</p>
<p>The Israelites regained God’s favor, however, and defeated Ai. Their victory made an impression on the other kingdoms west of the Jordan in the hills, valleys, and coastlands up to Lebanon, who allied to fight Joshua (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.1-2">Jos 9:1-2</a>). Gibeon, an Amorite city seven miles (11.2 kilometers) southwest of Ai, made peace with Israel, putting more fear in the hearts of the remaining kings (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.1-2">Jos 10:1-2</a>). Adoni-zedek, king of Jerusalem, was evidently the leader of the Amorite kings west of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.3">Jos 10:3</a>). Jerusalem was only eight miles (12.8 kilometers) southeast of Gibeon. Adoni-zedek called together the kings of Hebron, Jarmuth, Lachish, and Eglon, all within 50 miles (80.4 kilometers) of Jerusalem, to fight against Gibeon and Joshua (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.3-5">Jos 10:3-5</a>).</p>
<p>Joshua came to Gibeon’s defense and routed the Amorites, chasing them to the northwest and southwest. The Lord fought for Israel, raining hailstones on the Amorites at Azekah, southwest of Gibeon, and causing the sun to stand still in order to provide a longer battle day (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.6-14">Jos 10:6-14</a>).</p>
<p>In the far north, Jabin, king of Hazor, rallied the Canaanites and remaining Amorites all the way north to Mt Hermon (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.1-5">Jos 11:1-5</a>). But they too were overcome (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.10-23">Jos 11:10-23</a>). Toward the end of Joshua’s career, he reminded the people that it was the Lord who had given them the land of the Amorites (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.1-18">Jos 24:1-18</a>).</p>
<p>After the occupation of Canaan by Israel, Amorites still present in the land chased Dan’s tribe into the mountains and continued to live near Aijalon, 17 miles (27.4 kilometers) west of Jerusalem. They still held the slopes toward the south end of the Dead Sea as well (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.34-36">Jgs 1:34-36</a>). In the period of the judges, the Amorites and their gods posed a constant threat to Israel’s well-being (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.10">Jgs 6:10</a>).</p>
<p>At the end of the period of the judges, relations between Israel and the Amorites improved (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.14">1 Sm 7:14</a>). David continued to honor Joshua’s treaty with the Amorite remnant of Gibeon (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.2-6">2 Sm 21:2-6</a>). Solomon conscripted his labor forces from the Amorites and other peoples still surviving from Israelite conquest (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.20-22">1 Kgs 9:20-22</a>).</p>
<p>The OT treats the deliverance of the Amorites and their land into the hands of Israel as a great event comparable with the exodus itself, a victory to be remembered and celebrated (<a href="?bref=Ps.135.9-12">Pss 135:9-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.136.13-26">136:13-26</a>). If the people forgot, the Lord reminded them through his prophets (<a href="?bref=Amos.2.9-10">Am 2:9-10</a>). Long after Sihon and Og had been defeated, the area east of the Jordan was still remembered as the land of “Sihon king of the Amorites” (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.19">1 Kgs 4:19</a>). When the kings of Israel and Judah began to fail God, the memory of the Amorites provided a standard of comparison of evil. The Jews’ continuing fascination with idolatry led God to address Jerusalem, representing the Jewish people, through the prophet Ezekiel: “Your mother was a Hittite and your father an Amorite” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.16.45">Ez 16:45</a>). In the biblical view, the Amorites stood for everything that is abominable in the sight of God.</p>
  </body>
</item>