<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AndrewtheApostle">
  <title>Andrew, the Apostle</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ANDREW, T<span class="lc">he</span> A<span class="lc">postle</span></p>
<p class="fl">One of Christ’s 12 apostles. Andrew first appears in the NT as a disciple of John the Baptist (<a href="?bref=John.1.35,40">Jn 1:35, 40</a>). After hearing John say, “Look, there is the Lamb of God!” (<a href="?bref=John.1.36">Jn 1:36</a>), referring to Jesus, Andrew and another unnamed disciple followed Jesus and stayed with him for a day (<a href="?bref=John.1.36-39">Jn 1:36-39</a>). Andrew then told his brother, Simon Peter, that he had found the Messiah and brought Peter to Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.1.40-42">Jn 1:40-42</a>). From then on Andrew faded into the background, and his brother came into prominence. Whenever the relationship of the two is mentioned, Andrew is always described as the brother of Simon Peter and never the other way around (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.18">Mt 4:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.16">Mk 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.40">Jn 1:40</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.8">6:8</a>), although Andrew is also mentioned without reference to his relationship to Peter (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.29">Mk 1:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.18">3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.3">13:3</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.22">Jn 12:22</a>). Andrew’s father was John (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.17">Mt 16:17</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.42">Jn 1:42</a>; <a href="?bref=John.21.15-17">21:15-17</a>), and his hometown was Bethsaida (<a href="?bref=John.1.44">Jn 1:44</a>), a village on the north shore of the Sea of Galilee.</p>
<p>The Gospel of John mentions disciples being with Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.2.2">2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=John.4.2">4:2</a>), and it is likely that Andrew was one of that early group. Evidently, however, he returned to his activity as a fisherman on the Sea of Galilee, where he shared a house with Peter and his family in Capernaum (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.18-20">Mt 4:18-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.16-18,29-33">Mk 1:16-18, 29-33</a>). While they were fishing, Andrew and Peter received a definite call to follow Jesus and become those who fish for people. From among the disciples of Jesus a group of 12 were later specially chosen as apostles. Andrew is always listed among the first four named, along with Peter and two other brothers, John and James (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.2-4">Mt 10:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.13-16">Lk 6:13-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.13">Acts 1:13</a>).</p>
<p>Andrew is named in only three other contexts in the Gospels. At the feeding of the 5,000 he called attention to the boy who had five barley loaves and two fish (<a href="?bref=John.6.8-9">Jn 6:8-9</a>). When certain Greeks came to Philip, asking to see Jesus, Philip told Andrew and then the two of them told Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.12.20-22">Jn 12:20-22</a>). Finally, Andrew is listed among those who were questioning Jesus privately on the Mt of Olives (<a href="?bref=Mark.13.3-4">Mk 13:3-4</a>). The last NT mention of Andrew is in the list of apostles waiting in the upper room in Jerusalem for the promised outpouring of the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.12-14">Acts 1:12-14</a>).</p>
<p>Various documents associated with Andrew, such as the Acts of Andrew mentioned by the early church historian Eusebius, are of doubtful value. Some traditions indicate that Andrew ministered in Scythia. According to the Muratorian Canon, Andrew received a revelation at night that the apostle John should write the fourth Gospel. Tradition is rather uniform that Andrew died at Patrae in Achaia. A story developed that he was martyred on an X-shaped cross (a “decussate” or “saltire” cross), which has become known as St Andrew’s Cross. Another tradition is that an arm of the dead Andrew was taken into Scotland as a relic by Regulus, and thus Andrew became known as a patron saint of Scotland. On the calendar of saints of the Roman and Greek churches, Andrew’s date is set as November 30. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Apocrypha_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Apocrypha (Specific Titles of Apocryphal Writings): Andrew, Acts of</a>; Andrew, Story of; Andrew and Matthias, Acts of; Andrew and Paul, Acts of.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ApostleApostleship_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Apostle, Apostleship</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>