<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Anoint">
  <title>Anoint</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ANOINT</p>
<p class="fl">To pour oil or ointment onto a person or object in a ritualistic fashion.</p>
<p>The Hebrew word for anoint first appears in <a href="?bref=Gen.31.13">Genesis 31:13</a>, where it refers to Jacob pouring oil on the stone of Bethel (<a href="?bref=Gen.28.18-19">Gn 28:18-19</a>). At a later time the ceremony was repeated (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.9-15">Gn 35:9-15</a>). The ceremony was clearly religious, signifying induction into sacred use. As a religious act, the anointing was meant to endow the anointed one with the quality of the deity involved. From ancient times the Hebrews inaugurated officers of their national community by pouring special oil on the head of the person designated for office. The same practice was used to set objects apart for special divine use. </p>
<p>Scripture supplies few details of the ceremonial anointings of official things and persons. Jacob simply poured oil on a rock with an accompanying pronouncement. When anointing Israel’s first king, the prophet-judge Samuel took Saul aside for instruction (<a href="?bref=1Sam.9.25-27">1 Sm 9:25-27</a>), then “took a vial of oil and poured it on his head, and kissed him and said, ‘Has not the Lord anointed you to be prince over his people Israel’” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.1">1 Sm 10:1</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). For anointing the tabernacle and its priests, a special oil was compounded and used only for that sacred purpose. Skilled perfume makers blended the choicest spices (myrrh, cinnamon, sweet cane, cassia) in olive oil (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.22-25">Ex 30:22-25</a>). The Lord specified that everything set apart for God—the tabernacle, the ark, the table and its instruments, the lampstand and utensils, the incense altar and main altar, the washbasin—was to be anointed. Aaron the high priest and his sons the priests were also to be anointed (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.26-32">Ex 30:26-32</a>). The result was a holy place with holy furnishings, holy implements of worship, and holy ministers.</p>
<p>The offices of prophet, priest, and king were those associated with anointing in the nation of Israel. Prophets were sometimes, but not invariably, inducted by official anointing (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.16">1 Kgs 19:16</a>). They could be referred to as God’s anointed ones (<a href="?bref=1Chr.16.22">1 Chr 16:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.105.15">Ps 105:15</a>). At the institution of the levitical priesthood, all the priests were anointed to their offices, the sons of Aaron as well as Aaron himself (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.12-15">Ex 40:12-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.3">Nm 3:3</a>). Afterward, anointing was not repeated at the consecration of ordinary priests, but was especially reserved for the high priest (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.29">Ex 29:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.16.32">Lv 16:32</a>).</p>
<p>Before they had a king of their own, the Israelites were aware of anointing as a mode of inaugurating kings (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.8">Jgs 9:8</a>,15). Anointing became a divinely ordained rite accompanying induction of all the kings of Judah and Israel (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.1-6">2 Kgs 9:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.12">11:12</a>) from Saul onward (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.1">1 Sm 10:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.39">1 Kgs 1:39</a>). David’s anointing took place in three stages (<a href="?bref=1Sam.16.1,13">1 Sm 16:1, 13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.2.4">2 Sm 2:4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.5.1-4">5:1-4</a>). “The Lord’s anointed” or some similar phrase became a common designation for Hebrew kings (<a href="?bref=1Sam.12.3-5">1 Sm 12:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.1.14-16">2 Sm 1:14-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.38,51">Ps 89:38, 51</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.4.20">Lam 4:20</a>).</p>
<p>Anointing, however, had more than religious or ritualistic significance. Both the Egyptians and the Syrians practiced anointing for medical and cosmetic reasons, and the Scriptures indicate that such nonreligious practice was also a part of Israelite customs (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.20">2 Sm 12:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.3.3">Ru 3:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.15">Mi 6:15</a>). In fact, failure to anoint or perfume oneself indicated mourning or distress (<a href="?bref=2Sam.14.2">2 Sm 14:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.10.3">Dn 10:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.6.17">Mt 6:17</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT, anointing of the sick accompanied by prayer for healing by local church elders is recommended when requested by a sick person (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.14-16">Jas 5:14-16</a>). Anointing with oil was also a part of the apostles’ healing ministry (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.12-13">Mk 6:12-13</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>