<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Apostasy">
  <title>Apostasy</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">APOSTASY</p>
<p class="fl">Turning against God, as evidenced by abandonment and repudiation of former beliefs. The term generally refers to a deliberate renouncing of the faith by a once sincere believer rather than a state of ignorance or mistaken knowledge. Apostasy is distinguished from heresy (denial of a part of the faith) and from transfer of allegiance from one religious body to another within the same faith. Also, it is possible to deny the faith, as Peter once did, and then at a later time reaffirm it.</p>
<p>Originally, “apostasy” meant literal rebellion. Thus the Jews were described as “rebels” against King Artaxerxes (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Esd.2.23">1 Esd 2:23</a>) and Jason as a “rebel against the laws” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Macc.5.6-8">2 Macc 5:6-8</a>). OT descriptions of spiritual rebellion include departure from the law, forsaking temple worship, and willful disobedience toward God himself (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.22">Jos 22:22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.19">2 Chr 29:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.19">Jer 2:19</a>). The prophetic writings of Isaiah and Jeremiah provide many examples of Israel’s defections (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.2-4">Is 1:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.19">Jer 2:19</a>). Israelite kings were often guilty of apostasy: Rehoboam (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.22-24">1 Kgs 14:22-24</a>); Ahab (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.30-33">1 Kgs 16:30-33</a>); Ahaziah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.51-53">1 Kgs 22:51-53</a>); Jehoram (<a href="?bref=2Chr.21.6,10">2 Chr 21:6, 10</a>); Ahaz (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.1-4">2 Chr 28:1-4</a>); Manasseh (<a href="?bref=2Chr.33.1-19">2 Chr 33:1-19</a>); Amon (<a href="?bref=2Chr.33.21-23">2 Chr 33:21-23</a>).</p>
<p>In NT times many disciples withdrew from Christ (<a href="?bref=John.6.66">Jn 6:66</a>)—the most notorious example being Judas Iscariot. The Greek word from which “apostasy” is derived appears in only two passages. The apostle Paul was accused of apostasy for teaching others “to turn their backs on the laws of Moses” (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.21">Acts 21:21</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). And apostasy is given an eschatological (end times) significance in <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.3">2 Thessalonians 2:3</a>. Christians were warned not to be carried away and deceived in the widespread apostasy to come in the end times before the Lord’s return. That apostasy is linked to the rise of a man of rebellion who will be Satan’s tool (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.3-12">2 Thes 2:3-12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Tim.4.1-3">1 Tm 4:1-3</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="WarningsAgainstApostasy"/>
  </body>
</item>