<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ArcherArchery">
  <title>Archer, Archery</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ARCHER, ARCHERY</p>
<p class="fl">The archer used bow and arrows in peace and war. Nomads (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.20">Gn 21:20</a>), hunters (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.3">Gn 27:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.7.24">Is 7:24</a>), raiders (<a href="?bref=Gen.48.22">Gn 48:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.12">Jos 24:12</a>), and warriors (<a href="?bref=Ezek.39.9">Ez 39:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.1.7">Hos 1:7</a>) used this weapon throughout the biblical period. The efficiency of the bow and the making of arrows improved tremendously over the centuries. The finest bow was the “composite bow,” made from strips and bands of sinew glued to the parts furthermost from the core with animal horn glued to the inner surface. The best of these bows could fire arrows from 300 to 400 yards (274 to 366 meters). The archer needed to be a strong person to string and operate it.</p>
<p>While the archer used the bow for hunting, it was particularly useful in war. Saul and Jonathan fought with sword and bow (<a href="?bref=1Sam.18.4">1 Sm 18:4</a>), and David’s army contained skilled bowmen (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.2">1 Chr 12:2</a>). The kings of Israel equipped their troops with bows (<a href="?bref=2Chr.17.17">2 Chr 17:17</a>). Israel’s enemies, the Egyptians, Syrians, Assyrians, Babylonians, Persians, Greeks, and Romans, all had strong contingents of archers, with excellent pictures still available on some of their bas-reliefs.</p>
<p>Job used the metaphor of God’s archers round about him when describing his many bodily ailments (<a href="?bref=Job.16.13">Jb 16:13</a>). At times the archer’s bow represents violence (<a href="?bref=Ps.11.2">Pss 11:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.57.4">57:4</a>) or divine judgment (<a href="?bref=Ps.7.13">Pss 7:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.38.2">38:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.64.7">64:7</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ArmorandWeapons_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Armor and Weapons</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>