<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AsherTribe">
  <title>Asher (Tribe)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ASHER (T<span class="lc">ribe</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Israelite tribe that inhabited the fertile coastal territory when the Promised Land was divided for settlement. Asher’s allotment stretched north of Mt Carmel to a point slightly above the city of Sidon. The eastern boundary ran along the western slopes of the hills of Galilee (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.24-34">Jos 19:24-34</a>). The tribes of Zebulun and Naphtali were Asher’s eastern neighbors. Due south, the Carmel mountain range was a natural barrier between Asher and the tribe of Manasseh. The land of Asher was agriculturally rich and is still known for its olive groves. Economically, the people of Asher joined in maritime trade with the Phoenicians of the city of Tyre.</p>
<p>As a tribe, Asher fluctuated in size. From the few who entered Egypt with their father, Jacob, the tribe grew to 41,500 adult warriors at Mt Sinai (<a href="?bref=Num.1.40-41">Nm 1:40-41</a>). At the second census in the wilderness the tribe numbered 53,400 soldiers (<a href="?bref=Num.26.47">Nm 26:47</a>). At the time of King David the number varied from 26,000 to 40,000 warriors (<a href="?bref=1Chr.7.40">1 Chr 7:40</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.12.36">12:36</a>). Asher was never more than fifth in size among the tribes of Israel.</p>
<p>The tribe joined the rest of Israel in rejecting the optimistic reports of Caleb and Joshua about the land of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Num.13.30-14.10">Nm 13:30–14:10</a>). As a result, that generation perished in the wilderness after 40 years of wandering (<a href="?bref=Num.14.22-25">Nm 14:22-25</a>).</p>
<p>At the close of the northern campaign in the Promised Land, Joshua gave the remaining seven tribes their own territory (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.2">Jos 18:2</a>). The fifth partition went to Asher’s descendants. Earlier, Ahihud had been chosen by God to distribute land within the territory given to Asher’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Num.34.16,27">Nm 34:16, 27</a>). Certain Levites, descendants of Gershom, were allocated cities within its borders (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.6,30">Jos 21:6, 30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.62,74">1 Chr 6:62, 74</a>).</p>
<p>Like all the Israelite tribes, Asher was never able to possess all of its inheritance. Failure to drive out the inhabitants of Acco, Sidon, Ahlab, Achzib, Helbah, Aphik, and Rehob subjected the tribe to the degradations of pagan culture (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.31">Jgs 1:31</a>). The “unpossessed” territory of the Sidonians and the Phoenicians stretched along the coastal region for 200 miles (322 kilometers). Thus “the Asherites dwelt among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land; for they did not drive them out” (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.32">Jgs 1:32</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). It is possible that Asher’s tribe, having become a partner in the enterprises of the successful Phoenicians, lost all desire to expel them from their cities.</p>
<p>After the death of the Israelite judge Ehud, Israel fell into the hands of Jabin, king of Canaan. When the judge Deborah stirred up Barak to marshal Israel’s forces for battle, God gave their army a great victory and liberated them from their oppressor (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.1-24">Jgs 4</a>). After the victory Deborah complained that “Asher sat unmoved at the seashore, remaining in his harbors” (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.17">Jgs 5:17</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Eventually, through amalgamation, the tribe succumbed to Phoenician religious and cultural influences. Foreign invasion and pagan inroads were its downfall.</p>
<p>Little is said in the Bible of the tribe’s leadership. At the time of the exodus, when the nation was organized at Mt Sinai, Pagiel the son of Ochran became tribal chief (<a href="?bref=Num.1.13">Nm 1:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.2.27">2:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.7.72">7:72</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.10.26">10:26</a>). But the Bible is silent from then on about Asher’s leaders. None of the judges of Israel came from Asher, and in King David’s day the tribes of Asher and Gad were omitted from the list of the nation’s chief officers (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.16-22">1 Chr 27:16-22</a>).</p>
<p>Nevertheless, there are some bright spots in Asher’s tribal history. The tribe answered the call of Gideon to drive out the Midianite enemy (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.1-8,35">Jgs 6:1-8, 35</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.7.23">7:23</a>). They rallied with the rest of the tribes of Israel to defend Saul, their first king (<a href="?bref=1Sam.11.7">1 Sm 11:7</a>). Later, 40,000 Asherites sided with David to give him Saul’s kingdom (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.23-36">1 Chr 12:23-36</a>). After the fall of Samaria in 722 <span class="era">BC</span>, a small remnant came to Jerusalem to observe the first Passover feast in many years (<a href="?bref=2Chr.30.5">2 Chr 30:5</a>), when King Hezekiah (715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>) invited all the tribes to assemble for the Passover (<a href="?bref=2Chr.30.10-11">2 Chr 30:10-11</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT one of Asher’s descendants is mentioned, an 84-year-old widow named Anna, a prophetess. She described Jesus as “the redemption of Jerusalem” from the time of his dedication to the Lord in the temple (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.36-38">Lk 2:36-38</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>