<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Atonement">
  <title>Atonement</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ATONEMENT</p>
<p class="fl">In Christian thought, the act by which God and man are brought together in personal relationship. The term is derived from Anglo-Saxon words meaning “making at one,” hence “at-one-ment.” It presupposes a separation or alienation that needs to be overcome if human beings are to know God and have fellowship with him. As a term expressing relationship, atonement is tied closely to such terms as reconciliation and forgiveness.</p>
<p>In the <span class="sc">kjv</span> the word “atonement” occurs many times in the OT but only once in the NT (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.11">Rom 5:11</a>). Modern translations generally, and more correctly, render the word “reconciliation.” The idea of atonement is ever present in the NT, however, and is one of the fundamental concepts of Scripture. God is seen as taking the initiative in man’s salvation; thus atonement is the work of God, who opens the possibility for sinful human beings to receive pardoning grace. For the sinner, who cannot know God, who cannot bridge the gap between himself and God, a “new and living way” is opened up by God.</p>
<p>The need for atonement is bound up with man’s thoroughgoing sinfulness. All of Scripture (cited below from the <span class="sc">rsv</span> unless otherwise noted) points to the radical nature of that sinfulness. The prophet Isaiah affirmed, “All we like sheep have gone astray” (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.6">Is 53:6</a>). According to another prophet, Jeremiah, “The heart is deceitful above all things, and desperately corrupt; who can understand it?” (<a href="?bref=Jer.17.9">Jer 17:9</a>). David the psalmist cried, “There is none that does good, no, not one” (<a href="?bref=Ps.14.3">Ps 14:3</a>). Paul described the degeneracy of man caused by his disobedience and idolatry (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.18-32">Rom 1:18-32</a>) and summed it up: “All have sinned and fall short of the glory of God” (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.23">Rom 3:23</a>). Elsewhere Paul described men as enemies of God (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.10">Rom 5:10</a>), as “hostile to God” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.7">Rom 8:7</a>), as “estranged and hostile in mind, doing evil deeds” (<a href="?bref=Col.1.21">Col 1:21</a>). Adam’s race is just like Adam: “Therefore as sin came into the world through one man and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because all men sinned” (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.12">Rom 5:12</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="TheSignificanceOfAtonementInTheNewTestament"/>
<p>The problem of the sinfulness of humanity is compounded by the holiness of God, who cannot look upon sin. Isaiah saw the holy God in the temple and drew back because of his own sinfulness (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-5">Is 6:1-5</a>). Not only is man terribly sinful, but God is fearfully holy. Consequently man dreads God and can do nothing to change this situation. He is lost, helpless, standing under the awful judgment of God. He cannot justify himself before God and cannot merit God’s concern. The possibility of atonement, then, rests entirely with God. The nature of that atonement, as illustrated in biblical history, affirms simultaneously the nature of both God and man.</p>
<p>The Hebrew term frequently translated “atone” has the basic meaning “to wipe out,” “to erase, “to cover,” or perhaps more generally “to remove.” In the <span class="sc">kjv</span> it is translated by such expressions as “to make atonement,” “forgive,” “appease,” “pacify,” “pardon,” “purge,” “put off,” and “reconcile.”</p>
<p>The most common OT expression of the means of atonement was the sacrifice and offering up of the blood of a victim. In a sacrifice the shedding of blood was the central act. Life was in the blood (<a href="?bref=Lev.17.11">Lv 17:11</a>); in the pouring out of the blood, life was given up; that is, death occurred. Elsewhere blood may be a symbol for life, but in the sacrificial motif it symbolized death. Some scholars have argued that in the pouring forth of the blood, life was made available to the people. It was the life <span class="ital">of the flesh,</span> however, that was in the blood, and the flesh was sacrificed. In the NT it is by virtue of the resurrection that the life of Christ is made available to believers.</p>
<p>Not every OT mention of atonement referred directly to the shedding of blood. On the Day of Atonement one of two goats was slain, but the other was “presented alive before the Lord to make atonement” (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.10">Lv 16:10</a>). That “scapegoat” was driven out into the wilderness bearing the sins of the people. Banishment or expulsion took the place of blood as the goat, bearing the sins of the people, suffered the fate of the sinner. The goat was a substitute for the people. Money offered for the temple was also said to make atonement (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.16">Ex 30:16</a>). In another text Aaron and Moses prevented the spreading of a plague by carrying incense: “He put on the incense, and made atonement for the people” (<a href="?bref=Num.16.47">Nm 16:47</a>). Those few special expressions do not undo the basic OT theme of atonement through provision of a substitute animal. The NT summarizes that theme by saying that “without the shedding of blood there is no forgiveness of sins” (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.22">Heb 9:22</a>).</p>
<p>From atonement for sin in the OT came such terms as “expiation” and “forgiveness.” From the idea of atonement for the wrath or judgment of God came “propitiation” and “reconciliation.” Hence in modern English translations various terms attempt to express the concept of atonement provided by God.</p>
<p>Throughout the NT it is made clear that the work of Christ, primarily the cross, is what provides atonement. OT language continues to find expression in the NT, especially the term “blood.” Thus in the NT we have the “blood of the covenant” (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.28">Mt 26:28</a>) and the “new covenant in my blood” (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.20">Lk 22:20</a>) as well as the “blood of Christ” (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.13">Eph 2:13</a>) and the “blood of his cross” (<a href="?bref=Col.1.20">Col 1:20</a>). Almost equivalent are the frequent references to the cross and the death of Christ. The NT is the “new covenant” of Jesus Christ, sealed by his blood.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Propitiation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Propitiation</a>; <a href="?item=Expiation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Expiation</a>; <a href="?item=OfferingsandSacrifices_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Offerings and Sacrifices</a>; <a href="?item=AtonementDayof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Atonement, Day of</a>; <a href="?item=RedeemerRedemption_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Redeemer, Redemption</a>; <a href="?item=Ransom_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ransom</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>