<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AtonementDayof">
  <title>Atonement, Day of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ATONEMENT, D<span class="lc">ay of</span></p>
<p class="fl">Yom Kippur, the most important day in the religious calendar of Israel, falling on the 10th day of Tishri (the Hebrew month corresponding to mid-September through mid-October). On that day the high priest entered the Holy of Holies of the tabernacle (or temple) to atone for the sins of all Israel. The basic idea of atonement is a “covering” of sin; the purpose is to accomplish reconciliation between man and God. In the NT the Day of Atonement was referred to as the “fast” (<a href="?bref=Acts.27.9">Acts 27:9</a>). To the rabbis, it was the “Day” or the “Great Day.”</p>
<p>Although many additional rites were added over the centuries, the basic description of the original Day of Atonement is <a href="?bref=Lev.16.1-34">Leviticus 16</a>. Complex and detailed ceremonies all focused on the central objective of complete atonement by sacrifice. First, the high priest removed his official garments, made for beauty and glory, and clothed himself in white linen as a symbol of repentance as he went about the duties of the day. Next, he offered a bull calf as a sin offering for the priests and himself. That done, he entered the Holy of Holies with a censer of live coals from the altar of incense, filling the area with incense. He sprinkled the bullock’s blood on the mercy seat and on the floor before the ark of the covenant. Then he cast lots over two live goats brought by the people. He killed one of the goats as a sin offering for the nation, taking the blood inside the veil and sprinkling it as before, thus atoning even for the Holy Place. He confessed the sins of the nation over the live goat as he placed his hands on its head. Finally he sent the live goat, called the scapegoat (i.e., the escape goat), into the wilderness. Symbolically it carried away the sins of the people. Then the high priest clothed himself in his usual apparel and offered a burnt offering for himself and one for the people with the fat of the sin offering. Outside the camp the flesh of the bull calf and goat was burned.</p>
<p>Other OT references to the Day of Atonement include <a href="?bref=Exod.30.10">Exodus 30:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.23.26-32">Leviticus 23:26-32</a>, giving the date in a list of all the annual feasts; <a href="?bref=Lev.25.9-16">Leviticus 25:9-16</a>, stating that each jubilee year began on the Day of Atonement; and <a href="?bref=Num.29.7-11">Numbers 29:7-11</a>.</p>
<p>The Day of Atonement became so central to Judaism that it survived the destruction of the temple in <span class="era">AD</span> 70 and the end of the sacrificial system. It is the highest holy day of Judaism today. Although nowhere in the books of Moses is there an explanation of “afflicting the soul” required on the Day of Atonement (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.27-32">Lv 23:27-32</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>), the Jews have continuously interpreted it as referring to fasting (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.35.13">Ps 35:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.58.3-5,10">Is 58:3-5, 10</a>). In biblical times, celebration of the Day of Atonement showed that Israel believed the cleansing of their sins was accomplished by the rites commanded by God. The forgiveness and grace of God were granted them and were the basis for their continued fellowship with God as his covenant people. Because it was designated as a sabbath of solemn rest (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.31">Lv 16:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.23.32">23:32</a>), all work was forbidden on that day as on the weekly observance of the Sabbath.</p>
<p>As with all the prescribed sacrifices throughout the year, the question arises as to the need for a special time for atonement. It is clear that the ritual was meant to avert God’s wrath for sins already committed as well as to guarantee the continued presence of God. The sacrifice of the first goat and the sending away of the scapegoat were intended to cleanse the nation, the priesthood, and the sanctuary from sin. The intent of the whole sacrificial system reached its highest expression on that day, called by some the “Good Friday of the OT.” The daily, weekly, and monthly sacrifices left something undone, so that the high priest could not enter the holiest place throughout the year. On that one day, however, he was permitted to enter with sacrificial blood as he solemnly represented the nation before the bloodstained mercy seat.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="TheDayOfAtonementAndTheNewTestament"/>
<p>The underlying reason for the day was that other offerings for sin could not provide for unknown (“secret”) sins. Because of such sins the sanctuary, the land, and the nation remained ritually unclean. The Day of Atonement was instituted by God for the complete atonement of all sin (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.33">Lv 16:33</a>). In the person of the high priest the nation was most fully represented by the access of their mediator into the very presence of God. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Atonement_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Atonement</a>; <a href="?item=OfferingsandSacrifices_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Offerings and Sacrifices</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>