<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DanielPerson">
  <title>Daniel (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DANIEL (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. David’s second son, the first by his wife Abigail (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.1">1 Chr 3:1</a>); also called Kileab (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.3">2 Sm 3:3</a>).</p>
<p class="sp"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Kileab_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Kileab</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Priest, descendant of Ithamar. He signed Ezra’s covenant of faithfulness to God with Nehemiah and others after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.2">Ezr 8:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.10.6">Neh 10:6</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Jewish statesman and seer in the Babylonian court whose career is recounted in the book of Daniel. Daniel’s early life is cloaked in silence. Nothing is known of his parents or family, though he was probably descended from Jewish nobility (<a href="?bref=Dan.1.3">Dn 1:3</a>). If born during the time of King Josiah’s reforms (c. 621 <span class="era">BC</span>), Daniel would have been about 16 when he and his three friends—Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah—were deported from Jerusalem to Babylon by King Nebuchadnezzar. They may have been hostages to assure the cooperation of the royal family in Judah.</p>
<p class="list-text">Daniel, renamed Belteshazzar (meaning “may Bel [god] protect his life”), was trained for court service. He quickly established a reputation for intelligence and for absolute fidelity to his God. After three years of instruction, he began a court career that lasted nearly 70 years (<a href="?bref=Dan.1.21">Dn 1:21</a>). Daniel had hardly finished his training when he was called on to interpret one of Nebuchadnezzar’s dreams, in which a great image collapsed and disintegrated when struck by a stone. God revealed its meaning to Daniel, who explained it to the king. In gratitude Nebuchadnezzar offered him the post of governor of Babylonia, but Daniel requested that the honor be conferred on his three companions in captivity.</p>
<p class="list-text">Near the end of Nebuchadnezzar’s life, Daniel was able to interpret a second dream (<a href="?bref=Dan.4.1-37">Dn 4</a>). That dream intimated the king’s impending insanity. Daniel urged the king to repent (<a href="?bref=Dan.4.27">4:27</a>), but he did not, and subsequently for a period of time he became deranged.</p>
<p class="list-text">After the death of Nebuchadnezzar in 562 <span class="era">BC</span>, Daniel dropped from public view and evidently occupied an inferior position in the royal court. Although he received visions (<a href="?bref=Dan.7.1-8.27">Dn 7–8</a>) in the first and third years of the Babylonian regent Belshazzar’s reign (555 and 553 <span class="era">BC</span>), it was not until 539 <span class="era">BC</span> that Daniel made another public appearance. During a banquet hosted by Belshazzar, the king profaned the sacred vessels pillaged from the Jerusalem temple. A disembodied hand suddenly appeared and wrote on the palace wall the mysterious words, “Mene, Mene, Tekel, Parsin.” Summoned to explain the message, Daniel interpreted it as a forecast of the imminent end of the Babylonian kingdom. That same night Belshazzar was killed by the Persians, who attacked and successfully overtook the capital city (<a href="?bref=Dan.5.30">5:30</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Under Darius the Mede, Daniel became one of three “presidents” (administrators) of the realm (<a href="?bref=Dan.6.2">6:2</a>). Daniel’s rank, along with his capable and distinguished management, infuriated his political enemies. They persuaded Darius to pass a decree forbidding petition to any god or man but the king, under penalty of being cast into a lions’ den. Daniel’s religious integrity forced him to violate the law. Thrown to the lions, he remained miraculously unscathed. Vindicated, he was restored to office (vv <a href="?bref=Dan.6.17-28">17-28</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The latter part of the book of Daniel describes several visions he received of future events. The visions dealt with four beasts (ch <a href="?bref=Dan.7.1-28">7</a>), future kingdoms (ch <a href="?bref=Dan.8.1-27">8</a>), the coming of the Messiah (ch <a href="?bref=Dan.9.1-27">9</a>), and Syria and Egypt (chs <a href="?bref=Dan.11.1-12.13">11–12</a>). The prophet Ezekiel alluded to Daniel’s great wisdom (<a href="?bref=Ezek.28.3">Ez 28:3</a>) and ranked him in righteousness with Noah and Job (<a href="?bref=Ezek.14.14,20">14:14, 20</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DanielBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Daniel, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetProphetess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophet, Prophetess</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>