<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DanPlace">
  <title>Dan (Place)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DAN (P<span class="lc">lace</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. Phoenician city, originally named Leshem (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.47">Jos 19:47</a>) or Laish (<a href="?bref=Judg.18.7">Jgs 18:7</a>), which was conquered by Dan’s tribe when it migrated northward. The city lay a day’s journey from Sidon in the valley near Beth-rehob (v <a href="?bref=Judg.18.28">28</a>) at the southern base of Mt Hermon. It was the most northerly point of the ancient Israelite kingdom, and was used as a topographical marker in the phrase “from Dan to Beersheba” (cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.20.1">Jgs 20:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.10">2 Sm 3:10</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The site of Dan guarded a major trading route running between Damascus and Tyre, and was therefore an important commercial center. The Nahr el-Leddan, one of the principal sources of the Jordan, rose in the area, and this made the Huleh Valley below Dan lush and fertile even in the heat of summer. Consequently, the territory around the city produced grain and vegetable crops in abundance, as well as supplying the needs of flocks and herds adequately.</p>
<p class="list-text">In the early Iron Age, Dan was a prosperous city, as indicated in <a href="?bref=Judg.18.7">Judges 18:7</a>, but by the middle of the 11th century <span class="era">BC</span>, it had been destroyed, evidently as a result of occupation by the Danites. When Jeroboam I became king of the separate northern kingdom of Israel, Dan was one of two shrines where the golden calves were worshiped. The high place at Tell el-Qadi (Tell of Dan), a square masonry platform some 61 by 20 feet (18.6 by 6.1 meters), has been excavated, but no trace of the golden image has been found.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfTheTellOfDan"/>
<p class="list-text">The cultic worship of Baal at Dan survived even Jehu’s drastic purge (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.28-31">2 Kgs 10:28-31</a>), but during Ben-hadad’s reign, the city fell under Syrian control (cf. v <a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.32">32</a>). When the Syrians were attempting to ward off Assyrian attacks on their eastern border during the time of Jeroboam II (793–753 <span class="era">BC</span>), Dan was reconquered by the northern kingdom. It did not remain in Israelite hands for long, however, for its inhabitants were deported to Assyria (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.6">2 Kgs 17:6</a>) by Tiglath-pileser III (745–727 <span class="era">BC</span>). Nevertheless, the site continued to be inhabited (cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.4.15">Jer 4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.8.16">8:16</a>), and its high place, or acropolis, at the northern extremity of the mound was used for worship. This particular area was enlarged periodically in both Greek and Roman times, and it is from the latter period that a statue of Aphrodite came. In NT times Dan was eclipsed by Caesarea, which was only a few miles distant. Josephus (<span class="ital">War</span> 4.1) recorded that Titus crushed a revolt at Dan in <span class="era">AD</span> 67.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DanPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dan (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=DanTribeof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dan, Tribe of</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. KJV rendering of an obscure Hebrew word (Vedan) in <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.19">Ezekiel 27:19</a>, alternately translated “wine,” a commodity from Uzal, in the <span class="sc">rsv</span>.</p>
<p class="sp"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=UzalPlace_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Uzal (Place)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>