<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DanTribeof">
  <title>Dan, Tribe of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DAN, Tribe of</p>
<p class="fl">Israelite tribe named for the patriarch Jacob’s fifth son. The tribe of Dan, descended from Dan’s only known son, Hushim (cf. “Shuham” in <a href="?bref=Num.26.42-43">Nm 26:42-43</a>), had little distinction in its early years. Some Danites are mentioned in the wilderness narratives: Oholiab, a craftsman of the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.31.6">Ex 31:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.35.34">35:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.38.23">38:23</a>); another whose mother married an Egyptian and who blasphemed God (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.11">Lv 24:11</a>); and Ahiezer, chief prince of Dan during the exodus (<a href="?bref=Num.1.12">Nm 1:12</a>).</p>
<p>Dan was the second largest tribe at the first census taken in the wilderness (62,700 warriors—<a href="?bref=Num.1.38-39">Nm 1:38-39</a>). They were instructed to encamp on the north side of the Israelites’ camp along with Asher and Naphtali (<a href="?bref=Num.2.25-31">Nm 2:25-31</a>), and were to bring up the rear in the line of march (<a href="?bref=Num.2.31">Nm 2:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.10.25">10:25</a>). At the second census 40 years later, just before entering the Promised Land, they had grown only to 64,400 (<a href="?bref=Num.26.42-43">26:42-43</a>), still second in size. The tribe does not stand out in the Conquest narratives (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.16-3.29">Dt 2:16–3:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.1.1-24.33">Jos 1–24</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.1.1-36">Jgs 1</a>). Dan is listed among the tribes who reminded Israel of the covenant curses at Mt Ebal (<a href="?bref=Deut.27.13">Dt 27:13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Josh.8.30-33">Jos 8:30-33</a>). The tribe is called a “lion’s whelp” in Moses’ blessing (<a href="?bref=Deut.33.22">Dt 33:22</a>). Some believe that the reference to “Bashan” in that blessing prefigured the Danites’ migration to the northern territory where they eventually settled.</p>
<p>One of the most significant references to Dan’s tribe is the account of its northward migration (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.40-48">Jos 19:40-48</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.18.1-31">Jgs 18</a>). The Danites had been allotted a portion of Canaan between Judah and Ephraim bordering the Mediterranean seacoast (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.40-46">Jos 19:40-46</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.5.17">Jgs 5:17</a>), but were unable to occupy their territory except for the valley at Zorah and Eshtaol (<a href="?bref=Judg.13.25">Jgs 13:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.18.2">18:2</a>). As a result, a group of Danites, discouraged with their situation, marched north and captured Laish, located about 25 miles (40 kilometers) north of the Sea of Galilee and just below Israel’s northernmost border. Laish was renamed Dan at that time (<a href="?bref=Judg.18.27-29">18:27-29</a>). Their association with that northern territory eventually gave rise to the expression “from Dan to Beersheba” (<a href="?bref=Judg.20.1">Jgs 20:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.10">2 Sm 3:10</a>) as designating Israel’s northern and southern borders.</p>
<p>Southern Dan continued for some time, as illustrated in the exploits of Samson of the tribe of Dan (<a href="?bref=Judg.13.1-16.31">Jgs 13–16</a>). Evidently the southern Danites gradually merged into the tribe of Judah, and no historical reference to the southern Danite tribe is made in the rest of the OT. The Danites were mentioned in King David’s time as mustering a considerable army loyal to David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.35">1 Chr 12:35</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.27.22">27:22</a>).</p>
<p>The Danites were among the tribes who did not drive the Canaanites from their territory (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.4-5">Jos 13:4-5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.1.34-35">Jgs 1:34-35</a>). Joshua had to prod them into the task at the Shiloh assembly (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.1-4">Jos 18:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.19.40-48">19:40-48</a>). Eventually the Danites gave up the effort and sought other lands in the north, where conquest was easier. Their disobedience was further manifested in their open sin of setting up a “graven image” and establishing a rival priesthood, even though their priest was a Levite (<a href="?bref=Judg.18.30-31">Jgs 18:30-31</a>). The result of that idolatry was that, at the division of the Israelite kingdom at the end of King Solomon’s reign, King Jeroboam of the northern kingdom of Israel chose the city of Dan as one of the idol shrines in which to set up the golden calves (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.28-29">1 Kgs 12:28-29</a>). The Danites’ apostasy, and that of the other northern tribes, continued throughout their history (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.29">2 Kgs 10:29</a>), and because of it they were eventually carried captive to Assyria (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.1-23">2 Kgs 17:1-23</a>).</p>
<p>The tribe name is mentioned in the prophet Ezekiel’s idealized description of the restored land and Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Ezek.48.1-2,32">Ez 48:1-2, 32</a>). In the NT, the apostle John omitted the tribe from a list of Israel’s tribes (<a href="?bref=Rev.7.4-8">Rv 7:4-8</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=DanPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dan (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=DanPlace_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dan (Place)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>