<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DayoftheLord">
  <title>Day of the Lord</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DAY OF THE LORD</p>
<p class="fl">Expression used by OT prophets (as early as the eighth-century <span class="era">BC</span> prophet Amos) to signify a time in which God actively intervenes in history, primarily for judgment. Thus “the day of the Lord” is also called “the day of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>’s anger” (<a href="?bref=Zeph.2.2">Zep 2:2</a>).</p>
<p>Sometimes “the day of the Lord” is used in the OT to speak of a past judgment (<a href="?bref=Lam.2.22">Lam 2:22</a>). More often, an impending future judgment is in view (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.1-11">Jl 2:1-11</a>). Ultimately, though, the term refers to climactic future judgment of the world (<a href="?bref=Joel.3.14-21">Jl 3:14-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.4.5">Mal 4:5</a>). Often, prophecy of a near-future event and an end-time prophecy are merged—the immediate judgment being a preview of the final Day of the Lord. The prophecy of Isaiah against Babylon is an example (<a href="?bref=Isa.13.5-10">Is 13:5-10</a>). Jesus combined events described there with other prophecies to explain his second coming (<a href="?bref=Mark.13.24-37">Mk 13:24-37</a>). Another example is Joel’s prophecy of the Day of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Joel.1.15-2.11">Jl 1:15–2:11</a>). Though the prophet initially spoke of God’s judgment on Israel by a locust plague, that judgment prompted further pronouncements about a final Day of the Lord far beyond Joel’s time (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.14-17,31">2:14-17, 31</a>). That Day of the Lord extended even beyond the outpouring of the Holy Spirit at Pentecost predicted by Joel’s prophecy (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-32">Jl 2:28-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.16-21">Acts 2:16-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.12-13">Rv 6:12-13</a>). The NT uses the term exclusively to mean the end time.</p>
<p>The final Day of the Lord is characterized in the Bible as a day of gloom, darkness, and judgment. Associated with God’s judgment is language depicting changes in nature, especially a darkening of the sun, moon, and stars (<a href="?bref=Isa.13.10">Is 13:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.31">Jl 2:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.3.15">3:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.29">Mt 24:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.12">Rv 6:12</a>). Nations will be judged for their rebellion against God’s anointed people and king (<a href="?bref=Joel.3.19">Jl 3:19</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.2.1-12">Ps 2</a>). Israel is counseled not to be eager for that day, because it will also include judgment on the chosen nation (<a href="?bref=Amos.5.18-20">Am 5:18-20</a>). But the prophets promise that a believing “remnant” will be saved by looking to the Messiah they once rejected (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.32">Jl 2:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.12.10">Zec 12:10</a>). Following the judgment, the future Day of the Lord will be a time of prosperity, restoration, and blessing for Israel (<a href="?bref=Joel.3.18-21">Jl 3:18-21</a>).</p>
<p>The more explicit NT expressions—“the day of our Lord Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.8">1 Cor 1:8</a>), “the day of the Lord Jesus” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.5.5">1 Cor 5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.14">2 Cor 1:14</a>), and “the day of Christ” (<a href="?bref=Phil.1.10">Phil 1:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.16">2:16</a>)—are more personal and more positive. They point to final events related to Christian believers, who will not experience the wrath of God (<a href="?bref=1Thes.5.9">1 Thes 5:9</a>). When the Day of the Lord comes, the earth will be renewed and purified through a judgment of fire (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.10-13">2 Pt 3:10-13</a>). In the book of Revelation the final purging seems to come after the Millennium—that is, the 1,000-year reign of Christ (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.1">Rv 21:1</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Eschatology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eschatology</a>; <a href="?item=LastDays_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Last Days</a>; <a href="?item=LastJudgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Last Judgment</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>