<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DiasporaoftheJews">
  <title>Diaspora of the Jews*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DIASPORA OF THE JEWS*</p>
<p class="fl">Dispersion of Jewish people from Israel to foreign lands. <span class="greek">Diaspora</span><span class="ital">,</span> a Greek noun meaning a “sowing” or “scattering,” is regularly used in the Septuagint to mean “exile” (<a href="?bref=Jer.25.34">Jer 25:34</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.11.12">Is 11:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.23">Ez 20:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.10">Zep 3:10</a>). The word occurs twice in the NT (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.1">Jas 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.1">1 Pt 1:1</a>), referring to Christian Jews residing outside Palestine as a result of the several dispersions in Israel’s history. Diaspora sometimes refers to the exiled people, sometimes to the place of exile.</p>
<p class="h2" id="MajorDiasporas">Major Diasporas</p>
<p class="fl">From the end of the eighth century <span class="era">BC</span> onward, Jewish history was marked by several major dispersions.</p>
<p class="h3">Diaspora of the Northern Kingdom</p>
<p class="fl">After Solomon’s death, his kingdom broke in two. The northern kingdom of Israel sunk deeper into idolatry and immorality (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.14-18">2 Kgs 17:14-18</a>). Jeroboam, the first king of the divided Israel, established a pattern of apostasy (“falling away” from faith). Epitaphs for succeeding kings regularly recorded that the deceased ruler “did not turn from the sins of Jeroboam” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.31">10:31</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.11">13:11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.24">14:24</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.9,18,24,28">15:9, 18, 24, 28</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Assyria conquered the northern kingdom in 722 <span class="era">BC</span> and took over 27,000 Israelites into exile, as had been predicted (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.23">17:23</a>). They were settled in cities along the tributaries of the Euphrates River and in Media. Assyrians from cities around Babylon, in turn, colonized Israel (vv <a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.6,24">6, 24</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Diaspora of the Southern Kingdom</p>
<p class="fl">The southern kingdom of Judah suffered exile to the east in Babylonia and to the south in Egypt. The Babylonian king Nebuchadnezzar captured Judeans in several expeditions from 605 <span class="era">BC</span> to the fall of Jerusalem in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. The first deportation to Babylon took Jerusalem’s treasures from the temple and palace, and “all the princes, and all the mighty men of valor, ten thousand captives, and all the craftsmen and the smiths; none remained, except the poorest people of the land” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.12-14">2 Kgs 24:12-14</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Chr.36.10">2 Chr 36:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.52.29-30">Jer 52:29-30</a>).</p>
<p>A year later a second expedition focused on the rebellious Jewish vassal king Zedekiah and his sons (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.1,6-7">2 Kgs 25:1, 6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.52.4-11">Jer 52:4-11</a>). In the 19th year of Nebuchadnezzar’s reign, Babylonia struck Judah a third time, destroyed the temple and the king’s palace, and broke down the city’s walls. All but the very poorest people were carried away captive (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.8-21">2 Kgs 25:8-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.52.12-16">Jer 52:12-16</a>).</p>
<p>Shishak, king of Egypt, deported exiles from Judah as early as the 10th century <span class="era">BC</span>. Judah lost people and also temple gold at that time (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.25-26">1 Kgs 14:25-26</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.12.9">2 Chr 12:9</a>). About 400 years later, Johanan, a Judean, thought he could escape from Nebuchadnezzar by fleeing to Egypt. Johanan forced Jeremiah and a group of other Jews to go with him; they settled at Migdol, Tahpanhes, and Memphis. Nevertheless, the Babylonians pursued them, took control of Egypt, and executed many of the Jews there (<a href="?bref=Jer.43.5-44.30">Jer 43:5–44:30</a>). Records of property ownership and artifacts of an altar suggest that the few surviving exiles established permanent colonies in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Isa.19.18-19">Is 19:18-19</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Other Diasporas</p>
<p class="fl">The Egyptian king Ptolemy I (323–285 <span class="era">BC</span>) captured many Jews and carried them off to Egypt about 300 <span class="era">BC</span>. Those exiles populated Alexandria, a city thereafter noted as a center of both Greek and Jewish scholarship. Elsewhere large colonies of Jews were exported from Babylonia to Phrygia and Lydia by Antiochus III (the Great) of Syria (223–187 <span class="era">BC</span>). The Romans transplanted a sizable group of Jews to Rome. The Roman general Pompey took many there as slaves in the first century <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>How widely the Jews were scattered is suggested in the NT book of Acts, where Luke listed Jerusalem’s visitors: Parthians, Medes, Elamites, people from Mesopotamia, Judea, Cappadocia, Pontus, the province of Asia, Phrygia, Pamphylia, Egypt, and the areas of Libya toward Cyrene, visitors from Rome (both Jews and converts to Judaism), Cretans, and Arabians (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.9-11">Acts 2:9-11</a>). Those Jews of “the Diaspora” were in Jerusalem to celebrate the Feast of Pentecost.</p>
<p>Other Jewish communities were located in the Macedonian cities visited by the apostle Paul on his missionary journeys: Thessalonica, Berea, and Corinth (<a href="?bref=Acts.17.1,10">Acts 17:1, 10</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.2-4">18:2-4</a>). Around the middle of the first century <span class="era">AD</span>, the Roman emperor Claudius commanded all Jews to leave Rome (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.2">18:2</a>). Scholarly estimates of the Jewish population in Palestine at the time of Jesus’ birth range from about four to six million. The dispersion population numbered several times that of Palestine; communities with more than a million each flourished in Asia Minor, Mesopotamia, and Alexandria. Today, even with a national homeland, far more Jews still live outside Israel than inside.</p>
<p>In spite of their scatterings, Jews of various diasporas retained a basic unity with Palestinian Jews through several practices. (1) The great national feasts—Passover, Harvest, and Tabernacles (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.12-17">Ex 23:12-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.16.1-17">Dt 16:1-17</a>)—continued to be observed abroad. (2) The temple tax used for the temple’s upkeep (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.11-16">Ex 30:11-16</a>) was collected in foreign Jewish communities even after the temple had been destroyed. (3) All Jews everywhere recognized the authority of the Sanhedrin (the Jewish religious council) over them.</p>
<p class="h3">Positive Aspects</p>
<p class="fl">In exile the Jews tended to abandon the idol worship that had in part alienated them from God. Their exile led them to establish synagogues as institutions for prayer and education. Alexandrian Jews translated the OT Scriptures into Greek, at that time the international language. The result, called the Septuagint, was the version often cited by NT writers.</p>
<p>From the Christian point of view, the network of dispersed Jewish communities had a special significance. They provided strategic bases for the spread of Christianity, which quickly broke out of those communities and into the surrounding gentile world. Thus, God used the dispersions to bring the gospel to the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.11-15">Rom 1:11-15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.11-12">1 Cor 10:11-12</a>).</p>
<p>Finally, the arts, sciences, and humanities have been greatly enriched by the Jews scattered throughout Western culture. Few other peoples have endured so much ferocious ethnic bigotry as the Jews and yet rewarded that rejection with cultural gifts and graces of such excellence. Although the church of Jesus Christ has become a “new Israel” and a “chosen race” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Pt 2:9</a>), the testimony of history and of Scripture indicates that God still has a unique interest in the Jews.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=PostexilicPeriod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Postexilic Period</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>