<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DidacheTeaching">
  <title>Didache* (Teaching)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DIDACHE* (Teaching)</p>
<p class="fl">A manual of church discipline, otherwise known as “The Teaching of the Lord to the Gentiles through the Twelve Apostles.” Its origin and date are difficult to determine precisely, but scholars generally agree that it was written in Syria or Palestine during the late first century or early second century. The practices described in the manual were established much earlier, however. The Didache (which means “teaching”) was compiled from various sources that detail the traditions of well-established church communities.</p>
<p>This handbook contains a number of texts that were intended to instruct new converts in the Christian faith. Chapters 1–6 present the “Two Ways” of life and death, based on <a href="?bref=Deut.30.15">Deuteronomy 30:15</a>. This section resembles many Jewish teachings and may find its source in the apocalyptic writings of the Qumran community (where the Dead Sea Scrolls were compiled). The manual also contains several parallels with the Epistle of Barnabas and the Shepherd of Hermas. These first chapters include a distinctly Christian collection of sayings that resemble Jesus’ teachings about loving one’s neighbor (as recorded by Matthew and Luke).</p>
<p>Chapters 7–10 contain instructions for baptism, fasting, prayer, and the Eucharist. Baptism is to be performed “in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit”; fasting is to be practiced on Wednesdays and Fridays, in contrast with the Jews who fasted on Mondays and Thursdays; and the Lord’s Prayer (with the doxology) is to be recited daily. The prayers in chapters 9 and 10 are based on Jewish table prayers, so it is not clear whether they are meant for the Eucharist or for a common church meal (sometimes called a “love feast”). The prayers contain no references to the words of Jesus at the Last Supper, and they place the blessing of the cup before the blessing of the bread (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.16">1 Cor 10:16</a>). The Didache does note that believers are not required to use these model prayers.</p>
<p>Chapters 11–15 give instructions for church leadership. They discuss the marks of true apostles and prophets, who are referred to as “high priests,” and the church’s responsibilities toward them. The Didache ends with a prediction of the imminent return of Christ.</p>
<p>The Jewishness of the Didache may reflect the influence of the Jerusalem church’s teachings. The description of church leadership, however, seems to be drawn from Paul, who details the roles of apostles, prophets, and teachers in 1 Corinthians. The Didache also stresses the function of the prophets. The teachings of the Didache reflect those of a church in the developmental stages of its institutions and practices. The church still appears to be developing characteristics that clearly distinguish it from Judaism. The Didache was highly regarded by the early church. Eusebius listed it with the orthodox writings that were eventually excluded from the NT canon.</p>
  </body>
</item>