<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Disciple">
  <title>Disciple</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DISCIPLE</p>
<p class="fl">Someone who follows another person or another way of life and who submits himself to the discipline (teaching) of that leader or way. In the Bible the term “disciple” is found almost exclusively in the Gospels and the book of Acts, the only exceptions being <a href="?bref=Isa.8.16">Isaiah 8:16</a> and less directly <a href="?bref=Isa.50.4">Isaiah 50:4</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.54.13">54:13</a>, where the same Hebrew word is translated “learned” and “taught,” respectively. Yet clearly wherever there is a teacher and those taught, the idea of discipleship is present.</p>
<p>In the Gospels the immediate followers of Jesus, called by his authority from a wide variety of circumstances, not only the Twelve but all those who were sympathetic to his teaching and committed to him, are called “disciples.” The calling of these disciples took place at a time when other teachers had their disciples, most notably the Pharisees (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.18">Mk 2:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.33">Lk 5:33</a>) and John the Baptist (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.14">Mt 9:14</a>). It is evident from the practice of John the Baptist that different leaders called for different disciplines from their followers. John’s way was considerably more ascetic in character than that of Jesus; however, it too involved not only teaching regarding conduct and manner of life, but also a distinctive pattern of praying (<a href="?bref=Luke.11.1">Lk 11:1</a>).</p>
<p>The disciples of Jesus had a unique experience. Not only did they benefit from the immediate teaching of Jesus, his looks and tones of voice (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.21">Mk 10:21</a>) as well as his words, but they were also witnesses of the unfolding drama of redemption that had Christ as its center. They followed a teacher who embodied the substance of that teaching. The first disciples could be taught by Christ only little by little, not only because of the need to remove their misconceptions (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.21">Mt 16:21</a>), but also because the full significance of what Jesus said and did could not be most fully appreciated until after the events of his death and resurrection (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.9">Mt 28:9</a>). It is not surprising that the period of “discipling” covered the time before and after Christ’s death and resurrection, and also after Pentecost, when the Holy Spirit taught the disciples about matters that they could not “bear” while Jesus remained on earth (<a href="?bref=John.16.12">Jn 16:12</a>).</p>
<p>Groups of Jesus’ first disciples, both the Twelve and the Seventy (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.20">Mt 26:20</a>: <a href="?bref=Luke.10.1">Lk 10:1</a>), received his teaching, taught others in turn (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.1-11">Lk 10:1-11</a>), and were given power to heal (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.1">Mt 10:1</a>). They were also to proclaim the message of salvation through Christ. Yet the Twelve were given special prominence, and with the exception of Judas Iscariot (whose place was taken by Matthias, <a href="?bref=Acts.1.26">Acts 1:26</a>), they became the foundation teachers of the newly emerging Christian church. Their authority in the church, given by Christ (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.19">Mt 16:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.28.16-20">28:16-20</a>), was to be characterized by a unique style of self-giving service (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.24-30">Lk 22:24-30</a>). To this group of disciples, who came to be known as the apostles (though this term is occasionally given to a wider application), Saul of Tarsus was added. At his conversion on the road to Damascus, he saw the risen Lord and was immediately commissioned by Christ (<a href="?bref=Gal.1.12,16">Gal 1:12, 16</a>) as the apostle to the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.15">Acts 9:15</a>).</p>
<p>At the time of his ascension Christ commissioned the first disciples to “make disciples of all nations” (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.19">Mt 28:19</a>); hence, the term “disciple” is also used in the book of Acts to describe believers, those who confess Christ. Though they have not been directly called by Christ himself, such disciples are called by Christ’s Spirit through the message delivered by the first disciples; disciples called later are not in any sense inferior to the first disciples, even though they are less privileged. It was proper for early Christians to be called disciples of Jesus of Nazareth or simply “the disciples” (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.1-2,7">Acts 6:1-2, 7</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.36">9:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.26">11:26</a>) because they were carrying on the teaching of Jesus and living the life he had exemplified. They were thus recognized as a “school” or living community that embodied the teaching of their “master” in practice. The book of 1 John emphasizes that only those who keep Christ’s commandments show real love for God (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.3-6">1 Jn 2:3-6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.10-11">3:10-11</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>