<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Nadab">
  <title>Nadab</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NADAB</p>
<p class="list">1. Eldest son of Aaron and Elisheba, the daughter of Amminadab (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.23">Ex 6:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.2">Nm 3:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.24.1">1 Chr 24:1</a>), who became one of Israel’s first priests together with his brothers and father. He participated in the ratification of the covenant with God on Mt Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.1,9">Ex 24:1, 9</a>) and was ordained to the priesthood (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.1">28:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Nadab and his brother Abihu, Aaron’s second son, died because they offered “strange fire” to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.1-2">Lv 10:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.4">Nm 3:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.24.2">1 Chr 24:2</a>). Incense offered in the morning usually preceded the cutting up of the sacrifice. In this case “fire from the Lord devoured them.” The offering of “strange fire” does not appear anywhere else in the Bible.</p>
<p class="list-text">Rabbis have offered various explanations of the offense committed by Nadab and Abihu. Since an admonition against drinking wine in the tent of meeting follows this tragedy (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.9">Lv 10:9</a>), an early tradition held that the brothers were drunk. Death was the penalty for any priest drinking in this sacred tent.</p>
<p class="list-text">An interesting point arises in the instructions that Moses gave to the grieving father of Nadab and Abihu. Moses exhorted Aaron not to mourn or to interrupt his priestly functions. Since Aaron had been sanctified by the sacred anointing oil, he had to continue serving God. He was not allowed to go out of the door of the tent “lest he die.” Instead, the rest of Israel mourned for Nadab and Abihu (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.3-7">Lv 10:3-7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Son of Jeroboam, whom he succeeded to the throne of Israel (909–908 <span class="era">BC</span>). Nadab ruled two years (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.20">1 Kgs 14:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.25">15:25</a>), coming to power in the second year of Asa’s reign in Judah; he was succeeded in the third year of Asa’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.28">15:28</a>). His rule may have been arranged before the death of Jeroboam, for he surely recognized the dangers of the charismatic ideal that continued among the northern tribes. However, Nadab was not successful in stabilizing the kingdom. To gain the acclamation of the army, he went into battle against the Philistines at Gibbethon, about two and a half miles (4 kilometers) southwest of Gezer. Baasha from the tribe of Issachar, presumably a military officer, assassinated Nadab and all his sons and usurped the throne. So he fulfilled the prophecy predicted by Ahijah the Shilonite against the house of Jeroboam (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.29">29</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Jerahmeelite, the son of Shammai and grandson of Onam, and the great-grandson of Jerahmeel. Nadab in turn had two sons, Seled and Appaim (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.26-30">1 Chr 2:26-30</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Son of Jeiel and Maacah, a Gibeonite (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.30">1 Chr 8:30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.36">9:36</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>