<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NahumPerson">
  <title>Nahum (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NAHUM (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. A prophet of Judah whose name means “consolation” or “consoler.” This name fits his message, as he wrote to encourage the people of Judah while they were being oppressed by the Assyrians (<a href="?bref=Nah.1.1">Na 1:1</a>). Other than being the prophet who wrote the book of Nahum, nothing is known of him except that he came from the village of Elkosh. Its exact location is unknown, but four suggestions have been made. First, it was the town of Alqush, near Mosul on the Tigris River just north of Nineveh. A tradition declares this to be the site of Nahum’s tomb, but it is first mentioned by Masius in the 16th century. The tomb and its location have no archaeological confirmation, and its authenticity is highly suspect. Second, Jerome recounts a Jewish tradition identifying it with “a village in Galilee called ‘Helcesaei’ ” (Helcesei or Elcesi), and writes, “A very small one, indeed, and containing in its ruins hardly any traces of ancient buildings, but one which is well known to the Jews and was also pointed out to me by my guide.” This village is located about 15 miles (24.1 kilometers) northwest of the Sea of Galilee. Third, on the northern edge of the Sea of Galilee rest the ruins of Capernaum, meaning “village of Nahum.” But there is no proof that this name goes back to the prophet. Finally, some believe it should be identified with Elcesi, near Bet-gabre, about halfway between Gaza and Jerusalem in the territory of Judah. Internal evidence seems to support this position (<a href="?bref=Nah.1.15">Na 1:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">It is entirely possible that Nahum may have been a member of the northern tribes but migrated to Judah after the conquest of 722 <span class="era">BC</span> and ministered there.</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=NahumBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Nahum, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetProphetess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophet, Prophetess</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Ancestor of Jesus, according to Luke’s genealogy (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.25">Lk 3:25</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>