<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NamesSignificanceof">
  <title>Names, Significance of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NAMES, Significance of</p>
<p class="fl">In biblical times names were given in order to express something about a person, or to express something through him, and not simply to hang a convenient label around his neck. At least seven motivations appear in the choice of names:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. To record some aspect of a person’s birth. Moses was so called by his adoptive mother because he was drawn from the water, the sound of the name recalling a Hebrew verb “to draw out” (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.10">Ex 2:10</a>). The circumstances surrounding their births gave Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.26">Gn 25:26</a>) and also Samuel (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.20">1 Sm 1:20</a>) their names. In Samuel’s case it is interesting to note that his name, meaning “heard by God,” records not the offering of prayer but the hearing and answering of it. Something of the deeper and more far-reaching implications of naming is seen in the fact that while the names Jacob and Samuel arise from birth circumstances, they also reveal in advance the person the child will become: Jacob the sneaky opportunist (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.27.36">Gn 27:36</a>), Samuel the man of prayer (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.5-9">1 Sm 7:5-9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.8.6,21">8:6, 21</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.12.19-23">12:19-23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. To express parental reactions to the birth. Isaac means “laughter” (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.17.17">Gn 17:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.18.12">18:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.21.3-6">21:3-6</a>). Nabal (<a href="?bref=1Sam.25.25">1 Sm 25:25</a>), which means “fool,” must have been the essence of a mother’s prayer—“Let him not be a fool”—though sadly he was! Abimelech (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.31">Jgs 8:31</a>) means “My father is king” and may express a secret ambition of Gideon’s, at variance with his public testimony (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.22-23">Jgs 8:22-23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. To secure the solidarity of the family. This may explain the proposal to call the baby Zechariah in <a href="?bref=Luke.1.59">Luke 1:59</a>.</p>
<p class="list">4. To reveal the nature of the person, his function, or some other significant thing about him. The preeminent example of this is Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">Mt 1:21</a>), named for his saving vocation. Isaiah seems to have seen his own name as significant of his message “the Lord saves” (see <a href="?bref=Isa.8.18">Is 8:18</a> <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg).</p>
<p class="list">5. To communicate God’s message. Isaiah (see <a href="?bref=Isa.7.3">Is 7:3</a>) called his first son Shear-jashub (“a remnant shall return”) in order to embody the double-sided thrust of his message: as a result of faithlessness, the people will be reduced to a mere remnant (“only a remnant shall return”); as a result of God’s faithfulness, his people will be preserved in life (“a remnant shall indeed return”). He called his second boy Maher-shalal-hash-baz (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.3">8:3</a>), (“speed-prey-haste-spoil”), indicating the certainty of the imminent onset of a victorious foe.</p>
<p class="list">6. To establish religious affiliation. All the names in the Bible with the endings <span class="hebrew">-iah</span> (alternatively <span class="hebrew">-jah</span>) or <span class="hebrew">-el</span> (e.g., Jeremiah, Nathanael) are in fact statements with “the Lord” <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">-yah</span><span class="ital">)</span> or “God” <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">-el</span><span class="ital">)</span> as subject. For example, Adonijah (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.4">2 Sm 3:4</a>) means “the Lord is Sovereign”; Nathanael (<a href="?bref=John.1.47">Jn 1:47</a>) means “God gave.” Such names were often chosen in times of religious decline in order to affirm the true faith of the parents.</p>
<p class="list">7. To affirm authority over another. In the ancient Near East, the naming of an object or person implied power and authority over what was named (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.19-20">Gn 2:19-20</a>). Thus, a person not knowing another’s name could do neither harm nor good to that person (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.12,17">Ex 33:12, 17</a>). In the ancient world a name described the person or his work in some way. When the individual or his situation changed, so did the name, as with Abram (Abraham) and Jacob (Israel). Pharaoh, as master of the patriarch Joseph, changed Joseph’s name when his status altered, calling him Zaphenath-paneah (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.45">Gn 41:45</a>). When Eliakim was made king of Judah, the pharaoh changed the Jewish king’s name to Jehoiakim (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.34">2 Kgs 23:34</a>). In captivity, Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah were forced to change their names to Belteshazzar, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego by order of the eunuch (<a href="?bref=Dan.1.6-7">Dn 1:6-7</a>).</p>
<p class="sp">In the NT, John the Baptist was named by an angel who represented God, and similarly Jesus was given his name by an angel. The naming of those children symbolized God’s authority over John the Baptist and his special relationship as Father to Jesus.</p>
<p class="h2" id="NewNames">New Names</p>
<p class="fl">The ability of the name to reveal the nature or status of the person who bears it is well illustrated in the biblical practice of giving new names, as when Sarai became Sarah (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.15">Gn 17:15</a>). Three motivations are possible:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. The new name replaces the old in order to signify the bestowal of powers not hitherto possessed. In this case the new name is equivalent to the experience of regeneration. The childless Abram becomes the “father of a multitude of nations,” Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.5">Gn 17:5</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. The new name may indicate a new character and status with God, as when Jacob the trickster became Israel the man of power with God (<a href="?bref=Gen.32.27">Gn 32:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.12.3-4">Hos 12:3-4</a>); thus also, Simon became Peter (<a href="?bref=John.1.42">Jn 1:42</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. The new name may cement a new loyalty in the place of an old. Daniel the captive was given the name Belteshazzar, incorporating the name Bel, one of the gods of Babylon—presumably to turn him from the God of his fathers to that of his captors (<a href="?bref=Dan.1.7">Dn 1:7</a>).</p>
<p class="sp"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=GodNamesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Names of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>