<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Nathan">
  <title>Nathan</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NATHAN</p>
<p class="list">1. Son of David by Bathsheba, the third son to be born in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.14">2 Sm 5:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.3.5">1 Chr 3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.14.4">14:4</a>). Nathan, Solomon’s older brother, is featured in the apocalyptic oracle of <a href="?bref=Zech.12.12">Zechariah 12:12</a> and Christ’s line of descent via Joseph (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.31">Lk 3:31</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. One of the early prophets and adviser of David. When David’s military campaigns were almost completed, he shared with Nathan his desire to erect a suitable dwelling place for God. Nathan’s immediate reaction was favorable, but on receiving direct instructions from the Lord, he countermanded his initial approval. He foretold that one of David’s sons would build God a house, and that God would establish a house (dynasty) for David through his son Solomon. The prophecy includes not only the Davidic line but also the messianic king. Nathan’s oracle, therefore, was of vital importance, since it dealt with two great institutions, the temple and the Davidic monarchy (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.1-7">2 Sm 7:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.17.1-15">1 Chr 17:1-15</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">During the Ammonite war, David, having fathered an illegitimate child, tried to cover his sin by involving the woman’s husband, Uriah (<a href="?bref=2Sam.11.1-13">2 Sm 11:1-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.23.39">23:39</a>). When this attempt failed, he had Joab, the general of the army, engineer Uriah’s death, whereupon David took Bathsheba openly as his wife (<a href="?bref=2Sam.11.14-27">11:14-27</a>). Nathan confronted the king, courageously exposing the enormity of David’s crime by a parable that provoked the king’s righteous anger and turned the finger of condemnation upon David himself (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.1-9">12:1-9</a>). Nathan foretold the fearful consequences for David’s family resulting from his sin and evil example (vv <a href="?bref=2Sam.12.10-12">10-12</a>). This prophecy was fulfilled in rape, the deaths of three of David’s sons, and civil war (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.1-18.33">2 Sm 13–18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.1-53">1 Kgs 1</a>). Bathsheba’s child also would not live (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.14">2 Sm 12:14</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">When David was near death, one of his sons, Adonijah, seized power (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.1,10">1 Kgs 1:1, 10</a>). Nathan prompted Bathsheba to remind David of an earlier promise concerning Solomon’s succession, supporting her by his own timely intervention (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.10-27">10-27</a>). David immediately authorized Solomon’s coronation (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.28-53">28-53</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Nathan was an important chronicler (<a href="?bref=1Chr.29.29">1 Chr 29:29</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.9.29">2 Chr 9:29</a>). With David he played a vital part in developing the musical aspects of temple worship (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.25">2 Chr 29:25</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Man of Zobah and the father of Igal, one of David’s 30 heroes (<a href="?bref=2Sam.23.36">2 Sm 23:36</a>). He was possibly the Nathan noted as the brother of Joel (<a href="?bref=1Chr.11.38">1 Chr 11:38</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Father of two important court officials (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.5">1 Kgs 4:5</a>); probably either the prophet or David’s son.</p>
<p class="list">5. Descendant of Judah, in the clan of Jerahmeel, the son of Attai and the father of Zabad (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.36">1 Chr 2:36</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. One of a deputation sent by Ezra to secure Levitical reinforcements for the Israelites returning to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.16">Ezr 8:16</a>). Possibly Nathan was among those who covenanted to divorce their foreign wives (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.39">10:39</a>), but the name, meaning “gift,” was a very common one.</p>
  </body>
</item>