<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Nazarene">
  <title>Nazarene</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NAZARENE</p>
<p class="fl">Native or inhabitant of Nazareth, a NT town in lower Galilee.</p>
<p>Nazareth was Jesus’ hometown during the first 30 years of his life. Since the name Jesus was a common name among the Jews, and since surnames were not used, perhaps the designation Nazarene differentiated Jesus of Nazareth from others with the same name (see Greek texts of <a href="?bref=Matt.27.16-17">Mt 27:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.45">Acts 7:45</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.4.11">Col 4:11</a>; and <a href="?bref=Heb.4.8">Heb 4:8</a>, where the name Jesus refers to other men).</p>
<p>In the original texts, the designation Jesus the Nazarene was used by demons (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.24">Mk 1:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.34">Lk 4:34</a>), the crowd outside Jericho (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.47">Mk 10:47</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.18.37">Lk 18:37</a>), a servant girl (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.67">Mk 14:67</a>), soldiers (<a href="?bref=John.18.5-7">Jn 18:5-7</a>), Pilate (<a href="?bref=John.19.19">Jn 19:19</a>), the two disciples on the road to Emmaus (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.19">Lk 24:19</a>), and the angel at the tomb (<a href="?bref=Mark.16.6">Mk 16:6</a>).</p>
<p>The apostles in Acts used the designation to identify Jesus. Peter speaks of Jesus the Nazarene in his sermon on the day of Pentecost (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.22">Acts 2:22</a>), and at the temple gate in a subsequent healing (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.6">3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.10">4:10</a>). Paul identifies Jesus as such in <a href="?bref=Acts.26.9">Acts 26:9</a>.</p>
<p>One hostile reference to the name is in <a href="?bref=Acts.6.14">Acts 6:14</a>. The false witnesses against Stephen accused him before the Sanhedrin of saying, “This Nazarene, Jesus, will destroy this place [temple] and alter the customs that Moses handed down to us” (see Greek). Another antagonistic reference is in <a href="?bref=Acts.24.5">Acts 24:5</a>, the only reference to Jesus’ followers as Nazarenes. Tertullus accused Paul, saying, “For we have found him to be a troublemaker, a man who is constantly inciting the Jews throughout the world to riots and rebellions against the Roman government. He is a ringleader of the sect known as the Nazarenes” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>With regard to the name “Nazarene,” <a href="?bref=Matt.2.23">Matthew 2:23</a> has always been problematic: “So they went and lived in a town called Nazareth. This fulfilled what was spoken by the prophets concerning the Messiah: ‘He will be called a Nazarene’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). No OT prophecy directly states that the Messiah would be called a Nazarene. Some scholars relate Matthew’s reference to <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1">Isaiah 11:1</a>, which speaks of the Messiah as a Branch, a Hebrew term derived from the same root as “Nazareth.” Others suggest that the OT prophecies concern the despising and reviling of the Messiah as having been thought by others to be a Nazarene, when it was well known that the Messiah was supposed to come from Bethlehem, the city of David. Of course, that is where Jesus was born, but he was raised in Nazareth and subsequently was known as a Nazarene and thereby ridiculed. Thus, the prophecy was fulfilled when some of his contemporaries called him a Nazarene, from the despised town of Nazareth (<a href="?bref=John.1.46">Jn 1:46</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.13.54">Mt 13:54</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.2-3">Mk 6:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.22">Lk 4:22</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Nazareth_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Nazareth</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>