<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NebuchadnezzarNebuchadrezzar">
  <title>Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadrezzar*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NEBUCHADNEZZAR, NEBUCHADREZZAR*</p>
<p class="fl">Babylonian king (605–562 <span class="era">BC</span>) who captured and destroyed Jerusalem in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. He was the son of Nabopolassar and the foremost ruler of the Neo-Babylonian Empire (612–539 <span class="era">BC</span>); his name is alternately spelled Nebuchadrezzar in Jeremiah and Ezekiel (see <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg).</p>
<p>Nebuchadnezzar states that he conquered all of “Hatti-country,” which is a term used for all of Palestine and Syria, including Judah. Jehoiakim had been made king of Judah by Pharaoh Neco (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.34">2 Kgs 23:34</a>) and initially submitted to Nebuchadnezzar (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.2">24:2</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Dan.1.1-2">Dn 1:1-2</a>), but three years later rebelled. Jehoiakim died and his son Jehoiachin succeeded to the throne (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.6">2 Kgs 24:6</a>); however, he reigned for only three months. Nebuchadnezzar came to Jerusalem in 598 <span class="era">BC</span> and took Jehoiachin captive to Babylon (vv <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.10-17">10-17</a>). He replaced Jehoiachin with his Uncle Mattaniah, whom he renamed Zedekiah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.17">2 Kgs 24:17</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.36.10">2 Chr 36:10</a>).</p>
<p>Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.20">2 Kgs 24:20</a>). Nebuchadnezzar’s armies besieged the city of Jerusalem and captured Zedekiah. He was brought to Nebuchadnezzar at Riblah, where Zedekiah’s sons were slain before his eyes. He was then blinded, bound, and taken captive to Babylon (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.6-7">25:6-7</a>). The temple was looted and burned, the city walls were dismantled, and the city was plundered and razed (vv <a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.9-17">9-17</a>). The leading people of the nation were either killed or taken into captivity.</p>
<p>The remnant of the people in Judah were put under the charge of Gedaliah, the appointed governor. After his treacherous murder, the Jews fled to Egypt. Both Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.43.8-13">Jer 43:8-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.46.13-24">46:13-24</a>) and Ezekiel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.29.1-32.32">Ez 29–32</a>) prophesied that Nebuchadnezzar would invade Egypt. Josephus gives the date as the 23d year of Nebuchadnezzar (582/581 <span class="era">BC</span>), but a fragmentary historical inscription dating to the 37th year of Nebuchadnezzar (568/567 <span class="era">BC</span>) indicates that the defeat of Egypt occurred during the reign of Amasis.</p>
<p>Nebuchadnezzar’s military successes were in many respects overshadowed by his building activities in Babylon. The king voiced his pride when he declared, “Is not this great Babylon, which I have built by my mighty power as a royal residence and for the glory of my majesty?” (<a href="?bref=Dan.4.30">Dn 4:30</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The hanging gardens were acclaimed as one of the seven wonders of the ancient world. They were built on terraces in an effort to cure his Median queen of her homesickness for the mountains of her homeland.</p>
<p>The events of the book of Daniel center on Babylon and Nebuchadnezzar. Daniel was among the captives taken to Babylon in 605 <span class="era">BC</span>. Nebuchadnezzar became aware of Daniel when the king had a dream that none of his occult experts could interpret (ch <a href="?bref=Dan.2.1-49">2</a>). The Lord gave to Daniel the interpretation of the dream; the human image that the king saw in his dream represented the various governments from the New Babylonian Empire to the reign of the Messiah.</p>
<p>Nebuchadnezzar set up a large human statue that was 90 feet (27.4 meters) high and 9 feet (2.7 meters) wide. Failure to worship the image would incur death by fire. The three compatriots of Daniel refused and were thrown into a furnace from which the Lord delivered them unhurt (ch <a href="?bref=Dan.3.1-30">3</a>).</p>
<p>The king had another dream about a great tree that was cut down but later sprouted from the stump (<a href="?bref=Dan.4.4-27">4:4-27</a>). Again the “wise men of Babylon” could not give the interpretation, but Daniel informed the king that the dream prophesied a humbling experience lasting seven years as a consequence of the king’s pride (vv <a href="?bref=Dan.4.28-33">28-33</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BabylonBabylonia_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Babylon, Babylonia</a>; <a href="?item=DanielBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Daniel, Book of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>