<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Nethinim">
  <title>Nethinim*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NETHINIM*</p>
<p class="fl">Term appearing only in the books written after Israel’s return from exile (1 Chronicles, Ezra, Nehemiah). <span class="hebrew">Nethinim</span> derives from the verb <span class="hebrew">nathan</span><span class="ital">,</span> “to give, set apart, dedicate,” and means “those given” or “those set apart or dedicated.” The Septuagint translates the word <span class="greek">dedomenoi</span><span class="ital">.</span> Some recent translators have followed Josephus (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 11.5.1) by referring to them as “temple slaves.” The <span class="sc">nlt</span> reads “Temple assistants.”</p>
<p>Before the exile, the Nethinim were active in temple service. <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.2">First Chronicles 9:2</a> lists them with the priests and Levites who took possession of their allotted cities. Their listed order—priests, Levites, and Nethinim—suggests their subordinate role to the Levites (see also <a href="?bref=Neh.7.73">Neh 7:73</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.11.3,20-21">11:3, 20-21</a>). They returned from exile as temple personnel (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.43,58">Ezr 2:43, 58</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.7,24">7:7, 24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.8.17,20">8:17, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.46,60">Neh 7:46, 60</a>). They had their dwelling in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.7">Ezr 7:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.3.31">Neh 3:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.11.21">11:21</a>) and joined in the repair of the walls (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.26">Neh 3:26</a>).</p>
<p>The identification of the Nethinim is not absolutely certain. <a href="?bref=Num.31.47">Numbers 31:47</a> records that the Levites received captives who were assigned laborious and menial tasks. When the Gibeonites were accepted within Israel as servants, they too were appointed as water carriers and wood choppers for the entire community and the altar of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.9-27">Jos 9:9-27</a>). David augmented the number of tabernacle servants by assigning captives taken in war to these duties (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.20">Ezr 8:20</a>). At the completion of the temple, the temple services called for more workers, and Solomon added to their number. This new group became known as “Solomon’s men.” Ezra records that from the Nethinim, 392 returned from exile to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.58">2:58</a>) and performed the work in the rebuilt temple that had been done by their ancestors before the exile. Considered full members of the restored covenant community, the Nethinim devoted themselves to God (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.28">Neh 10:28</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>