<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NewHeavensandNewEarth">
  <title>New Heavens and New Earth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NEW HEAVENS AND NEW EARTH</p>
<p class="fl">Concept of a new or renewed universe first found in the book of Isaiah. God declares, “For behold, I create new heavens and a new earth; and the former things shall not be remembered or come into mind. . . . For as the new heavens and the new earth which I will make shall remain before me . . . so shall your descendants and your name remain” (<a href="?bref=Isa.65.17">Is 65:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.66.22">66:22</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Some scholars think that long before Isaiah’s time there existed among many ancient peoples the belief that the end of human history would correspond to its beginning and therefore some sort of universal restoration would take place. The world renewal taught in Scripture regards the event as supernatural and as taking place in a different and higher sphere.</p>
<p>That God is Creator of the heavens and earth is basic to all biblical theology. “In ages past you laid the foundation of the earth, and the heavens are the work of your hands” (<a href="?bref=Ps.102.25">Ps 102:25</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). If God created the heavens and earth, then it is entirely appropriate that, once they have served their purpose, God may do with them what he wishes. “Even they will perish, but you remain forever; they will wear out like old clothing. You will change them like a garment, and they will fade away” (v <a href="?bref=Ps.102.26">26</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The same metaphor is found in <a href="?bref=Isa.51.6">Isaiah 51:6</a>, which speaks of the earth wearing out like a garment.</p>
<p>Scripture (quoted below from the <span class="sc">nlt</span>) gives considerable attention to the passing away of the old order, speaking of a future time when heaven and earth will disappear (<a href="?bref=Isa.34.4">Is 34:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.51.6">51:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.35">Mt 24:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1">Rv 21:1</a>). A number of related phrases portray the same idea: “And this world is fading away” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.17">1 Jn 2:17</a>); “They [the heavens and earth] will wear out like old clothing” (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.11">Heb 1:11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.102.26">Ps 102:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.51.6">Is 51:6</a>); “But the day of the Lord will come as unexpectedly as a thief. Then the heavens will pass away with a terrible noise, and everything in them will disappear in fire, and the earth and everything on it will be exposed to judgment” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.10">2 Pt 3:10</a>). This consummation by fire will take place at the time of final judgment. It will be “the day when God will set the heavens on fire and the elements will melt away in the flames” (v <a href="?bref=2Pet.3.12">12</a>).</p>
<p>This judgment, which brings to a close the old order, clears the way for new heavens and a new earth. Peter continues, “But we are looking forward to the new heavens and new earth he has promised, a world where everyone is right with God” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.13">2 Pt 3:13</a>). It will be so wonderful that no one will even remember the old (<a href="?bref=Isa.65.17">Is 65:17</a>). Peter, preaching in Solomon’s Colonnade, says that Jesus will remain in heaven until the time comes for establishing all that God spoke by his holy prophets (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.21">Acts 3:21</a>). This recovery or renewal is eagerly awaited by the created order. Paul writes, “For all creation is waiting eagerly for that future day when God will reveal who his children really are” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.19">Rom 8:19</a>) because “all creation anticipates the day when it will join God’s children in glorious freedom from death and decay” (v <a href="?bref=Rom.8.21">21</a>).</p>
<p>The heaven that will be renewed is not the heaven of God’s presence, but the heaven of human existence, the starry expanse that constitutes the universe. In the book of Revelation we learn that the new Jerusalem comes down from heaven to earth (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.2,10">Rv 21:2, 10</a>) and forms the eternal dwelling place of God and his people. The new earth will be a place of perfect righteousness (<a href="?bref=Isa.51.6">Is 51:6</a>), divine kindness (<a href="?bref=Isa.54.10">54:10</a>), eternal relationship to God (<a href="?bref=Isa.66.22">66:22</a>), and total freedom from sin (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.21">Rom 8:21</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Eschatology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eschatology</a>; <a href="?item=Heaven_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Heaven</a>; <a href="?item=KingdomofGodKingdomofHeaven_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Kingdom of God, Kingdom of Heaven</a>; <a href="?item=New_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New</a>; <a href="?item=NewCreationNewCreature_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New Creation, New Creature</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>