<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NumbersBookof">
  <title>Numbers, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NUMBERS, Book of</p>
<p class="fl">Fourth book of the English Bible. Its title is the English translation of the Latin Vulgate title, <span class="ital">Numeri.</span> The book takes this name from the fact that several rosters of various kinds are recorded in the book, specifically, the two army musters in chapters <a href="?bref=Num.1.1-54">1</a> and <a href="?bref=Num.26.1-65">26</a>, the tribal camp and march arrangements in chapter <a href="?bref=Num.2.1-34">2</a>, and the Levitical censuses in chapters <a href="?bref=Num.3.1-51">3</a> and <a href="?bref=Num.4.1-49">4</a>.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Purpose">Purpose</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheologicalTeaching">Theological Teaching</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">The question of the authorship of Numbers is part of the larger question of the authorship of the Pentateuch. Until the appearance of the higher-critical documentary theories of the 19th century, the Mosaic authorship of the Pentateuch was almost universally held by both Jews and Christians alike. This time-honored tradition is supported by the Pentateuch itself (e.g., <a href="?bref=Exod.17.14">Ex 17:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.24.4">24:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.27">34:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.33.2">Nm 33:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.31.9,24">Dt 31:9, 24</a>), the rest of the OT (e.g., <a href="?bref=Josh.23.6">Jos 23:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.3.4">Jgs 3:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.4.4">Mal 4:4</a>), as well as Jesus’ teaching (e.g., <a href="?bref=John.5.46-47">Jn 5:46-47</a>), and the rest of the NT (e.g., <a href="?bref=Acts.28.23">Acts 28:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.10.19">Rom 10:19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.9.9">1 Cor 9:9</a>). Although discrepancies in the Pentateuch were widely and openly acknowledged, nevertheless Moses, the 15th-century <span class="era">BC</span> lawgiver, was affirmed as the primary author of the Pentateuchal literature.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="h3">Sinai Peninsula</p>
<p class="fl">The historical background of Numbers begins primarily in the geographical region of the Sinai Peninsula of the mid-second millennium <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The Sinai Peninsula is in the shape of an inverted triangle with the base on the north. It is approximately 240 miles (386.2 kilometers) long from north to south and 175 miles (281.6 kilometers) wide at the northern base, with an area of approximately 22,000 square miles (56,980 square kilometers). It is bounded on the north by the Mediterranean Sea and the southern border of Canaan, on the west by the Bitter Lakes and the Gulf of Suez, and on the east by the Arabah and the Gulf of Aqaba. Beginning in the north at the Mediterranean coast and moving south, for about 15 miles (24.1 kilometers) the soil is sandy. South of this coastal plain is a high plateau (Et-Tih) of gravel and limestone (about 2,500 feet, or 762 meters, above sea level), stretching south into the peninsula for approximately 150 miles (241.4 kilometers). Rising above the plateau at this point is a granite mountain formation with peaks up to 8,000 feet (2,438.4 meters) above sea level. In this mountainous region at the apex of the peninsular triangle, Jebel Musa (7,363 feet, or 2,244.2 meters, high), the traditional site where Israel camped before Mt Sinai and Moses received the law, rises above the plain.</p>
<p>The peninsula itself is comprised of five wilderness areas. In the north and immediately east of the land of Goshen is the approximately 40-mile- or 64.4-kilometer-wide wilderness of Shur, which runs past the River of Egypt (Wadi el-Arish) to the region of Kadesh-barnea and northeast to Beersheba. East of this region is the wilderness of Zin, extending east from the wilderness of Shur to the southern tip of the Dead Sea. Kadesh-barnea is located on its southern border (<a href="?bref=Num.20.1">Nm 20:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.33.36">33:36</a>). South of the wilderness of Shur is the wilderness of Etham, and east of this wilderness in the east-central region of Sinai is the great wilderness of Paran (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.19">Dt 1:19</a>). Kadesh-barnea is on the northern border of this territory (<a href="?bref=Num.13.26">Nm 13:26</a>). In this area the Israelites spent 38 of their 40 years of wandering. Southwest of the wilderness of Paran, on the western slopes of the peninsula, not far from the granite mountains standing in the southern apex of the triangle, is the wilderness of Sin.</p>
<p>While the region is generally desolate and barren, it is not impassable or incapable of sustaining travelers. Wells and springs dot both the western and eastern borders at reasonable distances from each other. The water table is fairly close to ground level, making the digging of wells possible (<a href="?bref=Num.20.17">Nm 20:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.21.16-18">21:16-18</a>). The limestone rocks are also capable of holding great amounts of water (<a href="?bref=Num.20.11">20:11</a>). Vegetation is sparse except around the more permanent streams where vegetation and date palms flourish. The rainy season in winter is approximately 20 days. Quail (<a href="?bref=Num.11.31-32">11:31-32</a>) are known to migrate across the peninsula to Europe in the spring.</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="KeyPlacesinNumbers"/>
<p class="h3">The Peoples Israel Confronted</p>
<p class="h4">Amalekites and Canaanites (<a href="?bref=Num.14.25,43-45">14:25, 43-45</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.24.20">24:20</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The Amalekites were descendants of Amalek, son of Eliphaz and grandson of Esau (<a href="?bref=Gen.36.12,16">Gn 36:12, 16</a>). They were generally a nomadic people. In the Sinai Peninsula they were the first to war against Israel at Rephidim (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.24.20">Nm 24:20</a>), perhaps the Wadi Refayid in southwest Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.8-16">Ex 17:8-16</a>), before Israel reached Horeb. A year later, the Amalekites settled in the hills and valleys north of Kadesh-barnea. In league with the Canaanites, the inhabitants of Palestine, they blocked the effort of Israel to invade the land of promise from the south (<a href="?bref=Num.14.45">Nm 14:45</a>). Israel’s will to wage war appears to have been completely broken for years to come.</p>
<p class="h4">Edomites (<a href="?bref=Num.20.14-21">20:14-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.21.4,10-11">21:4, 10-11</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Edom, or Seir (<a href="?bref=Num.24.18">24:18</a>), is the territory south of the Dead Sea occupied by Esau’s descendants. Stretching from its northern border at the Wadi Zered (<a href="?bref=Num.21.12">21:12</a>), which flowed into the Dead Sea at its southern tip, 100 miles (160.9 kilometers) south to the Gulf of Aqaba, it occupied both sides of the Arabah, with Kadesh-barnea again standing on the edge of its western border (<a href="?bref=Num.20.16">20:16</a>), giving it a land area of approximately 4,000 square miles (10,360 square kilometers). It is a rugged mountain region with peaks rising to 3,500 feet (1,066.8 meters). The “king’s highway,” an ancient trade route from Damascus through the Transjordan to the Gulf of Aqaba, passed through its territory and major cities, Bozrah and Leman. While Edom was not fertile, it did have cultivable areas (<a href="?bref=Num.20.17-19">20:17-19</a>).</p>
<p>During Israel’s march to the Transjordan region, Edom refused to let Israel journey directly east from Kadesh through its territory but forced Israel to move southeast into and up the Arabah (<a href="?bref=Num.21.4,11">21:4, 11</a>). In spite of this hostility to God’s people, Israel was forbidden to attack (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.2-8">Dt 2:2-8</a>) or to hate the Edomites (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.7">23:7</a>), and so Edom was spared from destruction during the conquest of the land. The area was later conquered by David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.13-14">2 Sm 8:13-14</a>) according to Balaam’s prophecy (<a href="?bref=Num.24.18">Nm 24:18</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">Arad (<a href="?bref=Num.21.1-3">21:1-3</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Arad was a south Canaanite settlement in the Negev. Its king, after fighting against Israel and taking some captives, was later defeated at Hormah.</p>
<p class="h4">Moabites (<a href="?bref=Num.21.11-15">21:11-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.22.1-24.25">22:1–24:25</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Moab, occupied by the descendants of Lot (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.37">Gn 19:37</a>), is the territory east of the Dead Sea lying primarily between the Wadi Arnon (<a href="?bref=Num.21.13">Nm 21:13</a>) and the Wadi Zered with a land area of approximately 1,400 square miles (3,626 square kilometers).</p>
<p>In the late middle Bronze Age, the Moabites had overflowed their main plateau and had extended well to the north of the Arnon all the way to the northern end of the Dead Sea (<a href="?bref=Num.21.20">21:20</a>). At the time of the events recorded in Numbers, however, the Amorites occupied the area from Arnon all the way north to the Wadi Jabbok (vv <a href="?bref=Num.21.13">13</a>, <a href="?bref=Num.13.21-24">21-24</a>), having earlier taken this land from Moab (vv <a href="?bref=Num.21.26-30">26-30</a>). The Moabite kingdom was highly organized, with agriculture and livestock, splendid buildings, distinctive pottery, and strong fortifications around her borders. Its god was Chemosh (v <a href="?bref=Num.21.29">29</a>).</p>
<p>Balak, king of Moab during the period of the conquest, in league with Midian, hired Balaam to curse Israel (chs <a href="?bref=Num.22.1-24.25">22–24</a>). When this failed, the two heathen powers sought to neutralize Israel by luring the people of God into the worship of Chemosh and into idolatry (<a href="?bref=Num.25.1-2">25:1-2</a>). In the war that ensued, Israel defeated Midian (<a href="?bref=Num.31.1-18">31:1-18</a>), but by God’s express command (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.9-13">Dt 2:9-13</a>) spared Moab. But as Balaam had prophesied earlier (<a href="?bref=Num.24.17">Nm 24:17</a>), David in the 11th century warred against and defeated Moab (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.2,13-14">2 Sm 8:2, 13-14</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">Amorites (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.21-35">21:21-35</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The Amorites, the people who had occupied northern Moabite territory (<a href="?bref=Num.21.25-30">Nm 21:25-30</a>), were descendants of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.16">Gn 10:16</a>) who had scattered throughout the hill country on both sides of the Jordan River. Heshbon was their capital city. Both Sihon of Heshbon and Og of Bashan were Amorite kings (<a href="?bref=Deut.3.8">Dt 3:8</a>).</p>
<p>As for Bashan (<a href="?bref=Num.21.33-35">Nm 21:33-35</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.1.4">Dt 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.3.1-12">3:1-12</a>), it is the fertile grazing region (<a href="?bref=Num.32.1-5">Nm 32:1-5</a>) east of the Sea of Kinnereth (Galilee), whose northern border extended to Mt Hermon and whose southern border, while normally the river Yarmuk, in the Mosaic age was the Wadi Jabbok (<a href="?bref=Josh.12.4-5">Jos 12:4-5</a>). Its land area covered approximately 5,000 square miles (12,950 square kilometers). Its major cities were Ashtaroth, Edrei, and Golan. After the conquest of the land, this territory fell to the half-tribe of Manasseh, with Gad occupying southern Gilead, and Reuben the region south to the Wadi Arnon.</p>
<p class="h4">Midianites (<a href="?bref=Num.25.16-18">25:16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.31.1-54">31:1-54</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The Midianites, descendants of Abraham through the concubine Keturah (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.2">Gn 25:2</a>), were desert dwellers in Transjordan from Moab to the region south of Edom. The elders of Moab and Midian cooperated in hiring Balaam to curse Israel (<a href="?bref=Num.22.4-7">Nm 22:4-7</a>). Later, when that effort proved fruitless, the Midianites, again with Moab, led Israel into idolatry and immorality (<a href="?bref=Num.25.1-6,14-15">25:1-6, 14-15</a>). Cozbi, the Midianite woman who was executed for her wickedness (<a href="?bref=Num.25.8">25:8</a>), was the daughter of Zur, one of the five Midianite kings confederate with the Amorite king Sihon (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.21">Jos 13:21</a>) who were later killed in Israel’s holy war against Midian (<a href="?bref=Num.31.8">Nm 31:8</a>). This war with Midian apparently broke the back of any remaining Amorite resistance, for <a href="?bref=Josh.13.15-23">Joshua 13:15-23</a> clearly intimates that as a result the tribe of Reuben occupied this territory.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Purpose">Purpose</p>
<p class="fl">Numbers serves a twofold purpose. First, as a historical book, it contains the account of Israel’s fortunes from Mt Sinai to the plains of Moab on the eve of the conquest of Canaan—that almost-40-year period spent in the wilderness of Sinai and in Transjordan (1447–1407 <span class="era">BC</span>). While recounting Israel’s many failures and God’s many faithful acts, it depicts Moses, Israel’s leader, in all of his greatness and in all of his weakness. The two army rolls (chs <a href="?bref=Num.2.1-34">2</a> and <a href="?bref=Num.26.1-65">26</a>) introduce the “acts” of the main drama of its history: the first in preparation for entering the land, which failed due to Israel’s unbelief; the second, after the death of the entire generation that left Egypt, in preparation for the successful invasion of Canaan under Joshua’s leadership.</p>
<p>Second, in line with Paul’s general belief that “whatever was written in former days was written for our instruction, that by steadfastness and by the encouragement of the scriptures we might have hope” (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.4">Rom 15:4</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), and in keeping with his specific teaching that “these things [that befell Israel in the wilderness] happened to them as a warning, but they were written down for our instruction, upon whom the end of the ages has come” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.11">1 Cor 10:11</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), Numbers serves a doctrinal, typical, and hortatory purpose (cf. v <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.12">12</a>). Historical events are divinely invested with spiritual truths, thereby becoming object lessons for the Christian.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.1.1-54">1</a></p>
<p class="fl">The Lord commanded Moses to register (<a href="?bref=Num.1.18">Nm 1:18</a>) the men able to go to war (vv <a href="?bref=Num.1.2-3">2-3</a>). The total number of soldiers in Israel was 603,550 (v <a href="?bref=Num.1.46">46</a>). The Levites were not numbered in this roll (vv <a href="?bref=Num.1.47-54">47-54</a>), since they were to be set apart for special service pertaining to the tabernacle.</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.2.1-34">2</a></p>
<p class="fl">The Lord instructed Moses concerning the arrangement of the tribes while encamped and on the march. With the tabernacle in the center of the camp, Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun, totaling 186,400 (v <a href="?bref=Num.2.9">9</a>), were to camp on the east; Reuben, Simeon, and Gad, totaling 151,450 (v <a href="?bref=Num.2.16">16</a>), were to camp on the south; Ephraim, Manasseh, and Benjamin, totaling 108,100 (v <a href="?bref=Num.2.24">24</a>), were to camp on the west; and Dan, Asher, and Naphtali, totaling 157,600 (v <a href="?bref=Num.2.31">31</a>), were to camp on the north.</p>
<p>On the march, Judah’s east group (v <a href="?bref=Num.2.9">9</a>) was to set out first, followed by Reuben’s south group (v <a href="?bref=Num.2.16">16</a>). The Levites with the tabernacle were to follow (v <a href="?bref=Num.2.17">17</a>). Then Ephraim’s west group (v <a href="?bref=Num.2.24">24</a>) was to follow the Levites, with Dan’s north group (v <a href="?bref=Num.2.31">31</a>) bringing up the rear. This means that the Levites were flanked by two groups, before and behind.</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.3.1-51">3</a></p>
<p class="fl">Aaron, the great-grandson of Levi through Kohath (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.16-20">Ex 6:16-20</a>), and his descendants were designated to serve as priests at the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Num.3.2-3">Nm 3:2-3</a>). The remaining descendants of Levi, from the families of Gershon, Kohath, and Merari, were to serve the Aaronic line at the tabernacle (vv <a href="?bref=Num.3.5-10">5-10</a>). The Gershonites were responsible for the tabernacle coverings, hangings, and screens (vv <a href="?bref=Num.3.25-26">25-26</a>); the Kohathites were responsible for the “furniture” in the tabernacle (v <a href="?bref=Num.3.31">31</a>); and the Merarites were responsible for the frames, bars, and foundations for the tabernacle (vv <a href="?bref=Num.3.36-37">36-37</a>).</p>
<p>God instructed Moses to number the three Levitical families. Gershon’s descendants, totaling 7,500 (v <a href="?bref=Num.3.22">22</a>), were to camp on the west, between the western group of tribes and the tabernacle. Kohath’s descendants, totaling 8,600 (v <a href="?bref=Num.3.28">28</a>), were to camp on the south, between the southern group of tribes and the tabernacle. Merari’s descendants, totaling 6,200 (v <a href="?bref=Num.3.34">34</a>), were to camp on the north, between the northern group of tribes and the tabernacle. Moses and the Aaronic family were to camp on the east, between the eastern group of tribes and the tabernacle (v <a href="?bref=Num.3.38">38</a>). Both in camp and on the march, then, the tabernacle was in the midst of Israel.</p>
<p>The census of Israel’s firstborn males disclosed 273 more male babies than Levites (vv <a href="?bref=Num.3.40-46">40-46</a>), and since the Levites were a ransom for Israelite males on a one-to-one basis, the 273 additional male children had to be ransomed by atonement money (vv <a href="?bref=Num.3.46-51">46-51</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.4.1-49">4</a></p>
<p class="fl">God instructed Moses that only Levites between the ages of 30 and 50 were to serve at the tabernacle. A census disclosed that there were 2,750 Kohathites (v <a href="?bref=Num.4.36">36</a>), 2,630 Gershonites (v <a href="?bref=Num.4.40">40</a>), and 3,200 Merarites (v <a href="?bref=Num.4.44">44</a>), making a total of 8,580 (v <a href="?bref=Num.4.48">48</a>) who were eligible to serve the Aaronic priests.</p>
<p>God further ordered the Aaronic priests, when the tabernacle was being dismantled for the march, to cover all the tabernacle “furniture” before the Kohathites even looked at them (v <a href="?bref=Num.4.20">20</a>) lest the Kohathites, either looking at or touching them (v <a href="?bref=Num.4.15">15</a>), should die (vv <a href="?bref=Num.4.15,20">15, 20</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.5.1-31">5</a></p>
<p class="fl">For ceremonial purposes, God demanded that lepers, those with a bodily discharge, and those who had touched the dead, must be put outside the camp until they were purified (vv <a href="?bref=Num.5.1-4">1-4</a>). Furthermore, God instructed those making restitution for a wrongdoing, if the wronged person was no longer alive, to give the restitution price to a priest (vv <a href="?bref=Num.5.5-10">5-10</a>).</p>
<p>Finally, if a woman was suspected by her husband of infidelity but there was no evidence of such, the woman was to undergo a trial by water ordeal to relieve the man of his suspicions. The priest was to give her holy water with dust from the floor of the tabernacle in it to drink. If she was guilty, the water by divine direction would cause her pain, make her abdomen swell, and her thigh waste away (vv <a href="?bref=Num.5.11-31">11-31</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.6.1-27">6</a></p>
<p class="fl">Laws pertaining to the Nazirite were given next. A Nazirite was a person who determined to take a vow to separate himself wholly to the Lord. To dramatize this separation, the Nazirite was to drink no intoxicating beverage, let the hair grow long, and touch no dead body (vv <a href="?bref=Num.6.3-6">3-6</a>). Should he defile himself, he was to follow prescribed rules for ceremonial cleansing (vv <a href="?bref=Num.6.9-12">9-12</a>). When his vow had run its course, he was to follow prescribed rules for terminating his vow (vv <a href="?bref=Num.6.13-21">13-21</a>). Finally, God instructed the Aaronic priesthood concerning the blessing they were to pronounce upon the Israelite worshiper (vv <a href="?bref=Num.6.22-27">22-27</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.7.1-89">7</a></p>
<p class="fl">The leaders in Israel brought six wagons and twelve oxen for use in the transfer of the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Num.7.3">7:3</a>). Moses gave two wagons and four oxen to the Gershonites (v <a href="?bref=Num.7.7">7</a>), and four wagons and eight oxen to the Merarites (v <a href="?bref=Num.7.8">8</a>). (The Kohathites were to carry the “furniture” of the tabernacle on their shoulders, v <a href="?bref=Num.7.9">9</a>.) For twelve consecutive days, to consecrate the altar after it was anointed (vv <a href="?bref=Num.7.10,88">10, 88</a>), the tribal leaders, in the order of march (cf. ch <a href="?bref=Num.2.1-34">2</a>), brought similar offerings. God demonstrated his pleasure with this gesture by speaking to Moses from the mercy seat (v <a href="?bref=Num.7.89">89</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.8.1-26">8</a></p>
<p class="fl">God granted the prerogative to light the seven-branched lampstand to the Aaronic priests (vv <a href="?bref=Num.8.1-4">1-4</a>). Following divine instructions, Moses and Aaron consecrated the Levites to the service of the tabernacle by means of a purification ceremony (vv <a href="?bref=Num.8.5-22">5-22</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapters <a href="?bref=Num.9.1-10.10">9:1–10:10</a></p>
<p class="fl">For the benefit of the worshiper who was ceremonially unclean or away on a journey at the time of the Passover, God granted permission to observe the Passover a month later (vv <a href="?bref=Num.9.6-12">6-12</a>; see also ch <a href="?bref=Num.27.1-23">27</a>).</p>
<p>God gave final instructions to the people before their departure from Sinai. They were to prepare for marching when they saw the cloud ascending from the tabernacle, and they were to stop at the place where the cloud settled down (<a href="?bref=Num.9.15-23">9:15-23</a>). The people were to assemble at the tabernacle if two silver trumpets were blown; only the leaders were to come if one was blown; and at the blast of a military alarm, the several groups of tribes were to prepare for an immediate march (<a href="?bref=Num.10.1-10">10:1-10</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapters <a href="?bref=Num.10.11-14.45">10:11–14:45</a></p>
<p class="fl">The next section recounts the march from Sinai to Kadesh-barnea, a period of time approximately one and a half to two months in length (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.10.11">10:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.13.20">13:20</a>). Almost immediately the people began to complain as they passed through the terrible wilderness of Paran (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.19">Dt 1:19</a>), angering the Lord at Taberah (<a href="?bref=Num.11.1-3">Nm 11:1-3</a>) and at Kibroth-hattaavah (<a href="?bref=Num.11.4-35">Nm 11:4-35</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.26-31">Pss 78:26-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.106.13-15">106:13-15</a>). Miriam and Aaron challenged Moses’ sole right to speak for God to the people, which resulted in temporary leprosy as punishment for Miriam (doubtless the leader in the provocation). Through Moses’ intercession, the two were forgiven (<a href="?bref=Num.12.1-16">Nm 12</a>). Out of this event, however, came the remarkable description of Moses’ relationship to God as a unique means of revelation (vv <a href="?bref=Num.12.6-8">6-8</a>).</p>
<p>From Paran (Kadesh-barnea) Moses dispatched the spies to survey the land (ch <a href="?bref=Num.13.1-33">13</a>). <a href="?bref=Deut.1.22">Deuteronomy 1:22</a> suggests that the plan to spy out the land originated with the people, with Moses (at God’s behest) acquiescing. At the end of 40 days, they returned. Only Caleb and Joshua urged the people to advance to the conquest; the other 10 spies spoke of foes too formidable for them to defeat. The people, greatly discouraged, attempted to stone Caleb and Joshua (<a href="?bref=Num.14.10">Nm 14:10</a>), and were prevented from doing so only by the sudden appearance of the glory cloud at the tabernacle. God swore in his wrath (<a href="?bref=Num.14.21">Nm 14:21</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.3.7-4.10">Heb 3:7–4:10</a>) that, with the exception of Caleb and Joshua, none of that generation would enter the land of promise (<a href="?bref=Num.14.21-35">Nm 14:21-35</a>). He then struck down the 10 unbelieving spies (v <a href="?bref=Num.14.37">37</a>). Presumptuously, and in spite of God’s express command to the contrary (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.42">Dt 1:42</a>), Israel attempted to advance on the land, leaving Moses and the ark of the covenant in the camp. They were challenged by the Amalekites and Canaanites.</p>
<p>Israel remained in this general area with tribal families fanning out over the wilderness and settling around springs and oases (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.46">Dt 1:46</a>). <a href="?bref=Num.15.1-21.20">Numbers 15:1–21:20</a> relates the account of the 38 years of wilderness wandering. Much of this time was probably spent around Kadesh-barnea (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.46">Dt 1:46</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.15.1-41">15</a></p>
<p class="fl">Further priestly legislation was given (<a href="?bref=Num.15.1-21">Nm 15:1-21</a>). Also, the procedure to be followed when an Israelite committed a sin deliberately and defiantly was spelled out in terms of excommunication: there was no atonement for such an attitude (vv <a href="?bref=Num.15.22-31">22-31</a>). A Sabbath violator was executed (vv <a href="?bref=Num.15.32-36">32-36</a>), perhaps as an illustration of the foregoing legislation. Finally, to assist them in obeying God’s laws, the Israelites were instructed to tie blue tassels to their outer garments as reminders (vv <a href="?bref=Num.15.37-41">37-41</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.16.1-50">16</a></p>
<p class="fl">Korah challenged Aaron’s high priesthood, and Dathan, Abiram, and On challenged Moses’ leadership (vv <a href="?bref=Num.16.1-14">1-14</a>). God, at Moses’ word, opened up the earth and swallowed the offenders (<a href="?bref=Num.16.32">Nm 16:32</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.9.6">Dt 9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.106.16-18">Ps 106:16-18</a>). Korah is regarded in the NT (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.11">Jude 1:11</a>) as a classic example of a rebellious malcontent.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Num.26.11">Numbers 26:11</a> states that Korah’s young children did not perish with him. Perhaps they became the ancestors of the “sons of Korah,” the sacred musicians of the temple who composed 12 Korahite psalms (<a href="?bref=Ps.42.1-49.20">Pss 42–49</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.84.1-85.13">84–85</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.87.1-88.18">87–88</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.17.1-13">17</a></p>
<p class="fl">God then instructed the leaders of each tribe to bring rods, 12 in all, to write the names of the tribes upon them (with Aaron’s name on Levi’s rod), and to deposit them in the tabernacle. The following day, Aaron’s rod had sprouted with blossoms and ripe almonds, thus vindicating Aaron’s special high-priestly status.</p>
<p class="h3">Chapters <a href="?bref=Num.18.1-19.14">18–19</a></p>
<p class="fl">Further priestly legislation was given. In <a href="?bref=Num.18.1-7">18:1-7</a>, the full responsibility for the priestly service was given to the Aaronic priests—a very natural consequence of the preceding chapter. The Levites were to assist the Aaronic order (v <a href="?bref=Num.18.6">6</a>). Since the tribe of Levi received no land inheritance, they were to be supported from the offerings of the people (vv <a href="?bref=Num.18.8-20">8-20</a>).</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Num.19.1-22">19:1-22</a> instructions concerning ceremonial impurity were given. When an Israelite became ceremonially unclean through contact with death (vv <a href="?bref=Num.19.11-16">11-16</a>), God required that he be purified from his sin (vv <a href="?bref=Num.19.9,17">9, 17</a>) by the sprinkling of specially prepared water upon him.</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.20.1-29">20</a></p>
<p class="fl">With Israel once again at Kadesh on the southern border of the wilderness of Zin in the first month of the 40th year of wandering, Miriam died and was buried (v <a href="?bref=Num.20.1">1</a>). According to the encampment list in chapter <a href="?bref=Num.33.1-56">33</a>, 18 encampments may have occurred for Israel since the nation had last been at this site (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.33.18-36">33:18-36</a>).</p>
<p>At this time the nation complained once again because there was little water (<a href="?bref=Num.20.2">20:2</a>). Moses, at God’s instruction, brought forth water from a rock (vv <a href="?bref=Num.20.8-11">8-11</a>), but because of a gross infraction by Moses and Aaron on this occasion, God announced that they would not be permitted to lead Israel in the conquest of the land (vv <a href="?bref=Num.20.12,23-24">12, 23-24</a>).</p>
<p>The chapter closes with Edom refusing Israel passage across its territory (vv <a href="?bref=Num.20.14-21">14-21</a>) and Aaron dying on Mt Hor on the border of Edom (vv <a href="?bref=Num.20.22-29">22-29</a>) in the fifth month of the 40th year (<a href="?bref=Num.33.38">33:38</a>). Eleazar, Aaron’s son, assumed the office of high priest.</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.21.1-35">21</a></p>
<p class="fl">After a quick victory over Arad (vv <a href="?bref=Num.21.1-3">1-3</a>), Israel started south to encircle Edom. Becoming impatient with God and with Moses, the people expressed their disgust with God’s provision of manna. The Lord sent poisonous snakes to the camp, causing many to die. But at God’s command Moses fashioned a snake out of bronze and placed it atop a standard. All who looked to the bronze snake survived (vv <a href="?bref=Num.21.4-10">4-10</a>). The bronze snake was preserved and later was destroyed by Hezekiah, the symbol having become by his time an idol (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.4">2 Kgs 18:4</a>). Later still, Jesus drew an analogy between these wicked sinners looking to the bronze snake and being delivered and men looking to him by faith and being saved (<a href="?bref=John.3.14-15">Jn 3:14-15</a>).</p>
<p>Leaving that fateful place, Israel journeyed into and up the Arabah, crossed the Wadi Zered in an eastern swing around Moab, finally crossing the Arnon into Amorite territory. Journeying north, they camped at Pisgah (<a href="?bref=Num.21.10-20">Nm 21:10-20</a>).</p>
<p>At this point the conquest of the Transjordan begins. In quick succession Israel defeated Sihon of Heshbon (vv <a href="?bref=Num.21.21-31">21-31</a>) and Og of Bashan (vv <a href="?bref=Num.21.33-35">33-35</a>) and settled in the plains of Moab (<a href="?bref=Num.22.1">22:1</a>). This encampment was the scene for the remainder of the activities of Numbers, Deuteronomy, and <a href="?bref=Josh.1.1-3.17">Joshua 1–3</a>. In a real sense, one can say the wilderness wanderings were now over.</p>
<p>Here is the place, then, to summarize the spiritual condition of Israel on the eve of the conquest of Canaan. Numbers makes it quite evident that the entire generation that left Egypt, with the exception of Joshua and Caleb, was to die in the wilderness because of its apostasy (cf. <a href="?bref=Amos.5.25">Am 5:25</a>), unbelief, and general failure to keep covenant with God. None of the generation of male children born in the wilderness had been circumcised (<a href="?bref=Josh.5.2-9">Jos 5:2-9</a>). <a href="?bref=Ps.90.1-17">Psalm 90</a> underscores Israel as the recipient of God’s wrath in the wilderness. It is in this pitiable spiritual condition that Israel arrived on the plains of Moab.</p>
<p class="h3">Chapters <a href="?bref=Num.22.1-24.25">22–24</a></p>
<p class="fl">Balak, king of Moab, frightened by Israel’s presence, joined with Midian to hire Balaam, the false prophet, to curse Israel. For gain, Balaam agreed (<a href="?bref=2Pet.2.15">2 Pt 2:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jude.1.11">Jude 1:11</a>), but God prevented him, causing him rather to bless Israel in his four oracular utterances (<a href="?bref=Num.23.7-10,18-24">Nm 23:7-10, 18-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.24.3-9,15-19">24:3-9, 15-19</a>) and to predict the destruction of Moab, Edom, Amalek (<a href="?bref=Num.24.20">24:20</a>), the Kenites (<a href="?bref=Num.24.21">24:21</a>), and Asshur (<a href="?bref=Num.24.24">24:24</a>). With that, Balak and Balaam separated. Balaam, in collusion with Midian, agreed to counsel Israel to commit idolatry and immorality (<a href="?bref=Num.31.16">31:16</a>). And so, where Balak failed to turn the Lord against Israel, Balaam succeeded (ch <a href="?bref=Num.25.1-18">25</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.25.1-18">25</a></p>
<p class="fl">Israel sinned against God by idolatrous and immoral acts with the people of Moab (vv <a href="?bref=Num.25.1-3">1-3</a>). In carrying out the command of God to destroy the reprobate Israelites, Phinehas killed Zimri and Cozbi, the latter being a daughter of one of the five kings of Midian (vv <a href="?bref=Num.25.4-14">4-14</a>). This event provided the occasion for God to declare a holy war against Midian (vv <a href="?bref=Num.25.16-18">16-18</a>; cf. ch <a href="?bref=Num.31.1-54">31</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.26.1-65">26</a></p>
<p class="fl">The Lord commanded Moses to take a roll of the men of the second generation who were capable of warring against Israel’s enemies. The total number came to 601,730 (v <a href="?bref=Num.26.51">51</a>), a reduction of 1,820 men from the first count. With a smaller force than the first generation, Israel conquered Canaan, clearly indicating that Israel could have spared itself the years of wandering if only the nation had obeyed God 38 years before Kadesh. The Levites totaled 23,000 males a month old and upward (vv <a href="?bref=Num.26.57-62">57-62</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.27.1-23">27</a></p>
<p class="fl">At the request of the daughters of Zelophehad (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.26.33">26:33</a>) that they be granted the right to inherit their father’s possessions since he had no sons, the Lord agreed that they could, using the occasion to give further laws of inheritance (vv <a href="?bref=Num.27.1-11">1-11</a>).</p>
<p>Reminded that he would soon die in Abarim, Moses requested that God appoint his successor. God selected Joshua, and Moses commissioned him (vv <a href="?bref=Num.27.12-23">12-23</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapters <a href="?bref=Num.28.1-30.16">28–30</a></p>
<p class="fl">Further priestly legislation regarding offerings for various occasions was given. God also instructed Moses to inform the people concerning vows. When a man made a vow, it was inviolable (<a href="?bref=Num.30.2">30:2</a>), but if a woman made a vow, the man (father, husband) responsible for her could nullify it if he felt that it was rash (vv <a href="?bref=Num.30.1-16">1-16</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.31.1-54">31</a></p>
<p class="fl">The account of the holy war declared against Midian in <a href="?bref=Num.25.16-18">25:16-18</a> is given. With Phinehas accompanying 12,000 warriors, Israel defeated Midian, killing Balaam along with the five kings and many male adults of Midian (<a href="?bref=Num.31.1-8">31:1-8</a>). The Midianite women and children were taken captive, but Moses commanded that all the male children and the nonvirgin women be killed (vv <a href="?bref=Num.31.9-18">9-18</a>). One must not conclude that this war meant the end of Midian as such, for Midian later proved a formidable foe of Israel in the time of the judges (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.1-40">Jgs 6</a>).</p>
<p>After the battle, the warriors were instructed to purify themselves, their clothing, and the booty from the war before coming into the camp (<a href="?bref=Num.31.19-24">Nm 31:19-24</a>). Furthermore, they were instructed to divide the booty in half and to contribute one-fifth of one percent of their half to the high priest (“the Lord’s tribute”). The other half was divided among the people who had remained in camp, after the Levites received a two percent contribution (vv <a href="?bref=Num.31.25-31">25-31</a>).</p>
<p>Verses <a href="?bref=Num.31.32-47">32-47</a> give the tally of the booty after its division into two parts and the amount that was given from each part to Eleazar and the Levites. The tally is said by some to be too high to be authentic, but there is no evidence that disputes the recorded figures.</p>
<p>In thanksgiving to God because no Israelite had been killed in the war (v <a href="?bref=Num.31.49">49</a>) and to make atonement for themselves (v <a href="?bref=Num.31.50">50</a>), the army officers brought a special offering of gold trinkets to Moses and Eleazar, which was placed in the tabernacle as a memorial (vv <a href="?bref=Num.31.48-54">48-54</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.32.1-42">32</a></p>
<p class="fl">At their request and on the condition that they aid the other tribes in the conquest of Canaan, Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh were allotted the Transjordan region. Moses earnestly besought the Lord to change his mind about not permitting him to enter the land of promise (<a href="?bref=Deut.3.23-27">Dt 3:23-27</a>). But God would not let him.</p>
<p class="h3">Chapters <a href="?bref=Num.33.1-34.29">33–34</a></p>
<p class="fl">At God’s command, Moses kept a written record of Israel’s itinerary from Egypt to the plains of Moab. Here is biblical evidence of the Mosaic authorship of Numbers.</p>
<p>The boundaries of the Promised Land were now given. The southern boundary would run from the southern tip of the Dead Sea, south of Kadesh-barnea up to the River of Egypt (Wadi el-Arish), and on to the Mediterranean Sea (<a href="?bref=Num.34.3-5">34:3-5</a>). The western boundary would be the coastline of the Mediterranean Sea itself (v <a href="?bref=Num.34.6">6</a>). The northern boundary, not realized until the times of David and Solomon (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.3-12">2 Sm 8:3-12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.65">1 Kgs 8:65</a>), was to extend from the Mediterranean Sea east to Hamath, at the head of the Orontes River (<a href="?bref=Num.34.7-9">Nm 34:7-9</a>). The eastern boundary was to be practically on a vertical line, with the Jordan Valley running north to the northern boundary (vv <a href="?bref=Num.34.10-12">10-12</a>). The nine and a half tribes were to divide this area among themselves (vv <a href="?bref=Num.34.13-15">13-15</a>).</p>
<p>The Lord then selected the men who were to bear the responsibility of dividing the land of Canaan among the western tribes after the conquest (vv <a href="?bref=Num.34.16-29">16-29</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.35.1-34">35</a></p>
<p class="fl">God instructed Israel to give 48 cities throughout the land on both sides of the Jordan to the Levites for a permanent possession (vv <a href="?bref=Num.35.1-8">1-8</a>), since that tribe was not included in the land allotments to the other tribes. The number of cities each tribe was to give was to be determined by its size (v <a href="?bref=Num.35.8">8</a>). Six of the Levitical cities, three on each side of the Jordan, were to be designated “cities of refuge” for the manslayer (v <a href="?bref=Num.35.6">6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Josh.20.1-9">Jos 20</a>).</p>
<p>Legislation concerning the manslayer follows (vv <a href="?bref=Num.35.9-34">9-34</a>). If the slayer committed murder, the kinsman avenger had the right to fulfill his role as executioner (vv <a href="?bref=Num.35.16-21">16-21</a>). If, however, the killing was unintentional, the manslayer was to flee to the nearest city of refuge for a trial. If found innocent of murder, he was assigned to remain within the city of refuge until the death of the high priest. If he left the city before then, the kinsman avenger was permitted to execute him (vv <a href="?bref=Num.35.22-34">22-34</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Chapter <a href="?bref=Num.36.1-13">36</a></p>
<p class="fl">Basing their question on the earlier law established in chapter <a href="?bref=Num.27.1-23">27</a>, the leaders from Manasseh asked whether an heiress should be allowed to marry outside her tribe, with the accompanying transfer of property from one tribe to another that would ensue. God directed that an heiress would have to marry within her tribe (vv <a href="?bref=Num.36.1-12">1-12</a>).</p>
<p>The last verse of the book refers to all the laws given in the plains of Moab (<a href="?bref=Num.26.1-36.12">26:1–36:12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.27.34">Lv 27:34</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheologicalTeaching">Theological Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">In the book of Numbers God is revealed as the unchangingly faithful God of the covenant (<a href="?bref=Num.23.19">Nm 23:19</a>). This faithfulness to his covenant required that he both guide and care for his people and punish their sins against him. But no impediment was so great that God’s design to bring his people to the land of promise was thwarted (<a href="?bref=Num.11.23">11:23</a>).</p>
<p>Both by his wrathful reaction to Israel’s sin and by the numerous priestly laws, God highlights his awesome holiness. The legislation expressly teaches that the person who approaches God must be clean. Even to look with unholy eyes upon the holiness of God meant death (<a href="?bref=Num.4.20">4:20</a>).</p>
<p>His sovereignty over all of life is evident from the attention he displays over even the minutest aspects of life. The phrase “And the Lord said unto Moses” occurs over 50 times, and the words that follow in each case deal with all kinds of matters.</p>
<p>As the God of the covenant, God’s “christological” character is also apparent. God’s blessing and faithfulness reflect the christological motif. Finally, Moses’ prophetic leadership (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.37-38">Acts 7:37-38</a>) and intercessory ministry (e.g., <a href="?bref=Num.11.2">Nm 11:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.12.13">12:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.14.19">14:19</a>), in the Aaronic priesthood (e.g., ch <a href="?bref=Num.16.1-50">16</a>), in the animal sacrifices (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.19.9">19:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.13">Heb 9:13</a>), and in the symbols (the manna, the water, the bronze snake) foreshadow the future Christ.</p>
<p>In Israel’s responses to God, the people depict all of human sinfulness and faithlessness. Israel’s wanderings illustrate the results of unbelief. The punishments of Israel prove the maxim of <a href="?bref=Num.32.23">Numbers 32:23</a>: “But if you fail to keep your word, then you will have sinned against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and you may be sure that your sin will find you out” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). Numbers forcefully teaches that safety and blessing are to be found only in trust in the Lord. Only he is capable of bringing men and women to the place of rest (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.9">Heb 4:9</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DeuteronomyBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Deuteronomy, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=ExodusBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Exodus, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=GenesisBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genesis, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=LeviticusBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Leviticus, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=Moses_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Moses</a>; <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>