<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Nurse">
  <title>Nurse</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NURSE</p>
<p class="fl">A woman who took care of an infant that did not belong to her, or a man who took care of young children. The work was limited to the nursing and caring of an infant. Women usually took care of their own children, such as Sarah (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.7">Gn 21:7</a>) and Hannah (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.23">1 Sm 1:23</a>). A wet nurse often became a part of the family circle and had a special place. Rebekah had a nurse, and when she passed away, the woman was even mentioned in the biblical text: “Now Deborah, Rebekah’s nurse, died and was buried under the oak below Bethel. So it was named Allon Bacuth” (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.8">Gn 35:8</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Moses’ mother became his nurse, as she was being paid by Pharaoh’s daughter (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.7">Ex 2:7</a>). Royal sons were cared for by nurses, as in the case of Joash, who was hidden with his nurse by Jehosheba his aunt (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.2">2 Kgs 11:2</a>). Since Joash was hidden for six years and was seven when he acceded to the throne, Joash was about a year old when he was hidden—and his nurse must have been a wet nurse.</p>
<p>Royal sons received special care and were under the supervision of a nurse after they had been suckled. Children were nursed up to the age of three, and when they were weaned, there was a feast (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.8">Gn 21:8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.23-24">1 Sm 1:23-24</a>). Thereafter, a nurse-teacher took charge of the youngster. Mephibosheth was five years old when his nurse fell with him, causing him to be lame (<a href="?bref=2Sam.4.4">2 Sm 4:4</a>). Naomi took care of her grandson as a nurse (<a href="?bref=Ruth.4.16">Ru 4:16</a>). It is probable that male nurses were used as teachers for the young aristocrats, such as we find in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.1">2 Kings 10:1</a>, when it is said that Ahab’s children had tutors (cf. also v <a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.5">5</a>). In this sense we must understand Moses’ reference to himself, too, as a “nurse”: “Did I conceive all these people? Did I give them birth? Why do you tell me to carry them in my arms, as a nurse carries an infant, to the land you promised on oath to their forefathers?” (<a href="?bref=Num.11.12">Nm 11:12</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Paul saw himself, too, as a “nurse” to the church (<a href="?bref=1Thes.2.7">1 Thes 2:7</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>