<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PetertheApostle">
  <title>Peter, the Apostle</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PETER, <span class="lc">The Apostle</span></p>
<p class="fl">One of the 12 disciples; rose to prominence both among the disciples during Jesus’s ministry and among the apostles afterwards.</p>
<p>There are actually four forms of Peter’s name in the New Testament: the Hebrew translated into Greek, “Simeon” to “Simon,” and the Aramaic translated into Greek, “Cephas” to “Petros” (meaning “rock”). His given name was Simeon bar-Jonah (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.17">Mt 16:17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=John.1.42">Jn 1:42</a>), “Simon the son of John,” which was a common Semitic naming practice. It is most likely that “Simon” was not merely the Greek equivalent of “Simeon” but that, having his home in bilingual Galilee, “Simon” was the alternate form he used in dealings with Gentiles. In fact, it was quite common for a cosmopolitan Jew to employ three forms of his name depending on the occasion: Aramaic, Latin, and Greek. The double name “Simon Peter” (or “Simon called Peter”) demonstrates that the second name was a later addition, similar to “Jesus, the Christ.” The number of times that the Aramaic equivalent “Cephas” is used (once in John, four times each in Galatians and 1 Corinthians), as well as its translation into the Greek (not common with proper names), indicates the importance of the secondary name. Both Aramaic and Greek forms mean “the rock,” an obvious indication of Peter’s stature in the early church (see below on <a href="?bref=Matt.16.18">Mt 16:18</a>). It is obvious that he was called “Simon” throughout Jesus’s ministry but came to be known as “Peter” more and more in the apostolic age.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#PetersBackground">Peter’s Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PetersConversionandCall">Peter’s Conversion and Call</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PetersPlaceamongtheTwelve">Peter’s Place among the Twelve</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PetertheRock">Peter the Rock</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PetertheApostle">Peter the Apostle</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PetersFutureMinistry">Peter’s Future Ministry</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="PetersBackground">Peter’s Background</p>
<p class="fl">Peter was raised in bilingual Galilee. <a href="?bref=John.1.44">John 1:44</a> says that the home of Andrew (his brother) and Peter was Bethsaida, the location of which is difficult to place archaeologically. The only site about which we know is east of the Jordan in the district called Gaulanitis. Yet <a href="?bref=John.12.21">John 12:21</a> places Bethsaida in Galilee; however, it is possible that John is reflecting the popular use of the term “Galilee” rather than the legally correct one. Peter and Andrew had a fishing business centered in Capernaum (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.21,29">Mk 1:21, 29</a>) and perhaps were partners with James and John (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.10">Lk 5:10</a>). It is also likely that they continued from time to time in their business while disciples, as indicated in the fishing scene in <a href="?bref=John.21.1-8">John 21:1-8</a>.</p>
<p>One difficulty with this is the series of statements saying, “We have left all and followed You” (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.27">Mt 19:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.28">Mk 10:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.18.28">Lk 18:28</a>). The majority of interpreters have given this an absolute sense of “sold” or “left” their business. However, <a href="?bref=Luke.18.28">Luke 18:28</a> occurs in the context of leaving their homes but obviously is not meant in an absolute sense. It seems most likely that the disciples did leave the practice of their fishing businesses to follow Christ, but kept the tools of their trade and returned to their trades when necessary.</p>
<p>They certainly did not abandon their families, as evidenced by Peter, who returned to his home at the end of each tour. The New Testament tells us that Peter was married. In <a href="?bref=Mark.1.29-31">Mark 1:29-31</a> Jesus heals his mother-in-law, who perhaps was living with Peter. In fact, it is possible that his home became Jesus’s headquarters in Galilee. (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.14">Matthew 8:14</a> may indicate that Jesus stayed there.) <a href="?bref=1Cor.9.5">First Corinthians 9:5</a> says that Peter, along with the other married apostles, often took his wife with him on his missionary journeys. Later tradition speaks of his children (Clement of Alexandria’s <span class="ital">Stromateis</span> 2.6.52) and says that Peter was present at the martyrdom of his wife (Eusebius’s <span class="ital">Ecclesiastical History</span> 3.30.2).</p>
<p class="h2" id="PetersConversionandCall">Peter’s Conversion and Call</p>
<p class="fl">Peter’s brother, Andrew, was a disciple of John the Baptist, according to <a href="?bref=John.1.35-40">John 1:35-40</a>. This follows the witness of John in <a href="?bref=John.1.29-34">1:29-34</a> and is the second stage of John’s discipleship drama in chapter one—i.e., after bearing witness he now sends his own followers to Jesus. Andrew and the unnamed disciple (perhaps Philip as in <a href="?bref=John.1.43">Jn 1:43</a> or the “beloved disciple,” whom many identify with John himself) then “follow” Jesus (a term used often in John for discipleship). The next day Andrew follows the Baptist’s example and finds his brother Simon, saying, “We have found the Messiah” (<a href="?bref=John.1.41">Jn 1:41</a>). Peter’s conversion is presupposed in <a href="?bref=John.1.42">John 1:42</a>, where Simon is brought to Jesus by Andrew and there given a new name.</p>
<p>There are three separate episodes in the Gospels in which Simon is called, and these overlap with three episodes in which he is given the name “Cephas” (“Peter,” which means “rock”) by Jesus. John locates the event in Judea where John the Baptist was baptizing. The synoptic Gospels have two different scenes. The first call takes place at the Sea of Galilee (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.16-20">Mk 1:16-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.4.18-22">Mt 4:18-22</a>). Jesus is walking along the shore and sees Peter and Andrew along with James and John casting their nets into the sea. At this time he calls them to become “fishers of men.” Luke then expands this into a fishing scene (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.1-11">Lk 5:1-11</a>), in which the disciples have fished all night and caught nothing but at the command of Jesus lower their nets and catch an amount of fish so great that the boat starts to sink. The episode concludes exactly like Mark’s abbreviated form: Jesus says that from now on they will “catch men,” and as a result they leave everything and follow him.</p>
<p>The second synoptic episode involving Peter’s call (and his new name) is the official choice of the Twelve upon the mountain (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.13-19">Mk 3:13-19</a> and parallels); in the list of the names we have “Simon he surnamed Peter.” The final occurrence dealing with Peter’s new name is found in <a href="?bref=Matt.16.17-19">Matthew 16:17-19</a>, in connection with Peter’s confession at Caesarea Philippi.</p>
<p>It is somewhat difficult to harmonize these episodes properly. Were there three different episodes in which Simon was called (<a href="?bref=John.1.42">Jn 1:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.20">Mk 1:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.16">3:16</a>) and three separate incidents in which he was given the name Cephas/Peter (<a href="?bref=John.1.42">Jn 1:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.16">Mk 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.16.18">Mt 16:18</a>)? Many academics assume that one single event, which happened at some point in time toward the beginning of Jesus’s ministry, was later expanded into these diverse traditions. However, a closer examination of the Gospel data does not require such a conclusion. <a href="?bref=John.1.35-42">John 1:35-42</a> is not an institutional scene that connotes an official call. Rather, it describes the first encounter with Jesus and the realization of his significance. The “renaming” is in the future tense and looks to a later event. Moreover, John deliberately omits most of the crisis events in Jesus’s life (the baptism, the choice of the Twelve, the Transfiguration, the words of institution at the Last Supper, Gethsemane) and replaces them with highly theological scenes that teach the spiritual significance of the events. This is what he has done here.</p>
<p>The same is true of the first synoptic call, i.e., the fishing scene. Again, there is no hint of official ordination to office here but rather an anticipated or prophetic hint of future ministry. This is especially true of the highly theological scene in Luke, which promises abundant results. Again in all three accounts the future tense is employed: “I will make you fishers of men” (Matthew and Mark), “You will catch men” (Luke). The call in <a href="?bref=Mark.1.20">Mark 1:20</a> and <a href="?bref=Matt.4.21">Matthew 4:21</a> and their reaction (leaving all behind and following Jesus) is the opening move that is finalized in the actual institutional scene in <a href="?bref=Mark.3.13-19">Mark 3:13-19</a> and parallels. The wording does not indicate that these two episodes represent the same event, because the actual commissioning of the disciples occurs in the second passage. We must differentiate between the original call to one segment (who became the so-called “inner circle” of the Twelve) and the final choice of all the disciples.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PetersPlaceamongtheTwelve">Peter’s Place among the Twelve</p>
<p class="fl">The prominence of Simon Peter in the Gospels and Acts cannot be disputed. While some have attempted to attribute this to his leadership role in the later church, there is no basis for that in the text of the NT. From the very beginning Simon attained preeminence above the others. In the lists of the Twelve just mentioned, Simon’s name always appears first, and in <a href="?bref=Matt.10.2">Matthew 10:2</a> it introduces his name as “the first.” Moreover, the Twelve are often designated “Peter and those with him” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.36">Mk 1:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.32">Lk 9:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.45">8:45</a>).</p>
<p>Throughout the accounts Peter acted and spoke on behalf of the other disciples. At the Transfiguration it is Peter who wanted to raise tents (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.5">Mk 9:5</a>), and he alone had sufficient faith to attempt walking on the water (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.28-31">Mt 14:28-31</a>). It is Peter who asks the Lord to explain his teaching on forgiveness (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.21">Mt 18:21</a>) and parables (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.15">Mt 15:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.41">Lk 12:41</a>) and who speaks the disciples’ minds in <a href="?bref=Matt.19.27">Matthew 19:27</a>, “Behold, we have left everything and followed you; what’s in it for us?” The collectors of the temple tax come to Peter as leader of the group (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.24">Mt 17:24</a>). As a member of the inner circle (with James and John, possibly Andrew in <a href="?bref=Mark.13.3">Mk 13:3</a>) he was often alone with Jesus (at the raising of Jairus’s daughter, <a href="?bref=Mark.5.37">Mk 5:37</a> and parallels; at the Transfiguration, <a href="?bref=Mark.9.2">Mk 9:2</a> and parallels; at Gethsemane, <a href="?bref=Mark.14.33">Mk 14:33</a> and <a href="?bref=Matt.26.37">Mt 26:37</a>). Jesus asks Peter and John to prepare the Passover meal in <a href="?bref=Luke.22.8">Luke 22:8</a>, and in <a href="?bref=Mark.14.37">Mark 14:37</a> (and <a href="?bref=Matt.26.40">Mt 26:40</a>) he directs his rebuke to Peter as representing the others (“Could you [plural] not watch with me one hour?”). Finally, the message of the angel at the tomb as recorded in <a href="?bref=Mark.16.7">Mark 16:7</a> said, “Go your way, tell his disciples and Peter.” Certainly Peter held a very special place among the Twelve.</p>
<p>This was especially evident in the Caesarea Philippi episode (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.27-33">Mk 8:27-33</a> and parallels). It was Peter whose confession became the high point of the Gospel accounts, “You are the Christ” (Luke adds “of God”; Matthew, “the Son of the living God”). After Jesus then spoke of the suffering of the Son of Man, Peter rebuked him, and in Mark’s description Jesus then turned, gazed at all the disciples, and said to Peter, “Get behind Me, Satan— because you are not thinking the things of God, but the things of humans” (v <a href="?bref=Mark.8.33">33</a>). This was obviously directed at them all through Peter.</p>
<p>The portrait of Peter that comes through all four accounts pictures him as impulsive, often rash; he is the first to act and speak his mind and was typically enthusiast for everything in which he had a part. At the sight of Jesus walking on the water, Peter asked that the Lord command him to do the same and then immediately leaped out of the boat and began doing just that. At the Transfiguration, while the others stood amazed and were silenced by the appearance of Moses and Elijah, Peter the man of action said, “if You wish, I will put up three [sacred] tents here” (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.4">Mt 17:4</a>). Mark and Luke both add here that Peter did not know what he was saying. Peter’s unguarded and unthinking tendency to protest Jesus’s statements is seen not only at Caesarea Philippi but also at the foot-washing scene in <a href="?bref=John.13.4-11">John 13:4-11</a> when he said first, “You shall never ever wash my feet”; and then after Jesus’s strong reply, “If I do not wash you, you have no part with Me,” he reversed himself completely, stating, “Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and head” (<a href="?bref=John.13.8-9">13:8-9</a>). Finally, in the account of the race to the tomb (<a href="?bref=John.20.2-10">Jn 20:2-10</a>), the beloved disciple, reaching the tomb first, paused while Peter immediately and impulsively entered it. Peter was certainly one who rushed in where others fear to tread. However, this very trait aligns him with all of us and may be one of the major reasons why he becomes the representative disciple throughout the Gospels.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PetertheRock">Peter the Rock</p>
<p class="fl">The key to the significance of Simon Peter is obviously the controversial addendum to the Caesarea Philippi episode, found only in <a href="?bref=Matt.16.17-19">Matthew 16:17-19</a>, in Jesus’s testimonial to Peter. There are several crucial aspects of this saying. The most important for this study is verse <a href="?bref=Matt.16.18">18</a>, “So I tell you, you are Peter. And I will build my church on this rock”. There have been many interpretations of this down through history: (1) It refers to Peter as the “rock” or first bishop of the church. This was the Roman Catholic interpretation from the third century on and was employed as a proof text for apostolic succession, but it is not hinted at anywhere in the context or even in the letters of the NT: it was not a first-century concept. (2) The majority of Protestants since the Reformation have taken this to be a reference to Peter’s statement of faith rather than to Peter himself; but this neglects the wordplay, which is even more pronounced in Aramaic, which has only one form for “Cephas” (rock). (3) An alternative has been to take “this rock” as a reference to Jesus himself, but that is imaginative and is hardly in the context. In conclusion, “this rock” is almost certainly a reference to Peter, but it must be understood in two ways. First, Peter was to become the foundation upon which Christ would build his church, a position clearly attested to in Acts. This does not mean that Peter had an authority above the other apostles. Paul’s rebuke of Peter in <a href="?bref=Gal.2.11-14">Galatians 2:11-14</a> demonstrates that he was not above them, and at the Jerusalem council in <a href="?bref=Acts.15.1-41">Acts 15</a> it is James who has the position of leadership. Second, Peter is seen here not merely as an individual but as the representative of the disciples. This view is coming to increasing prominence today. It recognized the Jewish concept of “corporate identity” in which the leader was identified with the corporate body (e.g., the king or high priest representing the nation before God). This concept is also in keeping with <a href="?bref=Matt.18.18-20">Matthew 18:18-20</a>, which passes on the same authority to the church as is here given to Peter. In this view Peter as the rock becomes the first of the building blocks upon which Christ, the chief cornerstone (to continue the metaphor), will build his church (see <a href="?bref=Eph.2.19-20">Eph 2:19-20</a>).</p>
<p>Two other aspects are worthy of note here. First, verse <a href="?bref=Matt.16.18">18</a> says, “the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.” The “gates of hell” is a common Jewish euphemism for death’s inevitable and irrevocable power. Jesus is saying that Satan will not be triumphant over the church, and his sphere of operations, death, will be defeated (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.26,54-55">1 Cor 15:26, 54-55</a>). The church would undergo persecution and martyrdom, but the church would be triumphant.</p>
<p>Second, verse <a href="?bref=Matt.16.19">19</a> promises, “I will give unto you [singular] the keys of the kingdom,” another statement used of apostolic succession by the medieval church. Again, this must be understood in light of corporate identity; Peter, as the main figure in the early church, here embodies the community in his leadership. The “keys of the kingdom” are in direct contrast to the “gates of hell” (cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.1.18">Rv 1:18</a>, “the keys of hell and death” and <a href="?bref=Rev.3.7">Rv 3:7</a>, the “key of David”), and this follows the imagery of the building seen in the rock upon which Christ will build his church. Here Peter is given the keys that will unlock the power of the kingdom in building God’s community, the church. The future tense (“will give”) undoubtedly points to the period after the resurrection, when that power was released and the church founded.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PetertheApostle">Peter the Apostle</p>
<p class="fl">Two events led to the new Peter who fills the pages of Acts: his reinstatement described in <a href="?bref=John.21.15-17">John 21:15-17</a> and the Lord appearing to him after the resurrection, which is never described but alluded to in <a href="?bref=Luke.24.34">Luke 24:34</a> and <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.5">1 Corinthians 15:5</a>. His denial was certainly proof that he was not yet able to assume his predicted position as the rock of the church. Both Luke and Paul seem to state that the risen Lord appeared to Simon Peter before the others, which would be fitting in light of his preeminence in the early church. During the Palestinian era, the fifteen-year period prior to the Gentile mission, Peter was the leading figure. The other people mentioned in <a href="?bref=Acts.1.1-12.25">Acts 1–12</a> are all secondary to Peter, the dominant director of church policy. These include John, who is with Peter in the temple (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.1">3:1</a>), the prison (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.13">4:13</a>), and Samaria (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.14">8:14</a>); Stephen, who was one of the Seven and whose revolutionary preaching led to his martyrdom (chs <a href="?bref=Acts.6.1-7.60">6–7</a>); Philip, another of the Seven who proclaimed the gospel in Samaria and to the Ethiopian eunuch (ch <a href="?bref=John.8.1-59">8</a>); Barnabas, who set an example of sharing with the community (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.36-37">4:36-37</a>) and was an official delegate to Antioch (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.20-30">11:20-30</a>); Paul, a miraculous convert and witness (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.1-30">9:1-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.25-30">11:25-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.12.25">12:25</a>); and James, who became the first apostolic martyr (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.2">12:2</a>). It is Peter who suggests the choice of the 12th disciple (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.15-17">1:15-17</a>), who proclaims the gospel at Pentecost (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.14-40">2:14-40</a>), who speaks the healing word (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.6">3:6</a>), and who defends the gospel before the Sanhedrin (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.8-12,19-20">4:8-12, 19-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.29-32">5:29-32</a>). The episode regarding Ananias and Sapphira is particularly poignant, because here Peter functions as the avenging messenger of God; nowhere is his authority more evident. We would also note his authority in the scene at Samaria concerning the attempt of Simon the Sorcerer to buy the charismatic power (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.18-24">8:18-24</a>). Again, it is Peter whose influence commands the situation. In these two incidents we certainly see the “binding and loosing” jurisdiction (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.16.19">Mt 16:19</a>) exhibited in Peter.</p>
<p>Yet Peter and the church still came under the severe criticism of their Jewish heritage. The evidence points to a Jewish style of making converts on the part of the early church. They viewed themselves as the righteous remnant, living in the age of Messianic fulfillment, but still interpreted themselves in a Jewish sense and conducted their evangelism in the proselyte form of their particular expression of the Jewish faith (i.e., Gentiles could only be converted through Judaism). Two events changed this. First, the Greek-speaking Jewish branch of the church–or Hellenists–rebelled against the Hebrew Christians, which resulted in the appointment of the seven deacons and a change in the orthodox policy of the Palestinian church. Second, this then led to a new preaching ministry, first by Stephen, whose insights ended in his martyrdom and the scattering of the Greek-speaking branch in chapter <a href="?bref=Acts.8.1-40">8</a>; then by Philip and others, who extended the gospel even further, to the Samaritans and God-fearers. As a result, Peter and John came to Samaria (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.14">8:14</a>), the next significant step toward the Gentile mission. That is how the centrality of Jerusalem ended in the unfolding story.</p>
<p>The two miracles of Peter, at Lydda (the paralytic) and Joppa (raising the dead woman) in <a href="?bref=Acts.9.32-42">Acts 9:32-42</a>, are probably intended to parallel similar miracles of Jesus in Luke’s first work (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.18-26">Lk 5:18-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.49-56">8:49-56</a>). This is part of a major theme in Acts whereby Jesus’s life and ministry are paralleled and continued in the work of the Spirit through the church. Again Peter is seen in a representative role.</p>
<p>The new relationships are extended in two further scenes. First, Peter stays with “Simon, a tanner,” in Joppa, an unclean trade; no pious Jew would knowingly have social contact with such a one. Even more important, God teaches Peter through a dream (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.10-16">10:10-16</a>) that the old separation between clean and unclean has been broken. This then leads Peter to the home of an uncircumcised Gentile, the most serious social taboo for the Jew, and subsequent events after that force Peter to admit Gentiles into the church without the necessity of Jewish proselyte requirements. The serious consequences of this are seen in the debate that followed in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.2-3">Acts 11:2-3</a>) and later at the council (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.1-21">Acts 15:1-21</a>). The centrality of this event is demonstrated in that Luke reproduces Peter’s speech, which seems to be a repetition of chapter <a href="?bref=Acts.10.1-48">10</a> but is meant to highlight this crucial episode. An often forgotten but significant fact for the early church is that, for Luke, the Gentile mission begins with Peter, not Paul. He is the one upon whom the saving act of God descends; and as the leader of the church, he was the first important witness to it.</p>
<p>The persecution of Herod Agrippa (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.1-4">Acts 12:1-4</a>) was likely due to the rage caused by this free interaction with Gentiles; and it ended the period of Peter’s leadership in Jerusalem. The Jewish people were greatly offended by the new Christian push; and according to Luke in Acts, the dream-like period of popularity, in which the common people supported the church, effectively ceased at this time. Peter’s miraculous release and the dramatic scene at Mary’s house demonstrate the special place of Peter, but the momentum shifts. Peter is forced to flee Jerusalem, and in the interim James arises to leadership (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.17">Acts 12:17</a>); at the Jerusalem council it is James who has the chair and presents the council’s decision (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.6-29">Acts 15:6-29</a>).</p>
<p>The exact relationship between Peter and the other disciples, especially with the so-called pillars—James and John—and the apostle Paul, cannot be established. The evidence is too vague. Many have thought that there were no truly universal leaders, because the early church was too diverse. However, that is unlikely, and Luke’s portrayal in Acts parallels Paul’s statement in <a href="?bref=Gal.2.8">Galatians 2:8</a> that Peter was the most exemplary apostle to the “circumcised” and Paul to the “Gentiles.” They were the universal leaders, while James became the local leader of the Jerusalem eldership. However, neither Peter nor Paul had dominical status similar to that of later popes (i.e., neither was the absolute spokesman of the church, and neither was above criticism). So-called emissaries from James could have such an influence on Peter that he would hypocritically change his behavior before Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.12">Gal 2:12</a>), and Paul could rebuke Peter publicly for doing so (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.11-14">Gal 2:11-14</a>). Paul never claimed authority over the other disciples and even sought their approval and an agreement with them for his ministry to the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.1-10">Gal 2:1-10</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="PetersFutureMinistry">Peter’s Future Ministry</p>
<p class="fl">We have very little hard evidence for Peter’s other movements. It seems as though Peter gradually turned from leadership to missionary work. However, this is an oversimplification. It is most likely that, following the similar pattern of Paul, he combined the two. The presence of a “Cephas party” at Corinth (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.12">1 Cor 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.3.22">3:22</a>) may indicate that Peter had spent some time there. This is made even more likely when Paul uses Peter as the main example for taking one’s wife on missionary expeditions (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.5">1 Cor 9:5</a>). The “Cephas party” probably consisted of those who were converted under his ministry; it is probable that they were Jewish Christians and opposed the “Paul party” on Jewish-Gentile debates reflected elsewhere in 1 Corinthians.</p>
<p>The First Epistle of Peter was sent to churches in northern Asia Minor—the provinces of Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia. The problem here is that there is no hint that Peter had been there and no personal notations in the epistle to demonstrate his acquaintance with these churches. However, it does show that he was very interested in them. In fact, some believe that the reason why Paul was not allowed into this district according to <a href="?bref=Acts.16.7-8">Acts 16:7-8</a> was that Peter was already ministering there. In short, the question of Peter’s involvement in Asia Minor remains open.</p>
<p>There is no final NT evidence that Peter went to Rome. <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.13">First Peter 5:13</a> says that the epistle was sent from “Babylon,” and it is doubtful that this was the literal Babylon, because there is no tradition that Peter ever went there, and Babylon was sparsely populated back then. It is probably a cryptic symbol for Rome, the “Babylon of the West.” It is most likely that the “Babylon” of <a href="?bref=Rev.14.8">Revelation 14:8</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.16.19">16:19</a> is also a symbol of Rome. This would fit the strong tradition in the early church that indeed Peter did minister there.</p>
<p>There are four early external witnesses concerning Peter’s death. <a href="?bref=John.21.18">John 21:18</a> mentions only the martyrdom of Peter but does not give any hint as to the place. First Clement was written at the end of the first century and reports the martyrdom of Peter and Paul among others. While 1 Clement 5:4 testifies only to the fact and not the place of Peter’s martyrdom, a study of two aspects favors Rome—the reference to a “great multitude” of martyrdoms, which best fits the Neronian persecution, and the phrase “glorious example among us,” which shows that the people of Clement’s own church (Rome) were involved. Ignatius’s letter to the Romans (4:3) also testifies generally to the martyrdom of Peter and Paul, and again the context favors Rome as the place. He says, “I did not command you as did Peter and Paul,” which shows that they had ministries in Rome. The Ascension of Isaiah 4:2-3, a Jewish Christian work of the same period, speaks of Beliar (probably Nero) who martyrs “one of the Twelve,” almost certainly Peter. Therefore the earliest evidence does not explicitly point to Rome as the place of Peter’s death, but that is the most likely hypothesis.</p>
<p>Definite statements to that effect appear toward the end of the second century. Dionysius, bishop of Corinth, in a letter dated c. 170 (preserved in Eusebius’s <span class="ital">Ecclesiastical History</span> 2.25.8) says that Peter and Paul taught together in Italy. At the end of that century Irenaeus says (in <span class="ital">Against Heresies</span> 2.1-3) that Peter and Paul preached in Rome, and Tertullian in the same general period adds that Peter was martyred “like . . . the Lord” (<span class="ital">Scorpiace</span> 15). Clement of Alexandria and Origen both allude to Peter’s presence in Rome, and the latter adds the belief that he was “crucified head-downwards” (Eusebius’s <span class="ital">Ecclesiastical History</span> 2.15.2; 3.1.2). The tradition that Peter was crucified may be supported in <a href="?bref=John.21.18">John 21:18</a>: “when you are old, you will stretch out your hands, and others will . . . take you where you don’t want to go.”</p>
<p>The fact that Paul’s Epistle to the Romans (c. 55–57) does not mention Peter tells us that he could not have gone there earlier than that. If 1 Peter was written during the Neronian persecution, as those who hold Peter’s authorship believe, he must have gone there sometime in the late 50s or early 60s. Of course, the extent of his ministry in Rome also cannot be known. Some indeed have suggested that he had little or no extensive stay in Rome. The facts, as they can be recovered, point to uncertain conclusions. Peter did have some type of ministry in Rome, though the extent of it cannot be known. However, it is doubtful, in light of the early testimony to his preaching ministry there, that he was merely passing through Rome when caught in Nero’s pogrom. Therefore he most likely spent the last years of his ministry in Rome and there suffered martyrdom under Nero, perhaps by crucifixion.</p>
<p>Simon Peter, along with Paul, was the leading figure in the early church. His impact has been tragically dimmed by the bitter debates of Roman Catholic– Protestant circles, but the biblical evidence is clear. He was the leading disciple of Jesus and indeed the “rock” who provided the foundation for the church. As the representative disciple, his enthusiasm and even his weaknesses have made him the supreme example of the growing disciple, one who, through the power of the risen Lord, rose above his faults to become a towering figure on the church scene.</p>
  </body>
</item>