<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Prophecy">
  <title>Prophecy</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PROPHECY</p>
<p class="fl">This term, and the related “prophet,” “to prophesy,” “prophetism,” and “prophetic”, are derived from a group of Greek words that, in secular Greek, mean “speak forth,” “proclaim,” “announce.” In biblical Greek, however, these terms always carry the connotation of speaking, proclaiming, or announcing something under the influence of spiritual inspiration.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#ProphecyintheOldTestament">Prophecy in the Old Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TypesofOldTestamentProphets">Types of Old Testament Prophets</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheMessageoftheProphets">The Message of the Prophets</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#ProphecyintheNewTestament">Prophecy in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheRoleoftheChristianProphet">The Role of the Christian Prophet</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="ProphecyintheOldTestament">Prophecy in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">One of the clearest and most significant statements on the nature of prophetic inspiration in the OT is found in <a href="?bref=Num.12.6-8">Numbers 12:6-8</a>: “The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to them, ‘Now listen to me! Even with prophets, I the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> communicate by visions and dreams. But that is not how I communicate with my servant Moses. He is entrusted with my entire house. I speak to him face to face, directly and not in riddles! He sees the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> as he is’ ”. Several important insights into the nature of prophetic inspiration are found in this passage: (1) The prophetic gift of Moses was unique in that he alone received revelations directly from God. (2) Ordinarily, prophetic revelation was received in a dream or a vision. (3) The meaning of prophetic revelation is not always completely clear; prophecy is sometimes ambiguous.</p>
<p>Further insight into the nature of prophetic revelation is found in <a href="?bref=Deut.18.18">Deuteronomy 18:18</a>: “I [God] will raise up for them a prophet like you [Moses] from among their brethren; and I will put my words in his mouth, and he shall speak to them all that I command him”. While this passage is of interest because Jesus was identified as “the prophet like Moses” who came in fulfillment of this prediction (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.22">Acts 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.37">7:37</a>), the more immediate historical reference is to the succession of prophets that guided Israel from Joshua to Malachi. The phrase “I will put my words in his mouth” refers to the process of divine inspiration and is reminiscent of the common OT prophetic formula “the word of the Lord came to [such and such a prophet]” (for examples, see <a href="?bref=1Sam.15.10">1 Sm 15:10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.24.11">2 Sm 24:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.9">1 Kgs 19:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Jon.1.1">Jon 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1">Hg 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.1,20">2:1, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.7.1,8">Zec 7:1, 8</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.8.1">8:1</a>). A true prophet is one who speaks (or repeats) all that God has told him.</p>
<p class="h3">Modes of Prophetic Inspiration</p>
<p class="fl">Dreams were a commonly recognized mode of inspiration throughout the ancient world, though they were more highly regarded in Greece than in ancient Israel. Revelatory dreams in the Bible fall into two major categories: (1) dreams whose meaning is self-evident, and (2) symbolic dreams that usually require the expertise of an interpreter of dreams. Both types normally involve both visual and auditory elements. In those dreams whose meaning is self-evident, normally a supernatural being (God or an angel) appears to the dreamer and speaks to him or her in a straightforward manner.</p>
<p>More frequently, revelation dreams have symbolic elements that require interpretation. The two great dream interpreters of the OT are Joseph and Daniel; the latter is clearly a prophet. The two symbolic dreams that Joseph himself dreamed (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.5-11">Gn 37:5-11</a>) had sufficiently self-evident meaning so that his brothers and father were able to interpret them immediately. The dreams of the butler and baker were more complex (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.1-19">40:1-19</a>), as well as Pharaoh’s dream (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.1-36">41:1-36</a>), which Joseph was able to interpret with the help of God. Similarly, Daniel was enabled to interpret the dreams of Nebuchadnezzar (<a href="?bref=Dan.2.25-45">Dn 2:25-45</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.4.4-27">4:4-27</a>). Joseph and Daniel both attributed the skill in interpreting such dreams to God (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.8">Gn 40:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.41.16,25">41:16, 25</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.2.27-30">Dn 2:27-30</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Dan.4.9">4:9</a>). While dreams are used almost interchangeably with visions in referring to modes of prophetic inspiration (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.28">Jl 2:28</a>), dreams do not occupy a significant part in the prophetic revelations of any of the OT prophets, with the exception of Daniel.</p>
<p>One of the most characteristic modes of prophetic inspiration was the vision (<a href="?bref=Num.12.6">Nm 12:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.24.4,16">24:4, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.12.10">Hos 12:10</a>). The revelatory visions experienced by the prophets were not limited to visual phenomena alone but also included the auditory dimension as well. In <a href="?bref=Isa.1.1">Isaiah 1:1</a>, the author describes his entire prophetic book as a “vision”: “These visions concerning Judah and Jerusalem came to Isaiah son of Amoz during the reigns of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah—all kings of Judah”. Yet in the very next verse, Isaiah says, “Hear, O heavens! Listen, O earth! This is what the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> says.” Again, in <a href="?bref=Amos.1.1">Amos 1:1</a>, “The <span class="ital">words</span> of Amos, who was among the shepherds of Tekoa, which he <span class="ital">saw</span> concerning Israel” (emphasis added).</p>
<p class="h3">Manifestations of Prophetic Inspiration</p>
<p class="fl">All prophecy, whether biblical or not, presume that the prophet either possessed or was possessed by a personal supernatural power. The behaviors expressed from this possession vary greatly.</p>
<p>The phenomenon generally called “ecstatic” prophecy appears to have existed in Canaan prior to the arrival of the Hebrew tribes in the 13th century <span class="era">BC</span>. The first reference to ecstatic prophecy in Israel occurs in <a href="?bref=1Sam.10.5-13">1 Samuel 10:5-13</a> (11th century <span class="era">BC</span>), and it persisted at least till the sixth century <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=Jer.29.26">Jer 29:26</a>).</p>
<p>The ecstatic prophet achieves a trancelike state by self-induced means. The most common devices used to achieve a state of ecstasy were musical instruments, such as the harp, tambourine, flute, and lyre (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.5">1 Sm 10:5</a>). Among the prophets of Baal, self-flagellation was another means of inducing ecstasy (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.28-29">1 Kgs 18:28-29</a>).</p>
<p>This kind of prophetic ecstasy was usually practiced by groups of prophets (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.5">1 Sm 10:5</a>), and such ecstasy was contagious. When Saul met a band of such prophets, the Spirit of God came upon him and he, too, began to prophesy (vv <a href="?bref=1Sam.10.10-13">10-13</a>), a phenomenon that occurred repeatedly to various messengers sent by Saul on a later occasion (<a href="?bref=1Sam.19.20-22">19:20-22</a>). At that time Saul again prophesied, and his ecstatic behavior is described in <a href="?bref=1Sam.19.24">1 Samuel 19:24</a>. When Elisha was asked to prophesy for King Jehoram of Israel, he first requested a musician. When the musician played, the power of the Lord came upon him (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.15">2 Kgs 3:15</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TypesofOldTestamentProphets">Types of Old Testament Prophets</p>
<p class="fl">There are two basic types of prophetic commission in the OT. One type is that of a narrative call by God to a particular individual whose objections to the call are gradually overcome in a dialogue between himself and God. The classic example of this type of prophetic commission is found in <a href="?bref=Jer.1.4-8">Jeremiah 1:4-8</a>:</p>
<p class="extract-fl-space">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave me a message. He said, “I knew you before I formed you in your mother’s womb. Before you were born I set you apart and appointed you as my spokesman to the world.”</p>
<p class="extract">“O Sovereign <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,” I said, “I can’t speak for you! I’m too young!”</p>
<p class="extract">“Don’t say that,” the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> replied, “for you must go wherever I send you and say whatever I tell you. And don’t be afraid of the people, for I will be with you and take care of you. I, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, have spoken!”</p>
<p class="sp">Similar prophetic commissions including such dialogues are associated with the calls of Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.1-4.17">Ex 3:1–4:17</a>) and Gideon (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.11-17">Jgs 6:11-17</a>).</p>
<p>The second major form of prophetic commission is the “throne vision.” An outstanding example is <a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-8">Isaiah 6:1-8</a>:</p>
<p class="extract-fl-space">In the year King Uzziah died, I saw the Lord. He was sitting on a lofty throne, and the train of his robe filled the Temple. . . .</p>
<p class="extract">Then I said, “My destruction is sealed, for I am a sinful man and a member of a sinful race. Yet I have seen the King, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Almighty!”</p>
<p class="extract">Then one of the seraphim flew over to the altar, and he picked up a burning coal with a pair of tongs. He touched my lips with it and said, “See, this coal has touched your lips. Now your guilt is removed, and your sins are forgiven.”</p>
<p class="extract">Then I heard the Lord asking, “Whom should I send as a messenger to my people? Who will go for us?”</p>
<p class="extract">And I said, “Lord, I’ll go! Send me.”</p>
<p class="fl">Here we have an account of the visionary presence of a prophet in the heavenly council; in this case, however, the prophet participates in the deliberations and thereby receives a prophetic commission. Though few prophets have left accounts of their divine commissions, most of them appear to have been conscious of having been “sent” by God (<a href="?bref=Isa.48.16">Is 48:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.8.1">Hos 8:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.7.14-15">Am 7:14-15</a>). According to Jeremiah, false prophets did not receive such divine commissions (<a href="?bref=Jer.23.21,32">Jer 23:21, 32</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.28.15">28:15</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheMessageoftheProphets">The Message of the Prophets</p>
<p class="h3">The Form of the Message</p>
<p class="fl">The most common opening formula for prophetic oracles in the OT is the phrase “Thus says the Lord,” which occurs hundreds of times in prophetic contexts. This formula clearly implies that the message so introduced is not the word of the prophet who speaks the oracle but of the God of Israel who delivered his word to his prophet. The use of this formula also reiterates the prophet’s sense of divine commission. In oracles introduced in this manner, God speaks in the first person. In fact, virtually all Israelite prophetic utterance is formulated as the direct speech of the God of Israel.</p>
<p>The prophets used many literary forms in which to express their oracles. Two of the more widely used forms of prophetic speech are the judgment speech and the oracle of salvation. The judgment speech is composed of at least two central elements: the speech of rebuke or invective, and the pronouncement of judgment (see <a href="?bref=2Kgs.1.3-4">2 Kgs 1:3-4</a>). The second common prophetic speech form is the oracle of salvation (see <a href="?bref=Isa.41.8-13">Is 41:8-13</a>). Other fixed forms of prophetic speech include the prophecy of salvation (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.14-21">43:14-21</a>), the proclamation of salvation (<a href="?bref=Isa.41.17-20">41:17-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.42.14-17">42:14-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.43.16-21">43:16-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.49.7-12">49:7-12</a>), and the oracle of sorrow (<a href="?bref=Isa.5.8-10">Is 5:8-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.10.1-4">10:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.18-24">Am 5:18-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.6.1-7">6:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.2.1-5">Mi 2:1-5</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Content of the Message</p>
<p class="fl">All of the prophets predict the future. Such prediction, however, is based not on human curiosity of what the future will hold but rather is rooted in the future consequences of past or present violations of the covenant, or on a future act of deliverance that will provide hope for a discouraged people. Most of the prophetic speeches that have been preserved in the OT were originally delivered as public proclamations or sermons. Most of these prophetic proclamations were caused by the iniquity and apostasy of Israel. Hosea and Jeremiah condemned Israel because she had broken the covenant (<a href="?bref=Jer.11.2-3">Jer 11:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.8.1">Hos 8:1</a>).</p>
<p>The prophets are frequently associated with social justice and social reform, and these elements were unquestionably an important dimension of their message. Amos denounced the rich who afflicted the poor (<a href="?bref=Amos.2.6-8">Am 2:6-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.4.1">4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.11">5:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.4-6">8:4-6</a>). He railed against sexual immorality (<a href="?bref=Amos.2.6-8">2:6-8</a>) and against those who take bribes (<a href="?bref=Amos.5.12">5:12</a>). Hosea provided a list of prevalent vices, including lying, killing, stealing, adultery, and idolatry (<a href="?bref=Hos.4.2">Hos 4:2</a>). Idolatry was a particular target for his denunciations (<a href="?bref=Hos.8.5">8:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.11.2">11:2</a>). The background for such heated denunciations of Israel’s behavior is God’s unending love for Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.4">Is 43:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.31.3">Jer 31:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.3.1">Hos 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.11.1-4">11:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.14.4">14:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.1.2">Mal 1:2</a>), which is inseparable from his election of Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.1">Is 43:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.33.24">Jer 33:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.5">Ez 20:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.3.1-5">Hos 3</a>).</p>
<p>The prophets were concerned not only with the transgressions of Israel and the historical judgment that would inevitably follow but also with the achievement of a final future time of bliss. The message of many of the prophets is thoroughly concerned with the end times. One such end-time concept is that of the Day of the Lord. The concept of the Day of the Lord first appears in Amos, where the emphasis lies on the disaster that will fall upon Israel on that day. In spite of Amos’s emphasis on disaster, the Day of the Lord is a conception that had both salvation and judgment overtones for Israel. While the disaster that will occur in the Day of the Lord can be viewed in terms of a literal historical fulfillment in the tragic events of 722 <span class="era">BC</span> (the fall of Samaria) and 586 <span class="era">BC</span> (the fall of Judah), there are nevertheless features of these predictions that go beyond historical fulfillment and reach toward end-time fulfillment.</p>
<p>Since the Israelite conception of “salvation” was largely temporal in its dimensions, it included such blessings as length of life, fruitfulness of the womb and field, peace and victory over one’s enemies, the abundance of water, and so on. In harmony with this conception of salvation, the future age is conceived in precisely those terms, as in <a href="?bref=Amos.9.13-15">Amos 9:13-15</a>.</p>
<p>The prophets pictured a time when David himself, or someone very much like him, would return and inaugurate a golden era reminiscent of the great Davidic and Solomonic period. The covenant of God with David was not a conditional covenant but rather one that was absolutely inviolable (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.4-17">2 Sm 7:4-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.1-52">Ps 89</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.33.19-22">Jer 33:19-22</a>), and it was with this knowledge that the prophets could look forward confidently to a restoration of David’s throne (<a href="?bref=Jer.17.24-26">Jer 17:24-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.5-6">23:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.33.14-15">33:14-15</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Charts/Charts.xml" name="MessianicPropheciesAndFulfillments"/>
<p class="h2" id="ProphecyintheNewTestament">Prophecy in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In contrast to the few self-proclaimed prophets of the period between the old and new testaments, early Christianity began with a short intense period of prophetic activity that lasted well into the second century <span class="era">AD</span>. Jesus, his disciples and followers, and the early Christians were convinced that the times in which they lived were times in which OT prophecy was being fulfilled (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.14-15">Mk 1:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.16-21">Acts 2:16-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.16.25-27">Rom 16:25-27</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.11">1 Cor 10:11</a>). Yet this era was not only one of fulfillment but also one of the renewal of the prophetic gift.</p>
<p class="h3">John the Baptist</p>
<p class="fl">John the Baptist is remembered in the NT primarily as the forerunner of Jesus whose coming was predicted by Malachi (<a href="?bref=Mal.4.5-6">Mal 4:5-6</a>). Yet, in his own right, John proclaimed the imminent judgment of God with a sense of denunciation and rebuke reminiscent of the OT prophets. John’s clothes, consisting of a hairy cloak and a leather girdle (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.6">Mk 1:6</a>), was reminiscent of the typical clothing of OT prophets (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.19">1 Kgs 19:19</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.1.8">2 Kgs 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.13-14">2:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.13.4">Zec 13:4</a>). John was regarded as a prophet by people everywhere (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.5">Mt 14:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.17.10-13">17:10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.11-13">Mk 9:11-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.11.32">11:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.76">Lk 1:76</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.26">7:26</a>). Luke reports, in a style similar to the OT prophetic narratives, that “the word of God came to John” (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.2">Lk 3:2</a>). Two short prophetic speeches have been preserved in <a href="?bref=Matt.3.7-10">Matthew 3:7-10</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.3.7-9">Lk 3:7-9</a>) and <a href="?bref=Mark.1.7-8">Mark 1:7-8</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.3.11-12">Mt 3:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.15-18">Lk 3:15-18</a>). In the first speech, John denounced those of his generation who had transgressed the covenant law and urged them to change their manner of life. In the second speech, John predicted the coming of the Mighty One, Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.11">Mt 3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.7">Mk 1:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.16">Lk 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.15,27,30">Jn 1:15, 27, 30</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.25">Acts 13:25</a>). John’s style, however, was not precisely that of the OT prophets. His statements were made on his own authority; never did he use formulas such as “thus says the Lord,” or present his prophetic utterances as if they were speeches made by God. Yet, in spite of these differences, John is appropriately regarded as the last representative of the OT prophetic tradition (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.13">Mt 11:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.16.16">Lk 16:16</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Jesus of Nazareth</p>
<p class="fl">Jesus was popularly regarded as a prophet (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.14">Mt 16:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.21.10-11">21:10-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.14-15">Mk 6:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.28">8:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.16,39">Lk 7:16, 39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.8,19">9:8, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.14">Jn 6:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.7.40,52">7:40, 52</a>). This assessment was based as much on the mighty deeds Jesus performed as on his prophetic speeches and predictions. Though Jesus nowhere claimed prophetic status directly, that claim is implicit in <a href="?bref=Mark.6.4">Mark 6:4</a>: “A prophet is honored everywhere except in his own hometown” (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.13.57">Mt 13:57</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.24">Lk 4:24</a>). It is implicit as well in <a href="?bref=Luke.13.33">Luke 13:33</a>: “Yes, today, tomorrow, and the next day I must proceed on my way. For it wouldn’t do for a prophet of God to be killed except in Jerusalem!”. In Acts, Jesus is regarded as “the prophet like Moses” predicted in <a href="?bref=Deut.18.18">Deuteronomy 18:18</a> (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.22">Acts 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.37">7:37</a>). Matthew presents Jesus as the New Moses, but he does not particularly emphasize his prophetic role. John, however, like Luke, emphasizes Jesus’s role as the prophet (<a href="?bref=John.4.19">Jn 4:19</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.14-15">6:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=John.7.40">7:40</a>).</p>
<p>While the Gospels and Acts reflect the notion that Jesus was a prophet, they also emphasize the fact that he was much more than a prophet. Nevertheless, the notion of prophetism was important enough in early Judaism that Jesus’s recognition as a prophet is very significant. There are 12 solid reasons for regarding Jesus as a prophet in the OT tradition: (1) The sovereign authority of Jesus’s teaching (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.27">Mk 1:27</a>), a feature underlined by his use of the introductory formula “(Amen) I say to you,” which is reminiscent of the formula “thus says the Lord” used by the OT prophets. (2) The poetic character of many of Jesus’s sayings is unlike contemporary rabbinic teaching but is similar to the poetic rhetoric of the OT prophets. (3) Jesus experienced visions (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.18">Lk 10:18</a>) like the ancient prophets. (4) Jesus, like the prophets, made many predictions (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.38">Mt 23:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.2">Mk 13:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.58">14:58</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.35">Lk 13:35</a>; etc.). (5) Like the OT prophets, Jesus performed symbolic acts (such as the cleansing of the temple, the entry into Jerusalem, and the Last Supper). (6) Jesus, like the prophets, when necessary, rejected the formal observance of religious ritual and emphasized the moral and spiritual dimensions of obedience to God. (7) Jesus announced the imminent arrival of the kingdom of God—an end-time proclamation similar to those made by the prophets. (8) Like the OT prophets, Jesus functioned as a preacher of repentance. (9) Jesus, like many of the prophets, was conscious of a special calling of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.24">Mt 15:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.31">Mk 8:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.37">9:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.36">14:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.18-26">Lk 4:18-26</a>). (10) Jesus, like the prophets, received divine revelation through intimate communion with God (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.27">Mt 11:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.22">Lk 10:22</a>). (11) Like the prophets, Jesus represented God; to obey him was to obey God, to reject him was to reject God (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.37">Mk 9:37</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.30-33">Ez 33:30-33</a>). (12) Like the prophets, Jesus was conscious of a mission to all Israel (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.24">Mt 15:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.19.28">19:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.22.30">Lk 22:30</a>).</p>
<p>Among the many prophetic predictions of Jesus are the following:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Predictions of the imminent arrival of the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.7-8,23">Mt 10:7-8, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.39">23:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.15">Mk 1:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.1">9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.28-29">13:28-29</a>)</p>
<p class="list">2. Predictions of the destruction of Jerusalem and the temple (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.37-39">Mt 23:37-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.2">24:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.26.61">26:61</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.27.40">27:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.2">Mk 13:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.58">14:58</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.15.29">15:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.34-35">Lk 13:34-35</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.21.6">21:6</a>; <a href="?bref=John.2.19-21">Jn 2:19-21</a>)</p>
<p class="list">3. Predictions of the coming of the Son of Man (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.23,32-33">Mt 10:23, 32-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.12.40">12:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.13.40-41">13:40-41</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.16.27">16:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.27,37-39">24:27, 37-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.38">Mk 8:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.26-27">13:26-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.62">14:62</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.26">Lk 9:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.30">11:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.8-9">12:8-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.17.24,26">17:24, 26</a>)</p>
<p class="list">4. Predictions of the end of the age. The longest prophetic section in the Gospels is the end-time discourse of Jesus in <a href="?bref=Mark.13.1-32">Mark 13:1-32</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.24.1-36">Mt 24:1-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.21.5-33">Lk 21:5-33</a>), in which a number of predictions concerning the destruction of Jerusalem and the end of the age are woven into a long discourse to the disciples.</p>
<p class="h3">Prophecy as a Gift for the Believers</p>
<p class="fl">The beginning of prophetic activity in early Christianity, according to Acts, coincided with the outpouring of the Holy Spirit upon the earliest Christians on the Day of Pentecost (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.1-21">Acts 2:1-21</a>). Peter’s sermon on the Day of Pentecost indicates that the outpouring of the Spirit fulfilled Joel’s prophecy (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.4,17-21">Acts 2:4, 17-21</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-32">Jl 2:28-32</a>). Further, since the Spirit had been poured out upon all early Christians (that Spirit being a Spirit of prophecy), all are actual or potential prophets.</p>
<p>According to <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.28">1 Corinthians 12:28</a> (see also <a href="?bref=Rom.12.6">Rom 12:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.11">Eph 4:11</a>), God has appointed in the church first apostles, second prophets, and third teachers. The names of several early Christian prophets have been preserved. These include Agabus (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.27-28">Acts 11:27-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.21.10-11">21:10-11</a>); Judas and Silas (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.32">15:32</a>); Barnabas, Simeon Niger, Lucius of Cyrene, Manaen, and Paul (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.1">13:1</a>); and the four virgin daughters of Philip the evangelist (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.8-9">21:8-9</a>). John, the author of Revelation, was certainly a prophet (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.3">Rv 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.22.9,18">22:9, 18</a>), though he never directly assumed that title.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheRoleoftheChristianProphet">The Role of the Christian Prophet</p>
<p class="fl">Christian prophets were leaders in early Christian communities (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.28">1 Cor 12:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.11">Eph 4:11</a>), who exercised their gift in church gatherings (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.1-3">Acts 13:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.27-28">11:27-28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.1-14.40">1 Cor 12–14</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.1.10">Rv 1:10</a>). Since the Spirit of God was particularly active in Christian worship, prophecy was a major means whereby God communicated with his people. Prophets, like apostles and teachers, did not hold offices in local communities like bishops, elders, and deacons. Rather, they were chosen, not by individual congregations, but by divine commission and so were honored and accepted in all local communities.</p>
<p>Early Christian prophets were both itinerant and settled, though itinerant prophets seem to have been more prevalent in Syria-Palestine and Asia Minor than in the European churches.</p>
<p class="h3">The Function of Prophecy</p>
<p class="fl">According to Paul, the central purpose of prophecy (as of all other spiritual gifts) is that of building up or edifying the church. According to <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.3">1 Corinthians 14:3</a>, “one who prophesies is helping others grow in the Lord, encouraging and comforting them”. Again, in <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.4">1 Corinthians 14:4</a>, Paul states that the “one who speaks a word of prophecy strengthens the entire church.” Paul discussed the subject of spiritual gifts, particularly tongues speaking and prophecy, because the Corinthians had placed an excessive emphasis on speaking in tongues. Paul did not object to speaking in tongues (<a href="?bref=1Cor.14.18,39">1 Cor 14:18, 39</a>), but he did point out that, since it was generally incomprehensible, the church could not be edified by it. Prophecy, which consisted of comprehensible speech inspired by the Spirit, contributed to the mutual edification, encouragement, and consolation of all present (<a href="?bref=1Cor.14.20-25,39">1 Cor 14:20-25, 39</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Content of Christian Prophecy</p>
<p class="fl">We know only a little about the content of prophecies given in the first-century church. Prophecies occasionally provided divine guidance in making important decisions in early Christianity. Through a prophetic message, Paul and Barnabas were selected for a particular mission (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.1-3">Acts 13:1-3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Tim.1.18">1 Tm 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.4.14">4:14</a>). Probably through a prophecy, Paul and Timothy were forbidden to preach the gospel in Asia (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.6">Acts 16:6</a>), and they were similarly forbidden by the Spirit of Jesus to go into Bithynia (v <a href="?bref=Acts.16.7">7</a>). Perhaps the most frequent use of prophecy is the prediction of the future. Agabus predicted a universal famine (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.28">11:28</a>) and the imminent arrest of Paul (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.11">21:11</a>). Other prophets had also predicted his impending imprisonment (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.23">20:23</a>). The prophecies contained in the Revelation of John are all oriented toward the future events that will gradually unfold in the last days. Yet the purpose of John’s elaborate prophecy is not to satisfy the curiosity of his audience but rather to comfort and encourage them as they go through persecution.</p>
<p class="h3">The Form of Christian Prophecy</p>
<p class="fl">Unlike the prophets of the OT, Christian prophets did not always present their message in the form of a direct speech from God or Jesus. There are few, if any, formal indicators of the presence of prophetic speech in early Christian literature. The book of Revelation is one notable exception.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Dreams_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dreams</a>; <a href="?item=Oracle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Oracle</a>; <a href="?item=Promise_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Promise</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetProphetess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophet, Prophetess</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetsFalse_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophets, False</a>; <a href="?item=VisionVisions_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Visions</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>