<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Light">
  <title>Light</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">LIGHT</p>
<p class="fl">Illumination that makes sight possible.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Light is a many-sided concept in the OT. The term is often used of ordinary, sensible light, but it also speaks of communicating spiritual truth. Light was the first thing God created after the heavens and earth (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.3">Gn 1:3</a>). God also made individual lights such as the sun, moon, and stars (v <a href="?bref=Gen.1.16">16</a>). Sometimes light is personified, as when its inaccessibility is indicated by saying that it is impossible to reach the place where it lives (<a href="?bref=Job.38.19">Jb 38:19</a>; cf. v <a href="?bref=Job.38.24">24</a>). There are also manufactured light sources, such as those used in the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.37">Ex 25:37</a>).</p>
<p>Light is a natural symbol for what is pleasant, good, or uplifting, or what is associated with important people and more especially with God. “Light is pleasant,” says the preacher (<a href="?bref=Eccl.11.7">Eccl 11:7</a>). During one of the plagues in Egypt, the Egyptians were in thick darkness while the Israelites had light (<a href="?bref=Exod.10.23">Ex 10:23</a>). When the Israelites left Egypt, they were led in the wilderness by a pillar of cloud by day and of fire by night (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.21">13:21</a>). The pillar gave them light when their enemies were in darkness (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.20">14:20</a>). In later days Israel remembered that God did not abandon his people even when they sinned; the pillar of fire was always there to show them the right way (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.19">Neh 9:19</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Neh.9.12">Neh 9:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.14">Pss 78:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.105.39">105:39</a>).</p>
<p>Light symbolizes the blessing of the Lord. Job said, “He floods the darkness with light; he brings light to the deepest gloom” (<a href="?bref=Job.12.22">Jb 12:22</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). In his time of trouble Job recalled earlier, better days: “I long for the years gone by when God took care of me, when he lighted the way before me and I walked safely through the darkness” (<a href="?bref=Job.29.2-3">Jb 29:2-3</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Similarly Eliphaz pictured the happiness that would come to Job if he followed Eliphaz’s advice: “Whatever you decide to do will be accomplished, and light will shine on the road ahead of you” (<a href="?bref=Job.22.28">Jb 22:28</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Eliphaz’s use of that expression shows what is commonly conveyed in his day. The psalmist counted it a blessing when God himself lighted his lamp (<a href="?bref=Ps.18.28">Pss 18:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.118.27">118:27</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.97.11">97:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.112.4">112:4</a>).</p>
<p>Light is closely linked with God; indeed, God can be said to be light: “No longer will you need the sun or moon to give you light, for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God will be your everlasting light, and he will be your glory. The sun will never set; the moon will not go down. For the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will be your everlasting light” (<a href="?bref=Isa.60.19-20">Is 60:19-20</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The psalmist rejoiced, “The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is my light and my salvation” (<a href="?bref=Ps.27.1">Ps 27:1</a>). God is said to be dressed in a robe of light (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.2">104:2</a>), and light dwells with him (<a href="?bref=Dan.2.22">Dn 2:22</a>). Darkness is no problem to God; darkness and light are alike to him (<a href="?bref=Ps.139.12">Ps 139:12</a>). Micah saw God as light and also as bringing his servants into the light (<a href="?bref=Mic.7.8-9">Mi 7:8-9</a>). Both are ways of affirming that there is blessing and victory with God, so that a servant of God should never be discouraged.</p>
<p>God’s blessing, described in terms of light, is also related to “the light of his presence.” Something of that expression’s meaning is seen from its use in <a href="?bref=Ps.4.6">Psalm 4:6</a>: “Many people say, ‘Who will show us better times?’ Let the smile of your face shine on us, <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). The parallelism shows that “good” and the lifting up of the light of God’s countenance are much the same. Similarly, it was the light of God’s countenance that brought victory (<a href="?bref=Ps.44.3">Ps 44:3</a>; here it is linked with God’s right hand and arm and his delight in his people). Those who walk in the light of God’s countenance are blessed (<a href="?bref=Ps.89.15">89:15</a>). There is another side to that expression, for secret sins are exposed in his light (<a href="?bref=Ps.90.8">90:8</a>). There is a close examination from which no one and nothing can escape. But the main idea is the blessing that follows when God looks upon his people. On one occasion the phrase is used of a person showing favor to others (<a href="?bref=Job.29.24">Jb 29:24</a>). An extension of the Lord’s blessing is the light God gives to the world through his servants (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.6">Is 42:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.49.6">49:6</a>). God’s servants can guide others to the revelation and blessing of God.</p>
<p>Light is associated with justice when the Lord says, “A law will go forth from me, and my justice for a light to the peoples” (<a href="?bref=Isa.51.4">Is 51:4</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). God’s light in that act of justice is a consuming fire. Sometimes light is connected with good behavior: “The path of the righteous is like the light of dawn, which shines brighter and brighter until full day” (<a href="?bref=Pr.4.18">Prv 4:18</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>The OT uses the absence of light as a synonym for disaster. There are those who grope in the dark without light (<a href="?bref=Job.12.25">Jb 12:25</a>). Bildad saw the light of the wicked put out in punishment and death (<a href="?bref=Job.18.5-17">18:5-17</a>). The wicked will be “thrust from light into darkness” (v <a href="?bref=Job.18.18">18</a>). In the aftermath of the Babylonian destruction of Jerusalem there came the lament “He has brought me into deep darkness, shutting out all light” (<a href="?bref=Lam.3.2">Lam 3:2</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">New Testament references to light are often figurative. Thus, on the Damascus road, Saul of Tarsus encountered “a light from heaven” (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.3">Acts 9:3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.22.6-11">22:6-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.13">26:13</a>). Was that light as we know it or something else? Likewise, what quality of light shone in the apostle Peter’s cell (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.7">12:7</a>)? The light in the heavenly city is not the kind of illumination seen on earth, “for the Lord God will be their light” (<a href="?bref=Rev.22.5">Rv 22:5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.21.11,23-24">21:11, 23-24</a>).</p>
<p>The association of God with light is recurrent in the NT. The apostle John wrote that “God is light and there is no darkness in him at all” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.5">1 Jn 1:5</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The apostle James referred to God as “the Father of lights” (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.17">Jas 1:17</a>). Or God may be thought of as living in light, light that no person can approach (<a href="?bref=1Tim.6.16">1 Tm 6:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Jn.1.7">1 Jn 1:7</a>). Jesus said, “I am the light of the world” (<a href="?bref=John.8.12">Jn 8:12</a>; see also <a href="?bref=John.9.5">9:5</a>), and “I have come as light into the world, that whoever believes in me may not remain in darkness” (<a href="?bref=John.12.46">Jn 12:46</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Jesus told his followers to believe in the light while it was with them (v <a href="?bref=John.12.35">35</a>). Such passages emphasize that Christ brought a revelation from God, but he was more than a revealer. He was himself that revelation, according to the apostle John (<a href="?bref=John.1.1-10">Jn 1:1-10</a>). John the Baptist came to bear witness to the light for the purpose of bringing people to believe (vv <a href="?bref=John.1.7-8">7-8</a>). Those who received Jesus, who believed in the light, received the right to become children of God (vv <a href="?bref=John.1.9-12">9-12</a>). Sometimes light is used to express the illumination that happens when people learn about God and his salvation (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.16">Mt 4:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.32">Lk 2:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.47">Acts 13:47</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.18">26:18</a>).</p>
<p>Perhaps thinking of a then-popular concept of a war between light and darkness, John wrote that the light shines in the darkness and adds that the darkness has not overcome it (<a href="?bref=John.1.5">Jn 1:5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.8">1 Jn 2:8</a>). John tells us that “the light from heaven came into the world, but they loved the darkness more than the light, for their actions were evil” (<a href="?bref=John.3.19">Jn 3:19</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). To love darkness brings condemnation, now and at the final judgment. John pointed out that evildoers keep away from the light; they do not want their evil exposed. But those who “do the truth” come to the light (vv <a href="?bref=John.3.20-21">20-21</a>). In John’s account of the raising of Lazarus, Jesus speaks of the possibility of walking without stumbling in the light of day, but then he goes on to the way a man stumbles in the night because he has no light (<a href="?bref=John.11.10">11:10</a>). The lack of light “in” the man shows that it is a spiritual process with which Jesus is concerned and not with making physical progress by daylight. He who follows Jesus will have the light of life (<a href="?bref=John.8.12">8:12</a>), which indicates what Jesus has in mind.</p>
<p>Those who respond to the light may be characterized as “sons of light” (<a href="?bref=John.12.36">Jn 12:36</a>). Their allegiance is to the light and their conduct has been shaped by this fact. The concept is not confined to John’s Gospel, for we also see it in Luke (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.8">Lk 16:8</a>). We find it in Paul’s affirmation that the Thessalonian Christians are children of light and of the day, not of the night or darkness (<a href="?bref=1Thes.5.5">1 Thes 5:5</a>). John speaks of walking in the light (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.7">1 Jn 1:7</a>) and sees the behavior of the Christian as effectively symbolized by light.</p>
<p>This way of looking at the Christian’s manner of life reaches its high point in the words of Jesus to his followers: “You are the light of the world” (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.14">Mt 5:14</a>), thus applying to them words that are also applied to himself. Of course, we are not the world’s light in the same sense as he is. When light refers to Christ, there is a reference to him as Savior and not merely as one who reveals great truths. When believers are called the light of the world, there is clearly no saving significance in the description: they do not accomplish the world’s salvation. But they do point it out. It is their function to live as redeemed people. They are to show the quality of life proper to the people of God and in this way act as light to the people of the world. They are to let their light shine before the world in such a way that people will see their good deeds and so come to praise God (not, be it noted, those who do the deeds, <a href="?bref=Matt.5.16">Mt 5:16</a>). It is important for those in this position to make full use of the light they have. It is tragic when the light that is in them is darkness (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.23">Mt 6:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.35">Lk 11:35</a>).</p>
<p>This metaphor is explained in a way that modern men and women may not fully understand, but the basic lesson is clear. Christians have been illuminated by the light that is Christ, who dwells within his people. If they ignore the illumination he brings and live like those in the dark, then indeed they are in deep darkness. They are worse than others because they know what light is and what it can mean to them, and have turned away from it.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Darkness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Darkness</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>