<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Mary">
  <title>Mary</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MARY</p>
<p class="fl">Popular feminine name among first-century Jews, borne by six (or seven) women in the NT.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Mary, the mother of Jesus. According to the infancy narratives of Matthew and Luke, Mary was a young Jewish virgin, probably from the tribe of Judah, who during her engagement to Joseph (of Davidic descent from the tribe of Judah) was discovered to be pregnant. It happened because she submitted to the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.18-25">Mt 1:18-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.26-38">Lk 1:26-38</a>). The couple married and lived first in Nazareth of Galilee, then traveled to Bethlehem (Joseph’s hometown) for a census, where Jesus was born (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.1">Mt 2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.5">Lk 1:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.4-5">2:4-5</a>). Matthew informs us that shortly after the birth the family had to flee to Egypt to escape Herod (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.13-14">Mt 2:13-14</a>). Later, the family resided again in Nazareth (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.23">Mt 2:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.39">Lk 2:39</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">We have little other information about Mary. She was certainly a concerned mother (as her scolding of Jesus in <a href="?bref=Luke.2.48">Lk 2:48</a> shows), and she later had a high estimate of Jesus’ ability (as at the wedding in Cana, <a href="?bref=John.2.1-4">Jn 2:1-4</a>). She had several other sons and daughters to care for. She appeared at the foot of the cross, where Jesus asked “the beloved disciple” to care for her in her grief (<a href="?bref=John.19.25-27">Jn 19:25-27</a>). After the resurrection she and Jesus’ brothers were among the disciples who experienced the outpouring of the Spirit on Pentecost (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.14">Acts 1:14</a>). No further mention is made of her.</p>
<p class="list-text">Mary’s song of praise, “The Magnificat” (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.46-55">Lk 1:46-55</a>) shows her strong humility and trust in God’s will. She is truly “blessed among women” (v <a href="?bref=Luke.1.42">42</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Mary, the mother of James and Joseph. This woman goes by several names, but in each account she appears among Jesus’ faithful female disciples, standing by the cross and witnessing the empty tomb. Matthew calls her “Mary the mother of James and Joseph” or just “the other Mary” (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.56,61">27:56, 61</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.28.1">28:1</a>); Mark names her “Mary the mother of James the younger and of Joses,” “Mary the mother of Joses,” or “Mary the mother of James” (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.40,47">15:40, 47</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.16.1">16:1</a>); in John’s Gospel, she is “Mary wife of Clopas” (<a href="?bref=John.19.25">19:25</a>), though she may possibly be a separate Mary. Tradition has it that this Mary was Jesus’ aunt, as Clopas was Joseph’s brother (Eusebius’s <span class="ital">Ecclesiastical History</span> 3.11).</p>
<p class="list">3. Mary Magdalene. We know little about this woman other than that her name indicates that she was from Magdala in Galilee. Somewhere in Galilee she met Jesus, who cast seven demons out of her. She then joined the band of disciples and followed Jesus wherever he went (<a href="?bref=Luke.8.2">Lk 8:2</a>), ending up in Jerusalem at the foot of the cross when all the male disciples had fled (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.40">Mk 15:40</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.25">Jn 19:25</a>). She observed Jesus’ burial (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.47">Mk 15:47</a>) and witnessed the events surrounding the resurrection. <a href="?bref=Matt.28.1">Matthew 28:1</a>, <a href="?bref=Mark.16.1">Mark 16:1</a>, and <a href="?bref=Luke.24.10">Luke 24:10</a> group her with the other women who went to the tomb. John says that she was the first among these women to discover the empty tomb, the first to report to the disciples, and the first to see the risen Christ as she stayed by the tomb after all the others had left (<a href="?bref=John.20.1-2,11-18">Jn 20:1-2, 11-18</a>). This faithful disciple, however, was not allowed to touch her Lord (v <a href="?bref=John.20.17">17</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Mary of Bethany. This Judean Mary was the sister of Martha and Lazarus. We know three facts about her. First, she was such a devoted follower of Jesus that she neglected her household duties to listen to him (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.38-42">Lk 10:38-42</a>; Jesus approved this). Second, she was apparently upset with Jesus when he did not come to heal her brother before he died (<a href="?bref=John.11.20,28-33">Jn 11:20, 28-33</a>). Finally, before Jesus died, she anointed him with an expensive ointment while he feasted at her home in Bethany (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.6-13">Mt 26:6-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.3-9">Mk 14:3-9</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.1-8">Jn 12:1-8</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Mary, mother of John Mark. This woman appears only once in Scripture (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.12">Acts 12:12</a>). Her house was the meeting place of the persecuted church. Since it was apparently large and she had servants, she was a wealthy woman, probably a widow (since no husband is mentioned). In her house the church prayed for Peter, and Peter came there after being released from prison. Her son John Mark accompanied Paul and probably Peter as well.</p>
<p class="list">6. Mary of Rome. In <a href="?bref=Rom.16.6">Romans 16:6</a> Paul greets a woman in Rome named simply “Mary, who has worked hard among you.” At some time she had been in Greece or Asia Minor, perhaps being expelled from Rome with Aquila and Priscilla (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.2">Acts 18:2</a>; c. <span class="era">AD</span> 49). While there she had met Paul, perhaps being converted by him, and had worked hard with him in his work of evangelism or caring for the church. By <span class="era">AD</span> 56 (a probable date for the book of Romans), she had returned to Rome. Paul praised her and his other coworkers living in Rome.</p>
  </body>
</item>