<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MediateMediator">
  <title>Mediate, Mediator</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MEDIATE, MEDIATOR</p>
<p class="fl">The act of an intermediary, go-between, or expert in divine things, not to negotiate agreement or compromise but to approach God on behalf of others, and so to convey desired knowledge and reassurance with divine authority.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Job voices longing for such a mediator (translated here from the LXX): “God is not a mortal like me, so I cannot argue with him or take him to trial. If only there were a mediator who could bring us together, but there is none. The mediator could make God stop beating me, and I would no longer live in terror of his punishment. Then I could speak to him without fear, but I cannot do that in my own strength” (<a href="?bref=Job.9.32-35">Jb 9:32-35</a>).</p>
<p>More familiar is the mediation of instruction concerning the divine character and will. The Mosaic covenant was given through the mediation of angels and of Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.18-21">Ex 20:18-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.33.2">Dt 33:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.53">Acts 7:53</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.19">Gal 3:19</a>; contrast <a href="?bref=Heb.6.13-17">Heb 6:13-17</a>, where God, acting alone, “mediated” an oath). The terms of the covenant law were expounded by prophets who “stood in God’s council,” and by priests who communicated God’s mind by oracle, sacred lot, and pronounced blessing (<a href="?bref=Deut.10.8">Dt 10:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.33.8-10">33:8-10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.15.3">2 Chr 15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.10-11,18-22,31-34">Jer 23:10-11, 18-22, 31-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.3.11">Mi 3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.2.7">Mal 2:7</a>).</p>
<p>Most familiar is the liturgical mediation of the priest, whether by Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.4-8">Ex 24:4-8</a>) or by an appointed person trained in the rituals of worship (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.1">28:1</a>). Because of Israel’s emphasis upon the holiness of God, sacrificial expiation, or “covering,” of sin figured largely in priestly mediation. The priest represented before God the people’s penitence, confession, and prayers for forgiveness, bearing the tribes’ names on shoulders and breastplate, and represented God, in turn, assuring his favor, forgiveness, and protection (see <a href="?bref=Heb.5.1-4">Heb 5:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.27-10.11">7:27–10:11</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">It was natural that the mission of Jesus should be described in mediatorial terms, and first as that of a prophet speaking for God to humans, making God known (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.15">Mk 6:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.28">8:28</a>). Where applied to Jesus, the actual title “mediator” refers mainly to his institution of a new covenant, establishing God’s new relationship with people (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.6">Heb 8:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.15">9:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.12.24">12:24</a>). The one other instance is <a href="?bref=1Tim.2.5">1 Timothy 2:5</a>, where the unity of God requires a sole, unrivaled mediator, namely, Christ.</p>
<p>This last reference mentions Christ’s giving himself as “a ransom for all.” This essentially priestly function is the theme of Hebrews. Christ as Son of God, divinely appointed, sinless, suffering, tempted, sympathizing, and obedient, is uniquely qualified to be High Priest of his people. As priest, he offers a perfect sacrifice and lives forever to intercede for those who draw near to God through him. This mediatorial ministry places Jesus at “the right hand of God.” His intercession for people is mentioned also in <a href="?bref=Rom.8.34">Romans 8:34</a> and probably in <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.1">1 John 2:1</a>, where ancient Greek commentators, <span class="sc">neb</span>, and other authoritative sources so understand “paraclete,” here applied to Jesus. His mediatorial sacrifice is mentioned in Matthew (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.28">Mt 26:28</a>), John (<a href="?bref=John.1.29">Jn 1:29</a>), Romans (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">Rom 3:25</a>), and 1 John (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.7">1 Jn 1:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.2">2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.10">4:10</a>).</p>
<p>Still more significant is the insistence, everywhere in the NT, that man’s knowledge of God, salvation, and hope come through Christ alone. Made poor for our sakes, he died and rose “for us”; our peace, access to God, reconciliation, expiation of sin, grace, truth, prayer, and “all spiritual blessings” are “through him,” “in him,” “through his blood,” and “in his name.” The purpose of God focuses in him; he mediated at Creation and at redemption (<a href="?bref=Col.1.15,22">Col 1:15, 22</a>); in him all the fullness of God dwells, and the face of Christ reveals God’s glory. No one knows the Father except the Son and those to whom the Son reveals him; no one comes to the Father but by him; neither is there salvation in any other.</p>
<p>Christ’s mediation is the fulfillment and end of all mediation between God and humankind. The book of Hebrews opens with the assertion that Christ surpasses all other mediators—angels, Moses, the Aaronic priesthood. His is a timeless priesthood, like Melchizedek’s. His sacrifice is unrepeatable, “once for all time,” and by it we have been consecrated to God “for all time.” The covenant he established between God and people offers better promises, sacrifice, sanctuary, and hope (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.19">Heb 7:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.8.6">8:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.1,11-15">9:1, 11-15</a>). Christ’s mediation so far excels all others that it can never be superseded; he is priest without rival and forever (cf. <a href="?bref=1Tim.2.5">1 Tm 2:5</a>).</p>
<p>Without using the priestly analogy, John emphasizes the same truth. The gulf between divine and human has been crossed, decisively and finally, by the Incarnation. Instead of standing between God and man, Christ unites both within himself by becoming man. Mediating in the beginning at Creation, Christ is himself the Word, which from God’s side mediates God’s mind, embodies God’s message, and conveys God’s power. No one has seen God at any time, but as unique Son and divine, Jesus “expounds” God (<a href="?bref=John.1.18">Jn 1:18</a>). From the human side, Jesus prays for the disciples (ch <a href="?bref=John.17.1-26">17</a>), offers perfect obedience, lays down his life for his flock, and offers the unblemished sacrifice that bears away the sin of the world.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Reconciliation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Reconciliation</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="AnyOtherMediators"/>
  </body>
</item>