<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Messiah">
  <title>Messiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MESSIAH</p>
<p class="fl">Title derived from the Hebrew, <span class="hebrew">mashiach</span><span class="ital">,</span> a verbal adjective meaning “anointed one.” Along with its NT equivalent, <span class="greek">christos</span> (Christ), it refers to an act of consecration whereby an individual is set apart to serve God and then anointed with oil. The verbal root <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">mashach</span><span class="ital">)</span> conveys this idea as well.</p>
<p>Israel’s ceremonial anointing with oil is present in several contexts. Priests were regularly anointed prior to their God-given service of sacrificing at the altar (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.3">Lv 4:3</a>). There is evidence of prophets being literally anointed (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.16">1 Kgs 19:16</a>), although it wasn’t standard practice. Samuel anointed Saul and David, and it became an established prerequisite for Hebrew kings before they assumed their positions of royal leadership. The king was especially considered to be the Lord’s anointed and as such held a secure position before men (<a href="?bref=1Sam.12.14">1 Sm 12:14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.19.21">2 Sm 19:21</a>) and God (<a href="?bref=Ps.2.2">Pss 2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.20.6">20:6</a>). Along with many messianic prophecies, this practice informed the Jews that a very special and unique Anointed One would eventually come to bring salvation to Israel.</p>
<p class="h2" id="MessiahintheOldTestament">Messiah in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Jewish hope for the coming Messiah actively developed from the period of David’s reign, when it was prophesied that his kingdom would have no end (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.16">2 Sm 7:16</a>). Israel was told that, through David’s descendants, his throne would have a never-ending dominion over all the earth (<a href="?bref=2Sam.22.48-51">2 Sm 22:48-51</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.33.1-26">Jer 33</a>). It is with this aspect of messianic salvation that Jewish minds have traditionally been preoccupied (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.1.6">Acts 1:6</a>).</p>
<p>Among Orthodox rabbis there has never been a lack of information concerning the details of the Messiah’s ministry. By and large, Jewish Orthodoxy still retains its time-worn belief in the Messiah’s reign in Jerusalem, the rebuilding of the temple, and the reestablishment of both priesthood and sacrifice.</p>
<p>While later Judaism looked for the Messiah as an important person who will reign at the end of time, modern Jewish thought has largely rejected the traditional view in favor of a belief in a messianic age. Prevalent liberal Judaism envisions the world ultimately perfected through the Judaic ideals of justice and compassion. Such conviction ignores mankind’s fallen condition and the teaching of Scripture. It replaces the need for a miraculous intervention from heaven with humanism.</p>
<p>While the Messiah’s origin is linked firmly to the house of David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.14">2 Sm 7:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.3.5">Hos 3:5</a>), the promise for a Messiah was given long before David lived. In fact, the hope for the Messiah is implicit in the first promise of the establishment of the kingdom of God. <a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Genesis 3:15</a> declares to Satan that God will place hostility between the serpent and the woman until the “seed” of the woman inflicts a fatal blow to the head of the serpent.</p>
<p>Messianic prophecy is progressive in nature; each prophecy casts more light on the subject. This occurs, for example, with the concept of the “seed”: Messiah is to be born of a woman (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Gn 3:15</a>), through the line of Shem (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.26">9:26</a>) and specifically through Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.22.18">22:18</a>). Yet even as late as <a href="?bref=Gen.22.18">Genesis 22:18</a>, the “seed” is not clearly presented as a person, since <span class="hebrew">zerah</span> (seed) may indicate a singular or plural object. Still less apparent in these early stages of messianic prophecy is the nature of the “bruising” that is to occur. Yet the idea of the Messiah being crushed for sin is implicit in this text of Genesis, as is the violence associated with its fulfilment. The main messianic prophet, Isaiah, gives full range to the truth that the Anointed One must bear extensive suffering (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.1">Is 53:1</a>). Under the figure “the Servant of the Lord,” four “servant songs” outline the mission of the future deliverer (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.1-7">Is 42:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.49.1-9">49:1-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.50.4-11">50:4-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.52.13-53.12">52:13–53:12</a>). Isaiah does not explicitly link the title Messiah with the Servant of the Lord, but identifying both figures as being one and the same person is justifiable. Both are uniquely anointed (<a href="?bref=Isa.61.1">61:1</a>); each brings light to the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Isa.55.4">55:4</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.49.6">49:6</a>); neither appear majestic at first (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.14-15">7:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1">11:1</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.42.3">42:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1">53:1</a>); and they both carry the Davidic title of  “branch” (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.1-4">11:1-4</a>). Both are humiliated and exalted (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.7">49:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.52.13-15">52:13-15</a>). While Cyrus may be spoken of as “anointed,” no final salvation work is attributed to him (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.1-5">45:1-5</a>). Israel, although chosen and loved by God (<a href="?bref=Isa.41.8">41:8</a>), is not fit as God’s servant to bring his redeeming work to mankind (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.18">42:18</a>). The fall of David’s dynasty points to Israel’s need for an anointed king who will heal the apostasy and disobedience (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.5">Ex 33:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.4.1">Hos 4:1</a>). More and more, OT history presents Israel’s broad moral failure. Her problem, which she shares with mankind, can only be solved by the making of a covenant whose surety and center is both a personal Savior and sovereign Lord (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.31-34">Jer 31:31-34</a>). The coming of such a champion lives in the promise of a shoot from the stump of Jesse’s fallen tree, who will bring the light of life to God’s people in darkness (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.2">Is 9:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1">11:1</a>).</p>
<p>It is difficult to deny that servanthood and lowliness belongs within the sphere of royalty (<a href="?bref=Zech.9.9">Zec 9:9</a>). The concept of the Messiah filling the roles of priest and king is unquestionable (<a href="?bref=Ps.110.1-4">Ps 110:1-4</a>); A suffering priest-king is far less obvious. Some among the Talmudic writers recognized the likelihood that the Messiah would have to suffer. In the Babylonian Talmud, tractate <span class="ital">Sanhedrin</span> 98b, the Messiah is said to bear sicknesses and pain. Among the prayers for the Day of Atonement may be found the words of Eleazar ben Qalir (perhaps as late as <span class="era">AD</span> 1000): “Our righteous Messiah has departed from us; we are horror-stricken, and there is none to justify us. Our iniquities and the yoke of our transgressions he carries, and is wounded for our transgressions. He bears on his shoulders our sins to find pardon for our iniquities. May we be healed by his stripes.” In a similar vein Rabbi Eliyya de Vidas writes, “The meaning of ‘He was wounded for our transgressions, bruised for our iniquities,’ is that since the Messiah bears our iniquities, which produce the effect of His being bruised, it follows that whosoever will not admit that the Messiah thus suffers for our iniquities must endure and suffer for them himself.” Despite this, it is very unlikely that anyone imagined the Messiah would save us by means of his own death (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.53.12">Is 53:12</a>). Because the paradox of humiliation and exaltation were difficult to harmonize, some assumed that God would send both a Messiah to suffer as well as a Messiah to reign. Biblically, it is evident that the Anointed One’s terrible fate of suffering is the necessary opening to infinite glory. He is pictured not only as a great king (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.13">52:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.53.12">53:12</a>) but also as humble (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.2">53:2</a>), humiliated (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.14">52:14</a>), rejected (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.3">53:3</a>), and bearing the consequences of mankind’s rebellion (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.53.5-6">5-6</a>). Yet he is raised up to intercede for, and richly bless, his people (v <a href="?bref=Isa.53.12">12</a>). The Messiah, having accomplished that full obedience that Adam and Israel failed to achieve, will bring Israel and the nations back to God (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.18-19">42:18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.49.3,6">49:3, 6</a>).</p>
<p>The writings of Daniel contain important messianic data. Daniel is unique because he boldly speaks of “Messiah the Prince” (<a href="?bref=Dan.9.25">Dn 9:25</a>), identifies him as the “Son of Man” (<a href="?bref=Dan.7.13">7:13</a>), and says he suffers (“cut off,” <a href="?bref=Dan.9.26">9:26</a>). This statement of the cutting off (death) of the Messiah makes possible his work of atonement (<a href="?bref=Dan.9.24">9:24</a>). The doctrine of atonement by means of a substitute is the only doctrine of atonement found in the Bible (cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.17.11">Lv 17:11</a>). Israel understood that to bear sin meant enduring the consequences, or penalty, for sin (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.14.33">Nm 14:33</a>). The same penal substitution is evident in Messiah’s atoning sacrifice. He is the substitute to whom is transferred the suffering that should have been the sinner’s. The penalty having been borne by another, the guilty is fully forgiven.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Ps.22.1">Psalm 22:1</a> records the sorrowful cry of the Messiah bearing man’s penalty for sin (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.27.46">Mt 27:46</a>) as he becomes sin on behalf of his people (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.21">2 Cor 5:21</a>). Yet his cry, “My God,” indicates an intimate relationship that cannot be destroyed. Once again the messianic humiliation prior to great exaltation is in view (<a href="?bref=Ps.22.27">Ps 22:27</a>). In the so-called “royal psalms” (e.g., 2; 72; 110) it is the priestly intercessor who is also ordained to be monarch and judge.</p>
<p>Jeremiah brings the portrait a step further. The one who will enable humans to enter into a saving covenant with God communicates God’s imputed righteousness: the Messiah, God’s righteous branch, becomes “the Lord our Righteousness.” Paradoxically, under the law no one could be crucified if not guilty of sin (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.22">Dt 21:22</a>). But it is Christ the righteous one who was crucified, thereby forever taking away from us any supposed confidence we would have through legalism (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.23">Dt 21:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.13">Gal 3:13</a>). More than forgiven, believers are considered righteous in him (<a href="?bref=Jer.23.5-6">Jer 23:5-6</a>).</p>
<p>While the birthplace of the Messiah was well established (<a href="?bref=Mic.5.2">Mi 5:2</a>), his deity was hotly contested. Although few in ancient Israel disputed the belief in a superhuman Messiah, it is doubtful that anyone imagined him to be “God with us” in the fullest sense of the expression (cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.1.3">Heb 1:3</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="MessiahintheNewTestament">Messiah in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The NT writers present the child of supernatural origins (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">Is 7:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.5.2">Mi 5:2</a>) as carrying the full weight of divinity (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.6">Is 9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.6">Phil 2:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.19">Col 1:19</a>). He is the Son of God, worthy to receive the worship of all people (<a href="?bref=Ps.45.6-7">Ps 45:6-7</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.1.8-9">Heb 1:8-9</a>).</p>
<p>The Jews of first-century Palestine knew that the messianic promise would be fulfilled in the coming of one like Moses (<a href="?bref=Deut.18.18">Dt 18:18</a>). Parallels between Jesus and Moses are abundant. As mediators, innovators, and propagators of new phases of spiritual life for the people, they are unmatched. Specifically, both are miraculously spared in infancy (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.1-25">Ex 2</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.2.13-23">Mt 2:13-23</a>); both renounce a royal court for the sake of serving the people of God (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.5-8">Phil 2:5-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.24-28">Heb 11:24-28</a>); both exhibit intense compassion for others (<a href="?bref=Num.27.17">Nm 27:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.9.36">Mt 9:36</a>); both have “face to face” fellowship with God (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.29-30">Ex 34:29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.7">2 Cor 3:7</a>); and each mediates a covenant of redemption (<a href="?bref=Deut.29.1">Dt 29:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.8.6-7">Heb 8:6-7</a>). But, as Luther observes, “Christ is no Moses.” In the end Moses is simply a household servant whereas the Messiah is the maker and master of all things (<a href="?bref=Heb.3.3-6">Heb 3:3-6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=John.1.1-2,18">Jn 1:1-2, 18</a>).</p>
<p>Family genealogies are important in Scripture. Rabbis agreed upon the absolute necessity of the Messiah being of David’s lineage based on <a href="?bref=Hos.3.5">Hosea 3:5</a> and <a href="?bref=Jer.30.9">Jeremiah 30:9</a>. The angel’s announcement immediately establishes the correct lineage for Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.32-33">Lk 1:32-33</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.2.4">2:4</a>), as does Matthew’s (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.1-17">Mt 1:1-17</a>). The list in Luke, like that of Matthew, shows the exclusive kingly descent verifying Jesus as Messiah (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.23-38">Lk 3:23-38</a>). Although variations occur between the two genealogies, there is a firm ground demonstrating the unique messianic stock. Fully aware of the messianic focus of Scripture (<a href="?bref=John.5.46">Jn 5:46</a>; <a href="?bref=John.8.56">8:56</a>), Jesus acknowledged himself to be the Christ on many occasions. He accepted the title from blind Bartimaeus (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.46-48">Mk 10:46-48</a>); from the crowds when he entered Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.9">Mt 21:9</a>); from the children at the temple (v <a href="?bref=Matt.21.15">15</a>); and in other contexts as well (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.16-18">Mt 16:16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.61-62">Mk 14:61-62</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.21">Lk 4:21</a>; <a href="?bref=John.4.25-26">Jn 4:25-26</a>). Nonetheless, he warned his disciples not to broadcast his mighty acts as Messiah before his resurrection (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.9">Mt 17:9</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.9.20-21">Lk 9:20-21</a>). Because of the commonly held (but false) belief that the Messiah’s was primarily a political liberator, Jesus actually avoided the use of that term and preferred to identify himself as “the Son of Man.” It wasn’t assumed that both designations referred to the same person (cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.14.61-62">Mk 14:61-62</a>). Borrowing mainly from Daniel’s vision of a heavenly conqueror (<a href="?bref=Dan.7.13-14">Dn 7:13-14</a>), Jesus consistently employed this less-known title and filled it with the true character and scope of messianic salvation. Jesus’s teaching in this regard enabled his disciples to correct their false views concerning his mission (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.21-23">Mt 16:21-23</a>). In time they would come to see him not only as Messiah but also as the theme of the entire OT (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.17">Mt 5:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.24.27,44">Lk 24:27, 44</a>; <a href="?bref=John.5.39">Jn 5:39</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.10.7">Heb 10:7</a>). When Jesus explained the Scriptures beginning with the Torah (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.27">Lk 24:27</a>), he did so as the living demonstration of God, the Word made flesh (<a href="?bref=John.1.14,18">Jn 1:14, 18</a>). Legitimate and detailed messianic accounts are found in many texts, such as <a href="?bref=Ps.2.1-12">Psalms 2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.16.1-11">16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.22.1-31">22</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.40.1-17">40</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.110.1-7">110</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">Isaiah 7:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.9.6">9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1">11:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.10-11">40:10-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.50.6">50:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.52.13-53.12">52:13–53:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.61.1">61:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.63.1-6">63:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.5-6">Jeremiah 23:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.33.14-16">33:14-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.23">Ezekiel 34:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.25">37:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.9.24-27">Daniel 9:24-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.11.1">Hosea 11:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.5.2">Micah 5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.9.9">Zechariah 9:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.11.13">11:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.12.10">12:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.13.7">13:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.3.1">Malachi 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.4.2">4:2</a>.</p>
<p>The messiahship of Jesus is firmly proclaimed by all four evangelists (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.1">Mt 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.1">Mk 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.24.26">Lk 24:26</a>; <a href="?bref=John.20.31">Jn 20:31</a>). Peter on Pentecost, Philip before the Ethiopian eunuch, and Apollos in open debate all argue convincingly that Jesus is the Messiah (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.36">Acts 2:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.8.35">8:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.28.28">28:28</a>). Peter says he was “made” both Lord and Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.36">2:36</a>), signifying that the resurrection rightfully confirms him as such. Similarly, the apostle Paul speaks of Jesus’s resurrection as a clear declaration of his inalienable right to the title (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.4">Rom 1:4</a>). For Paul, the ex-Pharisee and former persecutor of the church, “Jesus the Christ” is the very heart and soul of his preaching. Nothing is worthy to be compared to the glory of the Messiah; everything pales by comparison (<a href="?bref=Phil.3.5-10">Phil 3:5-10</a>). The apostle’s all-consuming passion is for others to know the fullness of God in the person of his only Son (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.14-19">Eph 3:14-19</a>).</p>
<p>The Holy Spirit in Scripture speaks of Jesus with a wide-range of designations—Holy One, Judge, Righteous One, King, Son of God, and Lord—but these are not the only ones. In him all messianic predictions converge; he is the proof that firmly establishes their validity. The Lord Jesus Christ is himself the heart and substance of that covenant through which sinful people may be reconciled to a holy God (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.6">Is 42:6</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.6">Jn 14:6</a>). Jesus is the Messiah of Israel, God in flesh, who fulfills every prophecy, type, and symbol—which are shadows of his coming. Therefore, all should trust in him, the source of all grace, the only eternal treasure (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.21">Mt 12:21</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.16-17">Jn 1:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.2.3">Col 2:3</a>). Anointed as prophet, he leads us into all truth (<a href="?bref=John.6.14">Jn 6:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.7.16">7:16</a>); as priest he intercedes for us (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.21">Heb 7:21</a>); and as king he reigns over us (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.9-10">Phil 2:9-10</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Atonement_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Atonement</a>; <a href="?item=Branch_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Branch</a>; <a href="?item=Christology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Christology</a>; <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Life and Teachings of</a>; <a href="?item=RedeemerRedemption_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Redeemer, Redemption</a>; <a href="?item=SonofGod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Son of God</a>; <a href="?item=SonofMan_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Son of Man</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>