<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MoabMoabites">
  <title>Moab, Moabites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MOAB, MOABITES</p>
<p class="fl">Name of a small kingdom in central Transjordan and also its inhabitants. The land of Moab was situated on the high plateau immediately east of the Dead Sea; the escarpment of the Jordan Rift formed an effective boundary between Moab and Judah. Moab’s northern boundary shifted in accordance with the kingdom’s military might, with the Heshbon vicinity forming the northern limit of Moab in periods of strength, and the Arnon River (modern Wadi el-Mojib) functioning as the northern border in times of weakness. The kingdom’s eastern boundary was formed by the fringe of the Syrian desert, since the latter demarcated Moab’s agricultural zone. On the south, Moab was separated from Edom by the Zered River (modern Wadi el-Hesa). Thus, even at its peak, ancient Moab covered a relatively small territory, measuring only about 60 miles (96.5 kilometers) north-south by about 20 miles (32.2 kilometers) east-west.</p>
<p>Most of Moab is gently rolling tableland that is divided by numerous ravines. Running through the heart of Moab is the King’s Highway, a route that probably had military and commercial importance throughout this region’s history (<a href="?bref=Num.21.21-22">Nm 21:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.11.17">Jgs 11:17</a>). The plateau has always been famous for its abundant pasturage (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.4">2 Kgs 3:4</a>), and Moab’s soil and climate are quite suitable for growing wheat and barley.</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="MoabEastofthePromisedLand"/>
<p class="h2" id="OriginandHistory">Origin and History</p>
<p class="fl">According to <a href="?bref=Gen.19.37">Genesis 19:37</a>, the Moabites descended from Moab, the son of Lot and his oldest daughter. <a href="?bref=Deut.2.10-11">Deuteronomy 2:10-11</a>, a passage whose context relates to the Moabites at the time of the Hebrew invasion, says that the pre-Moabite inhabitants of this region were the Emim, but the connection between Lot’s descendants, the Emim, and the occupants of Moab at the time of the Hebrew invasion is not identified. There is thus far no specific information concerning the establishing of the Moabite kingdom proper, which existed from around 1300 <span class="era">BC</span> to 600 <span class="era">BC</span>. Knowledge of this period of Moabite history and culture is derived from archaeological and textual sources, including Egyptian, Assyrian, and OT texts.</p>
<p>Prior to the Israelites’ passage through Transjordan, the Moabites had lost control of the land north of the Arnon and were dominated by Sihon, the Amorite king who ruled at Heshbon (<a href="?bref=Num.21.13,26">Nm 21:13, 26</a>). Having been refused permission to travel through Edom and Moab along the King’s Highway, the Hebrews defeated Sihon in one of their most celebrated military campaigns. Fearing that Israel might conquer his land, King Balak of Moab waged war against the Hebrews (<a href="?bref=Num.22.6">Nm 22:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.9">Jos 24:9</a>) and hired the Mesopotamian diviner, Balaam, to pronounce a curse upon his enemies (<a href="?bref=Num.22.1-24.25">Nm 22–24</a>). The tribes of Reuben and Gad settled in Sihon’s territory, and the Arnon formed the border between Israel and Moab (ch <a href="?bref=Num.32.1-42">32</a>). From the time of the Israelites’ rebellion at Shittim onward (ch <a href="?bref=Num.25.1-18">25</a>), the Moabite tableland north of the Arnon was a source of conflict between Moab and Israel.</p>
<p>Until his assassination by Ehud, the Moabite king Eglon oppressed the Hebrew tribes on both sides of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Judg.3.12-30">Jgs 3:12-30</a>). By Jephthah’s day, northern Moab was once again under Israelite control (<a href="?bref=Judg.11.26">11:26</a>). Obviously, as the book of Ruth indicates, there were also periods in which Moab and Israel lived in peace.</p>
<p>During the reigns of Saul and David, from the late-11th until the mid-10th centuries <span class="era">BC</span>, Moab and Israel were at war, with the latter usually holding the upper hand (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.47">1 Sm 14:47</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.8.2">2 Sm 8:2</a>). Solomon’s harem included Moabite women, and he also built a high place for Chemosh, the chief god of the Moabites (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.1,7">1 Kgs 11:1, 7</a>). Following the division of the Israelite monarchy in 930 <span class="era">BC</span>, Moab experienced a brief period of independence, but this ended when Omri and Ahab dominated the Moabites and their king, Mesha, during the ninth century <span class="era">BC</span>. (The famous Moabite Stone, which describes Mesha’s conflict with the Omride dynasty, and several shorter texts demonstrate that the language of Moab was closely related to OT Hebrew.) Conflict between Moab and her neighbors (e.g., Israel, Judah, Edom, and most importantly, Assyria) continued until the Babylonian king Nebuchadnezzar destroyed the Moabite kingdom early in the sixth century <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=Ezek.25.8-11">Ez 25:8-11</a>). This conflict is documented in the Assyrian literature, which indicates that Moab became an Assyrian vassal in the late eighth century <span class="era">BC</span>, and in the OT (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.1-27">2 Kgs 3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.32-33">10:32-33</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.20">13:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.2">24:2</a>). Indeed, the enmity between Moab, Israel, and Judah is especially evident in a series of prophetic oracles directed against the Moabites (<a href="?bref=Isa.15.1-16.14">Is 15–16</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.9.25-26">Jer 9:25-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.48.1-47">48</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.2.1-3">Am 2:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.8-11">Zep 2:8-11</a>). These passages call attention to some of the major towns in ancient Moab (Nebo, Medeba, Heshbon, Dibon, Ar, Kir, and Horonaim).</p>
<p>Following the Babylonian conquest, the region of Moab fell under Persian control and was occupied by various Arab peoples, most notably the Nabateans. Although a Moabite state was never reestablished, people of Moabite ancestry were recognized in late OT times (<a href="?bref=Ezra.9.1">Ezr 9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.13.1,23">Neh 13:1, 23</a>), since the postexilic Jewish community was concerned about observing the law recorded in <a href="?bref=Deut.23.3-6">Deuteronomy 23:3-6</a>. In <span class="era">AD</span> 106 the region of Moab became part of the Roman province of Arabia. Archaeological research has added much information that relates to Moabite history and culture from the prehistoric through Ottoman periods.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Religion">Religion</p>
<p class="fl">During the third and second millennia <span class="era">BC</span>, Moabite religion was probably similar to that practiced by the Canaanites, though the religion of Moab eventually developed into a relatively distinct system. Although other deities were worshiped by the Moabites, Chemosh was their national god. The OT refers to the Moabites as “people of Chemosh” (<a href="?bref=Num.21.29">Nm 21:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.48.46">Jer 48:46</a>), and the frequent appearance of “Chemosh” in Moabite personal names points to this god’s elevated status. In general, the Moabite Stone’s dozen references to Chemosh portray him as a god of war who leads his people against their enemies.</p>
<p>Divine guidance and favor were sought, and diviners and oracles were respected (<a href="?bref=Num.22.1-24.25">Nm 22–24</a>). A priesthood (<a href="?bref=Jer.48.7">Jer 48:7</a>) and sacrificial system (<a href="?bref=Num.22.40-23.30">Nm 22:40–23:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.25.1-5">25:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.27">2 Kgs 3:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.48.35">Jer 48:35</a>) were important aspects of Moabite religion. No Moabite sanctuary has been discovered, but their existence is mentioned in the Moabite Stone and the OT (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.7">1 Kgs 11:7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.13">2 Kgs 23:13</a>). Elaborately furnished tombs, like those found at Dibon, point to the Moabites’ belief in the afterlife.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CanaaniteDeitiesandReligion_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Canaanite Deities and Religion</a>; <a href="?item=MoabiteStone_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Moabite Stone</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>