<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Moon">
  <title>Moon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MOON</p>
<p class="fl">Lesser light source of the heavens (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.16">Gn 1:16</a>). Many Semitic languages use the same word for moon as the Hebrew. In three passages in the Hebrew OT (<a href="?bref=Song.6.10">Sg 6:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.24.23">Is 24:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.30.26">30:26</a>), the moon is called “the white one,” and paired with “the hot one,” the sun. Another term, “crescent,” is used in other languages such as Aramaic and Arabic, and “crescent ornaments” (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.21,26">Jgs 8:21, 26</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.3.18">Is 3:18</a>) are mentioned.</p>
<p>In the creation account, it is said concerning the functions of the two light sources: “They will be signs to mark off the seasons, the days, and the years” (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.14">Gn 1:14</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>)—that is, “times” are determined by their movements. For this reason, when telling about the mighty deeds of the Lord in Creation, the poet says, “You made the moon to mark the seasons” (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.19">Ps 104:19</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The ancient Hebrew calendar was lunar (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.43.6-7">Ecclus 43:6-7</a>), the months beginning with the new moon, marked by special rituals (<a href="?bref=Num.10.10">Nm 10:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.28.11-14">28:11-14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.2.4">2 Chr 2:4</a>). Two great festivals, Passover and Tabernacles, began in midmonth when the moon was full (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.5-6">Lv 23:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.81.3-5">Ps 81:3-5</a>; and <a href="?bref=Lev.23.34">Lv 23:34</a>, respectively). The seven-day week is a division of the 28-day lunar cycle into logical and convenient units, so the moon may be said to provide the basis for the significance of the number seven. In the same way, the beginning of the seventh month, the Festival of Trumpets (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.24">Lv 23:24</a>), marked the climax month of the sacred feasts; it also signified the New Year for regnal years and for agriculture (Josephus’s <span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 1.1.3; Mishnah, <span class="ital">Rosh Hashanah</span> 1:1).</p>
<p>One verse in the creation story speaks of the sun’s dominion over the day and the moon’s over the night (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.16">Gn 1:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.136.9">Ps 136:9</a>). The moon is also mentioned (alongside the sun) in the general order of creation when the spheres of the universe were established (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.35">Jer 31:35</a>). From this the light sources symbolize the continuity of the world order (<a href="?bref=Ps.72.5">Pss 72:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.37-38">89:37-38</a>). The darkening of the moon (and the sun) is a sign of the change of the order in creation in the latter days (<a href="?bref=Isa.13.10">Is 13:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.32.7">Ez 32:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.10">Jl 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.3.11">Hb 3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.29">Mt 24:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.24">Mk 13:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.12">Rv 6:12</a>; the converse is stated in <a href="?bref=Isa.30.26">Is 30:26</a>). Since the moon resembles the sun, it also has the power to smite (<a href="?bref=Ps.121.6">Ps 121:6</a>) and to influence the growth of crops in the field (<a href="?bref=Deut.33.14">Dt 33:14</a>). In the book of Deuteronomy, the Israelites were warned against worshiping the moon and the rest of the host of heaven (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.19">Dt 4:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.17.3">17:3</a>), but this foreign worship made its way into the Judean kingdom (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.3">2 Kgs 21:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.4-5">23:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.7.18">Jer 7:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.8.2">8:2</a>).</p>
<p>To keep an accurate control over the calendar and the feasts, the new moon was carefully observed seven times during the year in Jerusalem. This assured that the major feasts fell on the proper days. The Sanhedrin would gather early in the morning on the last day of the preceding month, and watchmen were posted to observe the moon’s first appearance. When the evidence became clear, the sacred word was pronounced and the day became the first of the new month. Fire signals beginning from the Mt of Olives announced the new moon; later they were replaced by messengers because the Samaritans had set up false signals along the way.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Astronomy_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Astronomy</a>; <a href="?item=CalendarsAncientandModern_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Calendars, Ancient and Modern</a>; <a href="?item=FeastsandFestivalsofIsrael_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Feasts and Festivals of Israel</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>