<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Mourning">
  <title>Mourning</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MOURNING</p>
<p class="fl">Established ritual for grieving, observed by the relatives and friends of a dead person. It began with closing the eyes of the dead (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.4">Gn 46:4</a>), embracing the body (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.1">50:1</a>), and preparing it for burial. The hot climate necessitated that burial take place immediately (<a href="?bref=Acts.5.1-10">Acts 5:1-10</a>). But there is very few detailed information about burial earlier than NT times (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.59">Mt 27:59</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.44">Jn 11:44</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.39-40">19:39-40</a>). Excavations suggest that the dead were buried fully clothed but not in coffins. The Israelites practiced neither embalming nor cremation, but decent burial was essential.</p>
<p>At the news of a death, it was customary to tear one’s garments (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.34">Gn 37:34</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.1.11">2 Sm 1:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.1.20">Jb 1:20</a>), put on sackcloth (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.31">2 Sm 3:31</a>), and take off one’s shoes (<a href="?bref=2Sam.15.30">2 Sm 15:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.1.8">Mi 1:8</a>) and headdress; a man might cover his beard or veil his face (<a href="?bref=Ezek.24.17,23">Ez 24:17, 23</a>). Mourners put earth on their heads (<a href="?bref=Josh.7.6">Jos 7:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.4.12">1 Sm 4:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.1">Neh 9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.2.12">Jb 2:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.30">Ez 27:30</a>) or rolled themselves in the dust (<a href="?bref=Job.16.15">Jb 16:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.1.10">Mi 1:10</a>) or sat on a pile of ashes (<a href="?bref=Esth.4.3">Est 4:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.58.5">Is 58:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.26">Jer 6:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.30">Ez 27:30</a>). Such mourning rites as shaving the hair and the beard and making cuts on the body (<a href="?bref=Job.1.20">Jb 1:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.22.12">Is 22:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.16.6">Jer 16:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.41.5">41:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.47.5">47:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.48.37">48:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.7.18">Ez 7:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.10">Am 8:10</a>) were condemned (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.27-28">Lv 19:27-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.1">Dt 14:1</a>) because of pagan associations. Mourners refrained from washing and discontinued the use of perfumes (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.20">2 Sm 12:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.14.2">14:2</a>).</p>
<p>Fasting was also a mourning rite (<a href="?bref=1Sam.31.13">1 Sm 31:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.1.12">2 Sm 1:12</a>). Neighbors or friends brought mourning bread and the “cup of consolation” to the relatives of the deceased (<a href="?bref=Jer.16.7">Jer 16:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.24.17,22">Ez 24:17, 22</a>). Food could not be prepared at the house of the dead because death rendered a place unclean. The dead were unclean to the extent that a priest could “profane” himself by taking part in mourning rites, except for his nearest blood relatives (mother, father, son, daughter, brother, and sister, on condition that she was still a virgin; <a href="?bref=Lev.21.1-4,10-11">Lv 21:1-4, 10-11</a>). These mourning rites were not acts of worship directed toward the dead, nor did they constitute a cult for the dead, but rather they were expressions of grief and affection.</p>
<p>At the graveside, lamentation for the dead was made (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.13.30">1 Kgs 13:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.26">Jer 6:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.16">Am 5:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.10">8:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.12.10">Zec 12:10</a>) by men and women in separate groups (<a href="?bref=Zech.12.11-14">Zec 12:11-14</a>). These exclamations of sorrow might develop into a rhythmic lament (<a href="?bref=2Sam.1.17-27">2 Sm 1:17-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.10">Am 8:10</a>). However, professional mourners, men and especially women (<a href="?bref=Jer.9.17-19">Jer 9:17-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.16">Am 5:16</a>), were employed. The book of Lamentations is a fine example of laments and is a reminder that among Jews mourning was not always associated with death. It expressed brokenness of spirit for sin, individual and national. National calamity also evoked great lamentation.</p>
<p>These mourning rites expressed great grief. But some of them—tearing clothes, wearing sackcloth, disfiguring oneself with dust and ashes, self-mutilation—point to paroxysms of grief, the religious significance of which now escapes us. This was far removed from mourning as an inner feeling or a mood of the mind. It was not just an involuntary outburst of feeling but rather a deliberate, established ritual. When death occurred, the Israelite wept because it was customary and seemly. It was not uncommon that monuments or memorials were built (<a href="?bref=2Sam.18.18">2 Sm 18:18</a>), but the average Israelite was too poor for this to be a common practice.</p>
<p>Mourning practices in NT times differed little from those described in the OT. Mourning was associated with Christ’s second advent (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.30">Mt 24:30</a>), with repentance (<a href="?bref=Jas.4.8-10">Jas 4:8-10</a>), with Christ’s leaving the 12 (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.15">Mt 9:15</a>), with deep spirituality (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.4">5:4</a>), as well as with death (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.38-39">Mk 5:38-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.13">Lk 7:13</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.33">Jn 11:33</a>).</p>
<p>True, the overthrow of death by Jesus Christ robbed death of its sting and the grave of its victory (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.54-57">1 Cor 15:54-57</a>), but the Christian still mourns, though not as those who have no hope (<a href="?bref=1Thes.4.13">1 Thes 4:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.4">Rv 21:4</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BurialBurialCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Burial, Burial Customs</a>; <a href="?item=FuneralCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Funeral Customs</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>