<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="IAmSayings">
  <title>“I Am” Sayings</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">“I AM” SAYINGS</p>
<p class="fl">Self-proclamations made by Jesus in the Gospel of John.</p>
<p>One of the distinctive elements of the teaching of Jesus is the way Jesus expresses important truths in terms of his own personal character and mission. These statements begin with the words “I am” and then continue to express a deep theological thought in terms of metaphorical statement. This method of teaching is preserved for us in the Gospel of John alone. While Matthew, Mark, and Luke emphasize Jesus’ mode of teaching in the form of the parable, John pictures Jesus as teaching in discourses. These discourses often find an “I am” statement as the key expression of the central thought.</p>
<p>The “I am” statements found in the Gospel of John are the bread of life or the living bread (<a href="?bref=John.6.35,48,51">6:35, 48, 51</a>), the light of the world (<a href="?bref=John.8.12">8:12</a>; see also <a href="?bref=John.9.5">9:5</a>), the gate (<a href="?bref=John.10.7,9">10:7, 9</a>), the good shepherd (<a href="?bref=John.10.11,14">10:11, 14</a>), the resurrection and the life (<a href="?bref=John.11.25">11:25</a>), the way, the truth and the life (<a href="?bref=John.14.6">14:6</a>), and the vine (<a href="?bref=John.15.1,5">15:1, 5</a>).</p>
<p>Each of these statements follows a basic pattern. They are written as metaphors in which one of the key elements is to be the Christ expressed as “I am.” The meaning of the metaphor is to be drawn chiefly from the explanatory statement connected with it. Thus when Jesus says, “I am the light of the world,” the explanatory statement follows, “So if you follow me, you won’t be stumbling through the darkness, for living light will flood your path” (<span class="sc">tlb</span>). This latter statement is intended to help a person interpret the metaphor. Most statements have such interpretive elements joined to them.</p>
<p>These metaphorical statements often complement Jesus’ miracles. The statement and a miracle each contribute to the understanding of the other. Thus when Jesus proclaims that he is the light of the world, he proceeds to bring sight to the blind man. The controversy that follows between the blind man and the Pharisees shows that the man has received spiritual sight as well as physical. Before Jesus raises Lazarus from the dead, he tells Martha that he is the resurrection and the life. The raising of Lazarus is intended to show Jesus’ power to give life now and to demonstrate his power to do what he proclaimed he was able to do. After Jesus had fed the 5,000, he declared that he was the living bread that had come from heaven. Each of these miracles is interpreted by the metaphorical “I am” statement. Each statement is intended to give the miracle meaning for the ministry of Jesus. They show us that Jesus’ miracles were not just acts of power or mercy but actions demonstrating the meaning of his ministry and teaching.</p>
<p>Many theologians consider the “I am” formula to reflect an identification of deity found in the OT (see <a href="?item=GodNamesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Names of</a>). When Moses was called, he asked God to identify himself in such a way that Moses might gain acceptance from the Hebrew people. God revealed himself to Moses as the great “<span class="divine-name">I Am</span>.” Moses was to tell the Israelites that “<span class="divine-name">I Am</span> sent me to you” (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.13-14">Ex 3:13-14</a>). From this “<span class="divine-name">I Am</span>” the name Yahweh is derived. Many believe that Jesus used this same formula from the OT to relate his deity. The “I am” statements in John’s Gospel help the reader identify Jesus as divine, as God.</p>
  </body>
</item>