<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Incarnation">
  <title>Incarnation*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">INCARNATION*</p>
<p class="fl">Literally, “in flesh”; theologically, the doctrine that in Jesus of Nazareth God took on human flesh and became the God-man. Historically, the doctrine of incarnation was central in the christological debates of patristic times and has recently come to the fore again in academic circles. Biblically, it expresses the mystery of Jesus’ identity.</p>
<p class="h2" id="NewTestamentTestimony">New Testament Testimony</p>
<p class="h3">The Synoptic Gospels</p>
<p class="fl">The Gospel of Mark has no account of the Incarnation and stresses Jesus’ messiahship more than his deity. As a result, some believe that it represents an earlier stage in the development of the church’s theology, before the doctrine of incarnation had evolved. That is doubtful for two reasons: Incarnation passages like the Philippians hymn (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.6-11">Phil 2:6-11</a>) probably antedate Mark’s Gospel, and Mark has a well-developed theology of the two natures of Christ. Although he stresses Jesus’ humanity, Mark accents it with an emphasis on divinity. Jesus was called the “beloved Son” by a heavenly voice at his baptism and transfiguration (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.11">Mk 1:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.7">9:7</a>); demons called him divine (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.11">3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.5.7">5:7</a>), as did a Roman centurion (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.39">15:39</a>). Jesus’ “Abba” prayers (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.36">14:36</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.26.39">Mt 26:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.22.42">Lk 22:42</a>) indicate his sense of divine identity, and at his trial he was charged with claiming the title “Son of the Blessed” (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.61-62">14:61-62</a>). Thus, though the Incarnation is nowhere explicitly stated in Mark, it is implicitly affirmed.</p>
<p>Matthew and Luke express the Incarnation. The birth narratives, of course, stress the event itself, with Matthew emphasizing Jesus’ royal messiahship, and Luke, the divine witness of the Holy Spirit. Matthew’s Gospel is Christ-centered; Luke concentrates on Christ as Savior, or more precisely, on salvation-history. Although Matthew presents Jesus’ humanity, he emphasizes his lordship (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.6-10">Mt 23:6-10</a>) and divine sonship. The Incarnation thus becomes the means whereby the divine becomes human in a universal sense (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.23">1:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.18.20">18:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.14">24:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.28.18-20">28:18-20</a>). Luke shows the greatest interest of the three in Jesus’ earthly life. Nevertheless, his Gospel does not stress the human side of Jesus as much as Mark’s. Luke portrays Jesus primarily as the divine Savior within history (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.11">Lk 2:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.16-30">4:16-30</a>). He combines Jesus’ messianic office and divine nature, showing that the incarnate Son of God suffered and was exalted in order to bring people to God.</p>
<p class="h3">John’s Writings</p>
<p class="fl">The apostle John’s doctrine of incarnation is more explicit than any of the others, teaching not only Jesus’ God-man status but also his preexistent “glory” (<a href="?bref=John.1.1-18">Jn 1:1-18</a>). Central in this presentation is the oneness between Jesus and God the Father (<a href="?bref=John.10.29-30">10:29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.8-11">14:8-11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.23">1 Jn 2:23</a>). The “I am” (the expressed Christ, taken from the OT title for the one true God and probably signifying God’s personal name, Yahweh) came to reveal God to his people (<a href="?bref=John.1.4-5,14,18">Jn 1:4-5, 14, 18</a>). Yet John also has the most balanced presentation of the Incarnation. The divine Logos or Word (<a href="?bref=John.1.1-18">1:1-18</a>) is the exemplar of perfect humanity; he “became flesh” (v <a href="?bref=John.1.14">14</a>) to enlighten people (vv <a href="?bref=John.1.5,9">5, 9</a>) and generate in them “eternal life” (<a href="?bref=John.3.14-18">3:14-18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.1.1-3">1 Jn 1:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.9">4:9</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Paul’s Epistles</p>
<p class="fl">The apostle Paul presented the Incarnation as Jesus’ path to suffering and redemption. In <a href="?bref=Gal.4.4-5">Galatians 4:4-5</a> the Incarnation (“born of woman”) came “in the fullness of time” or at the apex of salvation-history, to “redeem those who were under the law.” In the Philippians hymn (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.6-11">Phil 2:6-11</a>, quotes from <span class="sc">nasb</span>), the Incarnation is seen in terms of preexistence (“though he was in the form of God”), humiliation (“emptied . . . humbled”), and obedience (“becoming obedient to the point of death”). The goal of the Incarnation was the cross (“even death on a cross”), and its result was Christ’s exaltation. The hymn is perhaps the supreme theological statement on the Incarnation in the NT. Jesus’ human life was an “emptying,” a refusal to seize the prerogatives of his deity (“did not regard equality with God a thing to be grasped”).</p>
<p>Paul described Christ as a second Adam (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.12-19">Rom 5:12-19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45-47">1 Cor 15:45-47</a>), who brought humanity a new possibility to attain what Adam had forsaken. Through assuming the form of a man, Christ became the Redeemer who reconciles people to God (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">Rom 3:25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.19">2 Cor 5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.1.15">1 Tm 1:15</a>). Paul stressed even more, however, that the exalted Christ provides newness of life (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.4-6">Rom 6:4-6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.17-18">2 Cor 3:17-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.1-4">Col 3:1-4</a>). A hymn in the Letter to the Colossians (<a href="?bref=Col.1.15-20">1:15-20</a>) employs ideas from Jewish wisdom speculation, and possibly Greek themes, to show Christ as the “firstborn” and the “fullness of God.” The one who always existed as God, through his sacrificial death, became the exalted Lord and brought humankind to God (see also the “flesh-spirit” theme in <a href="?bref=Rom.1.3-4">Rom 1:3-4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.3.16">1 Tm 3:16</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Hebrews</p>
<p class="fl">The Letter to the Hebrews strongly speaks of the Incarnation. The opening hymn (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.1-3">Heb 1:1-3</a>) accents Christ’s exalted status as “the very stamp” of God’s image and the radiance of his glory. Christ is superior to the angels (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.4-9">1:4-9</a>), yet he became a man in order to suffer for human salvation (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.9">2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.5.7-9">5:7-9</a>). The Incarnation is aligned with sinful humankind’s need for a Savior. The purpose of Hebrews is to show Christ’s incomparable superiority to the OT sacrifices, and at the same time to stress his work of salvation. His real temptation (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.18">2:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.15">4:15</a>) combined with his sinlessness (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.15">4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.5.9">5:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.26">7:26</a>) is the human remedy for human sin. The Incarnation was Christ’s path to final, once-for-all atonement and victory over sin (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.28">7:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.26">9:26</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="HistoricalDevelopment">Historical Development</p>
<p class="fl">The first group to challenge the traditional doctrine of incarnation was the Gnostics, who in the late first century denied that Jesus was truly human. Their Greek belief that the physical creation was evil led them to deny the Incarnation. They believed Christ to be a quasi-spiritual being who merely appeared human. The theologian Marcion (d. c. 160), trained by Gnostic teachers, also accepted a docetic interpretation of Christ (his humanity was only apparent). Marcion taught his doctrine as an antidote to the OT or Jewish-oriented Christianity in his day. After his excommunication in <span class="era">AD</span> 144, Marcion founded his own church, and his views were widely disseminated in the next two centuries. Partly in reaction to Marcion’s christological heresy, the orthodox churches unified their doctrine.</p>
<p>The next challenge to the orthodox view came through the Arian, Apollinarian, and Nestorian controversies in the third and fourth centuries. Arianism held that the Incarnation was total, so that Christ the Logos was no longer fully God. At the same time, he was not fully human, so Christ was someone between two natures. The Council of Nicaea (<span class="era">AD</span> 325) affirmed that Jesus was indeed both God and man. A further question soon arose, however, as to the relation between his two natures. Apollinarius (310?–390?) taught that only the body of Jesus was human; his soul was absorbed completely into the divine Logos. Nestorius (c. 381–451) taught that the two natures must always remain distinct in the person of Christ; they functioned together but were separate in his being. The Council of Chalcedon (<span class="era">AD</span> 451) affirmed the unity of the two natures in Jesus. Many opponents of Chalcedon arose, called Monophysites, who believed in one divine nature in Jesus, who was only in a sense human. That movement caused serious political and religious divisions, and the Council of Constantinople (680–81) reaffirmed Chalcedon and established the orthodox incarnation theology.</p>
<p>In the eighth century, Spain and France were centers of the “adoptionist” controversy. Adoptionism taught that at birth Jesus was human, but at his baptism he underwent a “second birth” and was “adopted” as Son of God. It was condemned in a series of synods and never gained many adherents until modern times. During the scholastic age, Peter Lombard (1095?–1160) advocated what became known as “nihilism.” The Incarnation supposedly caused no fundamental change in Jesus’ deity, but his human nature was both insubstantial and unessential. That view likewise was condemned by Pope Alexander III (1159–81). Another debate at that time centered on the relationship between the fall and the Incarnation. Thomas Aquinas (1224–74) concluded that there was a cause-effect connection; the Incarnation was necessitated by sin rather than predestined apart from the fall.</p>
<p>The Roman Catholic Church and the Protestant Reformers follow basically the same orthodox teaching about the Incarnation. The conflict in the Reformation centered more on soteriology (the doctrine of salvation). Several aberrant antitrinitarian movements took advantage of the breakdown in ecclesiastical authority, however. Michael Servetus (1511–53) taught a pantheistic view of the Incarnation, focused on the divine Spirit becoming manifest in the human form of Jesus. Thus the Logos is not a distinct person in the Godhead, nor is it fundamentally different from a “divine spark” in every person. At the same time Laelius Socinus (1525–62) and his nephew, Faustus Socinus (1539–1604), taught a unitarian system. The Incarnation was not a transferral of the divine essence but a communication of divine authority and revelation. Christ thus did not die as an atonement but as a moral example. Both Servetus and Socinianism were condemned by Catholics and Protestants alike.</p>
<p>In the 17th and 18th centuries “kenoticism” (from Greek for “empty”) taught that in the Incarnation the Logos totally “emptied himself” (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.7">Phil 2:7</a>) of the divine attributes. That doctrine represented the final phase of a dialogue from the scholastic period about the exact communication between Jesus’ two natures. Was his human nature omnipotent? If not, how did the man Jesus exercise the divine attributes? The kenotic school believed that Jesus was fully human and that his divine nature was quiescent until after the Ascension. His miraculous powers were external, given by the Spirit. Against that view, the majority of theologians argued that Jesus was at all times both God and man, and that in <a href="?bref=Phil.2.6-8">Philippians 2:6-8</a> Jesus did not lay aside the attributes of deity (he still exhibited the “form of God”) but rather the majesty associated with deity.</p>
<p>The 19th and 20th centuries have given rise to a view that the Incarnation was a “myth,” a pictorial way of describing how God spoke through Jesus. The virgin birth was not historical, nor did any of the supernatural events of the Gospels ever take place. Rather, the stories in the Gospels were concoctions of the later church, efforts to portray Jesus’ impact on the movement. The Gospels, however, have too strong a flavor of accurate history for such a view to prevail (see <a href="?bref=Luke.1.1-5">Lk 1:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.35">Jn 19:35</a>; <a href="?bref=John.21.24">21:24</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Conclusion">Conclusion</p>
<p class="fl">The NT teaching on the Incarnation balances the humanity and divinity of Christ. Those two facts must harmonize in any theological system, for both are absolutely necessary parts of God’s redemptive plan. In the Incarnation, Jesus became a perfect human being. As God in human flesh, he suffered the divine penalty for sin as an innocent substitute. Being both God and man, Jesus simultaneously revealed God’s will for human life and reconciled sinful people to God through his own perfect life and death. Because of the Incarnation, therefore, those who believe in Christ have peace with God and new life from God.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Christology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Christology</a>; <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Life and Teachings of</a>; <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>; <a href="?item=VirginBirthofJesus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Virgin Birth of Jesus</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="ModernViewsOnTheIncarnation"/>
  </body>
</item>