<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Inheritance">
  <title>Inheritance</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">INHERITANCE</p>
<p class="fl">Legacy or bequest. Inheritance plays an unusually significant role in the Scriptures when it is used to convey theological truths. As we might expect, these theological applications reflect legal customs in force during OT and NT times.</p>
<p class="h2" id="LegalandHistoricalAspect">Legal and Historical Aspect</p>
<p class="h3">The Patriarchs</p>
<p class="fl">We learn something of early-second-millennium <span class="era">BC</span> practices from the patriarchal stories in Genesis. For example, the narrative indicates that the firstborn could normally expect to receive the birthright. Yet exceptions abound. Ishmael (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.15">Gn 16:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.17.15-21">17:15-21</a>), Esau (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.23">25:23</a>), and Reuben (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.3-4">49:3-4</a>) did not receive the birthright. Another item of special interest is Abraham’s suggestion that, in the absence of a son, his servant Eliezer might be regarded as the heir (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.2-5">15:2-5</a>); scholars have found confirmation of this practice in Hurrian legal documents of the second millennium.</p>
<p class="h3">The Hebrew Nation</p>
<p class="fl">According to <a href="?bref=Deut.21.15-17">Deuteronomy 21:15-17</a>, Hebrew firstborns were legally entitled to a double portion of the inheritance. Israelite law also made provision for widows through the practice of levirate marriage (<a href="?bref=Deut.25.5">Dt 25:5</a>; see <a href="?bref=Gen.38.8">Gn 38:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.5">Ru 4:5</a>).</p>
<p>According to <a href="?bref=Num.27.1-11">Numbers 27:1-11</a>, the daughters of Zelophehad argued that they should receive the inheritance since their father had died without sons. Consequently, God decreed that if a man died without sons, the inheritance should be transferred to his daughter; if he had no daughter, to his brothers; if he had no brothers, to his nearest relatives. This particular incident also illustrates the importance of preserving tribal possessions: the daughters of Zelophehad were not allowed to marry outside the tribe of Manasseh, for this would mean transferral of the property to another tribe (<a href="?bref=Num.36.1-13">Nm 36</a>).</p>
<p>How highly the Israelites valued their family’s inherited possessions may be gathered from <a href="?bref=Lev.25.25-28">Leviticus 25:25-28</a>. If an individual sold his land for financial reasons, provision must be made for a relative to redeem it; if he had no near relative, he could still purchase it back at a later time, and even if he could not afford to do so, the land automatically reverted to him in the Year of Jubilee, when all debts were canceled (note also <a href="?bref=Lev.27.14-25">Lv 27:14-25</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Apart from the reference to levirate marriage in <a href="?bref=Matt.22.23-33">Matthew 22:23-33</a> (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.18-27">Mk 12:18-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.27-40">Lk 20:27-40</a>), the NT has little to say about principles of property transferral during Roman times.</p>
<p>In the parable of the prodigal son, the younger son in the family requested his share of the inheritance (<a href="?bref=Luke.15.12">Lk 15:12</a>). One should also note that the elder son, who with false piety looked down on his brother’s behavior, had not protested when his brother asked for the inheritance; on the contrary, the elder brother too, without complaining, received his share—presumably a double portion.</p>
<p>In another significant passage (<a href="?bref=Gal.4.1-2">Gal 4:1-2</a>) Paul, seeking to illustrate a theological point, refers to secular practices. An heir, he tells us, is subject to guardians and managers during his childhood, up to the time he actually inherits. The point Paul wants to establish is clear enough, but the illustration does not coincide with what we know of Roman law and unfortunately scholars have been unable to identify the precise social custom in view. It may be that Paul was making reference, in general rather than strict legal terms, to some practice with which he and the Galatians were familiar.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheologicalAspect">Theological Aspect</p>
<p class="h3">Canaan as Israel’s Inheritance</p>
<p class="fl">The conviction that God gave Palestine to the Israelites for their inheritance serves as a bridge between the historical and the theological data. The historical element lies in the obvious fact that the Promised Land, a physical entity, was certainly occupied by the Hebrews and distributed among their tribes. Theologically, however, the Scriptures speak of this occupation as a divine gift; in effect, even the method of distribution was based on the concept that the land belongs to God (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.23">Lv 25:23</a>; see <a href="?bref=Exod.15.17">Ex 15:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.22.27">Jos 22:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.38.16">Ez 38:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.1.6">Jl 1:6</a>).</p>
<p>The theme goes back to <a href="?bref=Gen.12.1-3">Genesis 12:1-3</a>. God, in choosing Abraham, instructed him to move to a new country and promised to make him a great and blessed nation (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.8">Heb 11:8</a>). The significance of the land in this Abrahamic promise is made more explicit later, when we are told that God promised to give Canaan to Abraham’s descendants after four centuries of Egyptian bondage (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.12-21">Gn 15:12-21</a>; see <a href="?bref=Acts.7.5">Acts 7:5</a>).</p>
<p>Since Canaan was occupied by wicked inhabitants, the land was to be taken by force; to inherit the land therefore really means <span class="ital">to take possession</span> of it. Israel must trust God, whose land it is, to give them the victory (<a href="?bref=Josh.1.1-9">Jos 1:1-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.43-45">21:43-45</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.7.2">Jgs 7:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.44.1-3">Ps 44:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.19">Acts 13:19</a>). Once they conquered the land, it was apportioned among the tribes according to their size (following the instructions in <a href="?bref=Num.26.52-54">Nm 26:52-54</a>). God further commanded the people to divide the land by lot (vv <a href="?bref=Num.26.55-56">55-56</a>). Thus, from the initial promise to Abraham, to the actual apportionment of the land and even with reference to the future (<a href="?bref=Isa.60.21">Is 60:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.1-8">Ez 45:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.47.13-48.29">47:13–48:29</a>), the people were made fully aware that their inheritance lay in the hands of a sovereign Lord.</p>
<p class="h3">The Believer’s Inheritance</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT we find the concept of inheritance transferred from the purely physical to the spiritual. The tribe of Levi, which constituted the priestly clan, received no inheritance, because “the Lord is their inheritance” (<a href="?bref=Deut.18.1-2">Dt 18:1-2</a>; see <a href="?bref=Num.18.8-24">Nm 18:8-24</a>). The Levites, in other words, received no land apportionment, but in their service to God they could begin to enjoy the fuller blessings to which the land inheritance pointed.</p>
<p>That this truth could not be restricted to Levites is hinted at in <a href="?bref=Exod.19.6">Exodus 19:6</a>, where the whole nation is called “a kingdom of priests” (see <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Pt 2:9</a>). <a href="?bref=Ps.16.1-11">Psalm 16</a> makes it clear that no one understood more clearly than David what those words entailed. Even if he were deprived of Israel’s physical inheritance, he had received by lot a more beautiful heritage, the Lord himself, in whose presence he found full joy and everlasting pleasures (<a href="?bref=Ps.16.5-6,11">Ps 16:5-6, 11</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Ps.73.25-26">Pss 73:25-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.142.5">142:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.58.14">Is 58:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.3.24">Lam 3:24</a>).</p>
<p>In later Judaism, during and after the intertestamental period, the figure was extended considerably. For example, the rabbis began to speak of the law as the inheritance of the faithful. Further, they might give the idea a negative turn, as when the wicked are said to inherit hell (cf. <a href="?bref=Job.27.13">Jb 27:13</a>). Neither of these figures is found in the NT.</p>
<p>We also read in Jewish literature statements about inheriting the age to come, the kingdom, eternal life; these ideas occur frequently in the NT (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.29">Mt 19:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.25.34">25:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.25">Lk 10:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.18.18">18:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.9-10">1 Cor 6:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.50">15:50</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.21">Gal 5:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.5">Eph 5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.7">Ti 3:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.5">Jas 2:5</a>). Such an inheritance, however, belongs only to those who are sanctified by God’s word (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.32">Acts 20:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.18">26:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.12">Col 1:12</a>; note also <a href="?bref=John.17.17">Jn 17:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.23-24">Col 3:23-24</a>). These future blessings do not exclude the physical (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.5">Mt 5:5</a>; note <a href="?bref=Ps.37.11,29">Ps 37:11, 29</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.60.21">Is 60:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.4.13">Rom 4:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.3.13">2 Pt 3:13</a>), but they certainly exclude human frailty, for God’s inheritance is imperishable (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.50">1 Cor 15:50</a>). In short, our heritage is nothing less than full salvation (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.14">Heb 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.7">11:7</a>), which God carefully guards for us in heaven (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.4">1 Pt 1:4</a>).</p>
<p>Doubtless, the most significant feature in the NT is its emphasis that, as a result of the work of Christ, his people begin even <span class="ital">now</span> to receive the promised inheritance. The Gospel of John frequently stresses the present reality of eternal life, as does the Letter to the Hebrews (cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.6.12-17">6:12-17</a> with <a href="?bref=Heb.9.15">9:15</a> and <a href="?bref=Heb.11.13,39-40">11:13, 39-40</a>).</p>
<p>Paul treats this whole matter thoroughly in <a href="?bref=Gal.3.7-4.7">Galatians 3:7–4:7</a>. In response to the Judaizers, who claim that the Abrahamic inheritance is restricted to those who become Jews through circumcision, Paul argues vigorously that Abraham’s true children are those who believe, whether Jew or Gentile (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.7">3:7</a>; see <a href="?bref=Acts.26.16-18">Acts 26:16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.3.6">Eph 3:6</a>). They become heirs of God’s promise, for they receive the Spirit (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.14">Gal 3:14</a>). The principle of inheritance is promise, not the Law (v <a href="?bref=Gal.3.18">18</a>). Those who believe are brought into union with Christ (vv <a href="?bref=Gal.3.27-29">27-29</a>); but then they are not merely Abraham’s children but God’s (v <a href="?bref=Gal.3.26">26</a>), for Christ is the Son of God and God has determined to send the Spirit of his Son to believers so that they too may call God <span class="ital">Father</span> (<a href="?bref=Gal.4.4-7">Gal 4:4-7</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Rom.8.15-16">Rom 8:15-16</a>).</p>
<p>Indeed, Christ himself as the Son is the true heir (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.38">Mt 21:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.7">Mk 12:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.14">Lk 20:14</a>); he has inherited a name above every name (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.9">Phil 2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.1.4">Heb 1:4</a>) and has been appointed heir of all things (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.2">Heb 1:2</a>; see <a href="?bref=Ps.2.7-8">Ps 2:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.28.18">Mt 28:18</a>). But by his grace, all who become his through faith are counted joint heirs with him (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.17">Rom 8:17</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">God’s Inheritance</p>
<p class="fl">With a bold shift in the metaphor, the Scriptures speak of believers as God’s inheritance. In the beautiful “Song of Moses” the author speaks of God as the Israelites’ Father (<a href="?bref=Deut.32.6">Dt 32:6</a>), who has taken special interest in their inheritance (v <a href="?bref=Deut.32.8">8</a>). Then we are told why God cares: “For the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>’s portion is his people, Jacob his allotted inheritance” (<a href="?bref=Deut.32.9">Dt 32:9</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). This theme becomes very prominent throughout the OT (e.g., <a href="?bref=Deut.9.26-29">Dt 9:26-29</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.51-53">1 Kgs 8:51-53</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.28.9">Pss 28:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.33.12">33:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.74.2">74:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.19.25">Is 19:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.10.16">Jer 10:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.2.12">Zec 2:12</a>). Elsewhere, Israel is spoken of as God’s special possession (e.g., <a href="?bref=Exod.19.5">Ex 19:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.7.6">Dt 7:6</a>).</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Eph.1.14">Ephesians 1:14</a> “the redemption of the possession” refers to the final salvation of believers, who are God’s treasure. Further, “we have obtained an inheritance” (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">Eph 1:11</a>) may well be translated, “we have been made an inheritance,” that is, been “chosen as God’s portion,” a view supported by verse <a href="?bref=Eph.1.18">18</a>. No more fundamental idea than this can be found in Scripture, and its essence is expressed by the words of the One who sits on the throne: “He who conquers shall have this heritage, and I will be his God and he shall be my son” (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.7">Rv 21:7</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>; see <a href="?bref=Lev.26.11-12">Lv 26:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.7.14">2 Sm 7:14</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Adoption_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Adoption</a>; <a href="?item=Birthright_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Birthright</a>; <a href="?item=Firstborn_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Firstborn</a>; <a href="?item=Heir_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Heir</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>