<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Isaac">
  <title>Isaac</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ISAAC</p>
<p class="fl">Son of Abraham and Sarah, father of Jacob and Esau, one of the patriarchs of Israel.</p>
<p>The name Isaac has an interesting etymology. It is the Anglicized form of the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">Yitshaq</span><span class="ital">,</span> in Greek <span class="greek">Isaak</span><span class="ital">.</span> If taken as an imperfect form, it means “he laughs”; as a perfect form, it means “he laughed.” Scholars have debated this problem and also the absence of an antecedent subject. If God is implied, the name could indicate divine amusement at an aged couple ridiculing the prospect of having a child (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.17">Gn 17:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.18.12">18:12</a>) and then suddenly becoming parents, as God had promised.</p>
<p>Isaac’s pedigree is also interesting, for Sarah was not only the wife of Abraham but also his half sister (<a href="?bref=Gen.20.12">Gn 20:12</a>), and this fact alone may have interfered with conception in their earlier years. Because of this relationship, Isaac belonged to both sides of Terah’s family. According to prevailing custom, the son of the legal wife took precedence over the male offspring of concubines, so that Isaac had priority of inheritance over Ishmael. The gifts that Abraham subsequently gave to the sons of his concubines (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.6">25:6</a>) were without prejudice to the inheritance of Isaac.</p>
<p>Following God’s instructions (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.10-14">Gn 17:10-14</a>), Isaac was circumcised on the eighth day as a member of the covenant community. The next ceremony came when he was old enough for weaning, probably around three years old. In eastern countries where this procedure is still observed, the child’s transition from milk to solid protein and carbohydrates is normally celebrated in the context of a feast. During the celebration the mother chews a mouthful of solid food and then pushes it into the baby’s mouth with her tongue. The infant is often so shocked by this treatment that it promptly expels the food, whereupon the mother repeats the process. For an observer the procedure can be hilarious, and Ishmael may have been laughing at such a spectacle when he incurred Sarah’s wrath (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.8-10">21:8-10</a>).</p>
<p>During the years of Isaac’s adolescence, Abraham was living in Philistine territory (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.34">Gn 21:34</a>). The supreme test of the father’s faith and obedience came in this period. Having watched this son of God’s promise grow up into a healthy young man, Abraham is asked by God to offer him as a sacrifice. Isaac was familiar with sacrificial rituals and helped with the preparations, though probably not without some misgivings, for he was also familiar with the patriarchal traditions that gave the head of the family power of life or death over everyone and everything in the family. If he voiced any protest as he lay bound on the sacrificial altar, it is not recorded. When Abraham’s faith did not waver, God intervened at the crucial moment and provided another offering in the form of a ram. Because of his obedience, God promised Abraham great blessing, blessing in which Isaac also participated (<a href="?bref=Gen.22.1-24">Gn 22</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.25.11">25:11</a>). It was this act of faith and obedience that Paul honored centuries later by calling Abraham the forefather of the Christian church (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.1-25">Rom 4</a>).</p>
<p>After Sarah’s death (<a href="?bref=Gen.23.1-20">Gn 23</a>), Abraham set about securing a bride for Isaac, as it was the custom for parents to arrange marriages for their children. Rather than have Isaac marry a local pagan woman, Abraham sent his household steward to Nahor in Mesopotamia to seek a bride for his son from among his relatives. In an account that emphasizes faith, perseverance, and divine blessing, <a href="?bref=Gen.24.1-67">Genesis 24</a> describes how the servant met Rebekah and betrothed her to Isaac even before he had met the rest of her family. Bethuel, her father, and Laban, her brother, assented to this arrangement, and she left with the family’s blessing to take up her new responsibilities in Palestine as Isaac’s wife.</p>
<p>When Abraham died at a ripe old age, Isaac and Ishmael buried him in the cave of Machpelah (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.8-9">Gn 25:8-9</a>). Isaac was now patriarch of the family. He pleaded with God that his wife, Rebekah, might bear children, and as a result, she bore twin sons, Esau (“the hairy one”) and Jacob (“supplanter”). Esau became a hunter, and Isaac favored him, while Jacob was more of a settler and agriculturalist and was favored by his mother. Jacob was also crafty and took advantage of Esau’s extreme hunger one day, bargaining with his older brother to exchange his birthright for some lentil stew. Possession of the birthright secured for Jacob a double portion of the inheritance (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.17">Dt 21:17</a>).</p>
<p>When famine gripped the land, God instructed Isaac not to visit Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.2">Gn 26:2</a>), but to stay in Palestine, where he would enjoy great prosperity. When the men of the area asked about Rebekah, Isaac became fearful and said she was his sister. When the deception was uncovered, Abimelech the king rebuked Isaac and forbade anyone to interfere with him. Isaac prospered so greatly that Abimelech finally asked him to relocate, so he moved to Beersheba, where there was sufficient water for his flocks, and his fortune increased.</p>
<p>Although Esau was Isaac’s favorite son, he displeased his father by marrying two Hittite women. When Isaac felt that the end of his life was approaching, he wanted to bless his firstborn in the traditional patriarchal manner (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.1-46">Gn 27</a>). Rebekah overheard his instructions to Esau, and she encouraged Jacob to deceive the blind old man by disguising himself as Esau and taking his brother’s blessing. The deception succeeded, and Isaac gave Jacob the blessing of the firstborn. When Esau appeared to receive his blessing he was too late, and he was very bitter against Jacob because of what had happened. Rebekah sent Jacob away to her brother Laban in Mesopotamia, to escape Esau’s anger and also to obtain a wife. Esau did receive a blessing from Isaac, but a lesser one. Two decades later a rich and prosperous Jacob returned with his family. He made peace with Esau before Isaac died, and the brothers buried Isaac in Hebron (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.27-29">Gn 35:27-29</a>).</p>
<p>Isaac is given less prominence in the patriarchal narratives than Abraham or Jacob, but his importance for covenantal faith was recognized in such NT passages as <a href="?bref=Acts.7.8">Acts 7:8</a>, <a href="?bref=Rom.9.7">Romans 9:7</a>, <a href="?bref=Gal.4.21-31">Galatians 4:21-31</a>, and <a href="?bref=Heb.11.9-20">Hebrews 11:9-20</a>.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=PatriarchsPeriodofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Patriarchs, Period of the</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>