<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="IsaiahBookof">
  <title>Isaiah, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ISAIAH, Book of</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Date">Date</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LiteraryUnity">Literary Unity</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheologicalTeaching">Theological Teaching</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">The prophet Isaiah, whose name means “the Lord saves,” lived and ministered in Jerusalem. Because of his repeated contact with the kings of Judah, some scholars believed that Isaiah was related to the royal family, but this is not certain. According to chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.7.1-25">7</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.8.1-22">8</a>, Isaiah was married and had at least two sons, Shear-jashub and Maher-shalal-hash-baz, whose symbolic names illustrated God’s dealings with the nation as a whole. The “disciples” mentioned in <a href="?bref=Isa.8.16">8:16</a> probably assisted Isaiah in his ministry and may have helped him record the book that bears his name.</p>
<p>When Isaiah saw the Lord in the famous temple vision described in chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-13">6</a>, he was willing to go wherever God sent him, even though he would face strong opposition (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.9-10">6:9-10</a>). King Ahaz proved to be particularly resistant to Isaiah’s advice (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.4-17">7:4-17</a>), and the people in general ridiculed his preaching (<a href="?bref=Isa.5.10-12">5:10-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.28.9-10">28:9-10</a>). During the reign of the godly Hezekiah, however, Isaiah’s ministry was much appreciated, and the king consulted him eagerly during times of crisis (<a href="?bref=Isa.37.1-7,21-35">37:1-7, 21-35</a>).</p>
<p>Isaiah is usually regarded as the greatest of the writing prophets. Some of the chapters in his book display an unparalleled literary beauty and make use of poetic devices and a rich variety of symbols. Chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-66.24">40–66</a> contain many powerful passages that underscore the grandeur of the book. It is ironic, then, that many scholars attribute these chapters to a “second” or “third” Isaiah, unknown authors who wrote much later than Isaiah in connection with the Babylonian exile. Yet elsewhere in the OT, the names of all who wrote the prophetic books are preserved, and it would be most unusual for the Jews not to know who wrote such magnificent prophecy as chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-66.24">40–66</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Date">Date</p>
<p class="fl">Since many of the events recorded in chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.1.1-39.8">1–39</a> took place during the ministry of Isaiah, most of these chapters were probably written by about 700 <span class="era">BC</span> or shortly thereafter. The destruction of the Assyrian army in 701 <span class="era">BC</span> represents the climax of the first half of the book, fulfilling the prophecy of <a href="?bref=Isa.10.16,24-34">10:16, 24-34</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.30.31-33">30:31-33</a>. In <a href="?bref=Isa.37.38">37:38</a> Isaiah refers to the death of King Sennacherib, which did not occur until 681 <span class="era">BC</span>. This means that some of the earlier chapters, along with <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-66.24">40–66</a>, were probably written later, during Isaiah’s retirement years. A gap of several decades could help account for the change in subject matter that is found in the last half of the book. In these chapters Isaiah projects into the future as he addresses the Jews who would be in exile in Babylon about 550 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">Isaiah’s public ministry occurred primarily from 740–700 <span class="era">BC</span>, a period marked by the rapid expansion of the nation of Assyria. Under King Tiglath-pileser III (745–727 <span class="era">BC</span>), the Assyrians moved to the west and south, and by 738 <span class="era">BC</span> the Assyrian monarch was demanding tribute from Damascus and Israel. About 734 <span class="era">BC</span> Rezin of Damascus (Syria) and Pekah of Israel organized a coalition to rebel against Assyria, and they tried to enlist the support of King Ahaz of Judah. But Ahaz refused to join, and when the kings of Damascus and Israel invaded Judah (see <a href="?bref=Isa.7.1">7:1</a>), Ahaz appealed directly to Tiglath-pileser for help (cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.7-9">2 Kgs 16:7-9</a>). With little hesitation the Assyrians returned to capture Damascus and to turn the northern kingdom of Israel into an Assyrian province.</p>
<p>The puppet king Hoshea ruled over Israel from 732–723 BC but was imprisoned when he joined a revolt against Shalmaneser V, the new Assyrian king. Shalmaneser besieged the capital city of Samaria, which finally fell in 722 <span class="era">BC</span>, spelling the end of the northern kingdom. Sargon succeeded Shalmaneser in 722 and had to quell a number of revolts. In 711 <span class="era">BC</span> Sargon captured the Philistine city of Ashdod in a campaign that became the occasion of Isaiah’s prophecy of chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.20.1-6">20</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="IsaiahScroll"/>
<p>Even more important was the widespread rebellion that broke out with the accession of Sennacherib in 705 <span class="era">BC</span>. King Hezekiah of Judah withheld his normal tribute payment, and by 701 <span class="era">BC</span> Sennacherib had invaded Palestine to punish the rebels. The details of this campaign are given in <a href="?bref=Isa.36.1-37.38">Isaiah 36–37</a> and tell how city after city was captured by the Assyrians before the invaders stood at the gates of Jerusalem and demanded total surrender. With almost no hope of survival, Hezekiah nevertheless was encouraged by Isaiah to trust God, and in one night the angel of the Lord struck down 185,000 Assyrian soldiers, virtually wiping out Sennacherib’s army (<a href="?bref=Isa.37.36-37">Is 37:36-37</a>).</p>
<p>In an effort to befriend the enemies of Assyria, Hezekiah showed his treasures to envoys of the king of Babylon (<a href="?bref=Isa.39.1-4">39:1-4</a>). Isaiah warned that someday the Babylonian armies would conquer Jerusalem and carry off those very treasures, along with the residents of the city (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.39.5-7">5-7</a>). Not only did Isaiah predict the Babylonian captivity of 586–539 <span class="era">BC</span> (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.6.11-12">6:11-12</a>), but he also foretold that Israel would be released from Babylon (<a href="?bref=Isa.48.20">48:20</a>). The Chaldean kingdom led by Nebuchadnezzar would be God’s instrument of judgment upon Judah, but they too would suffer defeat. One of Isaiah’s most remarkable prophecies was the naming of Cyrus, king of Persia, the ruler who would conquer the Babylonians in 539 <span class="era">BC</span> and release Israel from exile (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.44.28">44:28</a>). Along with the Medes (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.13.17">13:17</a>), Cyrus won several important victories before sending his troops against Babylon. Isaiah hailed him as one anointed by the Lord to bring deliverance for Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.1-5">45:1-5</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="LiteraryUnity">Literary Unity</p>
<p class="fl">Largely because of the references to the later kingdoms of Babylon and Persia, the unity of Isaiah has been called into question. Chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-66.24">40–66</a> move abruptly into the exilic period of 550 <span class="era">BC</span>, almost 150 years after Isaiah lived. Moreover, the Servant of the Lord plays a prominent role in these chapters and the messianic king fades into the background. Brilliant poetic passages are found in chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-31">40</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">53</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.55.1-13">55</a>, and <a href="?bref=Isa.60.1-22">60</a>, demonstrating remarkable depth and power.</p>
<p>Although these factors are sometimes cited as a sign of disunity, there are actually strong indications for unity in the book. For example, the historical interlude (chs <a href="?bref=Isa.36.1-39.8">36–39</a>) forms a hinge or bridge that links chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.1.1-35.10">1–35</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-66.24">40–66</a>. Chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.36.1-37.38">36–37</a> complete the Assyrian section, and chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.38.1-39.8">38–39</a> introduce the Babylonian material. Most of the linking chapters are written in prose, while the others (in some translations) are largely poetry. From the standpoint of verbal or stylistic unity, one can point to Isaiah’s favorite title for God, “the Holy One of Israel.” This title appears 12 times in chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.1.1-39.8">1–39</a>, and <a href="?bref=Isa.14.1-32">14</a> times in chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-66.24">40–66</a>, but only seven times in the rest of the OT. A study of the famous Servant Songs of <a href="?bref=Isa.52.13-53.12">52:13–53:12</a> reveals several ties with earlier passages, especially in chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.1.1-6.13">1–6</a>. The servant who is smitten and wounded (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.4-5">53:4-5</a>) receives the same punishment as the beaten and injured nation of <a href="?bref=Isa.1.5-6">1:5-6</a> (also cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.52.13">52:13</a> with <a href="?bref=Isa.2.12">2:12</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.6.1">6:1</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheologicalTeaching">Theological Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">Isaiah is to the OT as the book of Romans is to the NT—a book filled with rich theological truth. Like Romans, Isaiah unveils the sinfulness of God’s rebellious people and his gracious provision of salvation. Because God is the Holy One of Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.4">1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.6.3">6:3</a>), he cannot ignore sin but must punish those who are guilty. Both Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.5.30">5:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.42.25">42:25</a>) and the other nations (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.11,17,20">2:11, 17, 20</a>) experience a time of judgment known as the Day of the Lord. In anger God raises his hand against his people (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.5.25">5:25</a>), but ultimately his wrath is poured out upon Babylon and the nations (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.13.3-5">13:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.2">34:2</a>).</p>
<p>With the fall of Assyria and Babylon, the Day of the Lord becomes a day of joyous victory (<a href="?bref=Isa.10.27">10:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.61.2">61:2</a>). According to <a href="?bref=Isa.63.4">Isaiah 63:4</a>, it is the year of the Lord’s redemption. Earlier, Israel had been redeemed from slavery in Egypt; now the return from the Babylonian captivity brings equal joy (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.9">52:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.61.1">61:1</a>). The ultimate redemption is to be accomplished through the death of Christ, and <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">Isaiah 53</a> describes our Lord’s suffering and death in graphic terms. His ministry as the Suffering Servant is also introduced in <a href="?bref=Isa.49.4">49:4</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.50.6-7">50:6-7</a>; meanwhile, <a href="?bref=Isa.49.6">49:6</a> states that the servant will be “a light for the Gentiles.” Looking ahead to the Second Coming, Isaiah predicts a messianic age of peace and righteousness. Nations will “beat their swords into plowshares” (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.4">2:4</a>) and the “Prince of Peace” will rule forever (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.6-7">9:6-7</a>).</p>
<p>Throughout the book God is pictured as the all-powerful Creator (<a href="?bref=Isa.48.13">48:13</a>)—the sovereign One seated on a throne, high and exalted; the King, the Lord Almighty (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.1,5">6:1, 5</a>). He controls the armies of the earth (<a href="?bref=Isa.13.4">13:4</a>) and removes rulers as he wills (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.23-24">40:23-24</a>). Before him, nations “are but a drop in the bucket” (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.15">40:15</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>), and compared with him all idols are worthless and without power (<a href="?bref=Isa.41.29">41:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.44.6">44:6</a>). This is the God who shows his fury to his foes and his love to his servants (<a href="?bref=Isa.66.14">66:14</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="DeuteroIsaiahASecondAuthorOfTheBookOfIsaiah"/>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Messages of Judgment and Hope (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.1-12.6">1–12</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In the opening chapter Isaiah characterizes Israel (including Judah) as “a sinful nation” that has rebelled against God. Although the people regularly bring offerings to him, their worship is hypocritical, an attempt to mask their oppression of the poor and helpless. The Lord encourages the nation to repent of their sin or face the fires of judgment. After this introduction, Isaiah turns to describe the peace of the messianic age in <a href="?bref=Isa.2.1-4">2:1-4</a>. The day will come when all nations will obey God’s word and live at peace. “The mountain of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>”—Jerusalem—will be raised up “and all the nations shall flow to it” (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.2-3">2:2-3</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). In the meantime, however, both Israel and the nations have exalted themselves against the Lord, and he will judge them in an awesome display of power. For Israel, God’s judgment will bring great upheaval, including the loss of its leaders. Defiant and ruthless, the rulers will face either death or deportation. Chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.3.1-26">3</a> ends by denouncing the pride and vanity of the women of Zion; they, too, will suffer disgrace. After Jerusalem is cleansed of its sin, the remnant will enjoy the rule of “the branch of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,” who will protect and shield his people (<a href="?bref=Isa.4.2-6">4:2-6</a>).</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Isa.5.1-7">5:1-7</a> Isaiah presents a short song about Israel as God’s vineyard. The Lord did everything possible to ensure a yield of good grapes, but the vineyard produced nothing but bad fruit and had to be destroyed. Isaiah then pronounces six woes against Israel, and announces that the Assyrian army will invade the land. Against the backdrop of Israel’s sin, Isaiah (ch <a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-13">6</a>) gives an account of the vision through which he was called as a prophet. Overwhelmed by the holiness of God and by his own sinfulness, Isaiah thought he was ruined, but when he was assured that his sins were forgiven, he responded positively to God’s call in spite of the stubbornness of the nation to which he was sent.</p>
<p>One of the most stubborn individuals in all the nation was King Ahaz of Judah, and chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.7.1-25">7</a> describes Isaiah’s encounter with this godless ruler. When Ahaz was threatened by Damascus and the northern kingdom, he refused to believe Isaiah’s promise that God would protect him. This was the occasion on which Isaiah gave Ahaz the sign of Immanuel (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">7:14</a>). The “virgin” refers ultimately to Mary and “Immanuel” to Christ (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.23">Mt 1:23</a>), but in the near fulfillment the child could be Isaiah’s own son Maher-shalal-hash-baz (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.3">Is 8:3</a>). (<span class="ital">See</span> four interpretations of this passage in <a href="?item=VirginBirthofJesus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Virgin Birth of Jesus</a>.) This name (meaning “swift to plunder and quick to spoil,” v <a href="?bref=Isa.8.1">1</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg) would be a sign that soon Judah’s enemies would fall; “Immanuel” signified that God would be with Judah (v <a href="?bref=Isa.8.10">10</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg). However, if Ahaz appealed for help to the king of Assyria, Isaiah warned him, Assyria’s powerful armies would one day invade Judah also (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.7.17-25">7:17-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.8.6-8">8:6-8</a>). The destruction brought by Assyria would plunge Judah into a time of famine and distress (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.21-22">8:21-22</a>).</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the gloom and darkness associated with the Assyrian invasion would not last indefinitely, and <a href="?bref=Isa.9.1-5">9:1-5</a> speaks of a time of peace and joy. Verses <a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-7.25">6-7</a> introduce a child who would become a righteous King and would rule forever. This “Prince of Peace” is the Messiah, the “Mighty God” whose kingdom is described in <a href="?bref=Isa.2.2-4">2:2-4</a>.</p>
<p>For the immediate future, however, both Israel and Judah will suffer the agony of war as punishment for their sins. God is angry with his people because they are proud and arrogant, and their leaders disregard the pleas of the poor and needy. Civil war and foreign invasion will crush the hapless nation (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.8-10.4">9:8–10:4</a>). But once Israel has been judged, God will turn his hand against Assyria, the instrument he has used to judge other nations. Because of her string of victories, Assyria is filled with pride and is eager for more triumph. Yet even at the moment when Jerusalem is about to succumb, God will cut down the Assyrian army like a cedar in Lebanon and spare his people (<a href="?bref=Isa.10.26-34">10:26-34</a>).</p>
<p>After Assyria’s defeat, Isaiah describes the restoration of Israel and the powerful rule of the Messiah (ch <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1-16">11</a>). Both Jews and Gentiles will be attracted to Jerusalem to enjoy an era of peace and justice. Like David, the Messiah will have the Spirit of God resting upon him as he judges the wicked and protects the needy. To conclude these opening messages, Isaiah offers two short songs of praise that celebrate God’s past deliverance and his promise of future blessing (ch <a href="?bref=Isa.12.1-6">12</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Oracles against the Nations (<a href="?bref=Isa.13.1-23.18">13–23</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Although Babylon is not the major power of the day, Isaiah begins his announcements of judgment with two chapters about the destruction of Assyria’s neighbor to the south. Babylon will eventually conquer Jerusalem (between 605 and 586 <span class="era">BC</span>), but the Medes (<a href="?bref=Isa.13.17">13:17</a>) along with the Elamites will capture Babylon (539 <span class="era">BC</span>). In spite of the glory to be achieved by future kings of Babylon, God will bring their pomp down to the grave (<a href="?bref=Isa.14.9-10">14:9-10</a>). The chapter ends with short prophecies against Assyria and the Philistines.</p>
<p>One of Israel’s oldest enemies was the nation of Moab, situated east of the Dead Sea. Even though it was a small country, Isaiah devotes two chapters to these descendants of Lot. Chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.15.1-9">15</a> describes the extensive mourning that will overwhelm their cities. After a brief interlude urging the Moabites to submit to Israel and to her God (<a href="?bref=Isa.16.1-5">16:1-5</a>), Isaiah notes that pride will lead to Moab’s downfall. Sounds of weeping fill the land as the vines and fields wither and are trampled.</p>
<p>In chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.17.1-14">17</a> the fourth oracle is directed against Damascus and Ephraim (the northern kingdom of Israel), probably reflecting their alliance against Judah about 734 <span class="era">BC</span>. Both nations will face ruin, and Ephraim is condemned for abandoning the Lord, her “Savior” and “Rock” (<a href="?bref=Isa.17.10">17:10</a>).</p>
<p>In chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.18.1-7">18</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.19.1-25">19</a> Isaiah turns to the south and addresses Ethiopia and Egypt, countries that had strong links from 715–633 <span class="era">BC</span>, when an Ethiopian named Shabako became pharaoh in Egypt. But Egypt is plagued with disunity and suffers greatly at the hands of Assyrian kings. In spite of the supposed wisdom of her leaders, Egypt faces economic and political ruin (<a href="?bref=Isa.19.5-15">19:5-15</a>). Yet the time is coming when the Egyptians will be restored and will worship the God of Israel. Along with Assyria and Israel, Egypt will become a blessing (<a href="?bref=Isa.19.24">19:24</a>). Some interpreters think this is a prophecy of the salvation of Gentiles during the church age, but others relate this day to the peace of the millennial age (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.2.2-4">2:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.6-9">11:6-9</a>). For the immediate future, however, Isaiah announces that Assyria will take many Egyptians and Ethiopians into captivity (ch <a href="?bref=Isa.20.1-6">20</a>).</p>
<p>A second oracle about Babylon (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.13.1-14.23">13:1–14:23</a>) is contained in chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.21.1-17">21</a>, and Isaiah is staggered as he considers the impact of Babylon’s fall (<a href="?bref=Isa.21.3-4">21:3-4</a>). When Babylon collapses, the world will know that her gods were powerless (<a href="?bref=Isa.21.9">21:9</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.14.8">Rv 14:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.18.2">18:2</a>).</p>
<p>Although it seems out of place among these oracles against the nations, chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.22.1-25">22</a> condemns the city of Jerusalem. Like the nations, Jerusalem is full of revelry (<a href="?bref=Isa.22.2">22:2</a>) but will soon experience the terrors of a siege. Since the people no longer rely on the Lord (v <a href="?bref=Isa.22.11">11</a>), he will hand them over to the enemy. Jerusalem’s unfaithfulness is exemplified by Shebna, a high official guilty of pride and materialism whose position will be taken by the godly Eliakim (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.22.15-23">15-23</a>).</p>
<p>The last oracle (ch <a href="?bref=Isa.23.1-18">23</a>) is directed against the city of Tyre, which resisted capture until Alexander the Great conquered the island fortress in 332 <span class="era">BC</span>. When Tyre fell, the economy of the entire Mediterranean world was shaken, for her ships had carried the goods of the nations far and wide.</p>
<p class="h3">Final Judgment and Blessing (<a href="?bref=Isa.24.1-27.13">24–27</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This section functions as a grand finale to chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.13.1-23.18">13–23</a> in that it anticipates God’s judgment upon the nations and the inauguration of the kingdom of God. A defiled earth must bear its punishment (<a href="?bref=Isa.24.5-6">24:5-6</a>) and even the forces of Satan face judgment (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.24.21-22">21-22</a>).</p>
<p>In chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.25.1-12">25</a> Isaiah rejoices over God’s great triumph and looks ahead to a day when death will be swallowed up and tears will be wiped from all faces (<a href="?bref=Isa.25.8">25:8</a>). Israel’s longtime enemies, symbolized by Moab, will be laid low (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.25.10-12">10-12</a>), but Jerusalem will be a stronghold for the righteous (<a href="?bref=Isa.26.1-3">26:1-3</a>). In <a href="?bref=Isa.26.7-19">26:7-19</a> the nation prays that these promises will become a reality. Verses <a href="?bref=Isa.20.1-21.27">20-21</a> indicate that the Lord will indeed respond, pouring out his wrath upon a sin-cursed earth and upon Satan himself (<a href="?bref=Isa.27.1">27:1</a>). When that takes place, Israel will be a fruitful vineyard, a blessing to the whole world (<a href="?bref=Isa.27.2-6">27:2-6</a>; contrast <a href="?bref=Isa.5.1-7">5:1-7</a>). First, however, Israel will have to endure war and exile, and then the remnant will return to Jerusalem.</p>
<p class="h3">A Series of Woes (<a href="?bref=Isa.28.1-33.24">28–33</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Returning to his own historical period, Isaiah pronounces a series of woes upon both the northern and southern kingdoms, as well as one upon Assyria (ch <a href="?bref=Isa.33.1-24">33</a>). Chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.28.1-29">28</a> begins with a description of the fading power of Samaria, the capital of the northern kingdom. Verses <a href="?bref=Isa.7.1-10.11">7-10</a> portray the leaders of Judah in the same light; they have disregarded Isaiah’s message and are out of touch with God. Judgment is on the way, and their false preparation (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.7.15,18">15, 18</a>) will be of no avail. God will fight against Israel (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.7.21-22">21-22</a>), and even Jerusalem will be put under siege until God in his mercy intervenes (<a href="?bref=Isa.29.1-8">29:1-8</a>). Because of their hypocritical worship, the people deserve to be punished, but in the future Israel will again acknowledge the Lord and be made physically and spiritually whole (<a href="?bref=Isa.29.17-24">29:17-24</a>).</p>
<p>Chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.30.1-33">30</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.31.1-9">31</a> denounce Judah’s proposed alliance with Egypt in the effort to thwart Assyria. God wants his people to trust him, not their unreliable neighbors to the south. The Lord promises to protect Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Isa.30.18">30:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.31.5">31:5</a>) and defeat the invading Assyrian army (<a href="?bref=Isa.30.31-33">30:31-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.31.8-9">31:8-9</a>). None can stand before his mighty sword.</p>
<p>Continuing on this positive note, Isaiah goes on to emphasize the righteous rule of the messianic king in chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.32.1-20">32</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.33.1-24">33</a>. Zion will enjoy peace and security at last (<a href="?bref=Isa.32.2,17-18">32:2, 17-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.33.6">33:6</a>), a great change from Isaiah’s own time. In eighth-century <span class="era">BC</span> Judah the women might feel secure (<a href="?bref=Isa.32.9">32:9</a>), but the Assyrian troops will devastate the crops and precipitate widespread mourning. However, the lamenting will soon end, as the prophet pronounces woe upon Assyria in <a href="?bref=Isa.33.1">33:1</a>. After Isaiah prays for the destruction of Assyria (<a href="?bref=Isa.33.2-9">33:2-9</a>), God promises to take action (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.33.10-12">10-12</a>). Gone will be the enemy soldiers and officials, for the Lord will save his people and bring them justice and security.</p>
<p class="h3">More Judgment and Blessing (<a href="?bref=Isa.34.1-35.10">34–35</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This section forms a climax to chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.28.1-33.24">28–33</a>. Once more, cataclysmic judgment precedes a time of blessing and restoration. In chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.34.1-17">34</a> Isaiah depicts a judgment of cosmic dimensions as he moves to a consideration of the last days. Heaven and earth endure the wrath of God that is poured out upon the nations, and verse <a href="?bref=Isa.34.4">4</a> provides the basis for John’s description of the great tribulation in <a href="?bref=Rev.6.13-14">Revelation 6:13-14</a>. Edom (like Moab; see <a href="?bref=Isa.25.10-12">Is 25:10-12</a>) represents a world judged by the sword of the Lord in his day of vengeance.</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.35.1-10">35</a>, on the other hand, speaks of joy and restoration in a passage that pulsates with life. A blooming desert corresponds to the physical and spiritual age when God will come to redeem his people. Both the return of the Israelites from the Babylonian captivity and the second coming of Christ fit this glorious scene.</p>
<p class="h3">Historical Interlude (<a href="?bref=Isa.36.1-39.8">36–39</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">These chapters form the hinge that connects the two halves of the book. Chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.36.1-22">36</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.37.1-38">37</a> contain the fulfillment of Isaiah’s prophecies about Assyria’s collapse, and chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.38.1-22">38</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.39.1-8">39</a> introduce the Babylonian captivity that forms the backdrop for chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-66.24">40–66</a>. In 701 <span class="era">BC</span> King Sennacherib of Assyria demands the unconditional surrender of Jerusalem. He sends his field commander to address the people and try to gain their submission. With persuasive words, the commander tries to convince the city that surrender is the best policy. Amazingly the people do not panic, and King Hezekiah asks Isaiah to pray for the beleaguered city. The prophet does so and announces that the proud Assyrians will not triumph. Instead, they suffer a terrible disaster as the angel of the Lord strikes down 185,000 men.</p>
<p>Chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.38.1-22">38</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.39.1-8">39</a> relate another crisis in Hezekiah’s life when he becomes desperately ill. Miraculously, God heals him, and Hezekiah praises the Lord for his gracious intervention. When the king of Babylon sends envoys to congratulate Hezekiah on his recovery, Hezekiah foolishly shows these messengers his royal treasures. Isaiah solemnly announces that someday the armies of Babylon will capture Jerusalem, plunder the land, and take away these treasures.</p>
<p class="h3">The Return from Babylon (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-48.22">40–48</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The Babylonian captivity eventually comes, but Isaiah promises that it will end. God, the incomparably powerful Creator, is far greater than any king, nation, or god, and he will bring his people back to Jerusalem. To accomplish this return from exile, God raises up Cyrus, the king of Persia (<a href="?bref=Isa.41.2,25">41:2, 25</a>). The Lord does not forget his people, and he encourages them to take heart and to rejoice.</p>
<p>In chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.42.1-25">42</a> we are introduced to a person even more significant than Cyrus the Persian. Verses <a href="?bref=Isa.42.1-7">1-7</a> (the first of four Servant Songs) describe the servant of the Lord, who will bring justice to the nations and will be “a light for the Gentiles” (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.6">42:6</a>). This is the Messiah, and the redemption he will accomplish on Calvary (cf. ch <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">53</a>) is greater than the release from Babylon. In light of the good news associated with the servant, Isaiah praises the Lord for punishing the wicked and rescuing his wayward people. Chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.43.1-28">43</a> declares that nothing will stand in the way of Israel’s return, and the Lord will remember their sins no more. In fact, he will pour out his Spirit on their descendants (<a href="?bref=Isa.44.3">44:3</a>).</p>
<p>A God so great is far more powerful than any idol. In <a href="?bref=Isa.44.6-20">44:6-20</a> Isaiah makes use of satire to show the worthlessness of man-made images. God alone has the power to create and to restore, and he will bring Cyrus on the scene to effect the release of the exiles and to begin the rebuilding of Jerusalem. Chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.46.1-13">46</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.47.1-15">47</a> contrast the God of Israel and the idols of Babylon. When God raises up Cyrus, Babylon’s idols will be unable to save their nation, and the queen of kingdoms (<a href="?bref=Isa.47.5">47:5</a>) will collapse along with her sorcerers and astrologers. The final chapter in this section (ch <a href="?bref=Isa.48.1-22">48</a>) restates God’s purpose of gaining release of the Israelites from Babylon through his chosen ally, Cyrus of Persia.</p>
<p class="h3">Salvation through the Servant of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.1-57.21">49–57</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.49.1-53.12">49–53</a> contain the final three Servant Songs (cf. also <a href="?bref=Isa.42.1-7">42:1-7</a>), culminating in the death of the servant for the sins of the world (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.13-53.12">52:13–53:12</a>). In the second Servant Song (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.1-7">49:1-7</a>), Isaiah describes the call and ministry of the servant, noting that he will face strong opposition as he accomplishes salvation for Israel and the nations. The rest of chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.49.1-26">49</a> deals primarily with the way God will bring Israel back from exile. Soon the land will be filled with a mighty throng (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.49.19-21">19-21</a>), and the Gentiles will acknowledge Israel and her God (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.49.22-23">22-23</a>).</p>
<p>Although Israel has fully deserved the exile because of her sins (<a href="?bref=Isa.50.1-3">50:1-3</a>), the suffering endured by the servant (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.50.4-11">4-11</a>; the third Servant Song) is wholly undeserved. The beating and mocking of verse <a href="?bref=Isa.50.6">6</a> are prophetic of Christ’s experience (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.27.26,30">Mt 27:26, 30</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.15.19">Mk 15:19</a>). In verses <a href="?bref=Isa.50.10-11">10-11</a> of <a href="?bref=Isa.50.1-11">Isaiah 50</a> the whole nation is challenged to trust in the Lord, as the servant did. There is, in fact, a believing remnant who obey the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.51.1-8">51:1-8</a>), and the Lord promises that he will restore them to their homeland. Israel has drunk the cup of God’s wrath (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.51.17,22">17, 22</a>), but the good news of release from exile causes even the ruins of Jerusalem to burst into songs of joy (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.7-10">52:7-10</a>).</p>
<p>Yet the best news of all is salvation from sin; the final Servant Song (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.13-53.12">52:13–53:12</a>) tells how Christ wins freedom for those held in bondage to sin. In this brief passage we learn how Christ suffers rejection (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.3">53:3</a>) and even disfigurement (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.14">52:14</a>). Led like a lamb to the slaughter (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.7">53:7</a>), he carries our sins in his body as he dies in ignominy. The people think he is suffering for his own sins (v <a href="?bref=Isa.53.4">4</a>), but he is “pierced” and “crushed for our iniquities” (v <a href="?bref=Isa.53.5">5</a>). The first and last paragraphs of this section (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.13-15">52:13-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.53.10-12">53:10-12</a>) state that through his suffering the servant is highly exalted. What seems like a terrible defeat is actually victory over death and Satan and brings salvation for many.</p>
<p>As a direct result of the servant’s death, great joy comes to all people. In chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.54.1-17">54</a> this joy is reflected in Jerusalem’s new status as the Lord’s wife. Her descendants will be numerous and eager to learn from the Lord. For the first time the plural “servants of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” appears (<a href="?bref=Isa.54.17">54:17</a>), apparently including all believers, whether Jew or Gentile (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.65.8-9,13-15">65:8-9, 13-15</a>). Joy and prosperity also characterize chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.55.1-13">55</a>, an invitation to a great spiritual banquet. All people are urged to turn to the Lord who keeps his promises to Israel. In <a href="?bref=Isa.56.1-8">56:1-8</a>, foreigners are invited to come to God’s “holy mountain” in Jerusalem, for the temple will be a house of prayer for all the nations (<a href="?bref=Isa.56.7">56:7</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.21.13">Mt 21:13</a>).</p>
<p>Believing Gentiles are contrasted sharply with unbelieving Jews, and in <a href="?bref=Isa.56.9-57.13">56:9–57:13</a> Isaiah returns again to the theme of judgment. Israel suffers because her leaders are wicked and because the people are guilty of idolatry. Spiritual healing is available, but unless individuals repent, they cannot be part of the remnant who will return from exile and enjoy peace in the Promised Land.</p>
<p class="h3">Ultimate Blessing and Final Judgment (<a href="?bref=Isa.58.1-66.24">58–66</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The last nine chapters of Isaiah emphasize redemption and glory, but the reality of judgment is also very much in evidence. In fact, chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.58.1-14">58</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.59.1-21">59</a> bemoan the sins of Israel. The people are hypocritical in their worship; they are selfish and fail to keep the Sabbath. Lying, oppression, and murder separate the people from God. When Isaiah openly confesses these sins (<a href="?bref=Isa.59.12-13">59:12-13</a>), the Lord suddenly takes action on behalf of his people. Like a mighty warrior, he rescues the believing remnant from Babylon and brings them back to Jerusalem.</p>
<p>In chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.60.1-22">60</a> the glory and wealth of Jerusalem reach new heights. Both the city and the sanctuary are adorned with splendor, matching the prosperity of Solomon’s reign. Just as the nations treated Solomon with honor, so earth’s leaders will assist and strengthen the returning exiles. While it is true that the Persian government did help the Jews repeatedly, the conditions described here will have their ultimate fulfillment during the Millennium and in connection with the new Jerusalem (cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.21.23">Rv 21:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.22.5">22:5</a>). The ancient ruins will be rebuilt (<a href="?bref=Isa.61.4">Is 61:4</a>), and the Lord will fulfill the covenant made with Abraham and David (<a href="?bref=Isa.61.8">Is 61:8</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.12.1-3">Gn 12:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.55.3">Is 55:3</a>). Jerusalem will be the city of the holy people, the redeemed of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.62.12">Is 62:12</a>), and the Lord will take delight in her (v <a href="?bref=Isa.62.4">4</a>).</p>
<p>In order to accomplish salvation for his people, God will have to judge the ungodly first. The great trampling of the winepress (<a href="?bref=Isa.63.2-3">63:2-3</a>) graphically portrays the judgment process and is linked with the Day of the Lord (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.13.3">13:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.2">34:2</a>). Since God has promised to intervene on behalf of his people, Isaiah prays for the realization of that promise (<a href="?bref=Isa.63.7-64.12">63:7–64:12</a>). He recalls God’s faithfulness in the past and pleads that he will again have mercy upon his suffering people.</p>
<p>The answer to Isaiah’s prayer is found in chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.65.1-25">65</a>. God does promise to give the Holy Land back to his servants, to those who worship him and obey him. But for that segment of the nation that continues in its obstinacy, God promises anguish and destruction. The ultimate joy of God’s servants is contained in a description of new heavens and a new earth (<a href="?bref=Isa.65.17-25">65:17-25</a>). Peace, long life, and prosperity will be among the blessings enjoyed in an era that seems to combine features of the Millennium and the eternal state (cf. ch <a href="?bref=Isa.60.1-22">60</a>).</p>
<p>In a fitting summary, chapter <a href="?bref=Isa.66.1-24">66</a> ties together the themes of salvation and judgment. God will comfort Jerusalem and abundantly bless her, but sinners are the objects of his wrath. Those who honor him will endure forever, but those who rebel will suffer everlasting rejection.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsaiahPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Isaiah (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=Messiah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Messiah</a>; <a href="?item=Prophecy_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophecy</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetProphetess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophet, Prophetess</a>; <a href="?item=ServantoftheLord_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Servant of the Lord</a>; <a href="?item=VirginBirthofJesus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Virgin Birth of Jesus</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>