<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ishmael">
  <title>Ishmael</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ISHMAEL</p>
<p class="list">1. Abraham’s first son, born of Hagar, Sarah’s Egyptian handmaid, at the instigation of Sarah herself. God promised to make a great nation of the childless Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.2">Gn 12:2</a>), assuring him that his son would be his heir (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.4">15:4</a>). But when Sarah was past 75 years old and still barren, she invoked the custom whereby a childless wife gave her maid to her husband as concubine and laid claim to the offspring of their union (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.1-2">16:1-2</a>). When Hagar conceived, the reproach attendant on barrenness prompted the maid to behave contemptuously toward her mistress, and with Abraham’s consent Sarah dealt harshly with her and she fled. An angel sent Hagar back to submit to her mistress and promised her a son to be named Ishmael meaning “God hears” (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.9-11">16:9-11</a>). The boy was born near Hebron when Abraham was 86 years old (<a href="?bref=Gen.13.18">13:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.16.16">16:16</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Abraham and Sarah received him as the son of God’s promise, as attested by their disbelief when the forthcoming birth of Isaac was announced (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.17">17:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.18.12">18:12</a>), and by Abraham’s subsequent wish that Ishmael should be accepted of God (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.18">17:18</a>). At age 13 he participated in the institution of circumcision as a witness of God’s covenant with Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.9-14,22-27">17:9-14, 22-27</a>), and the Lord promised to make Ishmael the father of 12 princes, from which would come a great nation, though the covenant was to be established with Isaac (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.20-21">17:20-21</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">There is no evidence that Ishmael was out of favor until Isaac’s weaning at about three years of age. When Sarah saw Ishmael “making fun” of her son Isaac, she determined that the son of a slave woman should not be heir with her son Isaac, and she demanded that Ishmael and Hagar be banished. Although vexed, Abraham received reassurance from the Lord and sent them away with some provisions. It was then clear to Abraham that Isaac, not Ishmael, was the son of God’s promise.</p>
<p class="list-text">Hagar survived in the wilderness with the guidance of an angel, and Ishmael became a hunter of wild animals. He settled in the wilderness of Paran and married an Egyptian woman (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.20-21">21:20-21</a>). Little else is recorded of him, except that he lived to assist in the burial of Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.9-10">25:9-10</a>), gave his daughter Mahalath in marriage (<a href="?bref=Gen.28.9">28:9</a>), and died at the age of 137 (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.17">25:17</a>). The names of his 12 sons and their settlements are recorded in <a href="?bref=Gen.25.13-16">Genesis 25:13-16</a>. In subsequent history, a caravan of Ishmaelite traders (also called Midianites, cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.8.22-24">Jgs 8:22-24</a>) bought Joseph from his brothers and sold him in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.25-28">Gn 37:25-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.39.1">39:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Though Isaac, rather than Ishmael, inherited the covenantal blessings, it is clear that the covenant was not the only means whereby divine favor could be bestowed. Abraham and Sarah overestimated the importance of Ishmael in God’s plan by mistaking him for the heir of covenant promises, but they also underrated God’s intentions for him by excluding him altogether from inheritance with Isaac.</p>
<p class="list-text">In the NT, Paul alludes to Ishmael while urging the Galatians not to see the law as a yoke (<a href="?bref=Gal.4.22">Gal 4:22</a>). He states that those who trust the law instead of putting their faith in God’s promises do not inherit the kingdom, just as the son of the slave woman did not receive inheritance with the son of the free woman (v <a href="?bref=Gal.4.30">30</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Son of Nethaniah, son of Elishama, of the royal family of Zedekiah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.25">2 Kgs 25:25</a>). He was prompted by Baalis, king of the Ammonites, to assassinate Gedaliah, Judean governor of the puppet regime, which Nebuchadnezzar left behind at Mizpah at the time of the Babylonian exile. Gedaliah ignored advance warning of the plot and refused to allow Johanan to assassinate Ishmael first (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.14-16">Jer 40:14-16</a>). While sharing a meal with Gedaliah, Ishmael and ten companions killed him, along with the Babylonian troops accompanying him. The next day he persuaded a group of 80 pilgrims passing from the north to the temple at Jerusalem to enter Mizpah, where he killed all but 10 who ransomed their lives with stores of food. Hiding all the bodies in a cistern, Ishmael took captive the rest of the population of Mizpah, including Jeremiah and women of the royal family, and set out to join the Ammonites. But Johanan, with an armed force, overtook Ishmael at Gibeon and rescued the captives, whereupon Ishmael fled to Ammonite territory (<a href="?bref=Jer.41.1-18">Jer 41</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Son of Azel, a Benjamite of the family of Saul (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.38">1 Chr 8:38</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.44">9:44</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Father of Zebadiah, the governor of the house of Judah under Jehoshaphat (<a href="?bref=2Chr.19.11">2 Chr 19:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Son of Jehohanan, and one of the commanders who allied with Jehoiada the priest to enthrone the child Joash and thus end the reign of Athaliah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.23.1">2 Chr 23:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. Son of Pashhur, and one of the priests who put away foreign wives during Ezra’s reforms (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.22">Ezr 10:22</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>