<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="IsraelHistoryof">
  <title>Israel, History of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ISRAEL, History of</p>
<p class="fl">An account of God’s sovereign purpose in calling a people out of paganism and establishing them as witnesses for the true faith among the nations, of God’s sovereign power in protecting them from extinction, of his sovereign justice in dealing with their departure from his ways of holiness, of God’s sovereign grace in forgiving their sins and restoring them to fellowship with himself by providing through them a Savior for the entire world.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#PatriarchalAge">Patriarchal Age</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#SojourninEgypt">Sojourn in Egypt</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheExodus">The Exodus</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#WildernessWanderings">Wilderness Wanderings</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheConquest">The Conquest</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheJudges">The Judges</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheUnitedMonarchy">The United Monarchy</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheDividedKingdom">The Divided Kingdom</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheRestoration">The Restoration</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheIntertestamentalPeriod">The Intertestamental Period</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheRomanPeriod">The Roman Period</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="PatriarchalAge">Patriarchal Age</p>
<p class="fl">The story of Israel begins with Abraham, whom God called first at Ur, and perhaps later at Haran (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.2-4">Acts 7:2-4</a>), to leave Mesopotamia and go into a land to which God would direct the way. In calling Abraham, God made with him a covenant (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.1-3">Gn 12:1-3</a>) that promised him a land, special divine favor (“I will bless those who bless you, and the one who curses you I will curse,” <span class="sc">nasb</span>), and the privilege of being a channel of blessing to the entire world (“In you all the families of the earth shall be blessed,” <span class="sc">nasb</span>). In <a href="?bref=Gen.12.4-8">Genesis 12:4-8</a> God confirmed this unconditional covenant, promising Abraham this new land forever, along with innumerable descendants. Subsequently, in <a href="?bref=Gen.15.1-21">Genesis 15:1-21</a>, God again confirmed the covenant but added the significant prediction that the guarantee of holding Canaan in perpetuity did not mean occupation of the land in every generation. God also spelled out the limits of the Promised Land (from the river of Egypt to the Euphrates, some 500 to 600 miles or 804 to 965 kilometers in extent). A final confirmation of the covenant to Abraham appears in <a href="?bref=Gen.17.6-8">Genesis 17:6-8</a>. It guaranteed the land of Canaan to Abraham’s posterity and added that kings (an anticipation of the Davidic dynasty) would arise in his line. The covenant was confirmed to Abraham’s son Isaac (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.3-5">Gn 26:3-5</a>) and his grandson Jacob (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.28.1-22">28</a>).</p>
<p>This period is known as the patriarchal age in Hebrew history. The patriarchs were Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. They were called patriarchs because they were fathers, not only to their immediate families, but also to the extended family of Hebrews, over which they exercised a fatherly control. They served as political, legal, and spiritual heads of their migratory community, looking after their interests and leading them in worship. Periodically they built altars on which they offered sacrifices. That the patriarchal community was very large can be seen from <a href="?bref=Gen.14.14">Genesis 14:14</a>, which says that Abraham had 318 armed men in his camp. If one assumes that most of the men were married and had one or more children each, the total extended family may have numbered in excess of 1,000.</p>
<p>Additional developments in the life of Abraham and Jacob were particularly important for world history. Abraham, frustrated at not having an heir, accepted Sarah’s suggestion to obtain an heir by the slave girl Hagar. (This was also the custom of the land.) The son born was named Ishmael, progenitor of the Arabs. Thus Abraham is revered by Arabs and Muslims as well as by Jews and Christians. He is the father of the Jews through his son Isaac, child of promise. He holds a special place in Christianity as an example of Christ, through whom all Christians obtain their salvation.</p>
<p>Jacob, a scheming scoundrel in his earlier years, wound up in exile in northern Mesopotamia for 20 years in the home of his uncle Laban. There he married Leah and Rachel and fathered the sons who became the progenitors of the 12 tribes of Israel. On his return to Palestine he met God along the banks of the Jabbok River (<a href="?bref=Gen.32.1-32">Gn 32</a>), and God changed his name to Israel (“a prince of God,” <span class="sc">kjv</span> mg).</p>
<p>The patriarchal period in Canaan lasted for 215 years. One estimate places Abraham’s entry into Canaan at about 2085 <span class="era">BC</span>, when he was 75 years of age. Jacob and his sons migrated to Egypt to escape a severe famine in Canaan in about 1870 <span class="era">BC</span>. During much of the patriarchal period, Palestine experienced a decline in population and was occupied largely by nomadic or seminomadic tribes. It was relatively easy for the Hebrews to enter such a situation. After 1900 Palestine began to enjoy more settled conditions. Shortly thereafter, the Hebrews made the trek into Egypt.</p>
<p class="h2" id="SojourninEgypt">Sojourn in Egypt</p>
<p class="fl">If Jacob and his sons entered Egypt about 1870 <span class="era">BC</span>, it was the period of the Middle Kingdom. And by that time other migrants from Asia were coming in increasing numbers. The Hebrews settled in Goshen, in the eastern delta region, under the protecting care of Joseph, who held a position at the Egyptian court roughly equivalent to that of prime minister. As more and more Asiatic Hyksos came into Egypt, they began to take over the country—northern Egypt at least. During this same time the Hebrews became increasingly numerous. Some who hold to a different chronology believe the Hebrews were welcomed into Egypt during the days of Hyksos domination (after 1750 <span class="era">BC</span>). At any rate, by about 1580 <span class="era">BC</span> native Egyptian princes regained control of the country and expelled many of the Asiatics.</p>
<p>In process of time there arose a king over Egypt who “knew not Joseph” (<a href="?bref=Exod.1.8">Ex 1:8</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). Very possibly this meant that a native Egyptian dynasty had arisen in Egypt and they were apprehensive over the fact that the growing numbers and wealth of the Hebrews might jeopardize their own supremacy. But Egyptian measures to subjugate the Hebrews and reduce their birthrate had a reverse effect (<a href="?bref=Exod.1.12">Ex 1:12</a>). Finally, the Egyptians ordered the killing of all male Hebrew infants at birth. Among those who disobeyed were the parents of Moses, who set him afloat in a waterproof basket made of reeds. Found by a daughter of Pharaoh, he was brought up in the Egyptian court, was given a first-class education, and became a high official of the realm.</p>
<p>At the age of 40, Moses identified himself with his own people. He killed an Egyptian in defense of a fellow Hebrew, and immediately fled to the land of Midian in the northeastern part of the Sinai Peninsula. He married and lived there for 40 years, becoming thoroughly familiar with the geography and the ways of the wilderness through which he would later lead the Hebrews. The Egyptians continued to oppress the Hebrew people severely until they cried urgently to God for deliverance. In response, God confronted Moses in the famous burning bush experience and called on him to return to Egypt and lead the people back into the land of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.1-4.31">Ex 3–4</a>). He was to have the help of his brother, Aaron.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheExodus">The Exodus</p>
<p class="fl">Understandably the pharaoh of Egypt was reluctant to permit the Hebrews to leave permanently. The value of this great labor force was incalculable. But finally, after suffering a series of ten plagues, lasting perhaps a year, the Egyptians were persuaded to let the Hebrews go (<a href="?bref=Exod.7.1-12.51">Ex 7–12</a>).</p>
<p>The plagues had a theological as well as a practical purpose. They discredited the gods of Egypt and exalted the most high God of heaven (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.12">Ex 12:12</a>). The plagues clearly discredited specific gods of Egypt (e.g., the Nile was worshiped as Hapi, plague one; the frog, worshiped as Heqt, plague two; the bull, worshiped as Ptah, plague five; the sun, worshiped as Amon-Re/Aton, plague nine). Taken together, they struck a direct blow at the Egyptian pantheon.</p>
<p>Just before the last plague, which was the night in which the death angel invaded the homes of the Egyptians, the Israelites made the Passover sacrifice according to divine instructions. This involved killing a lamb for each household (unless the household was too small; in that event, households could combine). Anyone who was careless about applying the blood to the doorpost or who rejected this divine provision came under the judgment of God. After the death of the firstborn throughout the land, the Egyptians begged the Hebrews to leave. Their company numbered 600,000 men over 20 years of age, plus women and children, for a total of over 2,500,000. In addition they took their flocks and herds and personal belongings.</p>
<p>The date they left Egypt is a matter of continuing debate. Traditionally a date of about 1446 <span class="era">BC</span> is given for the exodus (cf. <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.1">1 Kgs 6:1</a>, which places the exodus 480 years before construction of the temple started in 966 <span class="era">BC</span>) and 1406 <span class="era">BC</span> for the Conquest under Joshua, and there do not seem to be any compelling arguments for rejecting that position. But a great many scholars prefer 1275 <span class="era">BC</span> for a variety of reasons.</p>
<p>The early date of the exodus would place the later years of the wilderness wanderings and the subsequent conquest of Palestine during the reigns of Amenhotep III and IV (1412–1366), a time when the pharaohs allowed Egyptian control of Palestine to disintegrate. When the Egyptians did reassert their power, about 1300, they restricted their movements largely to the coastal area, and thus did not come in contact with the Hebrews who were living in the hill country of Judea, Samaria, and Galilee.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WildernessWanderings">Wilderness Wanderings</p>
<p class="fl">The wilderness wanderings were an important interlude in the history of Israel. During those years, significant and basic institutions came into existence at God’s command. At Sinai, Moses delivered to Israel the law, the pattern of the tabernacle (which later became the model for the temple) and orders for its operation, as well as detailed instructions for the priesthood and sacrificial system of worship.</p>
<p>The period of the wanderings was truly a remarkable time. The presence of God was evidenced by a pillar of cloud that hovered over the people by day and a pillar of fire by night. God provided food in the form of manna, periodically provided water by miraculous means, and made sure that clothes did not wear out. In spite of all that, the people murmured and complained continually.</p>
<p>At Sinai, God gave the law (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.2-24.18">Ex 19:2–24:18</a>), and the people promptly made a commitment to keep it (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.3">24:3</a>). Then God gave the pattern for the tabernacle and its furniture (chs <a href="?bref=Exod.25.1-27.21">25–27</a>, <a href="?bref=Exod.30.1-31.18">30–31</a>, <a href="?bref=Exod.35.1-40.38">35–40</a>) and established the priesthood (chs <a href="?bref=Exod.28.1-29.46">28–29</a>). While Moses was on the mountain receiving God’s revelation, the people grew restless and clamored for gods they could see. Even Aaron was carried away with the idolatrous wave and supervised the casting of a golden calf and building of an altar before it. The fact that they turned to Egyptian cattle worship so readily indicates that paganism must have made deep inroads among them while in captivity (chs <a href="?bref=Exod.32.1-34.35">32–34</a>). Moses’ intercessory response to God’s announcement that he would destroy Israel because of her idolatry led to a divine determination to execute judgment on only the worst offenders (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.9-14">32:9-14</a>).</p>
<p>Subsequently, God revealed the legal and priestly order (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.1-27.34">Lv 1:1–27:34</a>). Among the divinely appointed institutions described or alluded to in Leviticus are several special days or feasts, including the Sabbath, Passover, Feast of Unleavened Bread, Firstfruits, Pentecost or Feast of Weeks, Feast of Trumpets, Day of Atonement, Feast of Tabernacles, the Year of Sabbath, and the Year of Jubilee.</p>
<p>After camping at Sinai for about a year, the Israelites got their orders to go forward (<a href="?bref=Num.10.11-12">Nm 10:11-12</a>). Miriam (Moses’ sister) and Aaron criticized Moses’ leadership and suffered divine punishment as a consequence (ch <a href="?bref=Num.12.1-16">12</a>). When the people arrived at Kadesh-barnea, the gate to southern Palestine, they were frightened by the report of most of the spies who had been reconnoitering in Canaan and decided that they should not advance into Canaan. They called for a new leader to bring them back to Egypt. God declared that the entire generation would wander in the wilderness until the adults had died. Only Joshua and Caleb (the two spies in favor of invading immediately) would enter the Promised Land (<a href="?bref=Num.14.26-30">14:26-30</a>). Near the end of the period of wandering, Moses also lost the privilege of entering the land by an act of disobedience.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheConquest">The Conquest</p>
<p class="fl">The latter part of the book of Numbers describes how Moses led the Israelites to victory over the peoples living east of the Jordan River. Reuben, Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh requested permission to settle there and reluctantly were allowed to do so on the condition that they would join the rest of the Israelites in conquering Canaan before settling down. Prior to victories in Transjordan, a new census of adult males was taken in order to determine the military capabilities of Israel and to provide a basis for equitable division of the land they were about to enter. The number of males above 20 years of age was 601,730 (<a href="?bref=Num.26.51">Nm 26:51</a>). The book of Deuteronomy consists primarily of a series of speeches delivered by Moses in a covenant renewal ceremony on the plains of Moab just before his death and the appointment of Joshua as leader.</p>
<p>Joshua lost no time in moving forward. Spies sent across the Jordan to Jericho to reconnoiter reported a situation quite different from what the Hebrews had experienced at Kadesh-barnea a generation earlier. Now the people of Canaan were terrified because they had heard of the numerical strength and victories of the Hebrews. Apparently the day after the spies returned, Joshua moved the people to the edge of the Jordan and prepared to cross over. The waters parted for them here as the Red Sea had parted earlier.</p>
<p>The narrative of conquest that appears in the book of Joshua is not a detailed battle account. It describes a thrust into the middle of Palestine around Jericho and Ai, a southerly drive to defeat the Amorite league, and a northern campaign against Hazor and other towns. The history of Joshua is extremely telescoped, for Joshua’s major military action must have required about six years. Joshua’s friend Caleb was 79 when the Conquest began and 85 after the last great battle with Jabin, king of Hazor (<a href="?bref=Josh.14.7-10">Jos 14:7-10</a>).</p>
<p>When the war was over, major strongholds (e.g., Jerusalem) still remained in enemy hands, but the land west of the Jordan was allocated to the nine and a half Hebrew tribes. The task of reducing enemy towns was left to the individual tribes in whose land they were located. The Joshua account was not so much a narrative of Israelite battle prowess as of God’s faithfulness and intervention on behalf of his people. For example, at Jericho they did not attack but merely followed divine orders and watched the defenses collapse; at Gibeon hailstones killed more Amorites than Israelite soldiers did (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.7-11">Jos 10:7-11</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheJudges">The Judges</p>
<p class="fl">Joshua died some 30 years after he had led the Hebrews into Canaan, and he was followed by a series of divinely appointed leaders who ruled sometimes over the whole of Israel as a loose confederacy and sometimes over one or more tribes. They were judges, civil functionaries, and military leaders all at the same time.</p>
<p>The book of Judges pictures a series of recurring cycles: apostasy from God, punishment in the form of oppression by neighboring tribes, cries to God for relief, release from bondage under the leadership of a judge, and a period of rest from oppression.</p>
<p>Establishment of the chronology of the judges is one of the thorniest problems of Scripture. Adding up all years of oppression and rest mentioned in the book gives a total of 410. The book of Acts gives a total of 450 years from the days of Joshua to Samuel (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.19">Acts 13:19</a>). The difference in Acts may be accounted for by the addition of 40 years of Eli’s ministry (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.18">1 Sm 4:18</a>). Allowing 410 years for the period of the judges, about 30 for the Conquest to the judges, and 40 for the wilderness wanderings, means 480 years from 1050 <span class="era">BC</span>, the date for Saul’s kingship, and would give a date of about 1530 for the exodus. This is about 100 years more than even the early date for the exodus. The most probable explanation is that there is some overlap in oppressions and judgeships. For instance, the activities of Jephthah were centered on the eastern frontier, those of Samson in the Philistine plain to the southwest, and those of Deborah and Barak in the north.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheUnitedMonarchy">The United Monarchy</p>
<p class="fl">Because of the weakness of Israel resulting from political disunity and the ineptness and corruption of both Eli’s and Samuel’s sons, the people of Israel called for a king to rule over them. This demand was in reality a rejection of the divine plan of theocracy—the rule of God. God granted the Hebrews’ wish but warned them of the disadvantages of monarchy (<a href="?bref=1Sam.8.9-21">1 Sm 8:9-21</a>). The concept of kingship was not new to Israel. It had been hinted at in <a href="?bref=Gen.49.10">Genesis 49:10</a> and <a href="?bref=Num.24.17">Numbers 24:17</a>, and Moses had made some very clear statements about it in <a href="?bref=Deut.17.14-20">Deuteronomy 17:14-20</a>.</p>
<p>The first stage of Hebrew monarchy is commonly called the united monarchy because all Israel was ruled by a single king. This period lasted for 120 years—encompassing the 40-year reigns of Saul (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.21">Acts 13:21</a>), David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.5">2 Sm 5:5</a>), and Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.42">1 Kgs 11:42</a>).</p>
<p>The people asked for a king, and God granted them one, but not one like those of the surrounding nations. The Hebrew king was to be a man who followed God’s dictates in his public and private life, who did not intrude into the affairs of the priesthood, and who did not fall into idolatry, but exerted all his influence to keep the people faithful to God. If he failed in any of these respects, he ran the risk of being deposed by God, of having his line brought to an end, or even of having the people fall into captivity to a foreign power. All this must be kept in mind when evaluating the reigns of Saul, David, Solomon, and the kings of the divided monarchy.</p>
<p>Saul began well. He won a great victory over the Ammonites at Jabesh-gilead and showed considerable wisdom in administrative matters. But after about two years he intruded into the priest’s office to offer sacrifice, bringing the divine prediction that his kingdom would be taken from him (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.8-14">1 Sm 13:8-14</a>). He would go on to enjoy great military victory and ability as a ruler until about the middle of his reign.</p>
<p>After Saul’s disobedience to God’s command to totally destroy the Amalekites, the Lord repudiated Saul and instructed Samuel to anoint David privately as future king of Israel. David’s rise to prominence was spurred by his victory over Goliath and the accompanying defeat of the Philistines. Saul later made David commander of the army, and the young man soon earned a reputation greater than that of the king himself. Saul, who had become increasingly mentally disturbed after his relationship with God was broken, began to make attempts on David’s life, and for the last years of Saul’s reign David lived as a fugitive. Meanwhile, the Philistines got completely out of control and finally killed Saul and most of his sons in the great battle of Mt Gilboa, which gave the Philistines control over much of Palestine west of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=1Sam.31.1-7">1 Sm 31:1-7</a>).</p>
<p>Soon David became king in Judah with his capital in Hebron. A son of Saul, Ishbosheth, established himself at Mahanaim, east of the Jordan. For seven years the two tiny kingdoms existed side by side (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.2-11">2 Sm 2:2-11</a>). But after the Israelite king and his army commander were assassinated, David became ruler of a united Hebrew kingdom.</p>
<p>Not long after the beginning of his reign (1010–970 <span class="era">BC</span>) David completely defeated and subjugated the Philistines. Soon thereafter he captured Jerusalem, making it the capital of the united kingdom. During succeeding years, David built up an empire (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.10">2 Sm 8:10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.1-19.19">1 Chr 18–19</a>), conquering Moab, Edom, Damascus, Zobah, and Ammon, so he controlled territory from the Gulf of Aqaba (a branch of the Red Sea) and the Sinai in the south almost to the Euphrates in the north. Moreover, he established good relations, if not an alliance, with Tyre. The establishment of David’s empire was possible because of a power vacuum in the Middle East. The Egyptians, Mycenaeans, Hittites, and Assyrians were either decadent or removed from the stage of history. The Phoenicians, a peaceful commercial people, were also free to expand their trade, and they were happy to sell cedar to David for his palace and the temple.</p>
<p>Without doubt, David was Israel’s greatest king. Jerusalem came to be known as the city of David. When the king wanted to build the temple as God’s house, God replied that his son should do it instead. But God would in a very real sense build David’s house; he made a covenant with David, promising him that his house (dynasty, kingdom, throne) would be established forever (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.1-29">2 Sm 7</a>). Christ, the infinite One who came from the line of David, alone was capable of fulfilling this divine promise (see <a href="?bref=Luke.1.31-33">Lk 1:31-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.29-36">Acts 2:29-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.32-39">13:32-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.15.14-17">15:14-17</a>).</p>
<p>Like other Oriental monarchs, David fell into the practice of keeping a harem. Scripture names 8 wives and 21 children and refers to other wives and concubines. Such a situation opened the door to family rivalries and questions about succession to the throne. Two sons, Absalom and Adonijah, made a try for the throne, but both efforts were squelched. Solomon, son of David’s favorite wife, Bathsheba, became the next king.</p>
<p>Solomon (970–930 <span class="era">BC</span>) was a man of peace and a builder of palaces, cities, fortifications, and the temple. He fortified cities all over his realm and outfitted cities for his chariot corps and cavalry units. With the help of the Phoenicians, he built a seaport and kept a fleet at Ezion-geber, near modern Eilat on the Gulf of Aqaba. He greatly enlarged Jerusalem by enclosing the temple area to the north of David’s city and the southwestern hill now known as Zion. His best-known project was the temple, which took seven years to build. Twice the size of the tabernacle, it was built on the same basic plan; it measured 90 feet (27.4 meters) long and 30 feet (9.1 meters) wide and had magnificent appointments. But he also constructed a palace complex that took 13 years to complete. This included an armory, a throne room, the king’s private residence, and a house for the daughter of pharaoh.</p>
<p>Apparently much influenced by the spiritual testimony of David and desiring God’s blessing on his rule, Solomon made a great sacrifice to God at Gibeon near the beginning of his reign. God met him there and offered to grant whatever he might request. Solomon asked for understanding and wisdom to govern God’s people (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.3.9">1 Kgs 3:9</a>). His God-given wisdom is apparent in many administrative decisions and official policies and building plans.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, Solomon did not show such wisdom in maintaining a harem of 700 wives and 300 concubines or in excessive expenditures that left the state in serious financial straits. He even erected places of worship for his foreign wives, thus subsidizing their idolatries and incurring the wrath of God. In fact, foreign wives and their idolatry proved to be his downfall; before Solomon died, God informed him that for this reason he would divide the kingdom at his death and give most of it to someone other than Solomon’s son. But for David’s sake, God would keep Judah and Jerusalem in the hands of the Davidic line (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.9-13">1 Kgs 11:9-13</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheDividedKingdom">The Divided Kingdom</p>
<p class="fl">After the death of Solomon, the Near East was destined to become a very different place. Israel was no longer in a power vacuum. The Assyrian Empire rose in Mesopotamia, to be followed by the Neo-Babylonian and the Medo-Persian Empires in turn. Egypt was temporarily powerful in the south, but it would later come under control of Assyria and Medo-Persia. These empires exerted great pressure on Israel and dominated one or both of the two Hebrew kingdoms.</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="TheDividedKingdom"/>
<p>When Solomon died, his son Rehoboam took the throne and was forced to deal with a rising tide of resentment over the high taxes and economic stagnation of Solomon’s last years. When Rehoboam refused to give relief, all the northern tribes broke away and formed the northern kingdom, Israel, under the leadership of Jeroboam. The southern kingdom, Judah, was left with only the territory of Judah and Benjamin. A total of 20 kings ruled in each of the separate kingdoms. While the north had several dynasties and the reigns of kings were generally short, in the south the dynasty of David continued to rule and the reigns were longer.</p>
<p class="h3">The Northern Kingdom</p>
<p class="fl">The northern kingdom lasted from the division in 930 <span class="era">BC</span> until its conquest by Assyria in 722. Jeroboam, fearing that he would lose the loyalty of the people if they continued to go to Jerusalem to worship, set up a new religion of his own. Instituting calf worship, he built shrines at Dan in the north and Bethel in the south. This idolatry drew the condemnation of God and fulfilled the prediction that Jeroboam’s line would be wiped out. All his successors are said to have followed in his idolatrous steps. Israel found itself at war during much of its history—with Judah, Syria, or Assyria. Jeroboam established his capital first at Shechem and later at Tirzah.</p>
<p>Four other kings of the north require special comment: Omri, Ahab, Jehu, and Jeroboam II. Omri (885–874 <span class="era">BC</span>) must have been an impressive ruler. Generations later, Assyrians still spoke of Israel as the land of Omri. After he had established himself on the throne, he located the permanent capital of the kingdom at Samaria and began the palace complex there. Early in his reign he was successful in conquering Moab, and later he reestablished the good relations with Tyre that existed in the days of David and Solomon. Apparently he established a full alliance and cemented it with the marriage of his son Ahab to Jezebel, a princess of Tyre.</p>
<p>Ahab (874–853 <span class="era">BC</span>) was one of the most significant of Israel’s kings. He and his wife, Jezebel, promoted the vile idolatry of Baal worship with its religious prostitution, arousing the powerful opposition of the prophet Elijah. Ahab was a formidable military man, defeating the Syrians in major campaigns and participating in a coalition that fought the Assyrians to a virtual standstill. He also built extensively at Samaria, Hazor, Megiddo, and other towns, as excavations show.</p>
<p>Jehu (841–814 <span class="era">BC</span>) was God’s agent for punishing the house of Omri and destroying Baal worship in Israel. He did eradicate Baal worship and liquidated literally scores of relatives and court officials of Ahab. But he was so ruthless that he killed off the people who knew how to run the government; subsequently, it did not work well. Jehu also was forced to become a vassal to Assyria.</p>
<p>Jeroboam II ruled during most of the first half of the eighth century (793–753 <span class="era">BC</span>) and brought the kingdom to its greatest extent and prosperity. He, with his contemporary Uzziah in the south, ruled most of the land David had once controlled. This was possible because the Assyrians were in a period of decline during most of the first half of the century.</p>
<p>Prophets who were active during the history of the northern kingdom include the nonwriting prophets Elijah and Elisha and the writing prophets Jonah, Amos, and Hosea.</p>
<p class="h3">The Southern Kingdom</p>
<p class="fl">The history of the southern kingdom of Judah was quite different from that of the northern kingdom. The temple was there and so were large numbers of Levites, many of whom came south after the division of the kingdom to protest the idolatry of the north. In addition to this spiritual strength, there was greater political stability and unity, promoted by the fact that only two tribes—Judah and Benjamin—shared power, and all the kings were of the Davidic dynasty. Moreover, eight of the kings were good monarchs. There were also periodic religious revivals. God granted the southern kingdom about 100 more years of existence than the north. But Judah, too, fell into idolatry and went into captivity for her sins.</p>
<p>Rehoboam, the first king in the south, is especially remembered because he refused to listen to wise counsel about fiscal matters and perpetrated the division of the kingdom. He is also remembered for his religious policies. After a good beginning, he allowed apostasy to get out of control and brought the judgment of God in the form of an invasion in his fifth year (926 <span class="era">BC</span>) by Shishak I of Egypt, resulting in extensive plunder and payment of tribute. Thereafter, he launched an extensive program to fortify the realm. Shishak’s invasion did have the effect of producing a partial and temporary spiritual reform, but the general trend of Rehoboam’s reign was downward.</p>
<p>Conditions during the reign of his son, Abijam, were worse, but Asa (910–869 <span class="era">BC</span>) initiated a religious reform that was effective for most of his reign. When threatened by the northern kingdom during his latter years, however, Asa turned to Syria for help instead of to God, and he seems to have defied the prophets of God to his dying day.</p>
<p>Asa’s son Jehoshaphat (872–848 <span class="era">BC</span>) was apparently influenced by his father’s early religious devotion, and his reign was characterized by faithfulness, winning the favor of God. However, he seems to have made a full alliance with Ahab of Israel, which resulted in the marriage of his son Jehoram to Ahab’s daughter Athaliah. This alliance involved Jehoshaphat in almost ruinous joint ventures with Ahab, and later with two of his sons when they became kings of Israel. It also opened the door for the introduction of Baal worship into Judah when Jehoram came to the throne in the southern kingdom. For his sin Jehoram (853–841 <span class="era">BC</span>) suffered internal revolt, invasion, and death from a horrible disease.</p>
<p>After his death, his last remaining son, Ahaziah, ruled less than a year, following the wicked ways of his father. When Ahaziah died in battle, the queen mother, Athaliah, decided to seize the throne for herself and to secure her power by killing off all those in line to the throne. But she missed Ahaziah’s infant son Joash, who was kept hidden in the temple for six years.</p>
<p>When Joash was seven, Jehoiada the high priest arranged his coronation and also the execution of the murderous and idolatrous Athaliah. During his early years when Joash was influenced by good counsel, he did well. But after the middle of his reign (835–796 <span class="era">BC</span>), he began to listen to the princes who wanted to restore idolatry, and conditions deteriorated. Military reversals brought on economic decline and ultimately the king’s assassination.</p>
<p>His son Amaziah (796–767 <span class="era">BC</span>) started well with victory over Edom and faithfulness to God. But he, too, fell into idolatry and was totally defeated by the northern kingdom, being held prisoner there. At that point his son Uzziah took over (c. 792 <span class="era">BC</span>) and began a long and generally successful reign. During the several decades that followed, Assyria was in decline, and Uzziah and his contemporary in the north, Jeroboam II, were able to expand Hebrew holdings so that between them they controlled most of the territory Solomon had ruled.</p>
<p>Uzziah (792–740 <span class="era">BC</span>) was able to restore the power of Judah rather quickly after his father’s defeat by Israel. Then he subjugated the Philistines in the southwest and the Ammonites across the Jordan; he strengthened his hold on the Edomites. All during his reign economic conditions improved. But at the height of his power Uzziah foolishly violated the high priest’s prerogatives and offered sacrifice in the temple. For this he was smitten with leprosy; his son Jotham was co-regent during the years 750–740 <span class="era">BC</span>, going on to rule alone for about five more years. Meanwhile, Assyrian power became resurgent.</p>
<p>By and large, Jotham merely carried on the policies of Uzziah. But the administration of his son Ahaz (735–715 <span class="era">BC</span>) was very much affected by the Assyrian threat. Israel and Syria wanted him to join in war against Assyria, but he refused, being pro-Assyrian in sympathy. When Israel and Syria invaded Judah, King Ahaz sent tribute to Assyria and became her vassal in return for protection. This rash course of action was vainly opposed by Isaiah, who was prophet at court (c. 740–700 <span class="era">BC</span>). Contemporaneously, the prophet Micah ministered to the common people of Judah. The pro-Assyrian policy of Ahaz was accompanied by a renewed sympathy for idolatry, and this brought the judgment of God in the form of invasion by Edomites and Philistines and trouble with Assyria. In fact, during this period, Assyria had annexed the northern kingdom (722 <span class="era">BC</span>) and removed many of her people into captivity.</p>
<p>The next king of Judah, Hezekiah (715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>), was greatly sobered by the fall of Israel because of her sins, and he determined to launch a reform in his realm. He was anti-Assyrian too, but he did not dare to discontinue tribute payments and strike for independence until after Sennacherib came to the throne in Nineveh in 705 <span class="era">BC</span>. At first Sennacherib was too preoccupied to attend to Judah, but finally in 701 he invaded. Despite tremendous initial success, he was stopped by a divinely sent plague (<a href="?bref=Isa.36.1-39.8">Is 36–39</a>). Isaiah stood by the king to reassure and sustain him during this emergency.</p>
<p>Hezekiah’s son Manasseh (697–642 <span class="era">BC</span>) ruled longer than any other king of Israel or Judah. Unfortunately, he turned his back on his father’s example and caused the people to fall into gross idolatry (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.9">2 Kgs 21:9</a>). Carried away captive by the Assyrians late in his reign, he repented of his evil and God restored him to his throne; thereafter, he led some reforms. But the land was too steeped in iniquity to be rescued. His son Amon (642–640 <span class="era">BC</span>) reverted to the idolatry he knew in his youth.</p>
<p>The situation was different with Josiah (640–609 <span class="era">BC</span>), however. Throughout his reign he dedicated himself to reform. He sought to root out idolatry and to restore the temple and its worship. In 622 <span class="era">BC</span> the Book of the Law was found during repair of the temple, and its demands—which had been forgotten—made a great impression on king and people alike. It is certain that Jeremiah and Zephaniah ministered during Josiah’s reign, as did Nahum and Habakkuk (in all probability).</p>
<p>International conditions were now changing rapidly. Assyria was declining, and Nineveh fell to Babylon and the Medes in 612 <span class="era">BC</span>. Three years later Pharaoh Neco of Egypt marched north to aid his Assyrian ally. When Josiah tried to stop him, he was killed in battle.</p>
<p>From this point everything was downhill for Judah. None of the rest of the kings was devout, and political power and economic health rapidly declined. The people put one of Josiah’s sons, Jehoahaz, on the throne. He lasted three months. Pharaoh Neco replaced him with Jehoiakim (609–598 <span class="era">BC</span>), another son of Josiah. In 605 Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon defeated Neco, invaded Judah, and took tribute and hostages from Jehoiakim, including Daniel and his friends (<a href="?bref=Dan.1.1">Dn 1:1</a>). Jehoiakim revolted in 600 <span class="era">BC</span>, but Nebuchadnezzar did not come to deal with him personally until 597 <span class="era">BC</span>. He died before the Babylonians arrived, and his son Jehoiachin came to the throne in 598 <span class="era">BC</span> to rule for only three months before the Babylonians carried him away into exile. Ezekiel was among the many captives taken on that occasion.</p>
<p>The Babylonians then put Zedekiah, youngest son of Josiah, on the throne in 597 <span class="era">BC</span>. When he rebelled, Nebuchadnezzar laid siege to Jerusalem and took the city (587 <span class="era">BC</span>), destroying it and the temple and carrying off large numbers of people. The judgment of God had finally fallen on the Jews for their idolatrous ways.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheRestoration">The Restoration</p>
<p class="fl">In judgment God remembered mercy. This is evident in individual lives, when faithful ones like Daniel, Esther, or Nehemiah rose to a position of importance in political life, or as numerous other persons became prosperous in the foreign environment. It is evident on the community level as God moved to protect Hebrew enclaves scattered abroad and to restore an organized society in Palestine.</p>
<p>Among the exiles, Judaism as a way of life separated from its own political system or cultic center and began to emerge. Jews finally turned their backs on idolatry. And without a temple, priesthood, king, or land, they turned to the divine Scriptures as their rallying point and the foundation of their community. During this period they developed the synagogue as a place for fellowship, prayer, and study.</p>
<p>God’s restoration of an organized community to Palestine involved particularly the fortunes of his “anointed” Cyrus (<a href="?bref=Isa.44.28">Is 44:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.45.1">45:1</a>). Cyrus was a Persian prince who in 559 <span class="era">BC</span> revolted against the dominant dynasty controlling the Median Empire. After consolidating his hold on the throne, he proceeded to conquer Asia Minor and the Chaldean or Neo-Babylonian Empire. As a humane man and a wise administrator, he permitted the captive peoples to return to their homes and rebuild their communities. Cyrus’s decree to the Jews appears in <a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1-11">Ezra 1</a> and dates probably to 538 <span class="era">BC</span>. A total of almost 50,000 went back to Judah as a result of this edict (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.64-65">Ezr 2:64-65</a>).</p>
<p>Under the stresses and strains of reestablishment, the people built their houses but got no further than laying the foundation of a new temple. Finally, the prophets Haggai and Zechariah stirred the people to build the house of God (<a href="?bref=Ezra.5.1">Ezr 5:1</a>). They began in the second year of Darius I, the Great (520 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1">Hg 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.1.1">Zec 1:1</a>), and completed the work in his sixth year (515 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.6.15">Ezr 6:15</a>).</p>
<p>During the reign of Darius’s son Xerxes (486–465 <span class="era">BC</span>), a plot was hatched to exterminate all the Jews in the Persian Empire, which at that time controlled the lands where Jews lived. Fortunately, Xerxes (Ahasuerus in the book of Esther), in his third year (483 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Esth.1.3">Est 1:3</a>), went searching for a new queen and chose Esther, who managed to preserve her people.</p>
<p>Xerxes’ son Artaxerxes I (465–424 <span class="era">BC</span>) also figured significantly in Jewish history. In his seventh year (458 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.7">Ezr 7:7</a>), under the leadership of Ezra, a second contingent of Jews returned to Jerusalem. And in Artaxerxes’ 20th year (445 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Neh.2.1">Neh 2:1</a>), Nehemiah went to Jerusalem to supervise the rebuilding of the walls of the city. Malachi probably wrote his prophecy to the Jews in Jerusalem during the latter part of Artaxerxes’ reign.</p>
<p>After the fall of Samaria and the captivity of Judah, the Hebrews remaining in the land intermarried with various pagan groups in the area. Their offspring became the Samaritans, a religious and racial admixture. These people had moved into the vacuum left by the destruction of Judah, and naturally they looked with disfavor on an intrusion of Babylonian Jews into an area they had come to call their own. They did all they could to frustrate the efforts of Nehemiah to rebuild the walls. It took all the courage, tact, energy, and persuasiveness Ezra and Nehemiah could muster to prevent the returning Jews from intermarrying with racially mixed people of the land. Such intermarriage would have meant the ultimate absorption and destruction of the Jewish people.</p>
<p>A Samaritan temple was later built on Mt Gerizim (probably during the fifth century <span class="era">BC</span>), and it became the center of the Samaritan worship. The hostility between Samaritans and Jews continued on into the NT period (<a href="?bref=John.4.1-54">Jn 4</a>) and exists to the present.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheIntertestamentalPeriod">The Intertestamental Period</p>
<p class="fl">Alexander the Great conquered the Persian Empire with lightning speed. When the people of Jerusalem threw open their gates in 332 <span class="era">BC</span> and capitulated without a fight, Alexander treated them well. After his death in 323 <span class="era">BC</span>, Palestine passed back and forth among his successors until Ptolemy I of Egypt managed to establish control in 301 <span class="era">BC</span>. Thereafter the area remained in Egyptian hands until 198 <span class="era">BC</span>. The Ptolemies were tolerant and granted the Jews considerable autonomy, allowing them to develop their unique culture undisturbed as long as they paid their taxes and remained submissive. Many Jews settled in Alexandria and gradually forgot their Hebrew in the Hellenistic environment. As a result, a translation of the OT into Greek (the Septuagint) was produced there. While the Ptolemies did not force Hellenism on the Jews of either Alexandria or Palestine, many were influenced by Hellenistic ideas.</p>
<p>When Ptolemy V came to the throne as a minor in 203 <span class="era">BC</span>, Antiochus III of Syria took advantage of the weakened Egypt and conquered Palestine (198 <span class="era">BC</span>). Apparently the Jews hoped to gain something from the change and welcomed the Syrians. But their hope was ill-founded. Antiochus III suffered disastrous defeat at the hands of Rome at Magnesia in 190 <span class="era">BC</span>. Syria not only lost much territory but also was forced to pay a huge indemnity. Thereafter, the Jews suffered under great financial burdens, along with other peoples of the empire. The next Syrian king, Antiochus IV Epiphanes (175–164 <span class="era">BC</span>), decided to launch an effort to achieve greater internal strength and unity within the empire by forcing, among other things, a greater acceptance of Greek culture and the cult of the divine ruler. Naturally this idolatrous requirement weighed heavily on the monotheistic Jews and incited revolution.</p>
<p>But this does not completely explain the Maccabean revolt against Syria. In 168 <span class="era">BC</span> armed conflict broke out between Jewish factions in Jerusalem. Antiochus IV chose to interpret this as open rebellion and sent an army against the city. His forces demolished part of the city wall and many houses. After this Antiochus decided to suppress Judaism completely, and he dedicated the temple to Zeus and sacrificed swine on the altar. Circumcision, Sabbath observance, and other religious festivals were no longer permitted, and public worship of heathen gods became compulsory.</p>
<p>Some Jews capitulated to Antiochus’s orders or only resisted passively, but a few decided to resist openly. Chief among them were Mattathias and his five sons. After the early death of Mattathias, his son Judas Maccabeus led his forces to victory over the Syrians, regaining the right to restore Jewish worship. The rededication of the temple on December 25, 164 <span class="era">BC</span>, inaugurated the Festival of Hanukkah (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.4.36-59">1 Macc 4:36-59</a>). Subsequently, Jonathan and Simon (other sons of Mattathias) continued the struggle until independence was gained in 142 <span class="era">BC</span>; this was possible in large part because they saw how to take advantage of the increasing weakness of Syrian rulers and the competition for the royal office.</p>
<p>Simon ruled the Jewish state until his assassination in 134 <span class="era">BC</span>, when his son John Hyrcanus (134–104 <span class="era">BC</span>) took over. John Hyrcanus fought successfully in the east, north, and south, gaining land in Transjordan, capturing Shechem and the Samaritan temple on Mt Gerizim, and subjugating the Idumeans in the south, forcing them to adopt Judaism. His son Aristobulus ruled for only about a year (104–103 <span class="era">BC</span>), but he added a portion of Galilee to the kingdom. When he died, his widow married his brother Alexander Janneus (103–76 <span class="era">BC</span>). Janneus carried on almost incessant military action during his reign, and by the time of his death had almost recovered the kingdom of Solomon.</p>
<p>When Janneus died, Alexandra, widow of two kings, took the throne (76–67 <span class="era">BC</span>) and her eldest son, Hyrcanus II, became high priest. Her reign was peaceful and prosperous, but when she died, her sons fell to squabbling. Their appeals to Pompey, who was campaigning in the eastern Mediterranean area, were responsible for Roman interference in the region and conquest of Palestine in 63 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheRomanPeriod">The Roman Period</p>
<p class="fl">After the Romans took over Palestine, Hyrcanus II was confirmed as high priest and was also appointed as ethnarch or political ruler (63–40 <span class="era">BC</span>). But Antipater, father of Herod the Great, was the real power behind the throne, and during many of those years Hyrcanus was virtually unable to function because of the confusion of the Roman civil wars. Antipater was loyal to Rome and saw that Roman policies were carried out; he won Julius Caesar’s favor toward Jews of both Palestine and in the Dispersion.</p>
<p>With the support of Mark Antony, Herod managed to get himself appointed king of Judea by the Roman senate in 40 <span class="era">BC</span>. But a Parthian invasion of Syria and Jewish hatred for the Romans made it possible for Antigonus II, last king of the Maccabean family, to rule for three years (40–37 <span class="era">BC</span>). Finally, Herod ascended his throne in 37 and ruled until 4 <span class="era">BC</span>. As an allied king, Herod proved to be an excellent ruler from the Roman point of view and earned the title of “Great.” He brought some order to regions east of the Jordan and made possible organization of the Roman province of Arabia. He also furthered the cultural plans of Augustus for development of a Greco-Roman civilization throughout the whole empire.</p>
<p>Herod admired Greek culture and contributed to building projects in Rhodes, Antioch, Damascus, Athens, and elsewhere outside Palestine. Within Palestine he rebuilt Samaria and named it Sebaste in honor of Augustus (<span class="greek">Sebastos</span> is Greek for “Augustus”) and also constructed the great port of Caesarea. Probably about as large as Manhattan Island, it became the capital of Roman Palestine. Among his many other building projects, remodeling the temple in Jerusalem was the most famous. Begun in 20 <span class="era">BC</span>, it was not completed until just a few years before its destruction in <span class="era">AD</span> 70.</p>
<p>The material splendor of Herod’s reign did not win the affection or support of the Jews, however. Nor did he achieve peace and harmony in his family, among whom there were periodic eruptions of treason, unfaithfulness, and murder. He worried about any threat to his rule and cracked down hard to destroy such threats, as is evident from his slaughter of the infants in Bethlehem after the birth of Christ.</p>
<p>Ultimately, Herod controlled Idumea, Judea, Samaria, Galilee, Perea, and the area northeast of the Sea of Galilee. By his last will, his son Archelaus was to rule Idumea, Judea, and Samaria; Antipas, Galilee and Perea; and Philip, the region northeast of the Sea of Galilee. Archelaus was deposed in <span class="era">AD</span> 6, and his territory became a Roman province (<span class="era">AD</span> 6–41) to be ruled by direct appointees of Rome. The best-known of these was Pontius Pilate (<span class="era">AD</span> 26–36), who ordered the crucifixion of Jesus. Antipas was more successful and built a new capital at Tiberias, but he ran afoul of the emperor’s good pleasure in <span class="era">AD</span> 39 and was deposed. Philip was the most effective of the three and ruled until his death in <span class="era">AD</span> 34. Philip’s lands were later given to Herod Agrippa I in <span class="era">AD</span> 37; the holdings of Antipas were then added in <span class="era">AD</span> 39; and in 41 Agrippa also received Samaria, Judea, and Idumea.</p>
<p>Herod Agrippa I (<span class="era">AD</span> 37–44) was the heir of the Maccabees (through his grandmother Mariamne, first wife of Herod the Great), and for this reason had the support of patriotic Jews and of the Pharisees for his observance of divine ordinances. But when he built a new north wall for Jerusalem and dabbled in foreign affairs, he aroused the suspicions of the Romans; when he died in <span class="era">AD</span> 44, they turned the kingdom into a Roman province.</p>
<p>As is clear from the Gospels, several sects had arisen in Palestine by Roman times and were active during the first century. The Zealots opposed Roman rule and advocated armed rebellion. Herodians supported the Herodian family and Roman power. The Pharisees were fanatically devoted to the law and were supernaturalists in theological orientation. They were somewhat content to support Rome if given religious freedom, and they dominated the synagogues of the land. The Sadducees were antisupernaturalists, tended to collaborate with the ruling regime, and were dominant in the temple. Generally speaking, the literature of the intertestamental period and the popular mentality of the time tended to view the Messiah as a political deliverer who would free his people from foreign domination and set up a new independent kingdom.</p>
<p>Roman prefects ruled Palestine from <span class="era">AD</span> 44–66. They had a knack for offending the religious scruples of the Jews and alienating them in other ways. With Felix (<span class="era">AD</span> 52–60) there began a constant tension between Jews and Romans that led to the first Jewish revolt (<span class="era">AD</span> 66–70). While Paul was imprisoned in Caesarea (<a href="?bref=Acts.23.23-24.27">Acts 23:23–24:27</a>) about <span class="era">AD</span> 58–60, riots broke out there between Jews and Gentiles. Festus (<span class="era">AD</span> 60–62; <a href="?bref=Acts.25.1-27">Acts 25</a>) was an able administrator, but the situation was almost out of hand. After he died in office, there was virtual anarchy until his successor, Albinus, arrived (<span class="era">AD</span> 62–64). Totally incompetent and dishonest, Albinus was recalled in 64 and replaced by Florus (<span class="era">AD</span> 64–66). Florus was even worse, resorting to open robbery and bribery until there was no safety or justice in the land. Finally, the Jews could take no more.</p>
<p>The spark that ignited the fires of rebellion was an anti-Semitic act by the Hellenistic population of Caesarea in <span class="era">AD</span> 66. Soon riots spread to numerous cities, and Roman garrisons were massacred in several places. But the Jews were not united, and in Jerusalem armed bands of Jews fought with each other for mastery. Vespasian was chosen to command the Roman army of some 60,000 to deal with the insurrection. He had subjugated most of Palestine by the time he was elevated to the imperial chair in <span class="era">AD</span> 69 (after the death of Nero), and he left his son Titus in charge of completing the operations. In August of <span class="era">AD</span> 70 the walls of Jerusalem were breached, many of the people butchered, and the city and the temple leveled. Masada held out until <span class="era">AD</span> 73. Palestine had been flattened by Roman might. Loss of life and property had been incalculable and indescribable.</p>
<p>On two more occasions the Jews were destined to fight disastrously against the Romans. Under Trajan’s rule a rebellion of Jews broke out in Cyrenaica in <span class="era">AD</span> 115 and spread rapidly to Cyprus, Egypt, Palestine, and Mesopotamia. In the beginning it was an outgrowth of agitation between the Jews and their Hellenistic neighbors, but it developed into a challenge to Roman authority. This was particularly true after the successes of Parthia on Rome’s eastern frontier when there seemed to be some hope of success in throwing off the Roman yoke. Wherever Jews got the upper hand, they perpetrated massacres, and the non-Semitic population retaliated in kind. Trajan ruthlessly suppressed the rebels and restored order everywhere except Egypt; his successor, Hadrian, was left to accomplish that.</p>
<p>But Hadrian faced a new rebellion of his own, brought on by his law forbidding circumcision (which he considered to be inhumane) and his decision in <span class="era">AD</span> 130 to rebuild Jerusalem as Aelia Capitolina and erect a temple to Jupiter on the site of the temple of Yahweh. The latter would not only profane the temple site but also would preclude any rebuilding of the Jewish temple.</p>
<p>Leader of this second Jewish revolt was Simeon, prince of Israel, called Bar-Kochba (“Son of the Star”). Both sides fought with such great ferocity for over three years (<span class="era">AD</span> 132–135) that the population of Judea was almost exterminated. Jerusalem was rebuilt as a Roman colony, and Jews were forbidden to enter on pain of death. Even as late as the fourth century they were permitted to enter only once a year, on the anniversary of the destruction of the temple by Nebuchadnezzar. After the Bar-Kochba revolt, Judaism retreated increasingly within the citadel of the written and oral law, thus separating itself from the Gentiles.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Abraham_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Abraham</a>; <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>; <a href="?item=ConquestandAllotmentoftheLand_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Conquest and Allotment of the Land</a>; <a href="?item=David_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">David</a>; <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=Exodusthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Exodus, The</a>; <a href="?item=FirstJewishRevolt_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">First Jewish Revolt</a>; <a href="?item=Jew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jew</a>; <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>; <a href="?item=Moses_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Moses</a>; <a href="?item=PatriarchsPeriodofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Patriarchs, Period of the</a>; <a href="?item=Saul_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Saul #2</a>; <a href="?item=SolomonPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Solomon</a>; <a href="?item=PostexilicPeriod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Postexilic Period</a>; <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>