<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="IssacharPerson">
  <title>Issachar (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ISSACHAR (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. Jacob’s ninth son, the fifth by his wife Leah (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.17-18">Gn 30:17-18</a>); his name perhaps means “reward.” Jacob, in his final message to his 12 sons says, “Issachar is a strong donkey, lying down between the sheepfolds” (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.14">49:14</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>); the picture suggested is a loaded donkey who refuses to move his burden, a lazy man who is unwilling to do his share of the work. Little is known about Issachar except what he did along with the other sons of Israel. He had four sons (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.13">46:13</a>), who headed clans in the tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.7.1-5">1 Chr 7:1-5</a>). His family went with Jacob to Egypt, where they died (although Issachar’s remains were subsequently moved to Shechem with the other 12 patriarchs—<a href="?bref=Acts.7.16">Acts 7:16</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The descendants of Issachar numbered 54,400 at the first census (<a href="?bref=Num.1.29">Nm 1:29</a>), increased to 64,300 at the second (<a href="?bref=Num.26.25">26:25</a>), and to 87,000 during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.7.5">1 Chr 7:5</a>). Issachar was the main tribe involved in the fighting led by Deborah, herself a member of the tribe (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.15">Jgs 5:15</a>). During the time of David, there were men of the tribe of Issachar who had understanding of what Israel ought to do in warfare (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.32">1 Chr 12:32</a>). These men supported David as king to replace Saul.</p>
<p class="list-text">Issachar was assigned the fourth lot of land after the ark was taken to Shiloh (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.17">Jos 19:17</a>). This included the cities of Jezreel, Shunem, and En-gannim, and it lay between the mountains of Gilboa and Tabor. Their allotment was bordered on the south and west by the tribe of Manasseh, on the north by Zebulun and Naphtali, and on the east by the river Jordan. This territory was largely a fertile plain and was often threatened by the Canaanites nearby as well as by foreign invaders.</p>
<p class="list">2. Obed-edom’s son, who was a Levite gatekeeper during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.26.5">1 Chr 26:5</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>