<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Magic">
  <title>Magic</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MAGIC</p>
<p class="fl">Attempt to influence or control people or events through supernatural forces. These forces are called upon by means of ceremonies, the recitation of spells, charms, incantations, and other forms of ritual.</p>
<p>There are a number of terms used in the Bible that might fall into the broad category of magic. Several of the words are mentioned in <a href="?bref=Deut.18.9-14">Deuteronomy 18:9-14</a>. The use of magical and occult practices by Israel is not permitted. The people of God are instructed to avoid magical practices because God provides them with his personal revelation through his prophets. Human magical practices lead to either false hope or false fear and therefore lead away from the truth of God. Yet while magical practices cannot measure up to the accuracy of God’s prophet, the Bible does leave open the possibility that there may be supernatural reality behind some magical practices.</p>
<p>Magicians are prominent in the OT book of Exodus, where the magicians of Egypt contend with Moses. The text does not discount the success of the magicians as mere trickery, for they were at least partially successful at first (chs <a href="?bref=Exod.7.1-8.32">7–8</a>). But their failures begin to become clear in chapter <a href="?bref=Exod.8.1-32">8</a> and continue through chapter <a href="?bref=Exod.9.1-35">9</a>. The Bible does not flatly deny that there may be certain evil supernatural power at work in the person of the magician. What the Bible does make clear is that this power is not in accord with, nor can it defeat, the will of God.</p>
<p>The NT addresses the issue of magic in the book of Acts. When Philip went to Samaria, he encountered Simon the magician. Simon had drawn a great deal of attention to himself by amazing the people with his magic (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.11">Acts 8:11</a>). Philip’s message was believed and people began to be drawn to him. Simon saw the wonders that Philip was able to perform and thought that these powers were received through the ritual of the laying on of hands. Philip made clear that the wonders of his work could not be purchased but came through the gracious gift of God to the penitent.</p>
<p>Another important passage is found in <a href="?bref=Acts.19.11-20">Acts 19:11-20</a>. Certain Jewish exorcists thought they could magically use the name of Jesus in their work. The result was violent reaction: the man in whom resided the evil spirit leaped on them, mastered all of them, and overpowered them, so that they fled out of that house naked and wounded. This passage shows that the power responsible for the apostolic miracles was based upon the personal relationship of the apostle with the Lord Jesus Christ. The result of the above incident is also important; it led the people of Ephesus to make a clear decision between the word of the Lord and their magical practices. Several who practiced magic arts brought their books together and burned them in the presence of everyone. This dramatic display of the power of God and the need for clear loyalty to him led to further expansion of the gospel.</p>
<p>The biblical stand against magic is stated strongly in the last book of the Bible, where sorcerers are condemned to the lake of fire (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.8">Rv 21:8</a>). The biblical view is consistent in its opposition to magic. The Bible does not preclude the possibility that Satan can use magic for evil purposes, and magical practices are condemned because they may lead to false hope or false fear and away from loyalty to God’s Word.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Amulet_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Amulet</a>; <a href="?item=CanaaniteDeitiesandReligion_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Canaanite Deities and Religion</a>; <a href="?item=Frontlet_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Frontlet</a>; <a href="?item=Omen_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Omen</a>; <a href="?item=Soothsayer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Soothsayer</a>; <a href="?item=Sorcery_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sorcery</a>; <a href="?item=Psychics_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Psychics</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>