<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Manna">
  <title>Manna</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MANNA</p>
<p class="fl">Miraculous food the Lord provided for the Israelites in the desert. It originally appeared in the form of thin flakes, like frost on the ground, around the Israelite camp (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.14-15">Ex 16:14-15</a>). It is compared elsewhere with coriander seed and bdellium, or resin (<a href="?bref=Num.11.7">Nm 11:7</a>). Its taste is said to have been like that of honey or of fresh oil (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.31">Ex 16:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.11.8">Nm 11:8</a>). Since the experience of taste and color is somewhat subjective, these descriptions do not necessarily conflict. The word comes from the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">man</span><span class="ital">,</span> which means, “what?” When the Israelites saw the manna, they asked, “What is it?” (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.15">Ex 16:15</a>).</p>
<p>Attempts have been made to link manna with substances discovered by modern travelers in Sinai and Arabia. In early summer (June–July) the tamarisk tree in these regions exudes a sweet-tasting liquid, produced as the result of the activity of a tiny insect. This liquid falls to the ground, where it forms small grains that disappear when the sun gets hot. Reference also has been made to an edible lichen that in parts of southwest Asia is used instead of grain in years of famine. But the regularity, periodicity, and abundance of the manna cannot be explained on any but miraculous grounds. The Israelites were to gather it for one day at a time. Anything collected above that measure was subject to spoiling (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.20">16:20</a>). Only the Sabbath day was an exception to that rule. Manna was no longer provided after Israel entered Canaan (<a href="?bref=Josh.5.12">Jos 5:12</a>). When Israel craved other food besides manna, the people were punished with an excess of quail (<a href="?bref=Num.11.4-6,18-20">Nm 11:4-6, 18-20</a>). In poetic literature it was called “the grain of heaven” (<a href="?bref=Ps.78.24">Ps 78:24</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.105.40">105:40</a>), and “the bread of angels” (<a href="?bref=Ps.78.25">78:25</a>). Jesus pointed to himself as the true manna, the bread from heaven, which, when eaten, would nourish man unto life everlasting (cf. <a href="?bref=John.6.25-59">Jn 6:25-59</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>