<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ManNatural">
  <title>Man*, Natural</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MAN*, Natural</p>
<p class="fl">Expression occurring in <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.14">1 Corinthians 2:14</a> (<span class="sc">rsv</span> mg). The adjective translated there by “natural” is also found in <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.44">1 Corinthians 15:44</a> (twice), 46; <a href="?bref=Jas.3.15">James 3:15</a>; and <a href="?bref=Jude.1.19">Jude 1:19</a>. This adjective is related to the Greek noun usually translated “soul.” Its meaning, however, is primarily determined by its various contexts, particularly in 1 Corinthians, where all four occurrences are contrasted pointedly with “spiritual,” an adjective occurring frequently in the NT, mostly in Paul’s writings. In almost every instance it refers to the work of the Holy Spirit. Applied to things, “spiritual” means derived from, or produced by, the Holy Spirit (the law—<a href="?bref=Rom.7.14">Rom 7:14</a>; gifts—<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.1">1 Cor 12:1</a>; blessings—<a href="?bref=Eph.1.3">Eph 1:3</a>; sacrifices—<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.5">1 Pt 2:5</a>). When it is applied to persons, it means indwelt, motivated, and directed by the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.15">1 Cor 2:15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.37">14:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.6.1">Gal 6:1</a>). “Natural,” then, when contrasted with “spiritual,” generally describes what is devoid of or in opposition to the Holy Spirit and his work. In <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.14-15">1 Corinthians 2:14-15</a> “natural man” is set over against “spiritual man” (see <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Within this context the natural man is one who does not accept the things that come from the spirit of God (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.14">1 Cor 2:14</a>). Rather, these things are “foolishness” to him. He cannot understand them because they are “spiritually discerned.” This foolishness is the foolishness of unbelief (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.21">1:21</a>), and the discernment lacking is insight produced only by the Holy Spirit. Plainly, Paul has in view someone utterly without and even opposed to the Holy Spirit and God’s revealed truth.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.44-46">1 Corinthians 15:44-46</a>, the contrast between spiritual and natural occurs in a different context—that of the “body” in death as compared to the “body” in resurrection. The body of the believer laid in the grave (“sown”) is a natural body (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.44">44</a>a). The body of the believer raised from the dead will be a spiritual body, that is, a body renewed and transformed by the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.11">Rom 8:11</a>). In <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.44">1 Corinthians 15:44b</a> and <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45">45a</a>, however, the natural body is traced back by appeal to <a href="?bref=Gen.2.7">Genesis 2:7</a> to Adam before the fall, at Creation. This shows that biblically what is natural refers to the Creation. Originally, as created by God, the “natural” was “very good” (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.31">Gn 1:31</a>) but subsequently it has been subjected to corruption and death by the sin of man. Therefore, the sinful rebellion of the natural man, measured by the original creation, is thoroughly unnatural and abnormal. The opposing work of the Holy Spirit now, in Christ, not only removes this abnormality but brings the original purposes of Creation to their consummation (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.19-22">Rom 8:19-22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.17">2 Cor 5:17</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Man_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Man</a>; <a href="?item=ManOldandNew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Man, Old and New</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>