<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Martha">
  <title>Martha</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MARTHA</p>
<p class="fl">Sister of Mary and Lazarus, and friend of Jesus. Martha’s family lived in Bethany, a small town on the eastern slope of the Mt of Olives.</p>
<p>Luke gives an account of an incident concerning Martha when she was busy preparing and serving food while her sister, Mary, was listening to Jesus. Martha complained to Jesus that Mary was not helping her; Jesus corrected Martha gently: “My dear Martha, you are so upset over all these details! There is really only one thing worth being concerned about. Mary has discovered it—and I won’t take it away from her” (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.41-42">Lk 10:41-42</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). In saying this, Jesus challenged Martha’s anxiousness by pointing out that fellowship with him was life’s highest and most rewarding priority.</p>
<p>In John’s account of the death and resurrection of Lazarus, it is Martha who, upon Jesus’ arrival, goes out to meet him while Mary remains in the house (<a href="?bref=John.11.20">Jn 11:20</a>). Once again, Martha complains to Jesus, this time saying that if he had come earlier Lazarus would not have died (v <a href="?bref=John.11.21">21</a>). When Jesus replied that her brother would rise again, Martha naturally assumed that Jesus was speaking of the future resurrection. Jesus reassured Martha that he was the resurrection and the life and that she must trust in him (vv <a href="?bref=John.11.23-26">23-26</a>). Martha then confessed her belief that Jesus was the Christ (v <a href="?bref=John.11.27">27</a>). When Jesus asked that the tomb be opened, Martha protested that the smell would be unpleasant. Jesus replied firmly to her doubts, “Did I not tell you that if you would believe you would see the glory of God?” (v <a href="?bref=John.11.40">40</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Jesus then proceeded to raise Lazarus from the dead.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=John.12.1-11">John 12:1-11</a> Martha is again serving a meal for Jesus and Lazarus; this time she does not protest Mary’s elaborate show of affection for Jesus.</p>
  </body>
</item>