<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Mattathias">
  <title>Mattathias</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MATTATHIAS</p>
<p class="list">1. Member of the priestly family of Joarib (his genealogy can be traced in <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.2.1">1 Macc 2:1</a> and in Josephus’s <span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 12.6.3). He was a native of Jerusalem who settled in Modein and became the father of the nationalistic leaders, the Maccabeans, who led the Jewish revolt against the Syrians (167 <span class="era">BC</span>). In his attempt to wipe out Judaism and establish Hellenism, Antiochus Epiphanes, king of Syria, outlawed Jewish sacrifices, built pagan altars (including one to Zeus in the temple), and executed anyone who possessed the law (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.2.1-49">1 Macc 2:1-49</a>). Mattathias ignited the revolt against this oppression when Greek officers set up a pagan altar at Modein and ordered that sacrifices be offered to heathen gods. Mattathias refused, killed the Jew who volunteered, killed the Greek officer, destroyed the altar, and fled to the hills with a band of followers. He led guerrilla warfare against the Syrians, continued to circumcise children, and made strenuous efforts to preserve the law. His motto was “Let everyone who is zealous for the law come after me.”</p>
<p class="list-text">He led the revolt for about a year and died, probably in 167 <span class="era">BC</span>. His last bequest to his sons was “Obey the ordinance of the law.” He was succeeded in military leadership by his son Judas, and the Hasmonean dynasty of priests were his descendants. He is remembered in special Hanukkah prayers because of his zeal in fighting for religious freedom.</p>
<p class="list">2. Amos’s son and an ancestor of Jesus, according to Luke’s genealogy (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.25">Lk 3:25</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
<p class="list">3. Semein’s son and an ancestor of Jesus, according to Luke’s genealogy (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.26">Lk 3:26</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>