<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MatthewGospelof">
  <title>Matthew, Gospel of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MATTHEW, Gospel of</p>
<p class="fl">First Gospel and first book of the NT.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DateandProvenance">Date and Provenance</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Purpose">Purpose</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">Nowhere does the text of Matthew itself clearly identify the author. Yet, as did the ancient church, we may ascribe authorship to Matthew the apostle. He was otherwise known as Levi (see <a href="?bref=Mark.2.14">Mk 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.27,29">Lk 5:27, 29</a>). Before Jesus called him, he was a tax collector (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.9-38">Mt 9:9ff</a>.). It is interesting to note that Matthew called himself a tax collector, while none of the other Gospel writers did. Perhaps he did this to show how great an ascendancy he had been granted when the Lord called him, for tax collectors were despised and considered the lowest of people. The Gospel itself bears the impress of one knowledgeable of currency, for the Gospel writer speaks quite specifically about a two-drachma tax (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.24">Mt 17:24</a>), a four-drachma coin (v <a href="?bref=Matt.17.27">27</a>), and the various talents (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.24">18:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.25.15-46">25:15ff</a>.).</p>
<p class="h2" id="DateandProvenance">Date and Provenance</p>
<p class="fl">Scholars are divided about the date when Matthew was written primarily because there is still debate about which Gospel was first written: Matthew or Mark. If Mark was written before Matthew, then Matthew was very indebted to Mark for a great deal of material, and vice versa. Those who argue for Matthew’s priority do so on the basis that Matthew’s Gospel was (1) recognized in the early church as the first Gospel, (2) written to those who first needed a written account—the Jews, and (3) placed first in the NT canon. Whether it preceded or followed Mark, most scholars are certain that it was written before the destruction of Jerusalem (<span class="era">AD</span> 70) because the temple is spoken of as still standing (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.15">Mt 24:15</a>). Irenaeus indicated that Matthew wrote this Gospel while Peter and Paul were in Rome. This would make the time of writing in the 60s.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Purpose">Purpose</p>
<p class="h3">Apologetics</p>
<p class="fl">Matthew wrote to a community of Greek-speaking Jewish Christians, located in a center such as Antioch in Syria. The community was surrounded and beset by Jews hostile to the claims of Jesus and the Christian community.</p>
<p>Matthew wrote as a Jew for Jews. In Jesus of Nazareth, Matthew contends, the OT reached its appointed goal. Jesus is the Messiah of Israel’s expectation. In the opening chapter Matthew identifies him as “the son of David, the son of Abraham” (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.1">1:1</a>), indeed as “God with us” (v <a href="?bref=Matt.1.23">23</a>). In later chapters Jesus is revealed as the Son of Man of <a href="?bref=Dan.7.1-28">Daniel 7</a> and the Suffering Servant of <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">Isaiah 53</a>. Throughout the book (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.22-27.10">Mt 1:22–27:10</a>) the events of Jesus’ life are represented as the “fulfillment” of OT prophecies. He comes to offer Israel salvation from sin (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">1:21</a>). Nevertheless, the Jews have rejected him as their Messiah, and have thus placed themselves in the most perilous position (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.20-24">11:20-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.21.33-46">21:33-46</a>). One explanation for Israel’s rejection of Jesus is the failure of the Jewish religious leadership to prepare the people for his coming. In the strongest language, Matthew denounces the teachers of the law and the Pharisees. They have forsaken the Word of God in favor of their own traditions (ch <a href="?bref=Matt.15.1-39">15</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Teaching the Church</p>
<p class="fl">Matthew also wrote as a Christian for Christians. He presents Jesus as a new Moses, indeed as Yahweh incarnate, expounding his own law for his people (ch <a href="?bref=Matt.5.1-48">5</a>), now newly constituted around his person under the leadership of the apostles (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.2-4">10:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.16.18-19">16:18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.8-10">23:8-10</a>). If the Christian church is to function properly, the teaching of the Messiah on a host of moral and spiritual issues must be taken with utmost seriousness (chs <a href="?bref=Matt.5.1-7.29">5–7</a>, <a href="?bref=Matt.18.1-35">18</a>). To aid this purpose, Matthew takes the form of a theological textbook or a handbook for the church, to instruct the people of God concerning the person and work of Jesus. That these teachings may be more readily and firmly grasped, Matthew presents them in a highly organized and memorable way. To facilitate the learning of the material, he arranges Jesus’ teachings in five major discourses (interlocked with narrative portions) in which teachings of the same kind are clustered together (e.g., ch <a href="?bref=Matt.10.1-42">10</a> consists of a charge to missionaries, and ch <a href="?bref=Matt.13.1-58">13</a> consists of seven parables of the kingdom). Matthew’s leading theological themes may be identified as the <span class="ital">Son</span> of God (Jesus is Yahweh incarnate, “God with us”), the <span class="ital">kingdom</span> of God (in Jesus, God is invading history to inaugurate his final rule), the <span class="ital">salvation</span> of God (as the servant-king, Jesus has come to “save his people from their sins,” <a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">1:21</a>), and the <span class="ital">people</span> of God (Jesus has come to build his church, a redeemed community consisting of both Jews and Gentiles).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">The Coming of the Savior (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.1-2.23">1:1–2:23</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">His name reveals his mission: “Jesus” (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.1">1:1</a>) means “Yahweh saves.” He is “the son of Abraham,” who comes to fulfill God’s ancient promises to Jews and Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.1-3">Gn 12:1-3</a>). He is “Christ [or Messiah],” the son of David (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.1">Mt 1:1</a>), who comes to inaugurate the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.17">4:17</a>). More than that, as evidenced both by prophecy (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.22-23">1:22-23</a>) and by the nature of his conception (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.1.18-20">18-20</a>), he is “God with us”—now come to “save his people from their sins” (v <a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">21</a>). As the son of David, and in accord with prophecy, he is born in Bethlehem (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.1-6">2:1-6</a>). Drawn by the star of Israel’s Messiah (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.24.17">Nm 24:17</a>), Gentiles come to worship him (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.1-12">Mt 2:1-12</a>). When Herod seeks to destroy him, Jesus finds sanctuary in a gentile land; God’s calling his Son from Egypt marks the beginning of a mighty saving work—nothing less than a new exodus under Jesus, the new Moses (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.2.13-20">13-20</a>). Having been born in the humblest of circumstances, Jesus now comes to live in Nazareth (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.2.21-23">21-23</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Beginnings of Ministry (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.1-4.25">3:1–4:25</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In face of the judgment that Jesus is about to execute (as evidence of the kingdom’s arrival), John the Baptist calls Israel to repentance (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.1-12">3:1-12</a>). Jesus’ submission to John’s baptism, and the voice from heaven, show him to be a King who serves his subjects by taking their sins upon himself (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.3.13-17">13-17</a>). Like Israel at the exodus, Jesus is led into the wilderness for a period of testing (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.1">4:1</a>). When the devil seeks to turn him away both from God and from his appointed mission, Jesus gains victory by depending upon God and his Word (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.4.1-11">1-11</a>). Returning to Galilee, Jesus deliberately settles in territory with both Jewish and Gentile inhabitants (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.4.12-16">12-16</a>) and begins a ministry of preaching (like John, he calls for repentance in face of the dawning kingdom), teaching (he calls his first disciples), and healing (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.4.17-25">17-25</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientPapyrusManuscriptOfMatthew"/>
<p class="h3">The Sermon on the Mount (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.1-7.29">5:1–7:29</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Just as Moses ascended Sinai to receive God’s law for Israel, so Jesus—as both the new Moses and as God incarnate—ascends the mountain to set forth his instruction for the citizens of the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.1-2">5:1-2</a>). He begins with <span class="ital">gospel</span> (not law), declaring that God shall surely save those who—beset by sin—trust in God’s mercy, obey his commands, and long for him to establish his righteous rule in the earth (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.5.3-12">3-12</a>). Toward that end, disciples are a preservative (salt) and a witness (light) in a sinful society (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.5.13-16">13-16</a>). As the one who has come not to abolish the Law and the Prophets but to bring them to completion (i.e., to usher in the new age to which the OT pointed— v <a href="?bref=Matt.5.17">17</a>), Jesus calls his disciples to steadfast obedience to God’s law as now expounded by the Lawgiver himself (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.5.18-20">18-20</a>). God’s commands embrace inner desires as well as outward actions, must not be watered down or rationalized, and call for more radical obedience than ever before, now that the end has come (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.5.21-48">21-48</a>). In their giving, praying, and fasting, disciples are to combat hypocrisy by God-centeredness and self-forgetfulness (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.1-18">6:1-18</a>). The Lord’s Prayer (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.6.9-13">9-13</a>) calls upon God to honor his name by establishing his rule on earth, and to pardon, protect, and provide for his children. Given this prayer, and given the disciples’ God-centered view of reality (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.6.19-24">19-24</a>), there is no cause for anxiety (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.6.25-34">25-34</a>). Disciples must be discerning without being judgmental (<a href="?bref=Matt.7.1-6">7:1-6</a>), and depend on God for the power needed to love others (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.7-12">6:7-12</a>). Having completed his exposition of the law (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.21-7.12">5:21–7:12</a>), Jesus now calls would-be disciples to follow him (<a href="?bref=Matt.7.13-14">7:13-14</a>), warns against false teachers (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.7.15-20">15-20</a>), and insists that true disciples do God’s will (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.7.21-23">21-23</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Authority of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.1-9.38">8:1–9:38</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Having given his authority <span class="ital">verbal</span> expression in teaching (<a href="?bref=Matt.7.28-29">7:28-29</a>), Jesus now gives it <span class="ital">visible</span> expression in a series of healing miracles, again revealing himself as the servant of Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.17">8:17</a>). He heals a leper, a centurion’s servant, and a bleeding woman by his word (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.1-13">8:1-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.9.20-22">9:20-22</a>). His touch dispels a fever and raises a dead person (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.14-15">8:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.9.23-25">9:23-25</a>). A combination of word and touch cures the blind (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.27-31">9:27-31</a>). As “God with us,” Jesus calls for unqualified allegiance (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.18-22">8:18-22</a>). Though lacking even the natural protection enjoyed by animals (v <a href="?bref=Matt.8.20">20</a>), he demonstrates his sovereignty over the natural world—and thus his deity—by calming the storm (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.8.23-27">23-27</a>). In direct confrontations with demons, he shows his superiority over them (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.28-34">8:28-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.9.32-33">9:32-33</a>). Exercising God’s own authority, he declares sins forgiven (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.1-8">9:1-8</a>) and calls sinners to repentance and to discipleship (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.9.9-13">9-13</a>). Joy over the kingdom’s inauguration is mingled with longing for its consummation (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.9.14-17">14-17</a>). The summary of <a href="?bref=Matt.9.35-38">9:35-38</a> echoes <a href="?bref=Matt.4.23-25">4:23-25</a>, recalls chapters <a href="?bref=Matt.5.1-7.29">5–7</a>, and prepares for the next major discourse.</p>
<p class="h3">Jesus’ Charge to the Missionaries (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.1-42">10:1-42</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In response to the prayers that he has commanded, Christ now invests 12 disciples with apostolic authority and sends them out into his harvest field (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.37-10.4">9:37–10:4</a>). The discourse speaks both of the apostles’ immediate mission (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.5-15">10:5-15</a>) and of the church’s broader mission (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.10.16-42">16-42</a>). For now, the apostles are to concentrate on evangelizing Jews (v <a href="?bref=Matt.10.6">6</a>), in preparation for the mission to Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.19">28:19</a>). The “worthy” are those who welcome the apostles and their message; the “unworthy,” those who reject them (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.11-15">10:11-15</a>). In the broader mission, there is sure to be persecution (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.10.16-19,24-25">16-19, 24-25</a>), but this will actually aid the witness (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.10.17-23">17-23</a>). God will save his faithful missionaries (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.10.19-23">19-23</a>) but judge those who oppress them and who disown Christ (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.10.26-39">26-39</a>). A sure reward awaits both the herald and the recipient of the message (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.10.37-42">37-42</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Christ the Lord (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.1-12.50">11:1–12:50</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The judgment John predicted is already under way; one’s stand in the last judgment would be determined by his response to the words and works of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.2-6">11:2-6</a>). Like his herald, Jesus meets with widespread hostility and indifference (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.11.7-19">7-19</a>). Given the finality of the grace attending his ministry, those who reject him will suffer the severest judgment (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.11.20-24">20-24</a>). Yet there are others—the lowly, the burdened, the teachable—who learn (by revelation from God the Father and God the Son) that the “Lord of heaven and earth” is also the “gentle and humble” God who comes to give rest to those who trust in him (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.11.25-30">25-30</a>). As the one who ushers in the new age (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.6">12:6</a>), Jesus claims that he is the Lord of the Sabbath (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.12.1-8">1-8</a>). True rest (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.29">11:29</a>) comes to those who come to Jesus.</p>
<p>Viewing Jesus as the destroyer of the Sabbath, the Pharisees ascribe his miraculous powers to Satan (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.22-24">12:22-24</a>). On the contrary, says Jesus, the rule he is inaugurating is crushing Satan’s empire (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.12.25-29">25-29</a>). To reject this truth in the full awareness of what one is doing is to commit the unforgivable sin against the Holy Spirit (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.12.30-32">30-32</a>); the words of Jesus’ accusers expose them as persons destined for condemnation (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.12.33-37">33-37</a>). The requested sign from heaven will not be given. Jesus’ resurrection is the only sign they need.</p>
<p class="h3">The Parables of the Kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.1-58">13:1-58</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This, the third of Matthew’s five great discourses, contains seven parables. In the parable of the sower, four kinds of soil—hard, shallow, cluttered, and fruitful—illustrate the various responses to Jesus’ preaching (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.3-9,18-23">13:3-9, 18-23</a>). As those who have received Jesus’ proclamation of the kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.17">4:17</a>), the disciples are given more light, but the crowds must accept that initial proclamation before further light is given (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.10-17,34-35">13:10-17, 34-35</a>). In both the parable of the weeds (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.13.24-30,36-43">24-30, 36-43</a>) and the parable of the net (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.13.47-50">47-50</a>), Jesus assures his disciples that the final judgment will separate true believers from false, and warns against hasty, premature judgments (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.7.1-5">7:1-5</a>). The parables of the mustard and the yeast (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.31-33">13:31-33</a>) contrast the smallness of the kingdom’s inauguration with the fullness of its consummation. The parables of the hidden treasure and the pearl (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.13.44-46">44-46</a>) depict the kingdom as a value far surpassing all others (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.6.33">6:33</a>). Thus illuminated by Jesus, disciples have new treasures to add to their old (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.51-52">13:51-52</a>). The people of Nazareth, on the contrary, echo the crowds’ lack of understanding and the Pharisees’ hostility (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.13.53-58">53-58</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Spiritual Conflict (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.1-16.12">14:1–16:12</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In <a href="?bref=Matt.14.1-12">14:1-12</a> the preaching of John exposes the weakness of Herod, and the beheading of John anticipates the crucifixion of Jesus (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.17.12">17:12</a>). The true king is not Herod but Jesus. He is sovereign over nature itself (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.13-36">14:13-36</a>)—God incarnate, “God with us,” who feeds the hungry multitude in the wilderness (as God once provided manna) and walks upon and calms the sea (see <a href="?bref=Ps.89.9">Ps 89:9</a>). Peter models Christians’ faith, fear, and utter dependence on Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.28-31">Mt 14:28-31</a>). The Pharisees and teachers of the law appear to worship God but in fact are devoted to their own traditions, which they offer not as supplements but as <span class="ital">rivals</span> to the Word of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.1-9">15:1-9</a>). In verses <a href="?bref=Matt.15.10-20">10-20</a> Jesus teaches both that ceremonial law apart from moral law becomes empty ritual, and that the old distinction between clean and unclean foods (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.1-47">Lv 11</a>) is now as obsolete as the distinction between Jews and Gentiles. To underscore the point, Jesus enters pagan territory, heals a Canaanite (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.21-28">15:21-28</a>) and feeds a Gentile multitude (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.15.29-39">29-39</a>). Pharisees and Sadducees, for all their differences, are united in their opposition to Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.1-12">16:1-12</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Coming Salvation (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.13-17.27">16:13–17:27</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Going beyond the crowds’ respectful but inadequate estimates, Peter confesses Jesus to be “the Christ, the Son of the living God”—a recognition of Jesus’ deity granted by divine revelation (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.13-17">16:13-17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.11.25-26">11:25-26</a>). As it is God the Son who possesses and builds the church, Satan and death are victims rather than victors. Jesus will build his church on Peter’s confession that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of the living God. The apostles’ prohibiting and granting entry into the church (“binding” and “loosing,” respectively) depends upon the prior decision of heaven (i.e., God’s revelation of apostolic teaching). In face of Peter’s confession and the persistent false notions of messiahship (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.20,23">16:20, 23</a>), Jesus now (for the first time) predicts his sufferings and coming glory (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.16.21-28">21-28</a>). In anticipation of that glory, Jesus is transfigured before certain disciples; Moses and Elijah join God the Father in bearing witness to the unique splendor of God the Son (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.1-8">17:1-8</a>). Jesus then demonstrated his power by combating demonic powers (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.17.14-18">14-18</a>) and exhibited his authority by choosing to pay the temple tax using miraculous means (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.17.24-27">24-27</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Greatness in the Kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.1-35">18:1-35</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In this, the fourth of Matthew’s five great discourses, Jesus concentrates on the character and attitudes of church members. He calls upon his followers both to <span class="ital">become</span> and to <span class="ital">welcome</span> the lowliest (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.1-5">18:1-5</a>). Leaders especially are enjoined to deal harshly with themselves but gently with those under their care (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.18.6-9">6-9</a>). Remembering the Father’s love for sinners, Christians are to make every effort (both by prayer and by personal initiative) to restore offending brothers, with excommunication being the last resort (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.18.10-20">10-20</a>). Church members who really understand the Father’s amazing grace will never stop offering forgiveness and compassion to those who wrong them (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.18.21-35">21-35</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Instructions on the Way to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.1-20.34">19:1–20:34</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Given God’s creation ordinances, says Jesus, divorce itself is never <span class="ital">commanded;</span> it is only <span class="ital">permitted</span> in the case of sin—that is, where the marital bond has already been severed through infidelity (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.1-9">19:1-9</a>). As in <a href="?bref=Matt.5.17-48">5:17-48</a>, Jesus calls his followers to radical obedience (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.10-12">19:10-12</a>). Besides instructing disciples to become like children (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.1-4">18:1-4</a>), Jesus embraces children themselves with his love (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.13-15">19:13-15</a>). He appeals likewise to the rich young man (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.19.16-22">16-22</a>); but the man, while faithful to the commands about love of neighbor, is too bound by his wealth to give himself unreservedly to loving God. Yet those who abandon all to follow Jesus will receive wealth untold in the coming kingdom (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.19.27-30">27-30</a>). The basis for such blessings lies not in human merit but in the astonishing generosity of the gracious God (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.1-16">20:1-16</a>). None—not even the rich—are beyond the power of his grace. But God offers free salvation at great cost to himself (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.20.17-19">17-19</a>). Confronting competitiveness and ambition among his followers, Jesus teaches them that true greatness lies not in lording it over others but in serving them (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.20.20-34">20-34</a>), as shall be supremely demonstrated in his death as “a ransom for many” (v <a href="?bref=Matt.20.28">28</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Confrontations in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.1-22.46">21:1–22:46</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">As the Servant-King (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.3.17">3:17</a>), and as the Messiah destined for suffering (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.16.16-21">16:16-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.20.28">20:28</a>), Jesus enters Jerusalem not upon a war horse but upon a donkey’s colt, for he purposes not to declare war on his enemies but to hand himself over to them—and thus achieve his triumph through defeat (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.1-11">21:1-11</a>). As Lord of the temple, he demands that its commerce be halted and that it become (as God ordained) a place of worship for everyone, including the sick, the young, and the alien (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.12-17">21:12-17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.11.17">Mk 11:17</a>). He outwits those who refuse to acknowledge the heavenly source of his and John’s authority (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.23-27">Mt 21:23-27</a>). In dramatic and devastating fashion, first visibly (by cursing the fig tree—vv <a href="?bref=Matt.21.18-22">18-22</a>) and then verbally (in the three parables of <a href="?bref=Matt.21.28-22.14">21:28–22:14</a>), Jesus pronounces judgment upon those Jews who have refused to acknowledge him as Messiah and Son of God. Henceforth, the true people of God are those who believe in Jesus, whether Jews or Gentiles. He calls upon his people to pledge their supreme allegiance to God. In the resurrection what will matter most is one’s relationship to God (<a href="?bref=Matt.22.23-33">22:23-33</a>). Indeed, he who loves God with his whole being and his neighbor as himself has kept the two foundational commandments of the OT (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.22.34-40">34-40</a>). Henceforth, submitting to God means rightly recognizing Jesus; he is indeed David’s son (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.1">Mt 1:1</a>), but he is supremely David’s Lord—the exalted Son of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.22.41-46">22:41-46</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.16.16">16:16</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Woes upon the Scribes and Pharisees (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.1-39">23:1-39</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Five reasons are stated for Jesus’ denunciation of the Jewish religious leaders. First is their hypocrisy: their practice contradicts their teaching (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.1-4">23:1-4</a>), their external purity conceals inner rottenness (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.23.25-28">25-28</a>), and they appear to champion God’s cause but are really enemies of God’s servants (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.23.29-36">29-36</a>). Second is the pride that prompts their hypocrisy (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.5-12">23:5-12</a>). Third is their exploitation of, and their baleful influence upon, those under their charge (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.23.13-15">13-15</a>). Fourth is their preoccupation with the minutia of the law to the neglect of its weightier matters (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.23.16-24">16-24</a>). Fifth is their responsibility for the dreadful judgment that the whole nation is about to experience (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.23.33-39">33-39</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Coming of the End (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.1-25.46">24:1–25:46</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The introduction to this, the fifth and last of Matthew’s great discourses, makes it plain that there is the closest connection (for both Jesus and his disciples) between the coming destruction of Jerusalem and the end of the age (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.1-3">24:1-3</a>). Jesus first characterizes the time between his first advent and his return: there will be natural catastrophes, international warfare, the rise of false messiahs, the persecution of God’s people, and the universal proclamation of the gospel of the kingdom (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.24.4-14">4-14</a>). Then Jesus speaks of the catastrophe that is soon to befall the Jewish nation in particular (as already foretold in <a href="?bref=Matt.22.7">22:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.38">23:38</a>), culminating in the destruction of Jerusalem and its temple in <span class="era">AD</span> 70 (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.15-25">24:15-25</a>). Sometime thereafter (but after an interval known only to God the Father—v <a href="?bref=Matt.24.36">36</a>), the Son of Man will return in great glory, amid apocalyptic signs, to gather his people (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.24.26-31">26-31</a>). The present generation will not pass away before judgment falls upon Israel (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.24.15-25">15-25</a>), so let listeners take heed (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.24.32-35">32-35</a>). The same warning applies to the more remote coming of the Son of Man (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.24.36-51">36-51</a>): both the certainty of the event and the uncertainty of its time call for vigilance and faithfulness in the interval, for that event will bring both salvation and judgment. To drive the lesson home, Jesus tells the parables of the wise and foolish virgins (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.1-13">25:1-13</a>) and the talents (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.25.14-30">14-30</a>). The concluding parable of the sheep and the goats (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.25.31-46">31-46</a>) speaks of the urgent necessity of making the right response to the “brothers”—that is, the messengers—of Christ; those who feed, clothe, and otherwise care for the messengers of Christ thereby testify to their reception of the apostles’ message and their Lord (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.10.40-42">10:40-42</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Road to Golgotha (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.1-27.26">26:1–27:26</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">As though in response to Jesus’ own prediction, the chief priests and the elders hatch their murderous plot (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.1-5">26:1-5</a>), soon to be aided by Judas (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.26.14-16">14-16</a>). The anointing at Bethany (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.26.6-13">6-13</a>) testifies to the extravagance of love and the imminence of death. At the Passover meal (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.26.17-30">17-30</a>), signaling at what sacrifice the new exodus comes about (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.2.15">2:15</a>), Jesus interprets his forthcoming death as an atoning sacrifice for the forgiveness of sins (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.26-28">26:26-28</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">1:21</a>) and anticipates the day of final victory over sin and death in the consummated kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.29">26:29</a>). Jesus’ agony in Gethsemane (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.26.36-46">36-46</a>) expresses his horror over taking his people’s sins upon himself. By a stupendous act of filial obedience, he submits his will to the Father, that the Scriptures might be fulfilled (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.54">26:54</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.53.1-12">Is 53</a>). As the servant of God destined to suffer, Jesus resists attempts to thwart his arrest (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.47-56">26:47-56</a>). The Jews’ supreme court (the Sanhedrin) and their loftiest religious official (the high priest) condemn Jesus as a blasphemer because he dares to identify himself as “the Christ, the Son of God” (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.57-68">26:57-68</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.16.16">16:16</a>). As though joining the court’s repudiation, Peter—in fulfillment of Jesus’ prophecy (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.31-35">26:31-35</a>)—disclaims knowledge of Jesus (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.26.69-75">69-75</a>). Judas’s disillusionment finds expression in suicide (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.3-10">27:3-10</a>). The Jews hand Jesus over to Pilate the Roman governor (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.27.1-2">1-2</a>), he alone having the authority to pronounce the death sentence. Knowing that the charge of blasphemy will carry no weight with Pilate, the Jews now represent Jesus as a threat to Caesar. In the end, Pilate responds not to specific charges and evidence but to pressure from the crowd and the threat of riot (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.27.11-25">11-25</a>). He releases Barabbas and delivers Jesus to be crucified (v <a href="?bref=Matt.27.26">26</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Death of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.27-66">27:27-66</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Following his humiliating treatment at the hands of the Roman soldiers, Jesus is led to the place of execution; weakened by the beatings, he requires assistance (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.27-32">27:27-32</a>). He refuses the proffered narcotic so that he might keep his head clear (v <a href="?bref=Matt.27.34">34</a>). His being executed with malefactors (v <a href="?bref=Matt.27.38">38</a>) testifies to the purpose of his death (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">1:21</a>). A steady stream of abuse is hurled at him, in blasphemous disregard of the truth of the superscription “This is Jesus the King of the Jews” (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.37-44">27:37-44</a>). Finally, out of the darkness Jesus utters the cry of dereliction; now is revealed the ultimate horror (that from which his soul shrank in Gethsemane), the sin-bearer’s supreme agony—the beloved Son’s abandonment by the Father (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.27.45-49">45-49</a>). Having cried out with a loud voice (cf. <a href="?bref=John.19.30">Jn 19:30</a>), Jesus dies (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.50">27:50</a>). Immediately, the saving effects of his death become evident (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.27.51-53">51-53</a>): sinners, now forgiven, have access to the holy God (the veil of the temple is rent asunder), and there is hope of resurrection for those who have died. As at the beginning (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.1-12">2:1-12</a>), Gentiles instead of Jews confess Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.54">27:54</a>; contrast <a href="?bref=Matt.26.63-65">26:63-65</a>). Joseph’s careful attentiveness to Jesus’ burial contrasts with the ongoing attempts of the chief priests and Pharisees to resist Jesus’ power (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.57-66">27:57-66</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Triumph of the Savior (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.1-20">28:1-20</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Amid great glory and power and joy, the Savior’s victory over death is announced and attested (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.1-7">28:1-7</a>). The risen Jesus appears first to the women who stayed with him during his crucifixion (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.8-10">28:8-10</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.27.61">27:61</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.28.1">28:1</a>). The Jews’ response to the guards’ report signals their growing desperation before irresistible reality (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.11-15">28:11-15</a>). Meeting with the 11 disciples on the mountain in Galilee (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.28.16-20">16-20</a>), Jesus, the new Moses, continues his instructions. He now reveals the evangelistic purpose for which Matthew has been preparing readers from the very threshold of his Gospel. The apostles are to disciple all peoples by baptizing them into the name of the triune God and by teaching them to obey all that Jesus has commanded. The apostles go forth in the assurance that Jesus—as the Lord—stands over them, and that Jesus—as Immanuel—stands with them until the very end of the age.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Life and Teachings of</a>; <a href="?item=LukeGospelof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Luke, Gospel of</a>; <a href="?item=MarkGospelof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mark, Gospel of</a>; <a href="?item=MatthewPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Matthew (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=SynopticGospels_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Synoptic Gospels</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>