<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MealsSignificanceof">
  <title>Meals, Significance of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MEALS, Significance of</p>
<p class="fl">The meal played a significant role in family, social, and religious life. The evening meal was the time when all family members normally were gathered together, and was thus an important time of fellowship. Providing food for the traveler was both a social and a religious responsibility, while the ideal of a quiet social life was realized by having friends break bread with the family and discuss the problems of the day by the light of small oil lamps. The significance of the meal retains its central focus both in the Jewish religion with the Passover meal and in Christianity with the celebration of the Lord’s Supper.</p>
<p>In the ancient Near East two meals were normally eaten during the day. The first was the noonday meal, usually consumed by laborers in the field and consisting of such items as small cakes or flat loaves, figs or olives, and possibly cheese or curds of goats’ milk. This was considered a small meal, eaten for sustenance and refreshment at a time of relaxation and respite from the heat of the sun and the labor of the day (<a href="?bref=Ruth.2.14">Ru 2:14</a>). Breakfast was considered unnecessary, and biblical references to any such form of early morning meal are very few (<a href="?bref=Judg.19.5">Jgs 19:5</a>; <a href="?bref=John.21.12">Jn 21:12</a>).</p>
<p>Whereas in Egypt the main meal was served at noon, among the Hebrews the evening meal was the most important social occasion of the day. Then the exhausted field workers could return home to relax after their day’s work and enjoy the feeling of communal warmth as the family gathered together for their principal meal. This occasion coincided with the arrival of darkness, a time when there was insufficient light for fieldwork to continue.</p>
<p>The laborer’s meal consisted of bread or cakes made of hand-ground grain, goats’ cheese or curds, vegetables (especially beans, lentils, leeks, and peas, which were popular for the sake of variety although not always plentiful), and figs, olives, raisins, and dates. Meat was usually available, but for the majority was a luxury item. Food was cooked in olive oil, and honey was used for sweetening.</p>
<p>The meal was eaten together by the entire family. There was no separate dining room in the average house, and during the patriarchal period, meals were consumed while the family was seated on the floor, a mat often serving as a table (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.25">Gn 37:25</a>). Canaanite seating habits were adopted subsequently, and chairs and small tables were used (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.13.20">1 Kgs 13:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.23.5">Ps 23:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.23.41">Ez 23:41</a>). Eating in the Egyptian fashion in a reclining position became popular and continued throughout the Roman period. Musical entertainment, dancing, and riddles were sometimes provided on festive occasions for family and guests, since the meal period was the normal time for entertainment in Near Eastern society.</p>
<p>By NT times, a separate upper room often served as a dining room. Guests reclined by leaning on the left elbow so that they were close enough together on their couches to facilitate easy conversation. There was a strict hierarchy to the seating arrangements (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.43.33">Gn 43:33</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.9.22">1 Sm 9:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.6">Mt 23:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.39">Mk 12:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.14.8">Lk 14:8</a>) at all formal meals, the “highest” place being that to the right of the servants as they entered the room and the lowest to their left.</p>
<p>Guests washed their hands before and after meals, and normally partook of a form of meat and/or vegetable stew from a common bowl placed in the center of the table. Instead of cutlery, pieces of bread held in the fingers were made into the shape of a small scoop and dipped into the bowl. There would usually be only one main dish requiring preparation, so that the woman who had cooked the meal could partake of it with her guests, thus fulfilling the ideals of community at mealtimes.</p>
<p>On several occasions in the NT Jesus is mentioned as eating meals with disciples and friends. He and his followers were guests at the wedding feast held in Cana of Galilee (<a href="?bref=John.2.1-10">Jn 2:1-10</a>), and also at a dinner given by Matthew (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.10">Mt 9:10</a>), as well as at another given by Simon the Pharisee (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.36-50">Lk 7:36-50</a>). Jesus also was entertained at dinner somewhat unexpectedly by Zacchaeus (<a href="?bref=Luke.19.6-7">19:6-7</a>). On several occasions Jesus was a guest at a family gathering held at the home of Martha, Mary, and Lazarus in Bethany (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.38-42">Lk 10:38-42</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.2">Jn 12:2</a>). Following the customs of smaller towns and villages, passersby may well have called into the house to greet Jesus and perhaps converse with other guests.</p>
<p>There are two important meals described in Scripture, one involving the old covenant and the other the new, in which meals had a redemptive meaning for the people of God. The first was the institution of the Passover at the time of Israel’s departure from Egypt under Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.1-51">Ex 12</a>). The second was the institution of the Lord’s Supper. Both are discussed in detail in separate articles.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=FoodandFoodPreparation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Food and Food Preparation</a>; <a href="?item=FeastsandFestivalsofIsrael_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Feasts and Festivals of Israel</a>; <a href="?item=LordsSupperthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Lord’s Supper, The</a>; <a href="?item=Passover_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Passover</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>