<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Melchizedek">
  <title>Melchizedek</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MELCHIZEDEK</p>
<p class="fl">Mysterious biblical personality whose name means “king of righteousness.” The historical record about this priest-king is contained in <a href="?bref=Gen.14.18-20">Genesis 14:18-20</a>, and he is spoken of in <a href="?bref=Ps.110.4">Psalm 110:4</a> and <a href="?bref=Heb.5.10">Hebrews 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.6.20">6:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.1-17">7:1-17</a>.</p>
<p class="h2">In <a href="?bref=Gen.14.18-20">Genesis 14:18-20</a></p>
<p class="fl">Kedorlaomer, king of Elam, with three other Mesopotamian kings, raided a vassal confederacy of five kings near the shores of the Dead Sea. In the ensuing massacre and rout by the Mesopotamian confederacy, Abraham’s nephew Lot and his family and possessions were captured (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.1-12">Gn 14:1-12</a>). Abraham led an attacking force in pursuit of Lot’s captors, achieved victory, retrieved the plunder, and secured the release of Lot and his family (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.14.13-16">13-16</a>).</p>
<p>Upon his return, Abraham was greeted not only by the grateful kings of the Dead Sea confederacy but also by Melchizedek, king of Salem, who gave Abraham bread and wine along with his blessing as “priest of the most high God” <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">’El ‘Elyon</span><span class="ital">)</span> (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.18">Gn 14:18</a>). Salem is Jerusalem (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.76.2">Ps 76:2</a>). El Elyon is not the pagan deity of Canaanite worship by the same name but rather the title of the true God who created heaven and earth—an idea foreign to Canaanite religion (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.14.22">Gn 14:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.7.17">Pss 7:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.47.2">47:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.57.2">57:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.56">78:56</a>). Melchizedek correctly viewed Abraham as worshiping this same God (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.22">Gn 14:22</a>) and praised God for giving victory to Abraham. Abraham identified himself with the worship of the one true God represented by Melchizedek in that he received his gifts and blessing and gave him a tenth of everything, thus recognizing Melchizedek’s higher spiritual rank as a patriarchal priest. In contrast, Abraham disassociated himself from Canaanite polytheism by declining gifts from the king of Sodom.</p>
<p>It is interesting to speculate whether Melchizedek’s knowledge of the true God was received by tradition from the past ages closer to the Flood, or whether he, like Abraham, had been uprooted from paganism to monotheism by direct divine revelation. It is at least clear from <a href="?bref=Heb.7.3">Hebrews 7:3</a> that his priesthood was isolated and not received through a priestly pedigree.</p>
<p class="h2">In <a href="?bref=Ps.110.4">Psalm 110:4</a></p>
<p class="fl">In this messianic psalm, David envisioned one greater than himself whom he called “Lord” (v <a href="?bref=Ps.110.1">1</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.12.35-37">Mk 12:35-37</a>). Thus the perfect messianic king was not an idealization of the present ruler but someone to come. Also, he was to be not merely a man but more than this. The Messiah would be the Son of God as well as the son of David. The divine oracle of <a href="?bref=Ps.110.4">Psalm 110:4</a> is addressed to the Messiah: “You are a priest forever in the line of Melchizedek.” The significance of this statement is left for the inspired author of the letter to the Hebrews to develop.</p>
<p class="h2">In <a href="?bref=Heb.5.6-11">Hebrews 5:6-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.6.20-7.28">6:20–7:28</a></p>
<p class="fl">The argument of the writer of Hebrews is that the priesthood of Aaron has been superseded by the superior priesthood of Christ and that the superiority of Christ’s priesthood is demonstrated by its Melchizedekian character. First, both Christ and Melchizedek are kings of righteousness and kings of peace (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.1-2">Heb 7:1-2</a>). Second, both have a unique priesthood that does not depend on family pedigree (v <a href="?bref=Heb.7.3">3</a>). Third, both exist as priests continually (v <a href="?bref=Heb.7.3">3</a>).</p>
<p>Melchizedek was superior to Abraham, the father of Levi, because Melchizedek gave gifts to and blessed Abraham, and received tithes from him (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.4-10">7:4-10</a>); David predicted the succession of the Melchizedekian priesthood over the Levitical priesthood, showing the imperfection of the latter (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.7.11-19">11-19</a>); the Melchizedekian priesthood of the Messiah was confirmed by a divine oath, which was not true of the Levitical priesthood (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.7.20-22">20-22</a>); and the Melchizedekian priesthood possessed an unchangeable and permanent character (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.7.23-25">23-25</a>).</p>
<p>Certain scholars have thought that Melchizedek was an appearance of the preincarnate Christ in the OT (technically called a Christophany). They argue this on the basis of <a href="?bref=Heb.7.3">Hebrews 7:3</a>, which says that there is no record of his father or mother or any of his ancestors—no beginning or end to his life. However, this statement is simply to be understood in the sense that his priesthood was not connected to any priestly family line. Melchizedek had a priestly office by special divine appointment, and was thus a type of Jesus Christ in his priesthood. The writer of Hebrews says that Melchizedek was one “resembling the Son of God” (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.3">7:3</a>); this clearly indicates that he was not himself the Son of God.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=HebrewsLettertothe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hebrews, Letter to the</a>; <a href="?item=PriestsandLevites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Priests and Levites</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>