<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Memorial">
  <title>Memorial</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MEMORIAL</p>
<p class="fl">Something that keeps remembrance vivid. The ideas represented by the words “remember,” “remembrance,” and “memorial” are closely connected in common parlance as well as in biblical usage. The Hebrew and Greek words translated as “memorial” in the OT and NT are nominal derivatives of the verbal roots meaning “to remember.” It is for this reason that one cannot fully grasp the significance of the term “memorial” without first understanding something of the usage and meaning of the term “to remember.”</p>
<p>Although “remember” is usually understood as simply recalling to the mind something from the past, and “memorial” as that which serves to preserve the memory of something from the past, there is often another dimension to these terms in biblical usage. In the Bible, the verb “to remember” often represents a broader idea than simply to recall something from the past because it implies and includes resultant action as well. It is not just recalling, but recalling in a way that affects one’s present feeling, thought, or action. For example, when it is said in <a href="?bref=Gen.8.1">Genesis 8:1</a> that God “remembered Noah,” this does not mean that God merely recalled that Noah was in the ark. It includes this idea to be sure, but more than this it means that God is acting on Noah’s behalf. In a similar way, when <a href="?bref=Gen.30.22">Genesis 30:22</a> says that God “remembered Rachel,” the meaning is that after a long period of barrenness God is going to answer Rachel’s prayer for a child.</p>
<p>One of the most prominent uses of the idea to remember in the OT is the exhortation to the Israelites to remember the mighty acts of the Lord on their behalf in the past (<a href="?bref=Ps.77.11">Pss 77:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.7">78:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.105.5">105:5</a>). This also means much more than simply recalling events from past history. It means to live in the present in the light of God’s past actions. By drawing consequences for the present from the acts of God in the past, Israel’s faith is to be strengthened for the challenges and difficulties encountered in the present. Israel’s failure to remember in this way repeatedly led to apostasy and disobedience (<a href="?bref=Ps.78.11,42">78:11, 42</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.106.7,13,21-22">106:7, 13, 21-22</a>).</p>
<p>A brief survey of the usage of the term “memorial” demonstrates that it also often carries this added dimension of meaning. Here one notices in particular its use in connection with the Passover. <a href="?bref=Exod.12.14">Exodus 12:14</a> says that the Passover “shall be for you a memorial day” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). It is to be an observance that causes the Israelites to live in the present in the light of God’s past action in delivering them from sin and bondage in Egypt. This is much more than simply recalling the exodus as a historical occurrence.</p>
<p>In a similar way <a href="?bref=Josh.4.7">Joshua 4:7</a> describes setting up a monument of 12 stones in the midst of the Jordan River as a “memorial” to the miraculous provision for Israel’s crossing and entering Canaan. This memorial is to be “for the people of Israel for ever.” It is to remind them of God’s past deliverance so that they may take courage in their present circumstances.</p>
<p>Another usage of the term is found in connection with the “stones of remembrance” attached to the front of the ephod worn by the high priest (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.12,29">Ex 28:12, 29</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.39.7">39:7</a>). The significance of these stones was that they were to bring the names of the sons of Israel before the Lord. This is not simply in order for the Lord to recall their names but to assure the Israelites of his present concern for their well-being.</p>
<p>The term “memorial” is used with a somewhat different connotation in connection with the grain offering in <a href="?bref=Lev.2.2,16">Leviticus 2:2, 16</a>. The “memorial of the grain offering” is that portion that the priest offers upon the altar. The remainder is used for the sustenance of the priests themselves. The memorial is that which represents the whole: it does not serve just to remind God of the entire offering, but is viewed as an embodiment of it. A memorial in this sense may be viewed as embodying something of that which it represents.</p>
<p>In the NT the words “memorial” or “remembrance” occur rather infrequently, but in one instance with particular significance. When Jesus instituted the observance of the Lord’s Supper, the NT counterpart to the OT Passover, he said, “This is my body which is given for you. Do this in remembrance [or memorial] of me” (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.19">Lk 22:19</a>). The Lord’s Supper is observed as a remembrance of the suffering and death of Christ. It is much more, however, than simply recalling a historical fact; it is remembering in a way that fills the believer with thanksgiving and determines how he lives and acts in the present.</p>
  </body>
</item>