<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MerariMerarite">
  <title>Merari, Merarite</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MERARI, MERARITE</p>
<p class="fl">Transliteration of a Hebrew word meaning “bitter,” “bitter drink,” or “to be bitter.” It means the same in Arabic and Akkadian, but in Ugaritic it means “to strengthen, to bless.” Traditionally, the word has been understood to be derived from the Hebrew and thus to mean “gall” or “bitterness.” But the Ugaritic root meaning “to strengthen, to bless” is not foreign to the Hebrew way of thinking. When used as a person’s name, it probably should be understood to mean “strength” or “blessing.” Such an understanding may be preferred in many biblical references. In the case of Merari, the third son of Levi, this understanding is preferable in noting his importance and that of his family. It is inconsistent for the youngest son to have a name meaning “gall” or “bitterness” and then to have the greatest responsibility and the greatest reward for his service.</p>
<p>The Bible makes numerous references to Merari the son of Levi. He was the youngest of Levi’s three sons (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.11">Gn 46:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.6.16-19">Ex 6:16-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.17-20,33">Nm 3:17-20, 33</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.1">1 Chr 6:1</a>). He was the father of two sons, Mahli and Mushi (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.19">Ex 6:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.20">Nm 3:20</a>), who had the responsibility of carrying the frames (<span class="sc">kjv</span> “boards”), bars, pillars, bases (<span class="sc">kjv</span> “sockets”), vessels, and accessories of the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Num.3.36-37">Nm 3:36-37</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.4.31-33">4:31-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.7.8">7:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.10.17">10:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.7,34,40">Jos 21:7, 34, 40</a>). His descendants are known as Merarites. Chronicles makes numerous references to Merari’s family as an indication of its importance (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.1-81">1 Chr 6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.1-44">9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.1-29">15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.1-32">23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.26.1-32">26</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.1-36">2 Chr 29</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.1-33">34</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PriestsandLevites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Priests and Levites</a>; <a href="?item=LeviTribeof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Levi, Tribe of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>