<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MeunimMeunites">
  <title>Meunim, Meunites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MEUNIM, MEUNITES</p>
<p class="fl">People living in Edom (Mt Seir, <a href="?bref=1Chr.4.41-42">1 Chr 4:41-42</a>) who were dispossessed of their rich pasturelands by the Simeonites. Later, Meunites from Edom attacked Judah’s King Jehoshaphat (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.1">2 Chr 20:1</a>); later still, King Uzziah of Judah defeated them (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.7">26:7</a>). Their original land possession, association with Arabs and Ammonites, and prolonged hostility recall <a href="?bref=Judg.10.11-12">Judges 10:11-12</a>, where “Maonites” are named oppressors of Israel. This word, by Hebrew rules of vocalization, could well become “Meunites,” suggesting Maon (Ma’in, Maan) in the Edomite area south of the Dead Sea as their home.</p>
<p>The Meunim are listed among the families of temple servants returning to Jerusalem following the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.50">Ezr 2:50</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.52">Neh 7:52</a>). However, because ancient enemies seem unlikely temple servants, some suggest that these Meunim were descendants of the Caleb clan within Judah to whom another town named Maon, west of the Dead Sea and south of Hebron, was allotted (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.20,55">Jos 15:20, 55</a>). This Maon gave David refuge and another wife (<a href="?bref=1Sam.23.24-28">1 Sm 23:24-28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.25.1-44">25</a>).</p>
<p>This reconstruction involving two groups, two Maons, and temple servants with very foreign names, is tentative. An alternate view holds that hostile foreigners, formerly captured to become temple slaves (cf. <a href="?bref=Josh.9.7">Jos 9:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.44.6-8">Ez 44:6-8</a>), attained freedom during the exile and temple-guild status on returning.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=MaonPlace_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Maon (Place)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>