<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Michmash">
  <title>Michmash*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MICHMASH*</p>
<p class="fl">Town in southern Mt Ephraim near the edge of the wilderness that descends eastward toward the Jordan Valley. Though it must have been an Israelite settlement in the territory of Benjamin, it is absent from the list of Benjamite towns (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.21-28">Jos 18:21-28</a>). The ancient name is preserved in that of the Arab village of Mukhmas, situated on a narrow ridge to the east of Wadi Suweinit (valley of Zeboim) overlooking the deep canyon through which it runs. It is about two miles (3.2 kilometers) northeast of Geba (Jaba’), which stands on the western side of the same valley. A lateral road passed by Michmash to Jericho, and a longitudinal road also followed the watershed beside it. The latter route was of only secondary importance but still could serve as an alternate to the main route, the highway west of Bethel.</p>
<p>The town played its best-documented role in biblical history during the reign of Saul. When he mustered his troops, part were with him in Michmash while the rest were with Jonathan at Gibeah of Benjamin (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.2">1 Sm 13:2</a>). After Jonathan had smitten the Philistine commissioner at Geba, the Philistines came out in force and encamped at Michmash (v <a href="?bref=1Sam.13.5">5</a>) since Saul had withdrawn to Gilgal to assemble the rest of his forces. Then he went back to Geba, on the opposite side of the valley from the enemy. Using their base at Michmash (vv <a href="?bref=1Sam.13.11,16">11, 16</a>), the Philistines sent out raiding parties north to Ophrah, west to Beth-horon, and southeast along the edge of the valley of Zeboim (vv <a href="?bref=1Sam.13.17-18">17-18</a>); this passage serves to illustrate the value of Michmash as a strategic crossroads.</p>
<p>An outpost south of Michmash was manned by Philistines facing the Israelites on the opposite ridge (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.23">1 Sm 13:23</a>). Jonathan went out to the canyon where the two cliffs Bozez (on the side of Michmash) and Seneh (beside Geba) face one another. He and his armor bearer made a surprise attack on an outpost of soldiers, who then fled to Michmash. The resultant confusion among the Philistines was taken advantage of by Saul and his troops (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.1-23">14:1-23</a>). The Philistines withdrew under heavy Hebrew harassment by way of the lateral road via the Aijalon Valley (v <a href="?bref=1Sam.14.31">31</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>