<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Mind">
  <title>Mind</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MIND</p>
<p class="fl">One’s intellectual processes in a narrow sense or, more broadly, the sum total of a person’s mental and moral state of being. To the Hebrew way of thinking, there is no distinctive terminology for the concept of the mind. To the Greek world, the mind plays a very important role in the understanding of humans.</p>
<p>Since in the OT there was no separate word that could be used for the human mind, translators of the English versions have supplied other words (“soul,” “spirit,” or “heart”), as the context dictates. Thus, precise distinctions among these terms are hard to define. A person is a soul, having a spirit and a heart. Any of these terms may represent the mind. This means that the widely held distinction between the mind as the seat of thinking and the heart as the seat of feeling is alien to the meanings these terms carry in the OT.</p>
<p>While the “mind” denotes a person’s thoughts, the prominent idea of “mind” in the OT is that it denotes the heart (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.35">1 Sm 2:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.5">Ez 11:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.32">20:32</a>). The heart is often intended to include the entire inner person and thus often relates especially to the mind. In these instances it relates primarily to the functions of will and memory (<a href="?bref=Isa.46.8">Is 46:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.65.17">65:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.3.16">Jer 3:16</a>).</p>
<p>The basic patterns of Hebrew reasoning continue in the Gospel accounts. The conception of mind appears quite rarely. When used, it is mostly in connection with the heart—for example, the imaginations of the heart (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.51">Lk 1:51</a>). The only other occurrences of the word “mind” come in the statement of the great commandment: “You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your strength, and with all your mind” (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.22.37">Mt 22:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.30">Mk 12:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.27">Lk 10:27</a>). The Gospel writers are unanimous in their agreement that Jesus added “with all your mind” to <a href="?bref=Deut.6.5">Deuteronomy 6:5</a>. In Mark, however, the questioner repeats the command of Jesus but with a word for “understanding” in place of the word for “mind” (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.33">Mk 12:33</a>).</p>
<p>With the writings of Paul, one moves into the Greek world. Paul understood the mind as distinct from the spirit of man. It possesses the ability to understand and to reason (<a href="?bref=1Cor.14.14-19">1 Cor 14:14-19</a>); it is the seat of intelligence. In other places, “mind” is used in a broader sense that includes the entire mental and moral process or state of being of a human (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.2">Rom 12:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.23">Eph 4:23</a>). A human’s actions flow from the inclinations of his or her mind. Whether a person is good or evil depends on the state of the mind.</p>
<p>The state of a person depends upon what or who controls the mind. <a href="?bref=Rom.8.6-7">Romans 8:6-7</a> speaks of a person’s mind being controlled either by the flesh or by the Spirit. The person whose mind is controlled by the flesh is evil. The mind controlled by the Spirit leads to good. Other passages refer to the inclination of a person’s mind being controlled by the god of this world (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.4">2 Cor 4:4</a>). People whose minds are controlled by the “god of this world” will have their minds darkened and will not be able to understand the world as it really is (<a href="?bref=2Cor.3.14">3:14</a>). It is as a veil over one’s understanding. But the Lord can open people’s minds. For example, Jesus opened the minds of the disciples who walked the Emmaus road with him so that they might understand the Scriptures (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.45">Lk 24:45</a>).</p>
<p>For Paul, the action of conversion is considered to be a “renewing of the mind” (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.2">Rom 12:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.23">Eph 4:23</a>). In both cases, the process is one whereby God takes control of the mind of a person through the Holy Spirit and leads the thoughts of that person into proper channels. Thus, the renewed person is given power to make proper value judgments. Such people have new minds with which to make spiritual discernments (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.15-16">1 Cor 2:15-16</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Man_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Man</a>; <a href="?item=Heart_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Heart</a>; <a href="?item=Soul_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Soul</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>