<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Miriam">
  <title>Miriam</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MIRIAM</p>
<p class="list">1. Daughter of Amram and Jochebed and the sister of Aaron and Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.20">Ex 15:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.59">Nm 26:59</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.3">1 Chr 6:3</a>). Miriam first appears in Scripture as a young girl commissioned with the task of watching her infant brother’s cradle hidden in the reeds of the Nile River (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.4">Ex 2:4</a>)—the result of a scheme conceived by her parents (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.23">Heb 11:23</a>)—to escape the pharaoh’s edict that all Hebrew males be drowned at birth (<a href="?bref=Exod.1.22">Ex 1:22</a>). Miriam evidences not only courage and concern, but also displays a certain wisdom when her brother is discovered by the Egyptian princess (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.5-6">2:5-6</a>). Taking the initiative, she offers to secure a nurse for the child, and when this plan is accepted, she gets her mother (vv <a href="?bref=Exod.2.7-8">7-8</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Miriam first appears by name after the Israelites have crossed the Red Sea (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.20">Ex 15:20</a>). She is given the title of “prophetess” and is, with her brothers, appointed a leader in the nation (<a href="?bref=Mic.6.4">Mi 6:4</a>). Following the death of the Egyptian charioteers she leads the women of Israel in an anthem of praise accompanied with dancing and instrumental music (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.21">Ex 15:21</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Miriam appears in disgrace after her jealousy of and rebellion against Moses. With Aaron she murmurs against Moses because of his superior influence in the nation and because of his marriage to a Cushite woman (<a href="?bref=Num.12.1-2">Nm 12:1-2</a>). For this attack against God’s chosen spokesman, she is struck with leprosy (v <a href="?bref=Num.12.10">10</a>). Moses, however, intercedes on her behalf (<a href="?bref=Num.12.9-13">Nm 12:9-13</a>), and she was restored, but only after seven shameful days spent outside the camp while Israel waits to resume its march (<a href="?bref=Num.12.14-15">Nm 12:14-15</a>). This sad incident is the last recorded event in Miriam’s public life. She died near the close of the wilderness wanderings at Kadesh and was buried there (<a href="?bref=Num.20.1">20:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Child of Mered, descended from Ezra of Judah’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.17">1 Chr 4:17</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>