<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Mystery">
  <title>Mystery</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MYSTERY</p>
<p class="fl">Counsel, or secret plan, that God shares only with his people. In most biblical passages it relates to the wise counsel of God in his guidance of history to its destiny. The most specific and significant application of the concept of mystery is to the plan of God regarding the death of Christ. It does not refer to a secret that God is unwilling to tell or to something so obscure that it could not be understood even if told.</p>
<p>The passages in which its theological meaning is most clearly seen (among over 30 occurrences in Scripture) are <a href="?bref=Dan.3.18-28">Daniel 3:18-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.4.6">4:6</a> (Septuagint); <a href="?bref=Matt.13.11">Matthew 13:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.11">Mark 4:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.10">Luke 8:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.11.25">Romans 11:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.16.25">16:25</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.7">1 Corinthians 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.1">4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.51">15:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.9">Ephesians 1:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.3.3-6,9-12">3:3-6, 9-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.26-29">Colossians 1:26-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.2.2">2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.7">2 Thessalonians 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.3.9,16">1 Timothy 3:9, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.1.20">Revelation 1:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.10.7">10:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.5-18">17:5-18</a>.</p>
<p>In the passages in Daniel, the emphasis is on the revelation that God gave Daniel concerning the content and meaning of King Nebuchadnezzar’s dream about the future. It is important to note here that the dream was about what God was going to do. No wise man, enchanter, magician or diviner could explain it, but “there is a God in heaven who reveals mysteries” (<a href="?bref=Dan.2.28">Dn 2:28</a>).</p>
<p>Scholarly studies in recent years have determined that similar themes are found in other Jewish writings, including the Dead Sea Scrolls. The stress is on the decisions God has made about the future, especially the end time. The world wrestles with such matters as the problem of evil (i.e., Why, if God is both good and powerful, do people still suffer?). The believer identifies with these problems but knows that God has his providential plans and that one day he will make all things clear. The way God will bring vindication for those who are wronged in this world and judgment to those who do wrong is part of the content of the “mystery” and was a major emphasis in the writings around the time of Christ. God controls the affairs of the universe. The nations will eventually fulfill his purposes.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Matt.13.11">Matthew 13:11</a>, <a href="?bref=Mark.4.11">Mark 4:11</a>, and <a href="?bref=Luke.8.10">Luke 8:10</a> are part of the parables of the kingdom. The kingdom itself is related to the final climactic work of God in history. This is seen in some of the imagery of the parables, such as the harvest, which symbolizes future judgment. Therefore, the word “mystery” is appropriate and significant here. In the immediate context Jesus is explaining why he uses parables. They both vividly illustrate truth and conceal truth from those who are not receptive to it. Therefore, the word “mystery” (plural in Mt and Lk) describes the inner meaning of Jesus’ teaching about the kingdom. Those who accept the message will know its meaning; those who do not will lose not only the meaning but apparently also the opportunity to hear and respond to the message of salvation (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.12-15">Mt 13:12-15</a>).</p>
<p>Another aspect of this passage lies in the unasked question as to why, if the Messiah has come, evil still persists in the world. The servants in one of the parables wanted to pull up the weeds, symbolizing evil or evil persons, but were told to allow them to grow until the time of harvest—that is, the judgment (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.24-30">Mt 13:24-30</a>). The persistence of evil in the world and the way God will eventually deal with it is one of the “mysteries.”</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Rom.11.25">Romans 11:25</a> occurs in a large section (chs <a href="?bref=Rom.9.1-11.36">9–11</a>) that deals with the people of Israel and their future. Once again, the issue concerns a present problem and its future resolution. In this case the problem is the unbelief of Israel. The hardening of Israel during the present time is called a “mystery” (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.25">Rom 11:25</a>). God’s purposes will not be thwarted, however, “and so all Israel will be saved” (v <a href="?bref=Rom.11.26">26</a>). This emphasis on the purposes of God is closely intertwined with the concept of the “mystery” and is basic to this entire passage.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Rom.16.25">Romans 16:25</a> is broader in its scope, connecting the “revelation of the mystery hidden for long ages past” with Paul’s “gospel and the proclamation of Jesus Christ.” Here the focus is more closely on the meaning of the death of Christ.</p>
<p>God’s “secret wisdom” is mentioned in <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.7">1 Corinthians 2:7</a>. The context is the message of the cross that Paul preaches. This message is foolishness to those who consider themselves wise but are lost, and it is the “foolishness” of what is preached that brings salvation to believers (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.18-25">1:18-25</a>). Paul does not attempt to proclaim worldly “wisdom,” but he does declare a “message of wisdom” to those who are spiritually mature (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.6">2:6</a>). To these he speaks the “secret wisdom,” or literally, “wisdom in a secret” (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.7">7</a>). This passage clearly connects the basic concept of “mystery” as the counsel of God with the death of Christ as the means of salvation. It also connects mystery with the process of history (“the rulers of this age”) and with the sweep of God’s purposes from OT times into the future. Verse <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.10">10</a> emphasizes the fact that God has indeed revealed these mysteries to us.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.1">1 Corinthians 4:1</a> Paul again speaks from the context of a contrast between God’s wisdom and that of the world (<a href="?bref=1Cor.3.18-23">3:18-23</a>). He speaks not only of secret things or mysteries but also introduces the concept of stewardship. He has been entrusted with the revelation of God’s mystery and must be faithful in his ministry of declaring it. This theme will reappear in <a href="?bref=Eph.3.2-6">Ephesians 3:2-6</a>.</p>
<p>Paul returns to the relationship of mystery and the end time in <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.51">1 Corinthians 15:51</a>. The earlier passage (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.9-16">2:9-16</a>) showed that human knowledge cannot possibly anticipate what God has planned, but God has revealed this mystery to believers. A major aspect of this revealed mystery is the way in which the faithful will be brought into the presence of God: “Lo! I tell you a mystery. We shall not all sleep, but we shall all be changed, in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trumpet” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.51-52">15:51-52</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The other references to mystery in 1 Corinthians occur in the broad context of chapters <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.1-14.40">12–14</a> dealing with spiritual gifts, which include receiving divine revelation, so the term “mysteries” in <a href="?bref=1Cor.13.2">13:2</a> and <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.2">14:2</a> is appropriate.</p>
<p>Ephesians opens with a series of statements about God’s purpose in history, culminating in the universal headship of Christ (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.10">Eph 1:10</a>). These statements include such terms as “chose,” “destined,” “will,” “purpose,” “plan,” and “counsel.” This is clearly the range of ideas associated with the word “mystery” in ancient Jewish writings, and these ideas shed light on Paul’s use of the summary expression: “For he has made known to us . . . the mystery of his will” (v <a href="?bref=Eph.1.9">9</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Part of God’s purpose was to form a body of believers, reconciled to himself and to each other through the cross (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.14-18">Eph 2:14-18</a>). In this body, Jewish and Gentile believers have been made members together of one body and sharers together in the promise in Christ Jesus, a new phase of God’s revealed plan, which Paul here calls a “mystery” (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.6">3:6</a>). As noted above, Paul himself has a responsibility to minister the truth of this “mystery” faithfully (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.2-5">3:2-5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.1-5">1 Cor 4:1-5</a>).</p>
<p>Colossians continues to show Paul’s sense of responsibility regarding this “mystery,” which is now identified with the “word of God” (<a href="?bref=Col.1.25-29">Col 1:25-29</a>). Once again there is the idea of the span of history linked with the mystery that is known only by revelation: “the mystery that has been kept hidden for ages and generations, but is now disclosed to the saints” (v <a href="?bref=Col.1.26">26</a>). As in Ephesians, the church is the locus for the working out of God’s mystery, “which is Christ in you, the hope of glory” (v <a href="?bref=Col.1.27">27</a>). This Christ is proclaimed in wisdom, so that believers may reach mature completion in him (v <a href="?bref=Col.1.28">28</a>). The Colossian believers are asked to pray for Paul as he preaches this “mystery” (<a href="?bref=Col.4.3">4:3</a>).</p>
<p>It is made clear in <a href="?bref=1Tim.3.16">1 Timothy 3:16</a> that the “mystery of godliness” includes the basic elements associated with the “mystery,” such as its manifestation in the world and ultimate vindication. However, this grand plan of God does not unfold without opposition. In connection with the coming of the end time, Paul again mentions a mystery. This time it is a dark mystery, called the “secret power of lawlessness” (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.7">2 Thes 2:7</a>). A similar evil force, “Babylon the Great, the Mother of Prostitutes,” is introduced in the book of Revelation with the word “mystery” (<a href="?bref=Rev.17.5">Rv 17:5</a>). Perhaps the idea is that there are forces counter to God whose workings are also impossible for humans to understand. God’s truth and power will, however, prevail over these, as he brings his own mystery, his wise counsel, to fulfillment.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Rev.10.6-7">Revelation 10:6-7</a> declares this fulfillment. The ages of waiting in perplexity, of enduring evil, are over, as the angel announces, “There will be no more delay!” The time has finally come when “the mystery of God will be accomplished.” Note the dynamic quality of the mystery in this context. It is not just static truth but something that can be “accomplished.” This great climax to history is in accord with God’s previous revelation “to his servants, the prophets.” The mystery, then, is God’s wise counsel, which both guides history and is revealed in its culmination. It expresses God’s answer to the problem of evil and the vain opposition by evil powers. It declares the meaning of the central event in history, the death of Christ, and reveals the results of the resurrection in the ultimate transformation of all believers at the coming of Christ.</p>
  </body>
</item>