<items release="1.6">
<item typename="DictionaryLetter" name="W" product="TyndaleBibleDict">
  <body>
<p class="h1">W</p>
  <p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wadi_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wadi*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wages_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wages</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Waheb_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Waheb</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Walnut_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Walnut*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WanderingsintheWilderness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wanderings in the Wilderness</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WarHoly_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">War*, Holy</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Warfare_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Warfare</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WaroftheSonsofLightagainsttheSonsofDarkness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">War of the Sons of Light against the Sons of Darkness*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WarsoftheLordBookofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wars of the Lord, Book of the</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Watch_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Watch</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Watchman_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Watchman</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Watchtower_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Watchtower</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Water_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Water</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WaterGate_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Water Gate</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WaterHen_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Water Hen*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WaterLily_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Water Lily*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WatersofMerom_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Waters of Merom</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WaveOffering_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wave Offering*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Waythe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Way, the</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wealth_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wealth</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Weapons_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Weapons</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Weasel_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Weasel*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Weaving_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Weaving</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wedding_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wedding</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Weeds_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Weeds</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Week_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Week</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WeeksFeastof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Weeks*, Feast of</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WeightsandMeasures_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Weights and Measures</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Well_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Well</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WesternText_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Western Text*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Whale_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Whale*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wheat_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wheat</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wheel_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wheel</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Whirlwind_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Whirlwind</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=White_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">White</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Whore_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Whore</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wickedness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wickedness</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Widow_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Widow</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wife_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wife</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wilderness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WildOx_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wild Ox</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WildVine_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wild Vine</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WillofGod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Will of God</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Willow_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Willow</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WillowsRavineofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Willows, Ravine of the</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wine_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wine</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Winepress_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Winepress</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wineskins_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wineskins</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Winnower_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Winnower</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wisdom_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wisdom</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WisdomLiterature_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wisdom Literature*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WisdomofJesusBenSirach_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wisdom of Jesus Ben Sirach</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WisdomofSolomon_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wisdom of Solomon</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WiseMen_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wise Men</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WitchWitchcraft_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Witch*, Witchcraft</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WitheredHand_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Withered Hand*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Witness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Witness</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WitnessAltarof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Witness, Altar of</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wizard_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wizard*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Woe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Woe</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wolf_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wolf</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Woman_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Woman</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wonders_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wonders</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wool_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wool</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WordWordofGodWordsofGod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Word, Word of God, Words of God</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Work_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Work</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=World_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">World</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Worm_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Worm</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Wormwood_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wormwood*</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Worship_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Worship</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=WrathofGod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wrath of God</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Writer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Writer</a></p>
<p class="toc"><a href="?item=Writing_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Writing</a></p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wadi">
  <title>Wadi*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WADI*</p>
<p class="fl">Intermittent stream or torrent in the arid and semiarid regions of the Middle East. Although the streambeds were usually dry, they could attain flood stage during spring runoff or after heavy rainfalls. The most significant wadi in the Bible was the Wadi of Egypt (“Brook of Egypt” in modern versions), which served as the southwestern border of Canaan according to God’s instructions to Moses (<a href="?bref=Num.34.5">Nm 34:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.15.4,47">Jos 15:4, 47</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.65">1 Kgs 8:65</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.27.12">Is 27:12</a>). During the dry periods, wadis were important as roadways.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wages">
  <title>Wages</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WAGES</p>
<p class="fl">Payment received by a laborer in return for his work. Usually wages are calculated in terms of a medium of exchange, such as money, but they can be paid in any kind of goods or services. Jacob worked seven years in return for Laban’s younger daughter, Rachel (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.18-20">Gn 29:18-20</a>), and then had to work another seven years when Laban did not honor his agreement. Later, Jacob’s wages were sheep and goats (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.31-32">30:31-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.31.8">31:8</a>). Nebuchadnezzar was given the country of Egypt as wages for his work in capturing the city of Tyre (<a href="?bref=Ezek.29.18-20">Ez 29:18-20</a>).</p>
<p>Usually wages were agreed upon by employer and employee (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.15-19">Gn 29:15-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.20.2">Mt 20:2</a>), but sometimes the pay was at the discretion of the employer (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.4">Mt 20:4</a>). A fair wage for honest work is a biblical principle (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.7">Lk 10:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.5.18">1 Tm 5:18</a>). The Lord established laws to cover this principle and judged those who violated it. Wages were to be paid promptly (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.13">Lv 19:13</a>); the holding back of wages is condemned in the Scripture (<a href="?bref=Mal.3.5">Mal 3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.5.1-6">Jas 5:1-6</a>).</p>
<p>Wages were often a source of discontent and dispute between employer and employee. When soldiers came to John the Baptist to be baptized and asked about their future conduct, he urged them to be content with their wages (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.14">Lk 3:14</a>). Jacob and Laban had disagreements about wages and twice Jacob complained, “You have changed my wages ten times” (<a href="?bref=Gen.31.7,41">Gn 31:7, 41</a>).</p>
<p>The Bible also speaks of ill-gotten wages. The wages of a prostitute could not be brought into the house of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.18">Dt 23:18</a>), and people are warned against the error of Balaam, who corrupted Israel because he “loved the wages of unrighteousness” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.2.15">2 Pt 2:15</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Money_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Money</a>; <a href="?item=BankerBanking_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Banker, Banking</a>; <a href="?item=Poorthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Poor, The</a>; <a href="?item=Riches_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Riches</a>; <a href="?item=Work_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Work</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Waheb">
  <title>Waheb</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WAHEB</p>
<p class="fl">Town in the area of Suphah (<a href="?bref=Num.21.14">Nm 21:14</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Suphah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Suphah</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Walnut">
  <title>Walnut*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WALNUT*</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WanderingsintheWilderness">
  <title>Wanderings in the Wilderness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WANDERINGS IN THE WILDERNESS</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WarHoly">
  <title>War*, Holy</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WAR*, Holy</p>
<p class="fl">Warfare as described in the book of Deuteronomy, especially in chapter <a href="?bref=Deut.20.1-20">20</a>. Not merely a human enterprise fought by kings with trained soldiers and military equipment, it is God’s war in which he himself is involved together with his covenant people who are selected to fight in his name. The size of the army is not important; indeed, sometimes the numbers were pared down to dramatize the fact that the victory was gained, not by military superiority, but by the action of God against his enemies. When Israel lived in obedience to God as his covenant people and went into battle under his direction, war was within the will of God, commanded by him, and accomplished through trust in him. God was known as “a man of war,” and it is declared that “the battle is the Lord’s” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.17.47">1 Sm 17:47</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.18.17">18:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.25.28">25:28</a>). With this faith on the part of the Jews, it is easy to see how a concept of holy war developed, especially when they had the conviction that their enemies were God’s enemies and that they were the people through whom God would carry out his saving purposes for the world.</p>
<p>Moses believed that God declared war and sent his people into battle (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.16">Ex 17:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.31.3">Nm 31:3</a>). On several occasions, at crucial points in warfare, the “terror of the Lord” fell upon the enemy, enabling the numerically inferior army of Israel to gain an easy victory over vastly superior forces (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.10-14">Jos 10:10-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.4.12-16">Jgs 4:12-16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.5.24-25">2 Sm 5:24-25</a>). In a time of acute military crisis, Elisha was enabled to see the heavenly army of Yahweh drawn up on the hills around Samaria, ready to defeat the fierce, invading armies of Syria. In response to Elisha’s prayer, the Syrian soldiers were struck with blindness and rendered helpless against the Israelites (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.15-23">2 Kgs 6:15-23</a>). Various means were used to determine the will of God and to assure his active participation in war. In addition to the word of the prophet (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.5-23">1 Kgs 22:5-23</a>), Urim and Thummim (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.30">Ex 28:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.8">Lv 8:8</a>), the ephod (<a href="?bref=1Sam.30.7">1 Sm 30:7</a>), and the ark of the covenant were employed for this purpose. The leaders of God’s troops constantly sought his direction for military strategy during the progress of battle, for no step was to be taken without divine approval and guidance (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.19-23">2 Sm 5:19-23</a>).</p>
<p>Since God gave Palestine to his own people, the Jews, the land was indeed the Promised Land; it belonged by divine covenant to Israel and was in that sense “the Holy Land.” Any defense of that land against foreign invasion was a holy war. The invading enemy was trespassing upon sacred territory that belonged to God’s people by immutable decree and thus incurred the divine wrath. From this perspective the complete destruction of Israel’s enemies was necessary, particularly when the enemy was pagan and morally corrupt. A characteristic Hebrew word used for this concept, <span class="hebrew">herem</span><span class="ital">,</span> originally meant “devoted” and came to mean “devoted to destruction” as something hostile to the rule of God (<a href="?bref=Josh.6.17-18">Jos 6:17-18</a>). The divine plan must not be thwarted, obstructed, or aborted by any debasing idolatry or corrupting immorality (<a href="?bref=Deut.7.1-26">Dt 7</a>). Enemy cities within the boundaries of the land promised to the Jews were to be utterly destroyed—a practice known as “the ban.” Only silver, gold, and vessels of bronze and iron were to be spared. They were to be placed in the treasury of the Lord as sacred to him (<a href="?bref=Josh.6.17-21">Jos 6:17-21</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.15.3">1 Sm 15:3</a>).</p>
<p>There was a distinctly teleological aspect to the concept of holy war. It looked beyond the triumphs of God in specific battles to the conclusion of all hostilities and to a final time of peace that will vindicate the righteousness and sovereignty of God’s saving purposes and display his concern and goal for his own people. The final consummation will be preceded by a massive holy war, after which the weapons of warfare will be transformed into implements of peace (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.4">Is 2:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.4.3">Mi 4:3</a>) under the reign of the Messiah, the Prince of Peace (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.6">Is 9:6</a>), who will subdue all God’s enemies in a triumphant Day of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Ps.110.1-7">Ps 110</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.7.1-28">Dn 7</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.14.1-21">Zec 14</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Warfare">
  <title>Warfare</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WARFARE</p>
<p class="fl">The means by which one nation seeks to impose its will upon another by force. An index to the importance of warfare in antiquity is provided by the amount of technical skill directed to perfecting devices for destruction and defense.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="InstrumentsOfWarfare"/>
<p class="h2" id="MethodsofWarfare">Methods of Warfare</p>
<p class="h3">Standard Combat</p>
<p class="fl">Cavalry units were introduced at the close of the second millennium <span class="era">BC</span> and the beginning of the first. The cavalry charge provided a shock force to the great armies, and the cavalry’s mobility permitted concentration of firepower at decisive points. When the Assyrians coordinated their infantry, cavalry, and chariot corps into a powerful battle machine, smaller neighboring nations were more and more compelled to retreat behind their fortifications. They could not hope to engage the massive Assyrian army in standard combat in open terrain. No period is richer in illustrated monuments than Iron Age II; the Assyrian war reliefs present detailed illustrations of their conquests and the size of fortified cities. The few scenes depicting standard combat in open terrain show chariots charging from all directions and engaging the enemy at all stages of a battle. Other formations carry out mopping-up operations, finishing off pockets of enemy resistance remaining after the chariot charge.</p>
<p>The factor of terrain was always very important. In standard combat on open terrain it became conventional to place the best troops on the right side of the line. A Greek commander, Epaminodas (d. 362 <span class="era">BC</span>), introduced the variant of a slanting attack by a strengthened left wing, taking the Spartan army completely by surprise. Philip of Macedon and his son Alexander continued to surprise their enemies with variations on a plan of attack based on the phalanx.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="HelmetsAndArmorInBibleTimes"/>
<p class="h3">Battle in Open Terrain: The Duel</p>
<p class="fl">During certain periods in the ancient Near East, the duel presented an alternative to standard combat. The duel was a contest between two champions who represented the contending forces. The two armies would agree in advance to abide by the outcome of the fight. The duel was meant to avoid the heavy casualties of full-scale warfare. The earliest detailed written account of this unique form of warfare occurs in the Tale of Sinuhe. A chamberlain in the royal court of the 12th dynasty, Sinuhe voluntarily went into exile and traveled to northern Palestine and Syria, where he lived among Semitic tribes. There he was challenged to a duel by a local champion, whom he defeated and whose goods he then plundered.</p>
<p>Although the duel was common among other armies in subsequent periods, it was evidently unknown to Israel before the encounter between David and Goliath (<a href="?bref=1Sam.17.1-58">1 Sm 17</a>). The Philistine army had penetrated Judah as far as Socoh and were arrayed on one hill. Drawn up against them on an opposite hill was the army of Saul. The valley of Elah separated the two camps. The Israelites were challenged daily by the Philistine champion, Goliath, who proposed that the battle be decided through combat between two warriors. David accepted his proposal, but when he killed Goliath, the Philistines fled, unwilling to honor the terms of the prior agreement. The Israelite army then entered the contest, pursuing the Philistines and inflicting heavy casualties.</p>
<p class="h3">Assaults on Fortified Cities</p>
<p class="fl">Most cities in the ancient Near East were located at sites that could be defended against attack and that possessed economic advantages. An assault on a fortified city presented opposite problems for attacker and defender. The actions of one were a direct response to the actions of the other. Systems of defense were intended to thwart methods of attack, which in turn were designed to penetrate systems of defense.</p>
<p>There were five possible ways of conquering a fortified city: penetration from above the fortifications; direct penetration through the fortifications; penetration from below the fortifications; siege; and penetration by ruse. On many occasions, a combination of two or more methods was necessary to breach the defensive network.</p>
<p>The biblical narrative of the conquest of Shechem by Abimelech (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.1-57">Jgs 9</a>) gives an account of an assault on a fortified city in the period of the judges (Iron Age I). When the people of Shechem and their allies rebelled against Abimelech, he retaliated by attacking the city, advancing his army of mercenaries by night and launching an assault from ambush positions at dawn (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.32-35">9:32-35</a>). The men of Shechem engaged in open battle outside the city gates but were forced to retreat behind the security of the city walls. The next day Abimelech directed his assault against the city itself. Dividing his forces into three groups, he assumed direct command of one, which he committed to an attack on the city gates at the decisive moment of battle (vv <a href="?bref=Judg.9.43-44">43-44</a>). The gate was breached and the main walls seized, but the city’s surviving defenders fled to an inner citadel, the temple of Baal-berith.</p>
<p>Many reliefs depict groups of soldiers defending an inner citadel after a city’s wall was breached. Archaeological excavations at Shechem confirm that its temple, like those in other Canaanite cities, was built in the form of a fortified tower, supported by stout bastions near the entrance. The tower of Shechem was thus strongly fortified and occupied only a small area, enabling its defenders to concentrate their firepower on Abimelech’s troops. Since it could not be taken by storm, Abimelech ordered his soldiers to use their battle-axes to cut brushwood, which was piled against the stronghold and set on fire (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.48-49">Jgs 9:48-49</a>). All of the defenders within the tower died.</p>
<p>An assault on an inner citadel was always a hazardous undertaking for an attacking army, as shown in the sequel to the capture of Shechem’s tower. Abimelech turned his attention next to the city of Thebez and followed the same plan of assault that had proved successful at Shechem. But as he was preparing to burn the door of the tower to which the defenders had fled, his skull was crushed by a piece of millstone dropped on him by a woman (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.50-53">Jgs 9:50-53</a>). The incident was remembered and became proverbial for the danger of approaching too closely the walls of a fortified tower (<a href="?bref=2Sam.11.19-21">2 Sm 11:19-21</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Communications and Intelligence</p>
<p class="fl">From the patriarchal period (middle Bronze period), we have detailed written information on the use of communications systems in wartime. The documents from Mari on the Euphrates provide evidence for a well-developed communications system based on signaling. Signals were flashed by torches or firebrands at night in accordance with a prearranged code. The system was widely used in Mesopotamia and elsewhere to call for immediate help when a city was under attack.</p>
<p>In the late Bronze period horsemen were sometimes employed for isolated communication functions. Intelligence services played a role in planning and executing military operations. The importance of intelligence and the use of spies or scouts is stressed in the biblical accounts of the conquest of the land of Canaan. Before entering the land, Moses sent men on an espionage mission. He instructed them to gather information on the topography of the land, to observe the relative strength of its inhabitants, to determine whether the land was fertile, to survey the cities and see if they were fortified, and to report on the character of the land—whether it was capable of sustaining a large population (<a href="?bref=Num.13.17-20">Nm 13:17-20</a>).</p>
<p>Tactical intelligence was very important. Joshua dispatched spies to Jericho and to Ai before beginning military operations against them (<a href="?bref=Josh.2.1">Jos 2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.7.2">7:2</a>). The reports he received about the offensive spirit and strength of the Canaanites enabled him to formulate an attack plan. In the period of the judges the conquest of Bethel (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.22-26">Jgs 1:22-26</a>) was due directly to intelligence gathered by a reconnaissance patrol. The tribes of Joseph sent out scouts to keep the city under observation. It was strongly fortified and seemed impregnable. The scouts captured a man who emerged from the city—presumably not through the main gate, which was shut tight, but through a concealed postern or tunnel. In exchange for his own life and the safety of his family, he disclosed the location of the passage leading beneath the walls. The city was penetrated through the tunnel and captured.</p>
<p class="h3">Attack and Penetration: The Breach</p>
<p class="fl">Direct penetration through the fortifications of an ancient city meant breaching the gate or the main walls by using hammers, axes, pikes, spears, swords, or a battering ram. Illustrated monuments and written documents indicate that early in the middle Bronze period fortified cities were being attacked with battering rams. The earliest known illustration of a ram appears in a siege scene in the wall paintings from Beni Hasan (20th century <span class="era">BC</span>). The ram pictured is a relatively simple device, consisting of a hutlike structure with a slightly pointed roof, which could be moved near a fortress with the help of two parallel crossbars. The structure provided cover for two or three soldiers who operated by hand a very long pole with a sharp tip, presumably of metal.</p>
<p>The Mari documents provide information for the period 200 years later. They mention the effectiveness of battering rams constructed largely of wood. Although very heavy, the siege weapon could be moved over long distances. One document speaks of the use of a wagon drawn by draft animals and of a boat to transport a battering ram to the site of a besieged city.</p>
<p>Moving a battering ram into position always exposed the demolition unit to heavy fire from defenders on the walls above them. Its heaviness made it cumbersome to move. Moreover, the ground adjacent to the walls was usually rough, rocky, and steep. When the chosen point of penetration was a section of the wall, an assault force had to construct an earthen ramp, occasionally strengthened on the top surface and sides with wooden planks or stones. The ramp provided a track along which the battering ram could be moved from the foot of the slope to the outer wall. Once moved into operational position, the ram had to be braked to prevent it from rolling back. The building of such a ramp was evidently necessary in Joab’s campaign against the fortified city of Abel in Beth-maacah (<a href="?bref=2Sam.20.15">2 Sm 20:15</a>). The biblical account indicates that some sort of battering ram was in use in Israel under King David during the early monarchy.</p>
<p>The earliest Assyrian reliefs show that protection of the penetration units was a major consideration. High, mobile assault towers constructed of wood operated in tandem with a battering ram. Such towers, moved into position near a breach operation and manned by archers, provided covering fire directed against the defenders on the wall. Siege towers neutralized the defenders’ advantage in firepower and drew fire away from the crew engaged in breaching the walls.</p>
<p>The details of the Assyrian reliefs make it possible to visualize clearly the fate of Jerusalem, as announced to the prophet Ezekiel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.4.1-3">Ez 4:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.21.22">21:22</a>). The gate was the focal point of attack because it was the weakest point in the wall. Moreover, the path leading up to the gate made construction of a special ramp unnecessary. In the demolition of a gate, swords were sometimes used to pry the doors loose and to tear down hinges. Wooden doors unprotected by metal were often set on fire.</p>
<p>The battering ram continued to be used as an engine for breaching walls in the Hellenistic-Roman period. In 63 <span class="era">BC</span> the Roman commander Pompey brought up battering rams from Tyre against the defenders of Jerusalem, and with them penetrated the fortified wall that enclosed the temple. The siege machine shown on Trajan’s column had a beam with an iron head shaped like a ram. It was moved up to a wall in a frame protected by a wooden roof covered with clay or hides. A variation equipped for boring into a wall was used by Titus when besieging Jerusalem in <span class="era">AD</span> 70.</p>
<p>The battering ram was not the only device used to effect a breach in a wall. Troops trained as sappers would tear down a section of the wall by using sharp-headed levers (pikes, swords, spears) or even sledgehammers (cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.26.8-9">Ez 26:8-9</a>). In Ashurnasirpal’s army such men were issued full-length coats of mail to cover their whole bodies. Under later Assyrian kings, they were protected by both round and rectangular shields, which they carried on their backs when engaged in demolition. Later, Ashurbanipal relied exclusively on such sappers for direct penetration of a fortified city. He designed for their protection a huge shield, the curved head of which could be propped against the wall, screening the sapper from missiles while he worked beneath it.</p>
<p class="h3">Scaling the Walls</p>
<p class="fl">A battle scene depicted on limestone in the tomb of Anta at Dashashe in Upper Egypt (24th century <span class="era">BC</span>) provides the earliest known representation of siege activities. It shows the Egyptians raising a scaling ladder against the walls of a fortified city. By the time of Sargon, the thickness of walls was increased considerably, which permitted construction of much higher walls, more resistant to scaling. Such solid, massive walls also tended to blunt the effectiveness of a battering ram. Sargon, and especially his successor Ashurbanipal, responded by constructing longer scaling ladders, some of which could reach a height of from 25 to 30 feet (7.6 to 9.1 meters), judging from the number of rungs.</p>
<p class="h3">Penetration beneath the Walls</p>
<p class="fl">A tunneling operation could be started beyond the range of any weapons at the disposal of the defenders. Once underground, the penetration unit was shielded from enemy fire. The tunneling could be accomplished under cover of night, so that the element of surprise could be exploited to the maximum. It was, however, a lengthy process requiring considerable technical skill. Moreover, if the operation was detected by the defenders before its completion, they could destroy the penetration unit as it emerged from the tunnel. Attempts to penetrate fortified cities by tunneling beneath the walls was a characteristic feature of warfare in Iron Age II. That is confirmed by reliefs, written documents, and archaeological excavation of sites dating to this period, where the remains of attack tunnels have been discovered.</p>
<p class="h3">Siege</p>
<p class="fl">Particularly when a walled city was situated on a high hill, an extended siege provided an alternate method of conquering it. By encircling the city and preventing aid or supplies from reaching its defenders, the attacking army could starve the inhabitants out. That procedure minimized the element of risk for the attacking army. Its success depended upon their capacity to prevent outside assistance from reaching the city and the defenders from leaving it. An army would generally resort to siege when a city’s fortifications were too powerful for direct penetration. The siege of Samaria by the Assyrians lasted for three years (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.9-10">2 Kgs 18:9-10</a>).</p>
<p>The peculiar conditions of siege produced the catapult, a major innovation of Greek artillery and a logical improvement on the bow and the sling. Designed originally as a strengthened bow mounted on a stand and used to fire arrows only, it was introduced around 400 <span class="era">BC</span> by Demetrius I. He may have borrowed the idea from the Phoenicians at Carthage.</p>
<p>In the course of time the instrument was improved. The perfect weapon, called the torsion catapult, derived its power from many tightly twisted strands of elastic material, frequently supplied by women’s hair, which could be tightened with a windlass and then released suddenly. Firing arrows, large stones, or fire-baskets with an effective range of 200 yards (182.9 meters), a catapult could clear a wall of its defenders while a battering ram breached it or a boarding party attacked from a mobile tower.</p>
<p>For those in a besieged city, the critical problems were food and water supplies. The horror of famine is stressed in the biblical account of the siege of Samaria by the Syrian Ben-hadad in the days of the prophet Elisha. On that occasion women were reduced to eating their children (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.26-29">2 Kgs 6:26-29</a>). A besieging army would do everything in its power to aggravate such conditions. In one of the siege reliefs of Ashurnasirpal II, a defender has lowered a bucket from the wall to draw water from a stream below; an Assyrian soldier is shown cutting the rope with his dagger.</p>
<p class="h3">Ruses and Stratagems</p>
<p class="fl">Various ruses and stratagems could draw the defenders out of a city or infiltrate troops into the city. If a small force could enter a city by a cunning stratagem, it could overpower the guards and open the city gates to an attacking army. A city’s fortifications were of little value once an enemy had entered the city. Moreover, penetrating a city’s defenses at any one point frequently caused the entire defense system to collapse. The story of the Trojan horse is probably the most celebrated account of a stratagem circumventing the defense of a strongly fortified ancient city.</p>
<p>In the biblical account of the siege of Samaria by Ben-hadad, a sudden lifting of the Syrian siege led Joram, the king of Israel, to suspect a ruse. He refused to believe the report of four lepers that the Syrians had gone, leaving behind large food supplies (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.7.12">2 Kgs 7:12</a>). That was the same kind of tactic that Joshua had employed at Ai (<a href="?bref=Josh.8.3-8">Jos 8:3-8</a>).</p>
<p>On other occasions, powerful armies sought to break down resistance by psychological warfare, as in the unsuccessful attempt by Sennacherib to capture Jerusalem in the time of Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.1-19.37">2 Kgs 18–19</a>). The dialogue between the Assyrian general and Hezekiah’s delegates reveals that the Assyrian was trying to shake the confidence of the city’s defenders.</p>
<p>The ambush was a type of ruse used to trap and destroy an enemy at a moment when he was least able to counter a sudden, unexpected blow. Its effectiveness depended almost entirely on the element of surprise. By taking advantage of good intelligence, knowledge of the terrain, and the cover of night, a small force could stage a devastating ambush against vastly superior numbers.</p>
<p>The ambush was a standard method of combat during the period of the conquest of Canaan. The fall of Ai, for example, was due directly to the tactical success of an ambush (<a href="?bref=Josh.8.1-23">Jos 8:1-23</a>). Under cover of night, Joshua was able to move a large force to a concealed position behind the city. He then led the remainder of the Israelite army to the edge of a valley north of the fortified city, giving the appearance of a planned assault on the city. The diversion, as calculated, drew the main force of Ai away from the city to engage Israel on the plain of Arabah. When the Israelites fell back, appearing to be badly beaten, the remaining defenders of the city were summoned to pursue Joshua’s fleeing army. With the city left undefended, the main Israelite strike force rose from its ambush position, poured into the city, and set it on fire. Too late, the men of Ai saw the smoke from their burning city and realized the stratagem. Joshua’s army turned to counterattack their pursuers, who found themselves trapped between two bodies of Israelite forces. Assaulted from both front and rear, the king of Ai’s army was annihilated, victim of an effectively laid ambush.</p>
<p class="h2" id="FortificationsandDefense">Fortifications and Defense</p>
<p class="fl">The earliest known fortifications in the world, dated by some to about 7000 <span class="era">BC</span>, were discovered in 1954 at Jericho. They were impressive in conception and construction. The core of the defense system was a wall, part of which, bordering the western edge of the ancient city, was still standing to a height of 21 feet (6.4 meters). Further excavation uncovered a large moat that had been carved out of solid rock at the base of the wall, 27 feet (8.2 meters) wide and 9 feet (2.7 meters) deep. How that feat was accomplished when the only tools assumed to have been available were made of stone is a complete mystery. A third component of Jericho’s defense system was a huge stone circular tower 30 feet (9.1 meters) high, once evidently attached to the inner side of the western part of the wall. The exact purpose of the tower has not yet been determined, but Neolithic Jericho provides the earliest evidence of a fortified city supported by a wall, tower, and moat.</p>
<p>By the middle Bronze period, there were four components in a standard defense system: a moat, an advance (outer) wall, the main (inner) wall, and a well-fortified gate structure. The moat, advance wall, and subsidiary fortifications protecting the steep slope and lower portion of the main wall were intended to prevent breaching by a battering ram.</p>
<p class="h3">City Walls</p>
<p class="fl">Erection of a simple wall could halt a hostile advance only temporarily, since walls could be scaled or breached. Walls therefore provided a firing platform so defenders could repel attacks. The wall system consisted of three principal components: the wall itself, constituting the barrier; an upper structure, which provided the firing platform and cover for the defenders; and a series of obstacles and traps erected in front of the wall to keep archers at a distance and to prevent operation of a battering ram.</p>
<p>The battlement—a parapet built along the outer top edge of the wall—provided the defenders with a measure of security, freedom for mobility, and openings through which fire could be directed. From a distance the square notches looked like a row of teeth with gaps between them. The teeth, called merlons, provided a protective barrier against hostile missiles. The gaps, called embrasures or crenels, supplied openings through which the defenders could discharge their weapons. Special towers protruded from the outer face of the wall, spaced at a distance no greater than the double range of a bow. Such towers enabled the defenders to fire at troops who managed to reach the walls. One way of protecting the main wall was to construct an outer or advance wall that could be breached or climbed only under heavy fire from defending units on the battlements of the main wall. Another method was to dig a wide, deep moat around the base of the main wall. A moat kept the enemy from using a battering ram unless they could bridge the moat or fill it up at certain points, under concentrated fire from the defenders.</p>
<p>Casemate fortifications, introduced in the middle Bronze period, were developed from double walls built of dressed stones. The space between the walls was divided into chambers, or casemates, used for storage or dwellings. The Hittite casemate system, introduced into Palestine at least as early as the time of Saul, was widely adopted in Syria and Palestine. A fine example has been discovered at Gibeah, where Saul’s citadel was located, dating to the end of the 11th century <span class="era">BC</span>. The overall thickness of the double walls, including the casemates, reaches 15 feet (4.6 meters). The same type of construction has been found in excavations of three Solomonic cities—Hazor, Gezer, and Megiddo (cf. <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.15">1 Kgs 9:15</a>)—where the casemate walls have an overall thickness of 18 feet (5.5 meters).</p>
<p>Although the divided kingdoms of Judah and Israel were not noted for technical advancements in offensive warfare, a number of their kings worked at improving fortifications and means of defense. Uzziah was especially remembered for his accomplishments in defensive warfare. Along with other measures, “he produced machines mounted on the walls of Jerusalem, designed by brilliant men to shoot arrows and hurl stones from the towers and the corners of the wall” (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.15">2 Chr 26:15</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Those “machines” were special protective structures built to facilitate the task of the archers and to permit huge stones to be dropped on the heads of assaulting troops.</p>
<p class="h3">Gate</p>
<p class="fl">It was inevitable that the gate would be the focus of action in any assault on a fortified city. City gates were therefore designed to expose an attacking army to the greatest risk while providing maximum security to the defenders. The road approaching a city on a hill would wind up the slope, climbing obliquely to the left or the right. Such roads were usually laid out to reach the gate from the right, so an attacker would have to expose the right side of his body to the defenders on the wall. Since he carried his shield in his left hand, that made him more vulnerable.</p>
<p>To prevent the heavy wooden doors of the gate from being set on fire, they were usually plated with metal. A gate wide enough for chariots required double doors, making the line at the center where the two doors met the weakest point in the barrier. Double doors were therefore fitted with huge bolts and fortified with a heavy beam running across the back of both door panels and held in place by sockets set in the doorposts.</p>
<p>Another component in the defense complex at a gate consisted of towers erected on either side of the gate and protruding from the outer face of the wall. Enemy soldiers trying to smash the doors with axes or set them on fire with torches were thus exposed to heavy flanking fire from defensive units on the towers. From a roof over the gate having a balcony, concentrated firepower could be poured down on attackers’ heads. The addition of such auxiliary structures transformed a gate into a small fortress.</p>
<p class="h3">Inner Citadel</p>
<p class="fl">A major weakness of a city’s walls and gate was the magnitude of the circumference. An average-size city might have a perimeter of half a mile (.8 kilometer); a larger city, a perimeter of over a mile (1.6 kilometers). Yet the entire wall had to be defended against breaching, scaling, or tunneling. An attacking army would use diversionary tactics to keep defenders dispersed along the entire perimeter but concentrate their primary assault at one point in the wall. Once the wall was breached, perimeter fortifications served no further defensive purpose. Therefore, internal walls were often added to subdivide a city into several sections, each capable of independent defense. Also, on the highest point of land within the city a citadel would be constructed as a self-contained defensive unit.</p>
<p>The earliest examples of such fortifications, called migdols, are found in the late Bronze Age. They were originally small citadels built to guard important military targets such as sources of water, strategic routes, cultivated farmlands, or frontiers. A migdol of that type was discovered in Israel, not far from Ashdod, in 1960. It was square in plan, with rectangular bastions, and was two stories high, just like structures depicted in Egyptian reliefs from the same period. The same design was used to fortify temples inside of cities. Such fortified temples served as places of refuge and as a city’s final defense once its walls had been breached (cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.9.45-51">Jgs 9:45-51</a>).</p>
<p>In a later period an inner citadel could embrace a complex consisting of the fortified palace of the governor, dwellings of his chief ministers, and sometimes the temple. Such citadels resembled fortified cities, possessing a main wall, a gateway, an outer wall, and occasionally a moat. Being small in area and heavily fortified, citadels could be defended in a final effort by the governor and remaining inhabitants. Presumably Zimri could have held out against Omri’s army for an extended period in the citadel of Tirzah, had he not committed suicide by setting it on fire (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.17-18">1 Kgs 16:17-18</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Water Supply under Siege</p>
<p class="fl">Unless provision was made to keep a city’s inhabitants supplied with food and water during a protracted siege, no defense system could be effective. Several Judean kings made efforts to solve the food-storage problem. Rehoboam, for example, fortified a number of cities located on the western, eastern, and southern borders of his kingdom and made them centers for the storage of food, oil, and wine (<a href="?bref=2Chr.11.5-11">2 Chr 11:5-11</a>).</p>
<p>Storage of food was easier than storage of water. Cisterns built to collect rainwater were a partial answer, but cisterns often ran dry, particularly in times of drought. Cities were sometimes built on the banks of a stream or river, using the stream as part of the city’s defense system. But for a city built on a hill, the source of water might be a spring located at the foot of the slope and outside the city walls. Sometimes the mouth of the spring could be blocked and its location concealed from the enemy while still allowing access by the inhabitants. At Megiddo a vertical shaft 100 feet (274.3 meters) deep was connected by a horizontal tunnel about 200 feet (548.6 meters) long to the water supply at the western end of the city, beyond the fortifications. The work was undertaken in the time of either Solomon or Ahab.</p>
<p>The most celebrated measures to guarantee a supply of fresh water in a time of siege were those taken by Hezekiah at Jerusalem. That engineering achievement is recalled in all the summaries of his reign, both in the Bible and in the “Praise of Famous Men” in the apocryphal book of Ecclesiasticus (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.20">2 Kgs 20:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.32.30">2 Chr 32:30</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.48.17">Ecclus 48:17</a>). The prodigious feat commemorated in those references was the sealing of the spring of Gihon and the cutting of an 1,800-foot (548.6-meter) channel through solid rock in order to bring water into a reservoir in the city. How it was accomplished was reported by Hezekiah himself in the famous Siloam inscription. Two crews, working with hammers, wedges, and pickaxes, began at opposite ends. The crew that began at the spring was able to take advantage of the older tunnel (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.22.11">Is 22:11</a>). They turned due south, in the direction of the city. The other crew, starting from the reservoir, began in a northeasterly direction. They then turned southeast until they reached the north-south line followed by the crew tunneling from the spring, when they turned due north to meet them. The two crews almost passed each other, being about five feet (1.5 meters) apart, but a shout from one was heard through a crevice in the rock by the other. Both parties turned sharply right, and the tunnel was completed. Hezekiah’s precautionary step, taken before Sennacherib’s invasion of Judah, helps to explain why the Assyrians were unable to subdue Jerusalem by the siege tactics that had earlier subdued Samaria in the time of Sargon.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HebrewMilitaryOrganization">Hebrew Military Organization</p>
<p class="h3">Tribal Army</p>
<p class="fl">In their exodus from Egypt the Israelites were organized by tribes and divisions. That systematic arrangement for their trek through the wilderness provided a precedent for military organization. After the sojourn at Mt Sinai, the 12 tribes were divided into divisions or army corps, and certain grades in military rank began to appear. The “officers of the army” (<a href="?bref=Num.31.14">Nm 31:14</a>) had command over units of 1,000 or 100 men, which suggests that the tribal army was divided into decimal units. At a later period there is reference to units of 1,000 (the division), 100 (the company), 50 (the platoon), and 10 (the section). Except for the Levites, who were assigned as a tribe to the care of the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Num.2.33">Nm 2:33</a>), men from 20 years of age who were physically able to fight were assigned to a unit in the tribal army. Certain individuals, however, were exempted from military service (cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.20.5-9">Dt 20:5-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.5">24:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.7.3">Jgs 7:3</a>).</p>
<p>Until after the conquest of Canaan, the tribal army was essentially a militia recruited in an emergency. Internal organization of the militia was the responsibility of the tribe; each clan and family sent their quota of warriors when summoned to battle by tribal leaders. Because the clan formed the basic unit, recruits were under the command of their own leaders. David’s brothers, for example, served in a division composed of the fighting men from their clan under the command of a captain (<a href="?bref=1Sam.17.18">1 Sm 17:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.18.13">18:13</a>). When the emergency passed, the militia was disbanded and the soldiers returned to their home districts.</p>
<p>Because the land was divided among the tribes, no tribal or clan leader before Saul commanded the entire tribal confederation (cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.11.1-11">1 Sm 11:1-11</a>). In fact, tribal jealousies and rivalries threatened national solidarity and jeopardized united action even in a critical period. On some occasions, however, the severity of a crisis caused the armies of the various tribes to unite in common action. The multitribal armies were divided into companies of 1,000, 100, and 50, and still further into families under appointed officers. There is evidence of organization into units according to weaponry (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.24-38">1 Chr 12:24-38</a>). Benjamin’s tribe specialized in the bow and sling. The tribes of Gad, Judah, and Naphtali were expert with the spear and shield.</p>
<p>Provisioning the tribal army was the responsibility of each tribe (<a href="?bref=Judg.20.9-10">Jgs 20:9-10</a>). One out of every ten soldiers was appointed to secure food for the others, either from wealthy landowners (cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.25.1-44">1 Sm 25</a>) or from the natural resources of the land. In that early stage of military organization, a soldier’s pay generally consisted only of supplies and a portion of the spoils of battle (cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.30.21-25">30:21-25</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Professional Army</p>
<p class="fl">Not until the time of the united monarchy did Israel have a regular army. Transition from a people’s militia to a professional army took place under Saul, whose reign changed the tribal confederacy into a monarchy (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.2">1 Sm 13:2</a>). Philistine harassment of Israel encouraged establishment of a strong standing army. The army, however, was not large; it consisted of 3,000 men organized in three formations of 1,000 each (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.2">1 Sm 13:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.24.2">24:2</a>). Pay for those career soldiers was sometimes in the form of a land grant (<a href="?bref=1Sam.8.14">8:14</a>) as well as a share of booty. In the organization of Saul’s army, Abner, Jonathan, and David were given particular responsibilities. Abner was named commander of the army (<a href="?bref=1Sam.17.55">17:55</a>) and was probably also given direct command of one of the divisions. David’s band of valorous men, “the thirty,” provided the leadership core for his own military organization when he became king.</p>
<p>David continued the practice of maintaining a professional army. But he also developed a national militia of 12 regiments, each being called up for duty for one month of the year under professional officers (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.1-15">1 Chr 27:1-15</a>). Each regiment, recruited across tribal lines, consisted of 24,000 soldiers. David’s innovation provided him with a large reserve force that could be mustered for war in times of emergency. The reserves, and presumably the professional army as well, were organized into units of 1,000, 100, 50, and 10. Joab, a specialist in siege warfare (<a href="?bref=2Sam.20.15">2 Sm 20:15</a>), commanded the professional army, and Amasa was over the citizens’ militia. David, however, remained commander-in-chief of the military organization.</p>
<p>The Israelite group in King David’s professional army was an outgrowth of the small band of fighting men who had served with him during the period of conflict with Saul. That veteran group consisted of David’s family and clansmen, and others who felt themselves oppressed by the central authority under Saul (<a href="?bref=1Sam.22.1-2">1 Sm 22:1-2</a>). It ranged in size between 400 and 600 men (<a href="?bref=1Sam.22.2">1 Sm 22:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.23.13">23:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.27.2">27:2</a>). The presence of mercenaries in David’s army is clearly recorded. Uriah the Hittite and Ittai of Gath are conspicuous examples, along with many career soldiers of Philistine origin, such as the Cherethites and the Pelethites under Benaiah (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.18">2 Sm 8:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.15.19-22">15:19-22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.23.22-23">23:22-23</a>).</p>
<p>The Davidic dynasty maintained a permanent mercenary army until 701 <span class="era">BC</span>, after which it was considered too costly. The oppressive cost of maintaining a professional army, financed by burdensome taxes and forced labor, was in fact a major factor contributing to the disruption of the monarchy after Solomon’s death (cf. <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.26-29">1 Kgs 10:26-29</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.4-19">12:4-19</a>). After Sennacherib’s invasion in 701 <span class="era">BC</span>, the southern kingdom of Judah depended entirely on a citizens’ militia for its defense. It is commonly held that the northern kingdom of Israel did not employ a professional army, but it is evident that King Ahab used at least some mercenary soldiers in his defense against Ben-hadad of Syria (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.15-20">1 Kgs 20:15-20</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ArmorandWeapons_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Armor and Weapons</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="GodAndWar"/>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WaroftheSonsofLightagainsttheSonsofDarkness">
  <title>War of the Sons of Light against the Sons of Darkness*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WAR OF THE SONS OF LIGHT AGAINST THE SONS OF DARKNESS*</p>
<p class="fl">Scroll found in Cave One at Qumran (1947–48). It casts light on military regulations of the Jewish forces, on the religious life of the sectarians at Qumran, and particularly on their eschatological expectations. It was probably written about the middle of the first century <span class="era">BC</span> or the beginning of the first century <span class="era">AD</span>. Professor Sukenik of Hebrew University purchased the scroll, consisting of 19 sheets, from an antiquities dealer in Bethlehem (<span class="ital">see</span> discussion of discoveries at Wadi Qumran in <a href="?item=BibleManuscriptsandTextoftheOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bible, Manuscripts and Text of the (Old Testament)</a>), then edited the scroll. It was published posthumously in 1954.</p>
<p>The sectarians at Qumran divided all mankind into two camps: the Sons of Light and the Sons of Darkness. Only those in fellowship with the community at Qumran were reckoned to belong to the Sons of Light, and all other Jews, together with the Gentiles, belonged to Satan and his hosts. The scroll expresses the hope that the day of victory over the forces of darkness is approaching. The rule of the Romans (Kittim) “shall come to an end and iniquity shall be vanquished, leaving no remnants; [for the sons] of darkness there shall be no escape.” The Sons of Light will participate in the last battle.</p>
<p>In order to fight the Lord’s battle in the manner of the Lord, the Sons of Light have to be familiar with the rules of war. This scroll was written to indoctrinate the faithful in the biblical rules of war. Since the sabbatical years of rest must be observed, the faithful will fight against the evil forces only 35 out of 40 years.</p>
<p>Six priests in special dress were to proceed ahead of the forces while blowing a trumpet. On each of the trumpets is an inscription that bears out the belief that the battle is the Lord’s and that those who are called are summoned to avenge themselves on the enemies of the Lord and thus to vindicate his holiness. The priests, together with the Levites, blowing their horns, would confound the enemy. In the description of the ordering of the battle divisions, the priests again take up a prominent role. The priests and Levites were to go ahead of the battle formations. They were God’s appointed ministers, as representatives of God’s presence among the fighting forces. In the end, it was expected that God would conquer evil on behalf of the faithful remnant: “This is the day appointed by him for the defeat and overthrow of the Prince of the kingdom of wickedness, and he will send eternal succor to the company of his redeemed by the might of the princely Angel of the kingdom of Michael.”</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WarsoftheLordBookofthe">
  <title>Wars of the Lord, Book of the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WARS OF THE LORD, Book of the</p>
<p class="fl">Document mentioned once in the OT (<a href="?bref=Num.21.14">Nm 21:14</a>); it is found in a description of Moab’s border at the Arnon. The book was used as a source but is no longer extant. It probably contained a record of Israel’s conquest in Transjordan and may be identical to the “Book of the Upright [Jashar]” (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.13">Jos 10:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.1.18">2 Sm 1:18</a>). The passage in <a href="?bref=Num.21.1-35">Numbers 21</a> has a poetic style and pertains to Israel’s conquest and warfare. However, the extent of the quotation is debatable. Some limit it to verse <a href="?bref=Num.21.14">14</a>, others include verse <a href="?bref=Num.21.15">15</a>, and still others include verses <a href="?bref=Num.21.27-30">27-30</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Watch">
  <title>Watch</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WATCH</p>
<p class="fl">Time unit for the division of the night in both the OT and NT. During the OT period, the night was divided into three military watches. The beginning or evening watch ran from sunset to roughly 10:00 <span class="sc">pm</span> (<a href="?bref=Lam.2.19">Lam 2:19</a>); the middle or night watch was from 10:00 <span class="sc">pm</span> to 2:00 <span class="sc">am</span> (<a href="?bref=Judg.7.19">Jgs 7:19</a>); and the morning watch was from approximately 2:00 <span class="sc">am</span> until sunrise (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.24">Ex 14:24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.11.11">1 Sm 11:11</a>). During the Roman period, the number of watches was increased from three to four. These were either described by number (first, second, etc.) or as evening, midnight, cock-crowing, and morning (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.25">Mt 14:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.48">Mk 6:48</a>). The respective watches ended at roughly 9:00 <span class="sc">pm</span>, midnight, 3:00 <span class="sc">am</span>, and 6:00 <span class="sc">am</span>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Night_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Night</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Watchman">
  <title>Watchman</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WATCHMAN</p>
<p class="fl">Military or civil security person who had the responsibility to protect ancient towns or military installations from surprise attack or civil disasters (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.16">1 Sm 14:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.18.24-27">2 Sm 18:24-27</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.17-20">2 Kgs 9:17-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.21.6-9">Is 21:6-9</a>). Watchmen also had the responsibility of announcing the dawning of a new day (<a href="?bref=Ps.130.6">Ps 130:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.21.11-12">Is 21:11-12</a>). In a passage describing the function and responsibilities of the prophets, Ezekiel reported the watchman’s parallel responsibility to warn of impending danger. If the watchman (or prophet) failed in his task, he would be guilty of the blood of the people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.33.2-9">Ez 33:2-9</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.6.17">Jer 6:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.3.17">Ez 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.9.8">Hos 9:8</a>). In contrast to the faithful prophets, Isaiah compared the leaders of Israel to blind watchmen who lacked the ability to see Israel’s danger, much less lead the people to repentance (<a href="?bref=Isa.56.10">Is 56:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.7.4">Mi 7:4</a>). The prophets who served as Israel’s watchmen were the ones who first saw the coming destruction of Israel and also the ones who first announced their return to the land (<a href="?bref=Isa.21.11-12">Is 21:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.52.8">52:8</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Watchtower">
  <title>Watchtower</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WATCHTOWER</p>
<p class="fl">Platform from which farmers protected their land and livestock and from which soldiers guarded their cities. Watchtowers were built in the vineyards of Palestine. From the tower the watchman was assigned to oversee the vineyard, protecting it from wild animals and thieves (<a href="?bref=Isa.5.2">Is 5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.21.33">Mt 21:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.1">Mk 12:1</a>). Such structures are still used for similar purposes in Palestine and serve as the living quarters for the vineyard workers. Some watchtowers, like the tower of Eder (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.21">Gn 35:21</a>), were constructed in wilderness areas. They provided a protected shelter for shepherds to watch their flocks and a fortified outpost for sentinels to guard a city and to safeguard its commerce from marauding bandits (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.8">2 Kgs 18:8</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.20.24">2 Chr 20:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.32.14">Is 32:14</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Water">
  <title>Water</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WATER</p>
<p class="fl">One of the essentials of life, which covers much of the earth’s surface and is the primary component of the human body. Life cannot be sustained more than a few days without it.</p>
<p>In the beginning, water covered the earth. Then God brought up the dry land from the water (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.9-10">Gn 1:9-10</a>). As Peter said, “God made the heavens by the word of his command, and he brought the earth up from the water and surrounded it with water” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.5">2 Pt 3:5</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>When the Lord created the Garden of Eden, he made a river to water it. This river divided into four rivers, of which two are identified with certainty, the Euphrates and the Tigris, which have sustained agricultural life in the Mesopotamian area both in antiquity and today (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.10-14">Gn 2:10-14</a>). The Bible also relates that early in the history of the earth there was no rain but only a mist that watered the earth (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.2.5-6">5-6</a>). In the time of Noah, the Lord used an overwhelming mass and movement of water to destroy “the world that then existed” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.6">2 Pt 3:6</a>), as punishment for its wickedness.</p>
<p>In the Near East, water is of special importance, for much of the area receives only moderate amounts of rainfall. In Egypt, for example, only two to four inches (5.1 to 10.2 centimeters) of rain falls in the area of Cairo, and at Aswan the average annual rainfall is zero. Egypt is dependent upon the Nile, which is supplied by equatorial rains. By contrast, Palestine is watered well by “the rain from heaven” (<a href="?bref=Deut.11.10-11">Dt 11:10-11</a>).</p>
<p>Water has many symbolic usages in Scripture (quoted below mostly from the <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The righteous man is like a tree planted by streams of water (<a href="?bref=Ps.1.3">Ps 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.17.8">Jer 17:8</a>). The longing of the soul after God is likened to thirst for water: “My soul thirsts for you; my whole body longs for you in this parched and weary land where there is no water” (<a href="?bref=Ps.63.1">Ps 63:1</a>); “I thirst for you as parched land thirsts for rain” (<a href="?bref=Ps.143.6">143:6</a>). Jesus fulfills this need and declares, “If you are thirsty, come to me! If you believe in me, come and drink!” (<a href="?bref=John.7.37-38">Jn 7:37-38</a>). And Jesus said, “The water I give them takes away thirst altogether. It becomes a perpetual spring within them, giving them eternal life” (<a href="?bref=John.4.14">4:14</a>). The Spirit of Jesus is that spiritual water that satisfies the thirst of the human spirit (<a href="?bref=John.7.38-39">7:38-39</a>). The Word of God is also presented as water by which spiritual cleansing is effected. The Lord speaks of the cleansing of the church by “the washing of water with the word” (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.26">Eph 5:26</a>). And Paul said that people are saved “by the washing of regeneration and renewal in the Holy Spirit” (<a href="?bref=Titus.3.5">Ti 3:5</a>).</p>
<p>In the closing chapters of the Bible the Lord declares, “To all who are thirsty I will give the springs of the water of life without charge!” (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.6">Rv 21:6</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Even in the description of the heavenly Jerusalem there is mention of water—the river of the water of life: “The angel showed me a pure river with the water of life, clear as crystal, flowing from the throne of God and of the Lamb, coursing down the center of the main street” (<a href="?bref=Rev.22.1-2">22:1-2</a>). The final invitation of Scripture comes to us in similar terms: “Let the thirsty ones come—anyone who wants to. Let them come and drink the water of life without charge” (v <a href="?bref=Rev.22.17">17</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WaterGate">
  <title>Water Gate</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WATER GATE</p>
<p class="fl">One of the principal gates on the east side of Jerusalem. It was rebuilt during Nehemiah’s day and served as the location for Ezra’s reading of the law (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.26">Neh 3:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.8.3,16">8:3, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.12.37">12:37</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WaterHen">
  <title>Water Hen*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WATER HEN*</p>
<p class="fl">Designation for several birds living near water, such as the marsh hen, swan, or even the horned owl. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals</a>; <a href="?item=Birds_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Birds</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WaterLily">
  <title>Water Lily*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WATER LILY*</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WatersofMerom">
  <title>Waters of Merom</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WATERS OF MEROM</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=MeromWatersof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Merom, Waters of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WaveOffering">
  <title>Wave Offering*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WAVE OFFERING*</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=OfferingsandSacrifices_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Offerings and Sacrifices</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Waythe">
  <title>Way, the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WAY, The</p>
<p class="fl">One of the names applied to the early Christian community (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.2">Acts 9:2</a>). It was apparently used by both the Jewish and the secular community and appeared in both positive and negative assessments of the church (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.9,23">19:9, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.22.4">22:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.24.14,22">24:14, 22</a>). Paul’s use of the term in his defense before Felix suggests that the name had at least quasiofficial acceptance (<a href="?bref=Acts.24.14,22">24:14, 22</a>). Quite likely, the term came from Jesus’ own statement, “I am the way, the truth, and the life” (<a href="?bref=John.14.6">Jn 14:6</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="FollowersOfTheWay"/>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wealth">
  <title>Wealth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEALTH</p>
<p class="fl">Abundance, usually of money or material goods, whose value is ordinarily expressed in terms of some understood unit, such as a national currency. It is virtually synonymous with riches, and both may refer to family, friends, or even moral qualities.</p>
<p>In the OT riches are a mark of favor with God (<a href="?bref=Ps.112.3">Ps 112:3</a>), and he gives power to acquire wealth (<a href="?bref=Deut.8.18">Dt 8:18</a>). Both the piety and the wealth of Job are well known (<a href="?bref=Job.1.1-3">Jb 1:1-3</a>). Solomon was perhaps the richest man who ever lived; God granted him “riches, possessions, and honor” because Solomon had asked for wisdom and discernment rather than material things (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.3.10-13">1 Kgs 3:10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.1.11-12">2 Chr 1:11-12</a>). But the Bible makes it clear that a person’s life does not consist in the abundance of his possessions (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.15">Lk 12:15</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT wealthy men are often seen as godless—for example, the rich farmer (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.16-21">Lk 12:16-21</a>) and the rich man who neglected the beggar Lazarus (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.19-31">16:19-31</a>). The wealthy are condemned for oppression and greed (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.1-6">Jas 5:1-6</a>). <a href="?bref=Luke.6.24">Luke 6:24</a> pronounces woe against the rich, and all three synoptic Gospels speak of the dangers of riches (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.22">Mt 13:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.19">Mk 4:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.14">Lk 8:14</a>). But not all rich men were bad. Jesus was buried in the tomb of a rich man from Arimathea, named Joseph (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.57">Mt 27:57</a>). Nicodemus, who provided lavishly for the burial of Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.19.39">Jn 19:39</a>), was “a ruler of the Jews” (<a href="?bref=John.3.1">3:1</a>) and probably a man of wealth.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Mammon_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mammon</a>; <a href="?item=Money_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Money</a>; <a href="?item=Poorthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Poor, The</a>; <a href="?item=Riches_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Riches</a>; <a href="?item=Wages_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wages</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Weapons">
  <title>Weapons</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEAPONS</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=ArmorandWeapons_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Armor and Weapons</a>; <a href="?item=Warfare_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Warfare</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Weasel">
  <title>Weasel*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEASEL*</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Weaving">
  <title>Weaving</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEAVING</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=ClothandClothManufacturing_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cloth and Cloth Manufacturing</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wedding">
  <title>Wedding</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEDDING</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=MarriageMarriageCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Marriage, Marriage Customs</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Weeds">
  <title>Weeds</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEEDS</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants (Darnel Grass)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Week">
  <title>Week</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEEK</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=CalendarsAncientandModern_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Calendars, Ancient and Modern</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WeeksFeastof">
  <title>Weeks*, Feast of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEEKS*, Feast of</p>
<p class="fl">Celebration of the beginning of the wheat harvest (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.14-17">Ex 23:14-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.16.16">Dt 16:16</a>), occurring seven weeks after Passover on the sixth day of Sivan (June); also known as the Feast of Pentecost. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=FeastsandFestivalsofIsrael_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Feasts and Festivals of Israel</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WeightsandMeasures">
  <title>Weights and Measures</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEIGHTS AND MEASURES</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Introduction">Introduction</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#WeightMeasures">Weight Measures</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LinearMeasuresintheOldTestament">Linear Measures in the Old Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LinearMeasuresintheNewTestament">Linear Measures in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#CapacityDryMeasureintheOldTestament">Capacity (Dry Measure) in the Old Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#CapacityDryMeasureintheNewTestament">Capacity (Dry Measure) in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LiquidMeasuresintheOldTestament">Liquid Measures in the Old Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LiquidMeasuresintheNewTestament">Liquid Measures in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Introduction">Introduction</p>
<p class="fl">Units of measure in the ancient world were largely based on practical standards: the length of an arm, a day’s journey, how much a donkey could carry, and so forth. While this was a convenient system, it also suffered from a lack of standardization. Some arms were longer than others, and some donkeys could carry more than others. The history of weights and measures, therefore, becomes the story of seeking standards. This was not achieved in the OT but began to take place under Greek and Roman influences in NT times.</p>
<p>In the OT the measures that were used are frequently attested to in Mesopotamian, Egyptian, and Canaanite literature as well. The Israelites did not have their own unique set of measurements. Yet while the terms are shared, it is not unusual to find a particular term having one value in Israel and a noticeably different value in one of the other cultures.</p>
<p>By the time of the NT, other variables were added. The Israelites of this period were still using many of the measures that had been used and developed throughout the OT period. But added to that were the Greek and Roman systems of measurement. Sometimes these terms were adopted wholesale, while at other times Hebrew terms were adapted to Greco-Roman standards. On still other occasions, the Roman terms were apparently used when dealing with the government, whereas Hebrew terms were still used in everyday practice.</p>
<p>In most of the kinds of measurement, the base unit (i.e., the one that all of the others are fractions or multiples of) is the one about which there is the most uncertainty. So the cubit (length), the shekel (weight), the homer (dry volume), and the bath (liquid volume) are all to some degree uncertain. This makes all of the other measures based on them equally uncertain.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WeightMeasures">Weight Measures</p>
<p class="fl">The terms used for weights have benefited most from archaeological discoveries. Excavations provide stone weights that are occasionally inscribed with the unit they represent. When the stones are weighed, they frequently give a range of weights that have only a general consistency. However, comparing this data with that provided by the text has given the basis for fairly accurate determinations. The relative scale in any given location is more important than absolute values.</p>
<include_items src="../Charts/Charts.xml" name="TablesOfWeightsAndMeasures"/>
<p>There was standardization of weight measures, but precision was difficult to attain. The Israelite system is similar to that used by the Mesopotamians and the Canaanites. For most of the OT period, the weights system provided the monetary system. Minted coinage was the invention of the Persians. Up until that time, silver or gold or any other trading commodity had to be weighed out so that bartering or purchasing could take place. This made the weights system the core of the ancient economy. It also explains why the Scriptures speak so seriously against the use of false weights (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.36">Lv 19:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.25.13">Dt 25:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.16.11">Prv 16:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.10,23">20:10, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.11">Mi 6:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.12.7">Hos 12:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.5">Am 8:5</a>).</p>
<p>Stone weights were used on a set of balances for conducting business in the ancient marketplace. Scales or balances are mentioned half a dozen times in the OT, but none of those are in actual economic contexts (<a href="?bref=Job.6.2">Jb 6:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.31.6">31:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.62.9">Ps 62:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.12">Is 40:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.5.1">Ez 5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.5.27">Dn 5:27</a>). The scales used were generally of the beam-balance type with dishes on each end.</p>
<p class="h3">Talent</p>
<p class="fl">According to <a href="?bref=Exod.38.25-26">Exodus 38:25-26</a> the talent must have been equal to 3,000 shekels. (A hundred talents would then have been equal to 300,000 shekels, and if that is added to the 1,175 shekels in verse <a href="?bref=Exod.38.25">25</a>, the total is 301,775, or half a shekel for each of the 603,550 men—as verse <a href="?bref=Exod.38.26">26</a> states.) Excavated talents weigh from about 65 to 80 pounds (29.5 to 36.3 kilograms). In the OT the talent is used only for precious metals, usually silver or gold. According to <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.14">1 Kings 10:14</a>, the annual tribute income of Solomon’s kingdom was 666 talents, which apparently was considered quite extravagant. David bequeathed 100,000 talents of gold and 1,000,000 talents of silver to Solomon for the building of the temple (<a href="?bref=1Chr.22.14">1 Chr 22:14</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Mina</p>
<p class="fl">In the Canaanite material from Ugarit the mina equals 50 shekels, while in Babylon the mina equals 60 shekels. In <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.12">Ezekiel 45:12</a>, the mina is set at 60 shekels, but it is unclear whether this represents a change from previous standards.</p>
<p class="h3">Shekel</p>
<p class="fl">The shekel was the basic unit of weight. Besides the regular shekel, there was a “royal” shekel (<a href="?bref=2Sam.14.26">2 Sm 14:26</a>). Calculating by weights that have been excavated and found labeled as “beka” (one-half shekel), the shekel has been estimated to be about .4 ounce (11.4 grams).</p>
<p>The shekel is used in Scripture almost exclusively in contexts dealing with monetary value. Whether silver, gold, barley, or flour, the shekel valuation assigns the commodity a relative value in the economy. Exceptions to this are Goliath’s armor and spear (<a href="?bref=1Sam.17.5-7">1 Sm 17:5-7</a>), which are described in terms of their shekel weight.</p>
<p class="h3">Pim</p>
<p class="fl">The only reference to this unit is in <a href="?bref=1Sam.13.21">1 Samuel 13:21</a>, where it is the price charged to the Israelites by the Philistines for sharpening a plowshare. Excavated weights range from .25 to .3 ounce (7.1 to 8.5 grams), suggesting that the pim was two-thirds of a shekel.</p>
<p class="h3">Beka</p>
<p class="fl">Seven stones inscribed with this label range in weight from .2 to .23 ounce (5.7 to 6.5 grams). In <a href="?bref=Exod.38.26">Exodus 38:26</a> it is the amount levied on each individual for the census tax. There it is the equivalent of one-half shekel.</p>
<p class="h3">Gerah</p>
<p class="fl">Equal to one-twentieth of a shekel, or .02 ounce (.6 gram). The term is used five times (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.13">Ex 30:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.27.25">Lv 27:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.47">Nm 3:47</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.18.16">18:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.12">Ez 45:12</a>) and on each occasion is used to give a valuation to the shekel. Its use is strictly monetary in these contexts.</p>
<p class="h3">Litra</p>
<p class="fl">The NT uses the same weights that have already been identified in the OT usage, particularly the shekel, mina, and talent. There is one additional unit used: the litra, which is used in <a href="?bref=John.12.3">John 12:3</a> and <a href="?bref=John.19.39">19:39</a> with regard to spices. In Greek literature one litra is approximately 12 ounces (327 grams).</p>
<p class="h2" id="LinearMeasuresintheOldTestament">Linear Measures in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Measurements of length and depth generally were derived from a part of the body used to make the measurement. The basic unit was the cubit, and most others were related to it. Precise measurements of geographic distance are lacking in the OT and was most frequently stated in terms of the number of days it would take to arrive at a destination. A single day’s journey was mostly likely 20 to 25 miles (32.2 to 40.2 kilometers). A “pace” was equal to a “step”—about a yard (<a href="?bref=2Sam.6.13">2 Sm 6:13</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Cubit</p>
<p class="fl">The length from the tip of the forefinger to the elbow. There are both long and short cubits, which are used not only in Israel but in Mesopotamia and Egypt as well. <a href="?bref=Ezek.40.5">Ezekiel 40:5</a> identifies the long cubit as being the equivalent of a cubit plus a handbreadth (about 20 to 21 inches, or 50.8 to 53.3 centimeters). The inscription found inside the Siloam tunnel built by Hezekiah (715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>) indicates that the tunnel is 1,200 cubits long. The actual length of the tunnel was determined to be 1,749 feet (533.1 meters). This would yield a cubit of 17.49 inches (44.4 centimeters). All things considered, 17.5 inches (44.5 centimeters) is a good estimation of the length of the cubit in Israel. This would set the long cubit at approximately 20.5 inches (52.1 centimeters). The cubit was most frequently used to give the dimensions of buildings or objects (e.g., curtains, pillars, pieces of furniture, etc.). The largest structure measured in cubits was the ark that Noah built, which was 300 cubits long (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.15">Gn 6:15</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Span</p>
<p class="fl">The distance measured by the stretch of the hand from fingertip to fingertip, equal to one-half a cubit, or eight and three-quarters inches (22.2 centimeters). It is used only seven times in the OT, and four of those are to describe the dimensions of the high priest’s breastplate (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.15-16">Ex 28:15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.39.8-9">39:8-9</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Handbreadth</p>
<p class="fl">The width of the hand at the base, equal to one-sixth of a cubit, one-third of a span, or just under three inches (7.6 centimeters). The term is used only five times and gives the width of the rim around the table of showbread (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.25">Ex 25:25</a>) and Solomon’s molten sea (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.26">1 Kgs 7:26</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="LinearMeasuresintheNewTestament">Linear Measures in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the NT some of the units of length and depth represent Greco-Roman standards, while others are those used in the OT. Like the OT, the NT frequently uses imprecise designations for distance, such as a stone’s throw or a day’s journey. There are, however, a few occurrences of precise terms borrowed from Roman culture.</p>
<p class="h3">Cubit</p>
<p class="fl">For the Romans, the cubit was set at one and a half times their standard foot of 11.66 inches, equaling 17.5 inches (44.5 centimeters), just as the OT cubit.</p>
<p class="h3">Fathom</p>
<p class="fl">The distance between the fingertips of the left and right hand when the arms were outstretched. It is used only in <a href="?bref=Acts.27.28">Acts 27:28</a> and is considered to be about six feet (1.8 meters).</p>
<p class="h3">Furlong/Stadium</p>
<p class="fl">The length of the ancient Greek racecourse, equal to one-eighth of a Roman mile, or a little over 200 yards (182.9 meters). It is usually used to give approximate distance, but in <a href="?bref=Rev.21.16">Revelation 21:16</a> it is used to give the dimensions of the New Jerusalem and is measured with a measuring rod.</p>
<p class="h3">Mile</p>
<p class="fl">The only occurrence of this term, <a href="?bref=Matt.5.41">Matthew 5:41</a>, has reference to the Roman mile of 1,620 yards, about nine-tenths of a modern mile (1.4 kilometers).</p>
<p class="h2" id="CapacityDryMeasureintheOldTestament">Capacity (Dry Measure) in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Amounts of dry goods were oriented toward practical matters such as typical donkey loads, how much seed could be sown in a day, or how much seed would be needed to sow a certain size plot. As with the other types of measures, these then became standardized.</p>
<p class="h3">Cor/Homer</p>
<p class="fl">The most common dry commodity measure and the equivalent of one donkey load. Estimates of its standard size vary greatly, ranging from 3.8 bushels to 7.5 bushels (133.9 to 264.3 liters). Other than the seven occurrences in <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.11-14">Ezekiel 45:11-14</a>, the term occurs only four times in the OT. Three of these contexts feature seed or barley (<a href="?bref=Lev.27.16">Lv 27:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.10">Is 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.3.2">Hos 3:2</a>), while the fourth is in the context of Israelites gathering quail in the wilderness. A cor is used nine times and occurs with a variety of commodities, including oil, flour, wheat, and barley, in multiples all the way up to 20,000 (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.11">1 Kgs 5:11</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Lethek</p>
<p class="fl">Unit occurring only in <a href="?bref=Hos.3.2">Hosea 3:2</a>. The early versions of the Bible identified it as one-half of a cor, or homer.</p>
<p class="h3">Ephah</p>
<p class="fl">This is equal to one-tenth of a homer (<a href="?bref=Ezek.45.11">Ez 45:11</a>), or one-half of a bushel (17.6 liters). The term occurs dozens of times with all sorts of agricultural products. It seems to have been the unit most used in trading and selling. According to <a href="?bref=Zech.5.6-10">Zechariah 5:6-10</a>, the ephah refers to a container that would hold an ephah of produce, much like the modern-day bushel basket.</p>
<p class="h3">Seah</p>
<p class="fl">A fraction of the homer, which has a very wide range. The term measures flour, seed, barley, and grain, and is roughly one-third of an ephah. A bushel was about five seahs (<a href="?bref=1Sam.25.18">1 Sm 25:18</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg).</p>
<p class="h3">Omer/Issaron</p>
<p class="fl">The omer occurs only in the account of the collecting of manna by the Israelites (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.22">Ex 16:22</a>). It represents a day’s ration of manna and is identified as one-tenth of an ephah (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.36">Ex 16:36</a>). The issaron is a term that means a tenth. Its 25 occurrences are all in Exodus, Leviticus, and Numbers (mostly in <a href="?bref=Num.28.1-29.40">Nm 28–29</a>); it refers only to measures of fine flour.</p>
<p class="h3">Cab, Kab</p>
<p class="fl">This unit occurs only in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.25">2 Kings 6:25</a>. The estimate given by Josephus, one-eighteenth of an ephah (or about one-half of an omer), is usually accepted.</p>
<p class="h2" id="CapacityDryMeasureintheNewTestament">Capacity (Dry Measure) in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The following dry measures are used in the NT.</p>
<p class="h3">Choinix</p>
<p class="fl">Occurring only in <a href="?bref=Rev.6.6">Revelation 6:6</a> (see <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg), the choinix is a little more than a quart (1.1 liters). In Greek literature it was considered the amount of one man’s daily allowance of corn.</p>
<p class="h3">Modius</p>
<p class="fl">This is the “bushel” under which one’s lamp should not be hid (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.15">Mt 5:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.21">Mk 4:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.33">Lk 11:33</a>). It is actually equal to about a peck, 7.68 dry quarts (8.5 liters).</p>
<p class="h3">Saton</p>
<p class="fl">This is the equivalent of the OT seah and can therefore also be approximated at about a peck. It is used only twice in the NT in parallel passages of the parable of the leaven, which is like the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.33">Mt 13:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.21">Lk 13:21</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="LiquidMeasuresintheOldTestament">Liquid Measures in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Three basic measures were used for liquids in the OT.</p>
<p class="h3">Bath</p>
<p class="fl">The base unit for the measurement of liquids. The biblical data (<a href="?bref=Ezek.45.11-14">Ez 45:11-14</a>) sets it as the liquid equivalent to the dry measure, the ephah. It is one-tenth of a homer. Archaeology has also been able to provide some data for this determination. Jars inscribed as “bath of the king” were found at Lachish and Tell en-Nasbeh, and jars marked “bath” were found at Tell Beit Mirsim. The jars are not complete, so their capacity must be calculated based on a reconstruction. Using this data, the bath was approximately 5.5 gallons (20.8 liters). This estimate would provide acceptable results when factored into the information given in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.23-26">1 Kings 7:23-26</a>, where the “molten sea” of Solomon’s temple is described as being 30 cubits in circumference, 10 cubits in diameter, 5 cubits deep, and capable of holding 2,000 baths of water.</p>
<p class="h3">Hin</p>
<p class="fl">One-sixth of a hin of water was considered a person’s minimum daily requirement (<a href="?bref=Ezek.4.11">Ez 4:11</a>). A hin is equal to one-sixth of a bath, approximately one gallon (3.8 liters). It is used for a measure of oil, wine, and water, but no context ever mentions more than one hin. Rather, fractions of a hin are used. Occurrences are limited to Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Ezekiel and are therefore most commonly attested in the context of sacrificial libations.</p>
<p class="h3">Log</p>
<p class="fl">This unit occurs only in <a href="?bref=Lev.14.10-24">Leviticus 14:10-24</a> and equals one-twelfth of a hin, so about .3 quart or .3 liter.</p>
<p class="h2" id="LiquidMeasuresintheNewTestament">Liquid Measures in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The following liquid measures occur in the NT.</p>
<p class="h3">Bath</p>
<p class="fl">This is used only once (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.6">Lk 16:6</a>) and is the same as the OT bath.</p>
<p class="h3">Metretes</p>
<p class="fl">This is used only in <a href="?bref=John.2.6">John 2:6</a>, where it describes the containers in which water was turned to wine. Josephus identifies it as equivalent to a Hebrew bath, but in Greek usage it was the equivalent of about ten gallons (37.9 liters).</p>
<p class="h3">Sextarius/Xestes</p>
<p class="fl">A measure of capacity equal to about one and one-sixth pints (552 milliliters). In <a href="?bref=Mark.7.4">Mark 7:4</a> the word is translated “pitcher” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>) or “pot” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>, see mg).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Well">
  <title>Well</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WELL</p>
<p class="fl">Man-made reservoir fed either by subterranean springs or by rainwater. Because the majority of the biblical world ranges from arid to semiarid, wells were a critical source of water for humans, livestock, and the irrigation of crops. Unfortunately, most wells did not offer a reliable source of water, being dependent on the scarce rainfall or intermittent springs (<a href="?bref=Pr.25.26">Prv 25:26</a>). The discovery of a reliable source of water was therefore the cause of much rejoicing (<a href="?bref=Num.21.17-18">Nm 21:17-18</a>) and frequent conflict (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.25-30">Gn 21:25-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.26.19-22">26:19-22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.19">2 Kgs 3:19</a>). Successfully digging a well and defending one’s water rights often served as an important determinant of property rights (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.25-30">Gn 21:25-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.29.2-3">29:2-3</a>).</p>
<p>Good wells were generally considered signs of God’s providence (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.14">Gn 16:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.21.19">21:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.21.16-18">Nm 21:16-18</a>). Biblical writers therefore compared the water of spring-fed wells to God’s provision of salvation for his people (<a href="?bref=Isa.12.3">Is 12:3</a>; <a href="?bref=John.4.14">Jn 4:14</a>). The distinction between the relatively poor quality of water in cisterns that captured rainwater and the high quality of those wells that tapped springs of “living” (i.e., flowing) water helps clarify the dialogue between Jesus and the Samaritan woman when Jesus offered her “living water” (<a href="?bref=John.4.10-15">Jn 4:10-15</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Cistern_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cistern</a>; <a href="?item=JacobsWell_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jacob’s Well</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WesternText">
  <title>Western Text*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WESTERN TEXT*</p>
<p class="fl">According to the classification of B. F. Wescott and F. J. A. Hort, one of the four principal text types of the Greek New Testament. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=BibleManuscriptsandTextoftheNewTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bible, Manuscripts and Text of the (New Testament)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Whale">
  <title>Whale*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WHALE*</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wheat">
  <title>Wheat</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WHEAT</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Agriculture_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Agriculture</a>; <a href="?item=FoodandFoodPreparation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Food and Food Preparation</a>; <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wheel">
  <title>Wheel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WHEEL</p>
<p class="fl">Device originating in the region of Mesopotamia, probably dating from about 3500 <span class="era">BC</span>. The earliest known form is the two-wheeled cart of Sumer. The first wheels were probably just discs cut from trees, but later wheels were made by clamping three shaped planks together by copper clamps extending the length of the wheel. After 2000 <span class="era">BC</span> wheels with spokes appeared in northern Mesopotamia.</p>
<p>In the Bible, four Hebrew words are used to identify a number of types and usages of the wheel. These include the potter’s wheel (<a href="?bref=Jer.18.3">Jer 18:3</a>), chariot wheels (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.25">Ex 14:25</a>), and wheels for grinding grain (<a href="?bref=Isa.28.28">Is 28:28</a>). The most frequent and most important usage of the word “wheel” in the Bible, however, is in connection with Ezekiel’s vision of the chariot of God (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-28">Ez 1</a>, <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.1-22">10</a>). Associated with the cloud appearing in a stormy wind (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.4">1:4</a>) are fire, creatures, and wheels. Ezekiel draws the reader’s attention to each of these phenomena. The wheels move in the direction the creatures take them. The significance of the wheel in Ezekiel is the shape. The wheel is compound, a wheel within a wheel. This is not to say that two wheels are on the same axis. It rather signifies a wheel set in a wheel in such a way that its rim makes a 90-degree angle with the rim of the wheel in which it is set. The wheel has mobility; it can roll from east to west and from north to south. Wherever the living creatures go, it will follow. This speaks of God’s universal judgment, which no one can escape.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=EzekielBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ezekiel, Book of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Whirlwind">
  <title>Whirlwind</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WHIRLWIND</p>
<p class="fl">Term descriptive of any strong, potentially destructive wind (<a href="?bref=Job.27.20">Jb 27:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.77.18">Ps 77:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.11.40">Dn 11:40</a>). While whirlwinds are relatively common in the arid regions of the Middle East (e.g., dust devils), the apparent fury and destructiveness of the biblical “whirlwinds” makes it unlikely that the relatively harmless dust devils are intended (cf. <a href="?bref=Amos.1.14">Am 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.3.14">Hb 3:14</a>). Sirocco winds from the eastern deserts are occasionally cyclonic in form, but the winds in Scripture may not be whirlwinds in the technical sense.</p>
<p>Biblical whirlwinds were often associated with divine activity. Elijah was taken into heaven by a whirlwind (one case where “whirlwind” may properly be translated as such; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.1,11">2 Kgs 2:1, 11</a>). God frequently spoke out of the whirlwind (<a href="?bref=Job.38.1">Jb 38:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.40.6">40:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.77.18">Ps 77:18</a>). The description of the sudden destruction of divine judgment was frequently associated with storms, tempests, and whirlwinds (<a href="?bref=Hos.8.7">Hos 8:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.1.14">Am 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Nah.1.3">Na 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.3.14">Hb 3:14</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="White">
  <title>White</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WHITE</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Color_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Color</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Whore">
  <title>Whore</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WHORE</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=ProstituteProstitution_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prostitute, Prostitution</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wickedness">
  <title>Wickedness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WICKEDNESS</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Sin_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sin</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Widow">
  <title>Widow</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WIDOW</p>
<p class="fl">A woman whose husband has died. In the Scriptures, widows are often listed with the fatherless and orphans (<a href="?bref=Deut.14.29">Dt 14:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.16.11">16:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.19-20">24:19-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.26.12">26:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.94.6">Ps 94:6</a>). Laws were passed to make special provision for this group and to protect them against the unscrupulous. The primary law had to do with levirate marriage—i.e., the closest kin would marry the widow (if she was without a son) to continue the family line (see discussion under <a href="?item=MarriageMarriageCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Marriage</a>).</p>
<p>The plight of the widow was recognized in the number of laws designed for her protection and even survival. God was her legal protector (<a href="?bref=Ps.68.5">Ps 68:5</a>) and saw that she was provided with the essentials of food and clothing (<a href="?bref=Deut.10.18">Dt 10:18</a>). Those who denied her justice were cursed by God (<a href="?bref=Deut.27.19">27:19</a>). At harvesttime the widow might glean the grain in the fields, as well as some grapes and olives (<a href="?bref=Deut.24.19">Dt 24:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.2.2,7,15-19">Ru 2:2, 7, 15-19</a>), and she was also eligible for some assistance from the third-year tithe. Nevertheless, the poverty of widows and the cruel treatment extended to them was so widespread that frequent reference is made to it (<a href="?bref=Job.24.21">Jb 24:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.94.6">Ps 94:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.23">Is 1:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.3.5">Mal 3:5</a>). A special law provided that the widow’s garment could not be used as security for a loan (<a href="?bref=Deut.24.17">Dt 24:17</a>).</p>
<p>In the early Christian church there was a recognized group of widows eligible to receive charity. They were generally those over 60 years of age who had been faithful to their husband, were in poverty, had no relatives to support them, and had lived blameless lives filled with Christian good works (<a href="?bref=1Tim.5.9-16">1 Tm 5:9-16</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=FamilyLifeandRelations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Family Life and Relations</a>; <a href="?item=MarriageMarriageCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Marriage</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wife">
  <title>Wife</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WIFE</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=FamilyLifeandRelations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Family Life and Relations</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wilderness">
  <title>Wilderness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WILDERNESS</p>
<p class="fl">Land that is basically wild and sparsely inhabited or unfit for permanent human settlement. It may be desert, mountains, forest, or marsh.</p>
<p>In the Near East the wilderness is characteristically dry, desolate, and mostly rock and sand. It is rough, uneven, and interlaced with dry watercourses. The wilderness is not completely barren but provides seasonal pasture for flocks, depending on the rainfall.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Joel.2.22">Joel 2:22</a> declares that “the pastures of the wilderness are green,” and <a href="?bref=Ps.65.12">Psalm 65:12</a> states that the pastures of the wilderness drip with richness. But Jeremiah says that “the pastures of the wilderness are dried up” (<a href="?bref=Jer.23.10">Jer 23:10</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Joel.1.20">Jl 1:20</a>). And Job refers to the wilderness as a land where no human can live (<a href="?bref=Job.38.26">Jb 38:26</a>); it is a place for various animals and birds, such as wild asses, jackals, vultures, and owls (<a href="?bref=Ps.102.6">Ps 102:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.24">Jer 2:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.13.22">Is 13:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.13-15">34:13-15</a>).</p>
<p>Certain wilderness tracts are identified by name and are related to definite cities, persons, or events. Hagar wandered in the wilderness of Beersheba (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.14">Gn 21:14</a>). In the exodus from Egypt, the Israelites traversed the following wildernesses: Shur (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.22">Ex 15:22</a>), Etham (<a href="?bref=Num.33.8">Nm 33:8</a>), Sin (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.1">Ex 16:1</a>), Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.1-2">19:1-2</a>), Zin (<a href="?bref=Num.13.21">Nm 13:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.20.1">20:1</a>), Paran (<a href="?bref=Num.13.26">13:26</a>), Kadesh (<a href="?bref=Ps.29.8">Ps 29:8</a>), Moab (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.8">Dt 2:8</a>), and Kedemoth (v <a href="?bref=Deut.2.26">26</a>). When David was fleeing from Saul, David hid in the hill country of the wilderness of Ziph (<a href="?bref=1Sam.23.14-15">1 Sm 23:14-15</a>), in the wilderness of Maon (vv <a href="?bref=1Sam.23.24-25">24-25</a>), and in the wilderness of En-gedi (<a href="?bref=1Sam.24.1">24:1</a>).</p>
<p>In spite of the comparative desolation of the wilderness, villages or towns are sometimes associated with a wilderness setting. <a href="?bref=Josh.15.61-62">Joshua 15:61-62</a> lists the names of six cities and their villages “in the wilderness.” The future joy of the towns of the desert is proclaimed by Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.11">Is 42:11</a>).</p>
<p>The wilderness is associated with both austerity and temptation. Elijah, by his way of life and his dress, is often thought of in connection with the wilderness. His successor, Elisha, had occasion to minister in the wilderness of Edom (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.4-27">2 Kgs 3:4-27</a>).</p>
<p>Isaiah prophesied of the message of John the Baptist, who preached in the wilderness of Judea (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.3">Is 40:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.3.1-3">Mt 3:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.2-4">Mk 1:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.1-6">Lk 3:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.23">Jn 1:23</a>). Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, was led by the Spirit into the wilderness for 40 days. There he was tempted by the devil (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.4.1-2">Lk 4:1-2</a>), but there also angels ministered to him (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.13">Mk 1:13</a>). The anchorites (hermits) of Egypt and the Qumran community near the Dead Sea used the wilderness as an escape from the evils of urban life. Jesus, however, used the wilderness as a place of prayer and communion with the Father (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.16">Lk 5:16</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Desert_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Desert</a>; <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WildernessWanderings">
  <title>Wilderness Wanderings*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WILDERNESS WANDERINGS*</p>
<p class="fl">When the Israelites came out of Egypt, they spent some 40 years wandering in the wildernesses of the Sinai Peninsula and the Negev. Then they moved on to conquer the Promised Land. The most significant events in this period are described in the books of Exodus, Leviticus, and Numbers.</p>
<p>According to the Bible, their experiences during these hard years in the desert molded the various tribes of former Egyptian slaves into a nation. In Sinai they became one people with one God and one national goal, the conquest of Canaan.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Num.33.38">Numbers 33:38</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.1.3">Deuteronomy 1:3</a> describe the wilderness wanderings as lasting 40 years. Though 40 is sometimes used in the Bible as a large round number, the exactness of many of the dates in these narratives implies it should be taken literally. However, it is hard to know when this period began and ended.</p>
<p>According to <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.1">1 Kings 6:1</a>, Solomon started to build the temple 480 years after the Israelites left Egypt. The building of the temple began about 960 <span class="era">BC</span>, which would mean the exodus must have taken place about 1440 <span class="era">BC</span> and the conquest about 1400 <span class="era">BC</span>. However, contemporary scholars generally date the exodus and conquest more than a century later (1290–1250 <span class="era">BC</span>) on the grounds that this agrees with archaeological discoveries. But as yet, convincing proof for either position is lacking. Within the 40-year period of wanderings, there are full details of the first year and a half spent in the desert, from the exodus to the return of the spies (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.1-51">Ex 12</a>–<a href="?bref=Num.14.1-45">Nm 14</a>), and of the final year or so that involved the conquest of Transjordan (<a href="?bref=Num.20.1-29">Nm 20</a>–<a href="?bref=Deut.34.1-12">Dt 34</a>). Little is known of the intervening years when the tribes camped in the desert near such oases as Kadesh-barnea. The episodes described in <a href="?bref=Num.15.1-17.13">Numbers 15–17</a> presumably date from this little-known period.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>; <a href="?item=Exodusthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Exodus, The</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=SinaSinai_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sina, Sinai</a>; <a href="?item=SinWildernessof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sin, Wilderness of</a>; <a href="?item=ZinWildernessof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Zin, Wilderness of</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="TheIsraelitesWanderintheWilderness"/>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WildOx">
  <title>Wild Ox</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WILD OX</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WildVine">
  <title>Wild Vine</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WILD VINE</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants (Vine)</a>; <a href="?item=VinesVineyard_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Vines, Vineyard</a>; <a href="?item=Wine_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wine</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WillofGod">
  <title>Will of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WILL OF GOD</p>
<p class="fl">Important NT term indicating God’s choice and determination, emanating from desire.</p>
<p>Paul used a Greek word in <a href="?bref=Eph.1.5,9">Ephesians 1:5, 9</a>, and <a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">11</a> that conveys the idea of desire, even heart’s desire. The word is usually translated as “will”—“the will of God.” But the English word “will” sublimates the primary meaning. The Greek word <span class="ital">(</span><span class="greek">thelema</span><span class="ital">)</span> is primarily an emotional word and only secondarily is it volitional. “God’s will” is not so much “God’s intention” as it is “God’s heart’s desire.” God does have an intention, a purpose, a plan. It is called <span class="greek">prothesis</span> in Greek (see <a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">Eph 1:11</a>), and it literally means “a laying out beforehand” (like a blueprint). This plan was created by God’s counsel (called <span class="greek">boule</span> in Greek, <a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">Eph 1:11</a>). However, behind the plan and the counsel was not just a mastermind but a heart—a heart of love and of good pleasure. Therefore, Paul talked about “the good pleasure of God’s heart” (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.5">Eph 1:5</a>). Paul also said, “He made known to us the mystery of his heart’s desire, according to his good pleasure which he purposed in him” (v <a href="?bref=Eph.1.9">9</a>). Indeed, God operated all things according to the counsel of his heart’s desire or will (v <a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">11</a>).</p>
<p>The impetus of God’s eternal purpose came from a heart’s desire, and that heart’s desire was to have many sons and daughters made like his only Son (see <a href="?bref=Rom.8.26-28">Rom 8:26-28</a>). In love, he predestined many people to participate in this—not by their own merits but by virtue of being in the Son (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.4-5">Eph 1:4-5</a>). Notice how often in <a href="?bref=Eph.1.1-23">Ephesians 1</a> Paul speaks of the believers’ position “in him.” Outside of him (the Son), no one could be a son or daughter of God and no one could be pleasing to the Father. The many sons and daughters owe all their divine privileges to the Beloved, as ones graced in him and selected in him (v <a href="?bref=Eph.1.6">6</a>). Thus, predestination and election are issues of God’s will.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ElectElection_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Elect, Election</a>; <a href="?item=Predestination_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Predestination</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Willow">
  <title>Willow</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WILLOW</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants (Aspen)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WillowsRavineofthe">
  <title>Willows, Ravine of the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WILLOWS, Ravine of the</p>
<p class="fl">Ravine by which Moab’s abundance would be carried off (<a href="?bref=Isa.15.7">Is 15:7</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span> “Ravine of the Poplars”). Isaiah’s language suggests that it marked the southern border of Moab.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wine">
  <title>Wine</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WINE</p>
<p class="fl">Beverage made from fermented grape juice.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Origin">Origin</p>
<p class="fl">Noah was among the first to produce wine (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.21">Gn 9:21</a>), presumably on the slopes of Mt Ararat. But wine making was not confined to that region, because Egypt, and later Greece, had a fondness for the juice. In fact, wine making was known to have existed in the prehistoric period of Mesopotamia and was brought to Egypt before 3000 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The word “wine” may be identified with words for vine, vineyard, and black grapes. The vine, which brings forth the wine, was often identified in the Near Eastern world with the “tree of life.” In both Egypt and Mesopotamia a goddess was thought to protect the vine. The “mistress of the heavenly tree of life,” the goddess Siris, lived in the mountains of northwestern Assyria. First Enoch 32:4 calls the vine the tree of knowledge. According to Jewish tradition, the vine was saved from the Flood by Noah.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ProductionofWine">Production of Wine</p>
<p class="fl">Few ancient documents are extant on the art of wine making. Experience and the interests of a few early botanists appear to be the only source of knowledge available about the early vine growers. Aristotle’s gifted student Theophrastus of Eresos wrote a book entitled <span class="ital">Enquiry into Plants</span> showing a blend of practical experience and theory. Later, he followed with <span class="ital">On the Life of Plants,</span> a work giving detailed observations about wine making. His ideas on when to plant, how to prune, statements against grafting, and how to care for the vine demonstrate the Greek genius. They raised viticulture to a science that has changed little in the last 2200 years.</p>
<p>Great care was taken by Greek vine growers to ensure the success of their crops. The vines were close to the ground instead of being propped. In view of this, mice and foxes were especially undesirable, and much hoeing was needed to keep the soil free of weeds. But their method, overall, was very effective.</p>
<p>In early September the grapes were collected in the plains, and at the end of the month in the hills. With an initial festival of song and dance, the workers brought the bunches of grapes to the winepresses, low cement vats inclined toward one corner. After this, workers trod the grapes. The first <span class="ital">must</span> (juice from the crushing) was highly valued because it provided the choicest wines. The remaining juice was extracted by wringing the trodden grapes in a bag press usually made of cloth. A third class of wine was produced by mixing or even cooking the remaining grapes with some water and expressing the mixture. This type of wine was drunk only by the poor.</p>
<p>At a later time the Greeks invented a beam press in which a long beam, having a turning portion at one end and heavy stones on the other, compressed layers of grapes. The ancient Near East had these different methods of extracting wine, but the treading of grapes, even in Greece, was always the favorite method.</p>
<p>In Greece the fermentation period was usually six months, during which the liquid was constantly skimmed. However, in the ancient Near East the fermentation process was usually over in three or four days, the optimum growth temperature being 77 degrees. The ancients knew that any further fermentation would produce acid.</p>
<p>After desired fermentation, the wine was transferred to skins or pottery jars for transport or sale. The handles and stoppers were stamped to indicate the brand, the origin, and the vintage. At this time the wine was strained through perforated metal sieves or cloth to eliminate contaminates such as grit or insects.</p>
<p class="h2" id="KindsofWine">Kinds of Wine</p>
<p class="fl">Ancient poets discuss many different brands of wine, with Athenaeus mentioning 85 different varieties. Galen cites 60; Pliny mentions 150; and Strabo, 30. Wines are distinguished by different colors (black, red, white, or yellow) and by their taste (dry, harsh, light, or sweet). The biblical account enumerates various kinds of wine, such as the wines of Lebanon and Helbon. Hebron and Samaria were famous for their wine making. The Hebrew language has at least nine different words for wine, and the Greek has four that are mentioned in the NT.</p>
<p class="h2" id="NatureofWine">Nature of Wine</p>
<p class="fl">Few would question that at least some wine of the OT was fermented. Some scholars argue, however, that certain forms of wine in the ancient world were unfermented. They contrast two Hebrew words for wine, concluding that one particular Hebrew word that refers to fresh wine meant only grape juice (<a href="?bref=Pr.3.10">Prv 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.9.2">Hos 9:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.24">Jl 2:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.15">Mi 6:15</a>). The inconclusiveness of these arguments may be seen from the following points: (1) the Hebrew word is found in primarily neutral contexts; (2) often that particular word is found in contexts definitely including a fermented beverage (e.g., <a href="?bref=Gen.27.28">Gn 27:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.4.11">Hos 4:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.15">Mi 6:15</a>); (3) the Ugaritic parallel to the term in question refers with certainty to a fermented wine; (4) the Septuagint equivalents refer to fermented wine; (5) fermentation in the ancient Near East, unlike Greece, took only about three days; and (6) the Mishnah provides no such evidence of the practice of having unfermented wine. There seems to have been no attempts to preserve wine in an unfermented state; it may have been a near-impossible task. A careful examination of all the Hebrew words (as well as their Semitic cognates) and the Greek words for wine demonstrates that the ancients knew little, if anything, about unfermented wine.</p>
<p>Ample evidence is available to demonstrate that wine, though always fermented, was usually mixed with water in the classical and Hellenistic world. The wine was stored in large jugs called <span class="greek">amphorae</span><span class="ital">,</span> from which the wine was poured through a strainer into a large mixing bowl called a <span class="greek">krater</span><span class="ital">.</span> In the krater the wine was mixed with water. Then the drinking bowls or cups were filled.</p>
<p>The amount of wine per volume varied. The mixture that represented the greatest amount of water to wine was 20 to 1, apparently because the wine was so strong (Homer, <span class="ital">Odyssey</span> 10.208).</p>
<p>In the western Mediterranean world, the term “wine” referred to the mixture of wine and water. If one desired to mention wine without water, it was necessary to add the word “unmixed.” For the Greeks, to drink wine unmixed was regarded as barbaric. The evidence, however, seems to indicate that in the OT era wine was used without being mixed with water. The terminology of mixing water and wine is strikingly unattested. Wine diluted with water was symbolic of spiritual adulteration (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.22">Is 1:22</a>). By Roman times, this attitude had changed. The Mishnah assumes a ratio of two parts of water to one part wine; however, later Talmudic sources speak of three to one. A natural, nondistilled wine could reach as high as 15 percent alcohol content. If watered down three parts water to one part wine, the alcohol content would be 5 percent and still fairly potent.</p>
<p>Wine was mixed not only with water but also with other ingredients, similar to mixed drinks today. An example of this is seen in the Homeric “Hymn to Demeter,” where the goddess rejects straight wine and desires the drink mixed with meal, water, and a soft mint. Often strong wine was mixed into weak wine, resulting in a stronger drink. This is what is meant by “mixture” in the Bible (<a href="?bref=Ps.75.8">Ps 75:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.22">Is 5:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.18.6">Rv 18:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.13-15">19:13-15</a>). At times the fresh wine, high in sugar content, was evaporated, and this concentrated <span class="ital">must</span> was mixed with wine to obtain a higher alcohol content.</p>
<p>There is no mention of wine being mixed with water to make it safe for drinking, as is commonly accepted. Modern examples of pollution were not common in the ancient world, although this problem appeared occasionally. Examples are myriad concerning the fresh wells, springs, and moving bodies of water in biblical times, and methods were available to purify any impure water.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WineintheOldTestament">Wine in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The evidence, as seen above, suggests that wine in the OT was not mixed with water and was looked on with favor when taken in moderation. <a href="?bref=Judg.9.13">Judges 9:13</a> presents wine as that “which cheers God and men.” <a href="?bref=Ps.104.15">Psalm 104:15</a> portrays wine similarly: “wine which makes man’s heart glad” (cf. also <a href="?bref=Esth.1.10">Est 1:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.10.19">Eccl 10:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.55.1-2">Is 55:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.10.7">Zec 10:7</a>). The temperate use of wine was a normal and accepted part of life (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.18">Gn 14:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.19.19">Jgs 19:19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.16.20">1 Sm 16:20</a>). Levitical priests in service at the temple (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.8-9">Lv 10:8-9</a>), Nazirites (<a href="?bref=Num.6.3">Nm 6:3</a>), and the Recabites (<a href="?bref=Jer.35.1-6">Jer 35:1-6</a>) were forbidden to drink wine.</p>
<p>Wine had many uses in the OT world. The “drink offering” was wine (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.40">Ex 29:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.23.13">Lv 23:13</a>), and the worshiper regularly brought wine when offering sacrifice (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.24">1 Sm 1:24</a>). In addition, a supply of wine was kept in the temple for sacrificial purposes (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.29">1 Chr 9:29</a>). At times, wine was used in helping the weak and sick (<a href="?bref=2Sam.16.2">2 Sm 16:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.31.6">Prv 31:6</a>).</p>
<p>The strong drink of the OT seems to be closely related to Mesopotamian date wine. This same date wine, high in sugar content, must have also been high in alcohol content. One Hebrew word is consistently used as strong drink (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.9">Lv 10:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.29.6">Dt 29:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.15">1 Sm 1:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.1">Prv 20:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.31.6">31:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.29.9">Is 29:9</a>). There is an equivalent word to this in Ugaritic, translated “drunk,” which parallels the normal word for wine.</p>
<p>Negative reactions to intemperate wine drinking abound in the OT. Isaiah condemned those who drank wine to excess (<a href="?bref=Isa.28.1-8">Is 28:1-8</a>). Many admonitions of drinking wine in excess are given in the Scriptures (<a href="?bref=Pr.20.1">Prv 20:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.21.17">21:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.23.20-21">23:20-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.23.32-34">23:32-34</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="WineintheNewTestament">Wine in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Wine in the NT was a fermented beverage that was mixed with various amounts of water. It was also mixed with gall (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.34">Mt 27:34</a>) and myrrh (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.23">Mk 15:23</a>). Evidence strongly suggests that the wine used at the Lord’s Supper was a mixture of water and wine, probably three to one in agreement with the dictates of the Mishnah. The phrase “fruit of the vine” (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.27-29">Mt 26:27-29</a>) is often interpreted to mean fresh grape juice. However, fresh grape juice would be all but impossible to find.</p>
<p>The NT, as the OT, argues forcefully against the unrestrained use of wine. The biblical admonition is not to be drunk with wine (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.18">Eph 5:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.4.3">1 Pt 4:3</a>). Leaders in the church were to practice moderation in the use of wine (<a href="?bref=1Tim.3.3,8">1 Tm 3:3, 8</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.7">Ti 1:7</a>); the Greek says that they should “not be addicted to wine.”</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=VinesVineyard_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Vines, Vineyard</a>; <a href="?item=Winepress_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Winepress</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Winepress">
  <title>Winepress</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WINEPRESS</p>
<p class="fl">A sunken area (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.11">Jgs 6:11</a>) into which the grape harvest was thrown and then trodden with bare feet, amid shouts of joy and traditional vintage work songs (<a href="?bref=Jer.48.33">Jer 48:33</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.65.8">Is 65:8</a>). The red juice flowed through spouts into jars. Full winepresses meant prosperity; deserted ones spoke of destitution. The common winepress was a natural landmark (<a href="?bref=Judg.7.25">Jgs 7:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.14.10">Zec 14:10</a>); a privately owned one indicated the special care and efficiency of the vineyard’s owner (<a href="?bref=Isa.5.2">Is 5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.21.33">Mt 21:33</a>).</p>
<p>Grape treading provided a dramatic metaphor for the ruthless trampling by invading armies (<a href="?bref=Lam.1.15">Lam 1:15</a>). This vivid metaphor of battle is mingled with divine judgment (<a href="?bref=Isa.63.1-6">Is 63:1-6</a>) and anticipates the Lord’s final judgment, spoken of as “the winepress of the wrath of God” (<a href="?bref=Rev.14.18-20">Rv 14:18-20</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=VinesVineyard_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Vines, Vineyard</a>; <a href="?item=Wine_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wine</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="OneKindOfWinepress"/>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wineskins">
  <title>Wineskins</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WINESKINS</p>
<p class="fl">Containers made of animal hide for keeping wine. The term is prominent in Jesus’ maxim that new wine cannot be put in old wineskins but must be put in new wineskins because the new wine, when it ferments and expands, will break the old wineskins and spill out. New wine must be put into new wineskins, so that both can be preserved. This image indicates that Jesus’ new teachings and new kind of spiritual life could not be put into old Judaism. They required a new container—namely, the living church.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Winnower">
  <title>Winnower</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WINNOWER</p>
<p class="fl">One who removes chaff from grain. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Agriculture_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Agriculture</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wisdom">
  <title>Wisdom</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WISDOM</p>
<p class="fl">The ability to direct one’s mind toward a full understanding of human life and toward its moral fulfillment. Wisdom is thus a special capacity, necessary for full human living; it can be acquired through education and the application of the mind.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DivineWisdom">Divine Wisdom</p>
<p class="fl">Although the term “wisdom” is used primarily in the OT with reference to human beings, all wisdom is ultimately rooted and grounded in God. Wisdom forms a central part of the nature of God. In wisdom God created the universe (<a href="?bref=Pr.3.19">Prv 3:19</a>) and human beings (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.24">Ps 104:24</a>). Thus wisdom, in its positive connotations, is something inherent in God, reflected in creation, and a part of the reason for human existence.</p>
<p>Wisdom in creation is reflected in the form and order that emerged out of primeval chaos. The wisdom of God expressed in the creation of humanity means that human life may also be marked by form and order, and that meaning in life may be found in the created world, which contains marks of divine wisdom. The wisdom of God is creative, purposeful, and good; it is not merely the intellectual activity of God. The potential for human wisdom is rooted in the creation of mankind. Created by divine wisdom, human beings have within them the God-given capacity for wisdom. Thus, it is impossible to understand human wisdom without first grasping its necessary antecedent, divine wisdom.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HumanWisdom">Human Wisdom</p>
<p class="fl">The word “wisdom,” with reference to human beings, is used in a variety of different ways in the OT. The word is often used as virtually synonymous with the term “knowledge,” but in its general and secular uses it commonly indicates applied knowledge, skill, or even cunning. Wisdom could be defined as either “superior mental capacity” or “superior skill.” Thus, wisdom is used to describe both the cunning of King Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.1-6">1 Kgs 2:1-6</a>) and the skill of the craftsman Bezalel (<a href="?bref=Exod.35.33">Ex 35:33</a>). But it was also used to describe mental capacities and skills that had a moral component—the capacity to understand and to do good. Thus, when Moses delegated some of his authority to newly appointed judges, he chose men who were wise, understanding, and experienced (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.13">Dt 1:13</a>). Such men were considered the wise men in ancient Israel. Human wisdom, in this special sense, was not merely a gift from God, inherent at birth; it had to be developed consciously during a life lived in relationship with God.</p>
<p>Thus this positive and special kind of wisdom in human beings cannot be understood apart from God. A frequent theme of the Wisdom Literature in the OT is that the “fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom” (<a href="?bref=Pr.9.10">Prv 9:10</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Job.28.28">Jb 28:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.111.10">Ps 111:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.1.7">Prv 1:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.15.33">15:33</a>). In several ways, this theme sets a perspective for understanding true human wisdom.</p>
<p>First, human wisdom is possible only because of the divine wisdom present in creation; the potential for wisdom exists only because God created it. Second, if wisdom is to be developed in a human being, the starting point must be God—specifically, one must revere or fear God. This Hebraic concept of wisdom is strikingly different from the Greek concept. The Ionian philosophers, with remarkable power, developed a system of thought that began without the assumption of the existence of deity. They attempted to develop wisdom through human reason alone. But Hebrew wisdom, though it sought to develop both the reason and the intellect as did the Greeks, could start only with God. The mind and its capacities were God-given; thus, however secular in appearance the wisdom of the Hebrews might seem, it had God as its starting point. The reverence of God—namely the acknowledgment that God existed, created, and was important in human life—lay behind all the developments of Hebrew wisdom.</p>
<p>Human wisdom, in the Hebrew conception, is thus a development of the mind, an expansion of knowledge, and an understanding of both the meaning of life and how that life must be lived. It is thoroughly intellectual but has a powerful moral result. Wisdom was sought not for its own sake but always for its application to the meaning of life, because life—like wisdom—was God’s gift. This emphasis in Hebrew wisdom meant that the virtues of the wise man or woman were never described in intellectual terms alone. The wise are not the intelligentsia of Israelite society, but as the book of Proverbs makes clear, they were those whose lives were characterized by understanding, patience, diligence, trustworthiness, self-control, modesty, and similar virtues. In a word, the wise man was the God-fearing man; his wisdom lay not just in a static attitude of reverence but rather in the conscious development of the mind toward wisdom in the context of godly living.</p>
<p>From this general conception of wisdom there emerged in ancient Israel a special category of men, the wise men. Though wisdom was not limited to them, they were responsible for the growth and communication of wisdom in Israel. The wise men formed one of three classes of religious personnel. First, there were priests and Levites, whose responsibilities lay primarily within the context of established religion. They were the servants of the temple and the leaders of worship and also had certain responsibilities in the area of religious education. Second, there were the prophets, the spokesmen of God to the people of God. Third, there were the wise men. From a certain perspective, they possessed the most secular task among the three groups. They were involved in a variety of tasks, from governmental administration to moral and secular education. As moral educators, they instructed the young people of their day, not in how to make a living, but in how to live. Something of their curriculum has survived in the book of Proverbs. The books of Job and Ecclesiastes also reflect the thought of the wise men.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WisdomintheNewTestament">Wisdom in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The word “wisdom” is used in the NT both of the wisdom of God and the wisdom of humans. The continuation of the OT wisdom tradition is found in the NT’s use of the word in conjunction with God and in the positive connotations of the word in relation to human beings. But the NT also speaks negatively of human wisdom. Thus, Paul described his message as being “not in the plausible words of wisdom, but in demonstration of the Spirit and of power” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.4">1 Cor 2:4</a>). Purely human wisdom has no ultimate merit of its own, and Paul quotes the OT to demonstrate that God would destroy human wisdom (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.19">1 Cor 1:19</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.29.14">Is 29:14</a>). A clear distinction between good and evil wisdom is provided in the Letter of James (<a href="?bref=Jas.3.13-18">Jas 3:13-18</a>). A person whose life reflects jealousy and selfish ambition does not have the true wisdom of God but is earthly-minded and unspiritual. But true wisdom is God-given; this wisdom is “first pure, then peaceable, gentle, open to reason, full of mercy and good fruits, without uncertainty or insincerity” (v <a href="?bref=Jas.3.17">17</a>).</p>
<p>As wisdom was the primary possession of God, so too it was reflected in the life and ministry of Jesus. Jesus, during the years of his growth, reflected in his life the increase of wisdom (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.40,52">Lk 2:40, 52</a>), and his opponents, as well as his friends, recognized the wisdom in his teaching (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.54">Mt 13:54</a>).</p>
<p>Since wisdom is rooted and grounded in God, true and spiritual wisdom is God’s gift. It could be seen in the lives and words of the servants of God such as Stephen (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.10">Acts 6:10</a>) and Paul (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.15">2 Pt 3:15</a>). Spiritual wisdom, which provided the knowledge enabling a person to live fully the life given by God, was to be desired for oneself and prayed for in others (<a href="?bref=Col.1.9">Col 1:9</a>).</p>
<p>The most central aspect of wisdom in the NT is in the gospel of the crucified Christ. In his first letter to the Corinthian church, Paul contrasted vividly the positive and negative senses of wisdom in proclaiming the death of Jesus Christ. The world did not know God by their own wisdom (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.21">1 Cor 1:21</a>); that is, the true revelation of God and his redemption of mankind were not revealed to those who sought such truth through wisdom alone, namely, through the Greek approach to wisdom and philosophy. The gospel was declared in preaching, which was, from a strictly philosophical or wisdom perspective, a kind of foolishness. And yet the gospel of Jesus Christ was both the power of God and the wisdom of God (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.24">1 Cor 1:24</a>). Jesus, for those who believed, became the ultimate source of that wisdom that could come from God alone (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.30">1 Cor 1:30</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=WisdomLiterature_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wisdom Literature</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WisdomLiterature">
  <title>Wisdom Literature*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WISDOM LITERATURE*</p>
<p class="fl">Literature in the OT that has wisdom as its central theme. It comprises principally the books of Job, Proverbs, and Ecclesiastes and may also be found in portions of the Psalms and Prophets. The Wisdom Literature contains both the moral substance of true wisdom (as in Proverbs) and also the intellectual explorations of wise men seeking to understand the fundamental problems of human existence (as in Job, Ecclesiastes).</p>
<p>Wisdom Literature forms an important part of the OT. It falls within the third division of the Hebrew canon, called the Writings, and comprises basically three books: Proverbs, Ecclesiastes (or Koheleth), and Job. There are also wisdom psalms (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.1.1-6">Pss 1</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.32.1-11">32</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.34.1-22">34</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.37.1-40">37</a>) and wisdom-type passages in the Prophets (such as the parables of Isaiah). In the Greek OT (and the English Apocrypha), two additional books of wisdom are found. There is Ecclesiasticus, a second-century <span class="era">BC</span> work of Jesus ben Sirach, which has certain similarities to the book of Proverbs, and the Wisdom of Solomon, an anonymous work representing the flowering of Jewish wisdom in the Hellenistic period.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Proverbs">Proverbs</p>
<p class="fl">The starting point for an understanding of OT Wisdom Literature is Proverbs. Its wisdom concerns morality—the knowledge of how to live properly. It has a theological foundation, though much of its wisdom is secular in form. The starting point, as for all wisdom, is the reverence of God. But for the most part, the concern of the book is to convey the fundamentals of morality, the virtues of integrity, discipline, justice, and common sense, and to show by way of contrast the failure in life that awaits the fool. The book has a strongly didactic nature. Nowadays it can be read as a piece of literature, though its wisdom was designed to be learned, memorized even, by the young persons who received their education at the feet of the wise men. For those who learned its truth, for whom the short poetic sayings became a part of the subconscious mind, the wisdom of the proverbs served as a moral and spiritual guide throughout life. There was a way to live successfully, a way governed by morality, and success lay in the fact that the morally good life was the life lived according to the wisdom of the Creator of all life. Thus, the wise men of the proverbs functioned as guides, in both their teaching and their writing; they provided no new philosophical theories, no advanced intellectual speculation, but communicated that most valuable of all human kinds of knowledge: wisdom on how to live. Wisdom is “more precious than jewels, and nothing you desire can compare with her. Long life is in her right hand; in her left hand are riches and honor. Her ways are ways of pleasantness, and all her paths are peace” (<a href="?bref=Pr.3.15-17">Prv 3:15-17</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Ecclesiastes">Ecclesiastes</p>
<p class="fl">Ecclesiastes reflects the wisdom of a man who had lived long and seen the world from all perspectives. His faith was not the superficial faith of a man who lived easily and believed lightly. The man had seen that the righteous do not always prosper and the wicked suffer. Too often the righteous suffer, with no relief from their suffering, and the wicked enjoy their lives in carefree abandon. The writer of Ecclesiastes sought justice, but as he observed the world through honest and objective eyes, he could not see that justice was always done. More than justice, he sought truth, but even truth in its ultimate perspectives eluded him. All was vanity, a grasping after wind! Yet for all the skeptical and apparently negative tenor of Ecclesiastes, it is a magnificent monument of faith, a faith that held on to God despite the agony and pointlessness of a world filled with evil and vanity. This wise man could not soar with hope like that of the prophets, but he could hold on to the fundamental truth of God when all else, including understanding, failed. So the book of Ecclesiastes may become an intimate companion to those who see the world as it really is, in all its agony and apparent vanity.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Job">Job</p>
<p class="fl">Whereas the writer of Ecclesiastes described the grief and sadness of the world from the perspective of an observer, Job grasped the problems from within, from the perspective of the sufferer. Job knew the ancient proverbial wisdom and had lived his life by that wisdom, but he had an experience that called into question conventional morality and wisdom. He was a pious man, an upright man, whose life embodied the precepts of Proverbs. Prior to his experience, he had no cause to doubt a simple interpretation of proverbial wisdom: righteousness led to prosperity and happiness. But then Job’s world collapsed, and with it the wisdom by which he had lived. The loss of possessions, property, and prestige; the death of his children; the pain and suffering of terrible illness—all these things conspired to raise an enormous question as to the validity of traditional morality. But the wisdom of the book of Job raises an even more fundamental question than the validity of morality; Job questioned the premise of all wisdom, God himself. In what sense can God be just in the face of such apparent injustice? In what sense can God be just, when unjust men flourish and prosper (<a href="?bref=Job.21.7-15">Jb 21:7-15</a>)? Does God’s creation really reflect structure, order, and goodness, if the experience of Job is the measure of human life? Such are the radical questions evoked by Job, and they receive no simple solution. Yet in the great climax of the book of Job, namely, the encounter between God and Job (chs <a href="?bref=Job.38.1-42.17">38–42</a>), wisdom is set in its proper perspective. There remains always a mystery in God and in God’s ways that lies beyond the grasp of the human mind. Wisdom is pursuit of the knowledge of God, but wisdom as intellectual knowledge can never grasp ultimate truth in all its depth, for God is always greater than the human mind and human wisdom. Yet Job adds a further truth to the knowledge of conventional wisdom. While Job’s questions were not explicitly answered, they were effectively removed; it was the encounter of God with Job that transformed the man. Thus, the ultimate wisdom lies not in finding an answer to the ultimate questions but rather in the encounter with the living God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Conclusion">Conclusion</p>
<p class="fl">The teaching of the Wisdom Literature has manifold dimensions and in its totality is a compound of the various perspectives on the truth contained in Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, and Job. There is a fundamental knowledge and morality that is vital to proper and successful living and that must be communicated to the young as their basic rule of life. It will lead not always to material prosperity but to that more profound prosperity that transcends adversity—the prosperity of the person whose life is lived in reverence of God. With the passage of time and advancement of years, there comes to those educated in conventional wisdom the understanding that life and the world are not so simple. Faced with the temptation to jettison conventional morality and wisdom, a person may find that the more worldly wisdom of Ecclesiastes provides an anchor. Life may seem pointless, the world may seem to be essentially a place of vanity, but the truth of God and reverence for God must be maintained in the face of radical doubt (<a href="?bref=Eccl.12.13-14">Eccl 12:13-14</a>). To those who experience in some fashion the plight of Job, wisdom reaches its limits and points beyond itself; humans cannot always find an answer to the questions, and the last resort is simply the experience of the living God.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WisdomofJesusBenSirach">
  <title>Wisdom of Jesus Ben Sirach</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WISDOM OF JESUS BEN SIRACH</p>
<p class="fl">Deuterocanonical book that is also known as Ecclesiasticus (to be distinguished from the canonical book Ecclesiastes). The author is generally referred to as Jesus ben Sirach; however, in recently discovered Hebrew manuscripts, his name is given as Simon son of Jesus son of Eleazar ben Sirach. He was a Hebrew sage who lived in the beginning of the second century <span class="era">BC</span> and who taught in Jerusalem (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.50.27">Ecclus 50:27</a>; cf. <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.51.23">51:23ff</a>.). The work bears the imprint of a man steeped in a tradition later known as Sadducean.</p>
<p>This work was valued highly by both Jews and Christians. The author was a scribe who wished to give his teachings a more permanent form, for which he utilized the canonical Proverbs as a model. His instruction adheres closely to Jewish orthodoxy. The book was probably written about 180 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WisdomofSolomon">
  <title>Wisdom of Solomon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WISDOM OF SOLOMON</p>
<p class="fl">Deuterocanonical work containing a treasury of wisdom. A theological and/or philosophical treatise, the Wisdom of Solomon seeks to blend the piety of orthodox Judaism with the best of Greek philosophy.</p>
<p>The book tries to give the impression that the whole is the work of Solomon (see <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.8.9-21">Wisd of Sol 8:9-21</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.9.7-2">9:7-2</a>), but this is simply a device to gain authority for the statements of the book concerning wisdom. Originally composed in Greek rather than in Hebrew, it is likely the production of a cultivated Jew deeply influenced by Greek culture and ideas, familiar with the Septuagint, and writing at Alexandria probably in the first century <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The book was regarded as canonical by some of the early church fathers, including such notable figures as Origen, Eusebius of Caesarea, and Augustine of Hippo; it was even incorporated into the Muratorian Canon of the second century. Historically, it has been favorably regarded by Protestants, although not considered canonical. The Roman Catholic Church gave it official recognition as Scripture at the Council of Trent in <span class="era">AD</span> 1546.</p>
<p>The author sought to rekindle the religious zeal of his fellow Jews who have departed from the faith of their fathers, to encourage and fortify them for a life of faith and godliness in the midst of perplexities and persecutions and to demonstrate the folly of idolatry and the truth of Judaism. The book begins with the author being exhorted to “love righteousness, . . . think of the Lord with uprightness, and seek him with sincerity of heart” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.1.1">1:1</a>). From there on in, the book encourages people to become religious and to know God. By knowing God and conforming to his will, a person can attain immortality (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.15.3">15:3</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WiseMen">
  <title>Wise Men</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WISE MEN</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Magi_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Magi</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WitchWitchcraft">
  <title>Witch*, Witchcraft</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WITCH*, WITCHCRAFT</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Sorcery_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sorcery</a>; <a href="?item=Magic_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Magic</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WitheredHand">
  <title>Withered Hand*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WITHERED HAND*</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Deformity_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Deformity</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Witness">
  <title>Witness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WITNESS</p>
<p class="fl">One who tells what he or she has seen or personally experienced, often in a court of law. The term may also refer to the testimony the person has given.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WitnessintheOldTestament">Witness in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the judicial procedure outlined in the OT, one witness was not adequate for personal testimony against anyone, but two or three witnesses were required (<a href="?bref=Deut.17.6">Dt 17:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.19.15">19:15</a>). This principle was incorporated into Jewish law and is reiterated in the NT (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.18.16">Mt 18:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.13.1">2 Cor 13:1</a>).</p>
<p>The truth of testimony is so important that the Bible expressly forbids false witness in the ninth commandment (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.16">Ex 20:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.20">Dt 5:20</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.10.19">Mk 10:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.18.20">Lk 18:20</a>). The practical wisdom of Proverbs speaks out frequently against the false witness (e.g., <a href="?bref=Pr.6.19">Prv 6:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.14.5">14:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.25.18">25:18</a>). Nevertheless, false witnesses did arise (<a href="?bref=Ps.27.12">Pss 27:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.35.11">35:11</a>), and there are notable examples of the bringing of more than one witness in order to bring about the death of an innocent person. The case of Naboth and his vineyard is notorious; here Jezebel, wife of King Ahab, bribed two men to bear false witness against Naboth so that he would be stoned to death and her wicked husband could take the vineyard he coveted so intensely (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.1-29">1 Kgs 21</a>).</p>
<p>Witnesses could be tested by the judges. If the testimony of an accuser was found to be false, that person was subjected to the punishment he had sought to have executed on the defendant (<a href="?bref=Deut.19.16-21">Dt 19:16-21</a>). Proverbs also speaks of the punishment of the false witness (<a href="?bref=Pr.19.5,9">Prv 19:5, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.21.28">21:28</a>).</p>
<p>The OT records several accounts of legal proceedings in which witnesses are mentioned. Most of these involve the purchase or transfer of property. <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.7-12">Ruth 4:7-12</a> relates the redemption of a field from Naomi by Boaz. Isaiah found “reliable witnesses” concerning a property title written on a large tablet (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.1-2">Is 8:1-2</a>). To confirm the prophecy of the return of the exiles from Babylon, Jeremiah bought and paid for a field in the presence of witnesses, who also signed the deed for the property (<a href="?bref=Jer.32.6-15">Jer 32:6-15</a>).</p>
<p>At the conclusion of his farewell message at Shechem, Joshua declared that the Israelites themselves were witnesses that they had chosen to serve the Lord; then he set up a large stone and declared that it also was a witness (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.22-27">Jos 24:22-27</a>). The people of Israel themselves were declared God’s witnesses (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.10">Is 43:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.44.8-9">44:8-9</a>). They were witnesses to the existence of God, to his uniqueness, holiness, power, and love. When they failed to acknowledge his uniqueness and holiness and turned to idolatry, he sent them into captivity, as he had warned, for they had failed in their witness and had given opportunity for the enemies of God to blaspheme.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WitnessintheNewTestament">Witness in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the NT the various words for witness are mainly related to the verb <span class="greek">martureo</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “to bear witness, be a witness.” The word “martyr” shows the ultimate form of witness in that Christians have sacrificed their lives because of their witness for Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>John the Baptist was both a witness and a martyr. As the forerunner of the Messiah, his mission was to bear witness to the light and to identify the Lamb of God (<a href="?bref=John.1.7-8,19-36">Jn 1:7-8, 19-36</a>). The followers of Jesus, and particularly the 12 apostles, were witnesses to the person and character of Jesus. They knew him intimately, heard his teachings and observed his miracles; three were witnesses of his transfiguration (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.1-2">Mt 17:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.1.17-18">2 Pt 1:17-18</a>) and many were witnesses to his resurrection (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.48">Lk 24:48</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.4-8">1 Cor 15:4-8</a>). At the time of his ascension, the disciples were specifically commissioned to be his witnesses (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.8">Acts 1:8</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WitnessAltarof">
  <title>Witness, Altar of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WITNESS, Altar of</p>
<p class="fl">Altar built by the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh in the frontier of Israel near the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.10-34">Jos 22:10-34</a>). The building of the altar incited the remainder of Israel to threaten war for the presumed treachery. After the Transjordanian tribes explained their motives and Phinehas mediated the conflict, the altar was called “Witness” as a memorial of the resulting treaty.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wizard">
  <title>Wizard*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WIZARD*</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Magic_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Magic</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Woe">
  <title>Woe</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WOE</p>
<p class="fl">An exclamation denoting pain or displeasure. Less frequently, it occurs as a noun denoting a disaster or calamity. For example, in <a href="?bref=Rev.9.12">Revelation 9:12</a>, following the release of the demonic locusts from the abyss and their scourge upon those who follow the Beast, John announces, “The first woe is past; two other woes are yet to come” (<span class="sc">niv</span>). Again, in <a href="?bref=Rev.11.14">Revelation 11:14</a>, immediately before the seventh trumpet is sounded John writes, “The second woe has passed; the third woe is coming soon” (<span class="sc">niv</span>). The woes that Revelation describes are equivalent to the plagues of the OT, although somewhat more intense in that they are demonic in origin.</p>
<p>The Greek word is onomatapoeic: <span class="greek">ouai</span> (cf. the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">oi</span> and <span class="hebrew">hoi</span>). It is not necessarily a pronouncement of judgment in every case. At times it is an expression of regret or sorrow about the miserable situation that prompted the exclamation. In each case the context needs to be taken into consideration. In <a href="?bref=Matt.11.21">Matthew 11:21</a> (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.13">Lk 10:13</a>) when Jesus says, “Woe to you, Korazin! Woe to you, Bethsaida!” he was reproaching the people of those cities for their unbelief. The same is true in <a href="?bref=Luke.17.2">Luke 17:2</a> where Jesus pronounces woe upon the one who causes another to sin: “It would be better for him to be thrown into the sea with a millstone tied around his neck” (<span class="sc">niv</span>). In the Lucan Sermon on the Plain, the Beatitudes are followed by four woe statements. These statements are not so much threats as they are expressions of regret or compassion.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wolf">
  <title>Wolf</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WOLF</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Woman">
  <title>Woman</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WOMAN</p>
<p class="fl">Man’s companion created by God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HerCreation">Her Creation</p>
<p class="fl">Genesis provides two accounts of the creation of the first man and woman. In the first, <a href="?bref=Gen.1.26-28">Genesis 1:26-28</a>, God created humans in his image, as male and female. Hence, the female shares with the male the image of God, reflects his power and majesty on earth, and is commanded to multiply and bring dominion to the earth. From <a href="?bref=Gen.1.26-28">Genesis 1:26-28</a> there is no suggestion of inferiority of the female to the male, nor is there any suggestion of her submission to his dominance. Rather, they are pictured together, the male and the female, as the representation of their Maker.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Gen.2.20-25">Genesis 2:20-25</a> is the second portrayal of the creation of the first woman. In <a href="?bref=Gen.2.1-25">Genesis 2</a> the male was made before the female, a point that seems to give him some precedence. This may not be pressed too far, however, as the pattern in the creation texts is to move progressively from the lesser to the finer work! Yet it is because of his prior creation that the male is given the prerogative to name the female (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.23">Gn 2:23</a>). In Semitic thought, the giving of names signifies dominion or ownership. This means that Adam’s naming of his wife was an act of lordship. However, the name that he gives her is the equivalent to his own, meaning the male affirmed her equality with him. Paradoxically, then, this hierarchical relationship is also a relationship of equals.</p>
<p>The situation in <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Genesis 1</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.2.1-25">2</a> reveals a balanced relationship between the man and the woman who were the parents of all mankind: two persons who were altogether equal in status as coheirs of the mystery of the image of God and yet who dwell in a delicate one-to-one relationship in which one is the leader of the other. In Eden before the fall, this delicate balance was possible.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HerDownfallandPlight">Her Downfall and Plight</p>
<p class="fl"><a href="?bref=Gen.3.1-24">Genesis 3</a>, the story of the fall of mankind, speaks of the breaking of the delicate balance between the man and the woman and the ensuing struggles that have been passed down through the ages. In God’s words to the woman, he announced the pain that would accompany her childbearing (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.16">Gn 3:16</a>) and the conflict of interests that would affect her relationship with her husband: “Your desire will be for your husband, and he will rule over you” (<span class="sc">niv</span>). The Hebrew term “desire” <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">teshuqah</span><span class="ital">)</span> in the <a href="?bref=Gen.3.1-24">Genesis 3</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.4.1-26">4</a> passages is not a sexual longing but a desire to control, to master, to be in charge (the use of <span class="hebrew">teshuqah</span> meaning sexual desire is seen in <a href="?bref=Song.7.10">Sg 7:10</a>). Consequently, after the fall, the desire of woman has been to dominate her husband. Her determination to reject his leadership in their relationship of equals is a breaking of the balance in their relationship. For his part, the man tends to tyrannize the woman.</p>
<p>To the women who attempt to dominate their husbands, the apostle Paul says, “Wives, submit to your husbands as to the Lord” (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.22">Eph 5:22</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Her natural inclination needs transformation, so that she can submit to her husband as she submits to the Lord. For, Paul argues, the husband is to the wife as Christ is to the church (v <a href="?bref=Eph.5.23">23</a>). The husbands who tend to dominate their wives also need transformation so that they can love their wives, “just as Christ loved the church and gave himself up for her” (v <a href="?bref=Eph.5.25">25</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). By these words, the apostle Paul was presenting a means whereby couples could regain the bliss in their relationship that was the mark of Eden before the fall. Paul’s citation of <a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Genesis 2:24</a> in <a href="?bref=Eph.5.31">Ephesians 5:31</a> is a case in point: here a couple may regain the original oneness that God intended for them. The relationship of equal persons in a hierarchy of responsiveness is stated in the context of mutual submission, which is a mark of their greater submission to the Lord Jesus.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HerRoleinLifeaccordingtotheBible">Her Role in Life according to the Bible</p>
<p class="fl">A woman is a person in every respect as a man; she shares in the image of God and has the potential of varied ranges of response to culture, community, and life about her. It is a fact of Scripture that women are regularly associated with, and find their sense of worth in, childbearing. Yet the same Scriptures show that the nature of woman is not exhausted by associations with childbearing: she has her own identity in the community, in the church, and before the Lord in the whole of her life, not just when (or if) she bears and nourishes a child. Further, the biblical concept of childbearing always involves the husband, who is her partner at conception, at her side during delivery, and partner with her in the ongoing task of nourishing the child.</p>
<p>The image of the woman as the childbearer begins with the promise of God in <a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Genesis 3:15</a>, where he announced the ultimate victory over the evil one, Satan, by the offspring of the woman. This promise respecting the offspring of the woman became the universal blessing of God upon woman as the childbearer. Ultimately, through one born of a woman, there would come the final deliverance. There is a sense in which each birth experience is a participation in the continuity of this promise (see <a href="?bref=1Tim.2.15">1 Tm 2:15</a> and its possible relationship to this continuity of women, salvation, and childbearing).</p>
<p>Further, in the culture of the OT world, a woman’s genuine worth was solely, or largely, perceived in terms of childbearing. Yet it is not in childbearing alone that she finds worth and dignity before God. For the woman, as for the man, the issue of faith in the Lord is central. A woman who has a household of children but no faith in God might regard herself as a fulfilled person. Yet her care of her children is no substitute for piety to God. A woman who has no children, and perhaps no husband, may have her full identity and worth in her relationship with the God in whose image she is made and whose tasks she is commissioned by him to do. The gifts of God in a woman’s life may lead her to find opportunities in the community to express her devotion to God. Women apparently had the same opportunities as men to take a Nazirite vow (<a href="?bref=Num.6.2">Nm 6:2</a>; see also ch <a href="?bref=Num.30.1-16">30</a>).</p>
<p>Certain notable women in the Bible led lives of public service. Miriam, the sister of Moses and Aaron (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.20-21">Ex 15:20-21</a>), was a prophetess, musician, and national leader (<a href="?bref=Num.12.1-16">Nm 12</a>). Long after her time, God spoke through his prophets of the gift he had given to Israel in the person of the national leader Miriam (<a href="?bref=Mic.6.4">Mi 6:4</a>). There were other magnificent women who had exemplary lives: Deborah, the prophetess of God and the only named woman judge of Israel (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.1-5.31">Jgs 4–5</a>); Esther, the Hebrew queen of Xerxes who saved her people from the rash acts of the Persian king, a result of a frightful conspiracy; and Huldah, the prophetess who was the agent of the Lord’s word to Josiah at the inception of his revival (<a href="?bref=2Chr.34.22-28">2 Chr 34:22-28</a>). Huldah’s reception and transmission of the word of the Lord is the more remarkable because she was a contemporary with Jeremiah and Zephaniah. In this case God chose to speak through a woman.</p>
<p>In the NT, certain women were noted for their public ministries: the daughters of Philip, Phoebe, Priscilla, Junias, Tryphena, Tryphosa, Persis, Euodia, and Syntyche. These women mark the beginning of the fulfillment of Joel’s prophecy of a day in which women as well as men would be the instruments of the outpouring of the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-29">Jl 2:28-29</a>). Women such as Sarah, Ruth, and Hannah exercised their faith in God in the context of the home and family as well. And preeminently there is Mary, mother of Jesus, in whom the ideal of womanhood is conjoined to the fulfillment of the ancient promise to Eve that she would one day be the great victor over the enemy of mankind.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Eve_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eve</a>; <a href="?item=Man_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Man</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wonders">
  <title>Wonders</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WONDERS</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Miracle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Miracle</a>; <a href="?item=Sign_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sign</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wool">
  <title>Wool</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WOOL</p>
<p class="fl">Important commodity of the ancient Near East. King Mesha of Moab, a sheep breeder, annually sent the wool of 100,000 rams as tribute to King Ahab of Israel (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.4">2 Kgs 3:4</a>), and the people of Damascus traded wool with Tyre’s merchants (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.18">Ez 27:18</a>). Woolen garments were commonly worn by the Israelites (<a href="?bref=Lev.13.47-59">Lv 13:47-59</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.51.8">Is 51:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.2.5,9">Hos 2:5, 9</a>), though woolen garments mingled with linen fabric were forbidden (<a href="?bref=Deut.22.11">Dt 22:11</a>). In fact, wearing wool was prohibited entirely for Israelite priests serving in the sanctuary’s inner court (<a href="?bref=Ezek.44.17">Ez 44:17</a>).</p>
<p>Wool is sometimes a biblical symbol for whiteness and purity, it is a simile for redemption (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.18">Is 1:18</a>), for the hair of the Ancient of Days (<a href="?bref=Dan.7.9">Dn 7:9</a>), and for the hair and head of the Son of Man (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.14">Rv 1:14</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ClothandClothManufacturing_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cloth and Cloth Manufacturing</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WordWordofGodWordsofGod">
  <title>Word, Word of God, Words of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WORD, WORD OF GOD, WORDS OF GOD</p>
<p class="fl">A “word” is an expression that communicates. On the level of human communication, “words “usually refer to verbal expression. When God “spoke” over the centuries, though, he communicated in various ways (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.1">Heb 1:1</a>), culminating in that epitome of all divine expression, Jesus Christ, his Son.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheImportanceofWords">The Importance of Words</p>
<p class="fl">In a mainly nonliterary society the dependability of the spoken word was all-important in law, trade, religion, marriage, and reputation. Receipts, agreements, and records had little usefulness. Personal integrity and sincere speech were essential to communication and, for most people, to self-expression and stable relationships. The words of poets, prophets, storytellers, and instructors were carefully preserved.</p>
<p>Words were diligently tested. Foolish words, flattery, deceit, words of enticement, lies, rumor, scandal, and blasphemous speech were all recognized as evil. The oath had to be inviolable in commercial, judicial, and civic affairs. The spoken blessing had power within itself and could not be withdrawn (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.30-38">Gn 27:30-38</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.10.12-13">Mt 10:12-13</a>); so also the vow (<a href="?bref=Judg.11.34-35">Jgs 11:34-35</a>) and the curse (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.12-13">Gn 27:12-13</a>). Equally powerful was the word of command—of priestly, judicial, or royal authority (<a href="?bref=Eccl.8.4">Eccl 8:4</a>).</p>
<p>This estimate of human words lingers in the NT. The word reveals the inner self, and so every careless, hurtful, deceitful word will be judged (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.34-37">Mt 12:34-37</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.5.22">5:22</a>), as will blasphemy (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.10">Lk 12:10</a>). Paul (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.29">Eph 4:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.4">5:4</a>) and James (<a href="?bref=Jas.3.1-12">Jas 3:1-12</a>) preserve this Hebrew reverence for the spoken word.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheWordsofGod">The Words of God</p>
<p class="fl">God’s spoken word has been preserved in Scripture. His word came to and through the prophets (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.22">1 Kgs 12:22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.17.3">1 Chr 17:3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.3.2">Lk 3:2</a>), who spoke and acted “by the word of the Lord.” His word also came in the law, which God “spoke” on Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.1">Ex 20:1</a>); hence, “statutes,” “commandments,” and “precepts” are synonyms for God’s “word” (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.119.1-176">Ps 119</a>).</p>
<p>Periods when no such divine communication came constituted “famine” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.3.1">1 Sm 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.11">Am 8:11</a>). Mingled with warnings and injunctions were divine promises. All God’s words were dependable (<a href="?bref=Isa.31.2">Is 31:2</a>), firmly fixed in heaven (<a href="?bref=Ps.119.89">Ps 119:89</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.8">Is 40:8</a>), and backed up by divine oath (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.12">Jer 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.110.4">Ps 110:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.12.25,28">Ez 12:25, 28</a>). A word, expressing the divine mind, was not threatening or burdensome; it was a delight, hope, joy, and protection against sin (<a href="?bref=Ps.1.1-6">Pss 1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.119.1-176">119</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.15.16">Jer 15:16</a>). Men can live by it (<a href="?bref=Deut.8.3">Dt 8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.4.4">Mt 4:4</a>).</p>
<p>God’s word has power to execute his will. It will not return to him “empty” but accomplish that which he purposes (<a href="?bref=Isa.55.11">Is 55:11</a>). By his speech alone, God created the world, and his word upholds it (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Gn 1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.33.6">Ps 33:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.1.2">Heb 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.3">11:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.3.5">2 Pt 3:5</a>). Eventually, this divine revelation was put into writing, which makes the Bible also “the word of God” (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.13">Mk 7:13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.16.29-31">Lk 16:29-31</a>; <a href="?bref=John.5.39">Jn 5:39</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus spoke the word of God. He was “mighty in word” (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.19">Lk 24:19</a>); he taught with authority (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.22,27">Mk 1:22, 27</a>), exercising power over the sea, disease, demons, and death (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.8,13">Mt 8:8, 13</a>). His “word of the kingdom” is the living seed, which, planted in the good soil of receptive hearts, bears fruit for God (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.19">Mt 13:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.14">Mk 4:14</a>). The word that Christ gives to his disciples cleanses them and frees them (<a href="?bref=John.8.31">Jn 8:31</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.48">12:48</a>; <a href="?bref=John.15.3">15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.14">17:14</a>). The word of faith the church preaches (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.8-9,17">Rom 10:8-9, 17</a>) is variously described as the word of salvation, the word of grace, the word of reconciliation, the word of the gospel, the word of righteousness, and the word of life.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TheTitleWordInJohn11"/>
<p class="h2" id="TheWordofGod">The Word of God</p>
<p class="fl">Deliberately recalling <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Genesis 1</a>, the Gospel writer, John, named the Son of God “the Word.” As the Word, the Son of God fully conveys and communicates God. The Greek term is <span class="greek">logos</span><span class="ital">;</span> it was used in two ways by the Greeks. The word might be thought of as remaining within a person, when it denoted his thought or reason. Or it might refer to the word going forth from a person, when it denoted the expression of his thought, i.e., speech. As a philosophical term, the <span class="greek">logos</span> denoted the principle of the universe, even the creative energy that generated the universe. In both the Jewish conception and the Greek, the <span class="greek">logos</span> was associated with the idea of beginnings—the world began through the origination and instrumentality of the Word (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.3-31">Gn 1:3ff</a>., where the expression “God said” is used again and again). John may have had these ideas in mind, but most likely he originated a new term to identify the Son of God as the divine expression in human form (<a href="?bref=John.1.14">Jn 1:14</a>). He is the image of the invisible God (<a href="?bref=Col.1.15">Col 1:15</a>), the express image of God’s substance (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.3">Heb 1:3</a>). In the Godhead, the Son functions as the revealer of God and the reality of God, which is a central theme throughout John’s Gospel. John used a similar title in his first epistle: “the Word of life” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.1-3">1 Jn 1:1-3</a>). And in <a href="?bref=Rev.19.11-16">Revelation 19:11-16</a>, Jesus is presented as the King of kings and Lord of lords, who has a name on him: “the Word of God.”</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Bible_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bible</a>; <a href="?item=JohnGospelof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">John, Gospel of</a>; <a href="?item=Logos_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Logos</a>; <a href="?item=Revelation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Revelation</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Work">
  <title>Work</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WORK</p>
<p class="fl">A term referring either to God’s activity or to people’s regular occupation or employment.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheValueofWork">The Value of Work</p>
<p class="fl">The Bible’s positive outlook on work is rooted in its teaching about God. Unlike other ancient religious writings, which regarded creation as something beneath the dignity of the Supreme Being, Scripture unashamedly describes God as a worker. Like a manual laborer, he made the universe as “the work of his fingers” (<a href="?bref=Ps.8.3">Ps 8:3</a>). He worked with his raw material just as a potter works with the clay (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.9">Is 45:9</a>). The intricate development of the unborn child in the womb and the vast, magnificent spread of the sky both display his supreme craftsmanship (<a href="?bref=Ps.139.13-16">Pss 139:13-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.19.1">19:1</a>). In fact, all creation bears witness to his wisdom and skill (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.24">104:24</a>). The almighty Creator even had his rest day (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.2-3">Gn 2:2-3</a>) and enjoyed job satisfaction when surveying his achievements at the end of the week (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.31">1:31</a>).</p>
<p>This vivid biblical description of a working God reaches its climax with the incarnation of Jesus. The “work” that Jesus was given to do (<a href="?bref=John.4.34">Jn 4:34</a>) was, of course, the unique task of redemption. But he was also a worker in the ordinary sense. His contemporaries knew him as “a carpenter” (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>). In NT times carpentry and joinery were muscle-building trades. So the Jesus who stormed through the temple, overturning tables and driving out the men and animals (<a href="?bref=John.2.14-16">Jn 2:14-16</a>), was no pale weakling but a workingman whose hands had been hardened by years of toil with the ax, saw, and hammer. Hard, physical labor was not beneath the dignity of the Son of God.</p>
<p>If the Bible’s teaching about God enhances work’s dignity, its account of mankind’s creation gives all human labor the mark of normality. God “took the man and put him in the Garden of Eden to till it and keep it” (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.15">Gn 2:15</a>). And God’s first command, to “fill the earth and subdue it” (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.28">1:28</a>), implied a great deal of work for both man and woman. In an important sense, people today are obeying that command of their Creator when they do their daily work, whether they acknowledge him or not. Work did not, therefore, arrive in the world as a direct result of the fall into sin (though sin did spoil working conditions, <a href="?bref=Gen.3.17-19">3:17-19</a>). Work was planned by God from the dawn of history for mankind’s good—as natural to men and women as sunset is to day (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.19-23">Ps 104:19-23</a>).</p>
<p>With this firm emphasis on the dignity and normality of labor, it is no surprise to find that Scripture strongly condemns idleness. “Go to the ant, O sluggard; consider her ways, and be wise” (<a href="?bref=Pr.6.6">Prv 6:6</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Paul is equally blunt: “If any one will not work, let him not eat” (<a href="?bref=2Thes.3.10">2 Thes 3:10</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). He set a good example (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.33-35">Acts 20:33-35</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.2.9">1 Thes 2:9</a>). Those who refuse to work, he insists, even for spiritual reasons, earn no respect from non-Christian onlookers by depending on others to pay their bills (<a href="?bref=1Thes.4.11-12">1 Thes 4:11-12</a>). Wage earners, on the other hand, have the material resources of Christian service (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.28">Eph 4:28</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Vocations">Vocations</p>
<p class="fl">In biblical times the Greeks and Romans catalogued jobs according to importance or desirability. Routine manual labor, for example, was considered inferior to work involving mental activity.</p>
<p>Jewish teaching contrasts strongly with this attitude. “Hate not laborious work,” taught the rabbis (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.7.15">Ecclus 7:15</a>). Even the scholar had to spend some time in manual work. A few trades, like that of the tanner, were regarded as undesirable (a taboo broken very quickly by the early church—see <a href="?bref=Acts.9.43">Acts 9:43</a>), but there is no indication in the Bible that some jobs are more worthwhile than others in God’s sight. The Lord calls craftsmen into his service (<a href="?bref=Exod.31.1-11">Ex 31:1-11</a>), just as much as prophets (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.8-9">Is 6:8-9</a>). So Amos was summoned from his fruit-picking to prophesy (<a href="?bref=Amos.7.14-15">Am 7:14-15</a>), but with no suggestion that he was being promoted to a superior role. The important thing was not the nature of the occupation but the readiness to obey God’s call and to witness faithfully to him, whatever the job.</p>
<p>The Bible has some poignant things to say about the relationship between employer and employee. The OT prophets voice the strongest criticism. God is especially concerned to see that the weak get justice (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.17">Is 1:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.8">Mi 6:8</a>). So, naturally, his spokesmen declare his anger when employers exploit their laborers and cheat them of their wages (<a href="?bref=Jer.22.13">Jer 22:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.3.5">Mal 3:5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jas.5.4">Jas 5:4</a>). A person who wants to please God must “stop oppressing those who work for [him] and treat them fairly and give them what they earn” (<a href="?bref=Isa.58.6">Is 58:6</a>, <span class="sc">tlb</span>).</p>
<p>In Bible times, the scales were weighted heavily in favor of the employer. But Scripture is not blind to the existence of selfish, greedy employees. Every worker deserves a just wage (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.7">Lk 10:7</a>), but those with special power must not try to increase their pay by threats and violence (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.14">3:14</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="WorkingforChrist">Working for Christ</p>
<p class="fl">God is a working God who is pleased when his people work hard and conscientiously. That conviction lies at the heart of the Bible’s teaching about Christian attitudes toward secular employment. And quite naturally, the NT extends the same positive emphasis to cover all Christian service, paid or unpaid. The world is God’s harvest field, said Jesus, waiting for Christian reapers to move in and evangelize (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.37-38">Mt 9:37-38</a>). Paul used the same agricultural illustration and added another from the building trade to describe the Lord’s work of evangelism and teaching (<a href="?bref=1Cor.3.6-15">1 Cor 3:6-15</a>). Church leaders must work especially hard, he said (<a href="?bref=1Thes.5.12">1 Thes 5:12</a>), to stimulate <span class="ital">all</span> God’s people to be involved in the Lord’s work (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.58">1 Cor 15:58</a>). All Christians should see themselves as “God’s coworkers” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.3.9">3:9</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="World">
  <title>World</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WORLD</p>
<p class="fl">An important NT term from the Greek word <span class="greek">kosmos</span> (meaning that which is ordered or arranged), having five different meanings:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. The universe created by God with design and order (e.g., <a href="?bref=Matt.13.35">Mt 13:35</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.24">Jn 17:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.24">Acts 17:24</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. The planet earth (e.g., <a href="?bref=John.11.9">Jn 11:9</a>). This includes the idea of earth as the dwelling place of human beings (<a href="?bref=John.16.21">16:21</a>) and of earth as contrasted with heaven (<a href="?bref=John.6.14">6:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.46">12:46</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. The total of humanity (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.14">Mt 5:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.3.16">Jn 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.13">1 Cor 4:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. The total of human existence in this present life, with all of its experience and possessions (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.26">Mt 16:26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.33">1 Cor 7:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. The world order as alienated from God, in rebellion against him, and condemned for its godlessness. It is “this world” (<a href="?bref=John.8.23">Jn 8:23</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.25">12:25</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.3.19">1 Cor 3:19</a>), as opposed to “that which is to come.” The ruler of this world is the devil (<a href="?bref=John.12.31">Jn 12:31</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.30">14:30</a>; <a href="?bref=John.16.11">16:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.10">1 Cor 5:10</a>)—as John said it, “The whole world is under the control of the evil one” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.5.19">1 Jn 5:19</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Christians are not of this world (<a href="?bref=John.15.19">Jn 15:19</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.16">17:16</a>), even though they live in the world and participate in its activities (<a href="?bref=John.17.11">17:11</a>). The believer is regarded as dead to the world (<a href="?bref=Gal.6.14">Gal 6:14</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Col.3.2-3">Col 3:2-3</a>). The Christian is to be separated from the world (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.27">Jas 1:27</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">One’s relationship with the world is an indicator of one’s relationship with God. Those who love the world are void of love for God the Father (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.15">1 Jn 2:15</a>). The Scripture points out that “all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh and the lust of the eyes and the pride of life, is not of the Father but is of the world” (v <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.16">16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The world and its desires or lusts are transient, passing away, but the doer of God’s word abides forever (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.17">1 Jn 2:17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.4.18">2 Cor 4:18</a>). Friendship with the world is enmity toward God (<a href="?bref=Jas.4.4">Jas 4:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The discourse of Jesus on the night before his crucifixion contains much teaching about the world. The world cannot receive the Spirit of truth (<a href="?bref=John.14.17">Jn 14:17</a>). Christ gives a peace that the world cannot give (v <a href="?bref=John.14.27">27</a>). Jesus offers love, while the world gives hatred and persecution (<a href="?bref=John.15.19-20">15:19-20</a>). The world’s hatred of God is also directed against the followers of Christ (vv <a href="?bref=John.15.18-21">18-21</a>). Although the disciples of Jesus have tribulation “in this world,” they are to be of good cheer, for Jesus has overcome the world (<a href="?bref=John.16.33">16:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Another Greek word sometimes translated “world” is <span class="greek">aion</span><span class="ital">,</span> which emphasizes the temporal aspect of the world. It is used of time without end, eternity (e.g., <a href="?bref=Rom.1.25">Rom 1:25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.31">2 Cor 11:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.4.20">Phil 4:20</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Age_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Age</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Worm">
  <title>Worm</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WORM</p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wormwood">
  <title>Wormwood*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WORMWOOD*</p>
<p class="fl">Strong, bitter-tasting plant that symbolized bitterness and sorrow (<a href="?bref=Pr.5.4">Prv 5:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.9.15">Jer 9:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.8.11">Rv 8:11</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Worship">
  <title>Worship</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WORSHIP</p>
<p class="fl">Expression of reverence and adoration of God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WorshipintheOldTestament">Worship in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The 1,500 years from the days of Abraham to the time of Ezra (c. 1900–450 <span class="era">BC</span>) saw many significant changes in the form of worship in ancient Israel. Abraham, the wandering nomad, built altars and offered sacrifices wherever God appeared to him. In Moses’ time the tabernacle served as a portable sanctuary for the Israelite tribes journeying through the wilderness. Solomon built a temple in Jerusalem that lasted more than three centuries until its destruction by the Babylonians in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. When the Jews returned from exile, they built a new temple, which was later renovated and enlarged by Herod the Great. Though all the temple buildings were destroyed by the Romans in <span class="era">AD</span> 70, the foundations remained. Jews still pray by the Western Wall (called the Wailing Wall).</p>
<p>If the form of worship changed with times and situations, its heart and center did not. God revealed himself to Abraham, promising that his children would inherit the land of Canaan. Abraham demonstrated his faith through prayer and sacrifice. Throughout the biblical period listening to God’s Word, prayer, and sacrifice constituted the essence of worship. The promises to Abraham were constantly recalled as the basis of Israel’s existence as a nation and its right to the land of Canaan.</p>
<p>From time to time every family visited the temple in Jerusalem. Eight days after a baby boy was born, he was circumcised to mark his membership in Israel. Then, a month or two later, the baby’s mother went to the temple to offer sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Lev.12.1-8">Lv 12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.2.22-24">Lk 2:22-24</a>).</p>
<p>Animals were sacrificed in the lambing and calving season. The first lamb or calf born to every ewe or cow was presented in sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.30">Ex 22:30</a>). Similarly, at the beginning of the harvest season, a basket of the first fruits was offered, and at the end, a tenth of all the harvest, the tithe, was given to the priests as God’s representatives (<a href="?bref=Num.18.21-32">Nm 18:21-32</a>). <a href="?bref=Deut.26.5-15">Deuteronomy 26:5-15</a> gives a typical prayer for use on such occasions.</p>
<p>Sometimes a person would decide to offer a sacrifice for more personal reasons. In a crisis, vows could be made and sealed with a sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Gen.28.18-22">Gn 28:18-22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.10-11">1 Sm 1:10-11</a>). Then when the prayer was answered, a second sacrifice was customarily offered (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.3,14">Gn 35:3, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.24-25">1 Sm 1:24-25</a>). Serious sin or serious sickness were also occasions for sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.1-5.19">Lv 4–5</a>, <a href="?bref=Lev.13.1-15.33">13–15</a>).</p>
<p>The worshiper brought the animal into the temple court. Standing before the priest, he placed one hand on its head, thereby identifying himself with the animal, and confessed his sin or explained the reason for offering the sacrifice. Then the worshiper killed the animal and cut it up for the priest to burn on the great bronze altar. Some sacrifices (burnt offerings) involved the whole animal being burnt on the altar. In others, some of the meat was set aside for the priests, while the rest was shared by the worshiper and his family. But in every case the worshiper killed the animal from his own flock with his own hands. These sacrifices expressed in a vivid and tangible way the cost of sin and the worshiper’s responsibility. As the worshiper killed the animal, he recalled that sin would have caused his own death, had God not provided an escape through animal sacrifice.</p>
<p>Three times a year all adult men went to the temple to celebrate the national festivals (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.17">Ex 23:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.16.16">Dt 16:16</a>): Passover (held in April), the Feast of Weeks (held in May), and the Feast of Booths (in October). When possible, the whole family accompanied the men. But if they lived a long way from Jerusalem, they would go up for only one of the festivals (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.3">1 Sm 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.41">Lk 2:41</a>).</p>
<p>These festivals were tremendous occasions. Hundreds of thousands of people converged on Jerusalem. They would stay with relatives or camp in tents outside the city. The temple courts would be thronged with worshipers. The temple choirs sang psalms appropriate for the festival, while the priests and Levites offered hundreds (at Passover, thousands) of animals in sacrifice. Groups of worshipers carried away with emotion would break forth into dancing. Those of more sober temperament were content to join in the singing or simply pray quietly.</p>
<p>The major festivals were joyful occasions, for they celebrated the deliverance of Israel from Egypt. At Passover each family ate roasted lamb and bitter herbs to reenact the last meal their forefathers ate before leaving Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.1-51">Ex 12</a>). At the Feast of Booths, they built shelters of branches and lived in them for a week, as a reminder that the Israelites camped in tents during the 40 years of wandering in the wilderness (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.39-43">Lv 23:39-43</a>). These great festivals served as reminders of how God had delivered them from slavery in Egypt and had given them the land of Canaan as he had promised to Abraham.</p>
<p>Each of these three festivals lasted a week, but there was one day in the year that was totally different, the Day of Atonement, when everyone fasted and mourned for their sins. On this day the high priest confessed the nation’s sins as he pressed his hand on the head of a goat. Then the goat was led away into the wilderness, symbolizing the removal of sin from the people (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.1-34">Lv 16</a>).</p>
<p>Sometime after the destruction of the first temple, synagogues developed for public worship. The services were more like modern church worship, consisting exclusively of prayer, Bible reading, and preaching. There were no sacrifices made in the synagogues. When the second temple was destroyed in <span class="era">AD</span> 70, synagogues became the only places where Jews could worship in public. Then there were no more sacrifices at all. The NT pictures this as fitting, for Jesus was the true Lamb of God (<a href="?bref=John.1.29">Jn 1:29</a>); because of his death, there is no need for further animal sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.11-12">Heb 10:11-12</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="WorshipintheNewTestament">Worship in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The Jews had become far too dependent on a physical place, the temple, for their worship. When Jesus arrived on the scene, he proclaimed that he himself was the temple of God; in resurrection, he would provide the spiritual dwelling where God the Spirit and people, in spirit, could have spiritual communion (see <a href="?bref=Matt.12.6">Mt 12:6</a>; <a href="?bref=John.2.19-22">Jn 2:19-22</a>). In other words, worship would no longer be in a place but in a person—through Jesus Christ and his Spirit the worshipers could come directly to God (see <a href="?bref=John.14.6">Jn 14:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.19-20">Heb 10:19-20</a>).</p>
<p>This shift in worship—from physical to spiritual—is the theme of <a href="?bref=John.4.1-54">John 4</a>, a chapter that recounts Jesus’ visit to the Samaritans. After Jesus’ encounter with the Samaritan woman, she acknowledged that he must be a prophet, and then she launched into a discussion concerning the religious debate between the Jews and the Samaritans over which place of worship was the right one—Jerusalem or Mt Gerizim. The Samaritans had set up a place for worship on Mt Gerizim in accordance with <a href="?bref=Deut.11.26-29">Deuteronomy 11:26-29</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.27.1-8">27:1-8</a>, while the Jews had followed David and Solomon in making Jerusalem the center of Jewish worship. The Scriptures affirmed Jerusalem as the true center for worship (<a href="?bref=Deut.12.5">Dt 12:5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.6.6">2 Chr 6:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.7.12">7:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.67-68">Ps 78:67-68</a>). But Jesus told her that a new age had come in which the issue no longer concerned a physical site. God the Father would no longer be worshiped in either place. A new age had come in which the true worshipers (Jew, Samaritan, or Gentile) must worship the Father in spirit and in truth.</p>
<p>“In spirit” corresponds to Jerusalem, and “in truth” corresponds to the Samaritans’ unknowledgeable ideas of worship, God, etc. Formerly, God was worshiped in Jerusalem, but now the true Jerusalem would be in a person’s spirit. Indeed, the church is called “the habitation of God in spirit” (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.22">Eph 2:22</a>). True worship required a people to contact God, the Spirit, in their spirit, as well as a people who knew the truth. New Testament worship must be in spirit and in truth. Since “God is Spirit,” he must be worshiped in spirit. Human beings possess a human spirit, the nature of which corresponds to God’s nature, which is spirit. Therefore, people can have fellowship with God and worship God in the same sphere that God exists in.</p>
<p>In a sense, <a href="?bref=John.4.1-54">John 4</a> anticipates <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-27">Revelation 21</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.22.1-21">22</a>, where God provides the rivers of the water of life to all the believers and where the Lamb and God are the temple in the New Jerusalem. The believers receive life from God and they worship in God. There is a profound, even mystical connection between drinking of the Spirit and worshiping God in the Spirit (see <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.13">1 Cor 12:13</a>). This is also described in <a href="?bref=Ezek.47.1-23">Ezekiel 47</a>, which pictures the river flowing from God’s temple as a symbol of God’s never-ending supply. In <a href="?bref=John.4.1-54">John 4</a>, Jesus provides the living waters to all who receive the gift of God, and he directs people to a new temple, a spiritual one, where God is worshiped in spirit.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WrathofGod">
  <title>Wrath of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WRATH OF GOD</p>
<p class="fl">A term for God’s displeasure with human beings and their sinful actions. The word “wrath” is a concept represented by many different words and idioms in the original languages of the Bible, all of which express the notion of justifiable anger for unjust actions.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT God is said to be angry with nations, sinners, and even with his covenant people. God’s anger is first expressed toward the covenant community of Israel for having refused to believe his word about entering into the Promised Land. After they had been rescued from Egypt, had received the Ten Commandments and the covenant, and had seen his glory (<a href="?bref=Num.11.10">Nm 11:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.12.9">12:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.22.22">22:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.32.10-14">32:10-14</a>), they still disbelieved. Consequently, God in his wrath condemned the Israelites to wander in the wilderness until they died. The major reason for the Lord’s anger in the OT was that his own people constantly broke the covenant. They provoked him by their idolatry (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.15">Dt 2:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.25">4:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.9.7-8,19">9:7-8, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.2.14">Jgs 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.9">1 Kgs 11:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.9,15">14:9, 15</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.18">2 Kgs 17:18</a>), by their mixing paganism with the worship of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.10-17">Is 1:10-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.20">Jer 6:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.6.6">Hos 6:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.21-27">Am 5:21-27</a>); by their wanton rebellion (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.46">1 Kgs 8:46</a>), their unbelief (<a href="?bref=Num.11.33">Nm 11:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.14.11,33">14:11, 33</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.95.10-11">Ps 95:10-11</a>), and their disregard for his concern for love, justice, righteousness, and holiness (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.22-24">Ex 22:22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.15-17">Is 1:15-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.7-12">Am 5:7-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.3.1">Mi 3:1</a>).</p>
<p>The wrath of God also extends to all humanity (<a href="?bref=Nah.1.2">Na 1:2</a>). The concept of the Day of the Lord was developed by the prophets to warn Israel and the nations that no one can escape the righteous expression of God’s wrath (<a href="?bref=Amos.5.18-20">Am 5:18-20</a>). The Day of the Lord is the day of his wrath (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.15">Zep 1:15</a>).</p>
<p>The OT presents the concept of the wrath of God in balance with three other doctrines: his forbearance, his love, and his readiness to forgive. First, God is patient. The Hebrew word for “patient” is related to the word for “wrath” and means “length of wrath”; that is, God does not quickly become angry. He is longsuffering (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6">Ex 34:6</a>). Second, God is full of compassion and fidelity (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6">Ex 34:6</a>). Even when his children sin against him, he is like a father who is full of compassion and love. He is always faithful to his children. Third, he is ready to forgive those who sin against him when they atone for and are cleansed from their sins (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6">Ex 34:6</a>). The pleasure of his love is so much greater than his wrath (<a href="?bref=Ps.30.5">Ps 30:5</a>). Micah prayed that the Lord may soon forgive and restore his people on the ground that he cannot be angry forever (<a href="?bref=Mic.7.18">7:18</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.89.46">Ps 89:46</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.3.5">Jer 3:5</a>). In <a href="?bref=Ps.103.8-13">Psalm 103:8-13</a>, the psalmist likens God’s love and forgiveness to that of a father who does not harbor his anger continually, nor does he vex his children with discipline, so great is his love for those who fear him.</p>
<p>The purpose of God’s wrath is not to destroy humanity (<a href="?bref=Hos.11.9">Hos 11:9</a>). His wrath is neither a vindictive, emotional overreaction, nor is it unpredictable. In his wrath he sovereignly imposes limits on nations (Babylon, Assyria) and disciplines his own people with the desired end that they return to him (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.13-14">Jl 2:13-14</a>). The OT presentation of the Day of the Lord doesn’t end with God’s anger; it concludes with the restoration of the earth, when the whole earth will be filled with knowledge of God (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.9">Is 11:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.2.14">Hb 2:14</a>) and wickedness will be no more (<a href="?bref=Isa.65.25">Is 65:25</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The NT also teaches the wrath of God side by side with the doctrine of his grace, love, and forbearance (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.7">Mt 3:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.21.23">Lk 21:23</a>; <a href="?bref=John.3.36">Jn 3:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.18">Rom 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.6">Eph 5:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.14.10">Rv 14:10</a>). Those who do not profess faith in the risen Christ remain in their sins and will be subject to God’s wrath, whereas those who believe in him are delivered from God’s wrath (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.3">Eph 2:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.10">1 Thes 1:10</a>). The good news of the NT is that Jesus has come to deliver us from the wrath of God (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.9">Rom 5:9</a>). Those who have been delivered are reconciled with God (v <a href="?bref=Rom.5.10">10</a>) because they no longer are under condemnation (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.1">8:1</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Death_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Death</a>; <a href="?item=Hell_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hell</a>; <a href="?item=Judgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judgment</a>; <a href="?item=LastJudgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Last Judgment</a>; <a href="?item=Love_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Love</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Writer">
  <title>Writer</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WRITER</p>
<p class="fl">Professional scribe and/or secretary; religious scribe and/or secretary.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ProfessionalScribesandSecretaries">Professional Scribes and Secretaries</p>
<p class="fl">Scribes were employed as secretaries in Palestine, Egypt, Mesopotamia, and the Greco-Roman Empire. Court scribes would sometimes rise to positions of social prestige and considerable political influence, much as a secretary of state today.</p>
<p>There were schools for the training of such scribes. To master the difficult art of writing on clay probably required as much time then as it takes students now to develop the ability to read and write. Would-be scribes could either enter a regular school or work as an apprentice under a private teacher, though most of them apparently followed the latter procedure. Scribes who were willing to teach could be found everywhere, even in the smaller towns. In fact, most of the scribes had at least one apprentice, who was treated like a son while learning the profession. Such students learned not only from private tutoring but also from the example of their teacher. This kind of education was sufficient to equip young scribes for the normal commercial branches of the craft. They were fully prepared to handle the necessary formulas for the various kinds of legal and business documents, and they could easily take dictation for private correspondence.</p>
<p>For additional study and training, however, it was necessary to attend the regular schools. The schools were attached to temples, and only these schools had the proper facilities to teach the sciences (including mathematics) and literature, which the more advanced scribes had to master. There a budding scribe could study to become even a priest or a “scientist.” In the ruins of ancient cities archaeologists have discovered “textbooks” used by the pupils. Excavators have also uncovered schoolrooms with benches on which the students sat. Some of the ancient Near Eastern texts that have been unearthed are nothing but schoolboy exercises or student copies of originals. These copies are usually not as beautiful or as legible as the originals, which were written by master scribes.</p>
<p>When the teacher wanted to give the students an assignment, he had available in the temple school virtually every type of text imaginable. For elementary work he could have the students practice writing a list of cuneiform signs, much like our learning the letters of the alphabet—except that there were some 600 signs! Another simple assignment would have been to copy dictionaries containing lists of stones, cities, animals, and gods. After such preparatory work, the students could then move on to literary texts and, for example, accurately reproduce a portion of one of the great epics, a hymn, or a prayer. Through arduous study and a lengthy program of instruction and practice, a gifted student could become qualified for scribal service in almost any field.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ReligiousScribe">Religious Scribe</p>
<p class="fl">The scribe in Israel undertook a wide range of writing tasks. Often the scribe sat at the gate of the city or in an open area undertaking numerous kinds of writing tasks for illiterate citizens, correspondence, writing of receipts, and contracts. More officially, he kept records and wrote annals. Religious scribes copied the Scriptures. Several of these men are mentioned in the OT: Shebna (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.18,37">2 Kgs 18:18, 37</a>), Shaphan (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.8-12">2 Kgs 22:8-12</a>), Ezra (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.6,11">Ezr 7:6, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.8.1,9,13">Neh 8:1, 9, 13</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.12.26,36">12:26, 36</a>), Baruch (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.26,32">Jer 36:26, 32</a>), and Jonathan (<a href="?bref=Jer.37.15,20">Jer 37:15, 20</a>).</p>
<p>Paul made use of secretaries or scribes (called amanuenses) when he composed his epistles. The usual procedure for a dictated epistle was for the amanuensis to take down the speaker’s words and produce a transcript, which the author would then review and edit. Taking the edited copy, the amanuensis would produce a final draft, which the author would sign in his own handwriting. Two NT epistles provide the name of an amanuensis: Tertius for Romans (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.22">Rom 16:22</a>) and Silvanus for 1 Peter (<a href="?bref=1Pet.5.12">1 Pt 5:12</a>). Some of Paul’s epistles indicate that he provided the concluding salutation in his own handwriting: 1 Corinthians (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.21">1 Cor 16:21</a>), Galatians (<a href="?bref=Gal.6.11">Gal 6:11</a>), Colossians (<a href="?bref=Col.4.18">Col 4:18</a>), and 2 Thessalonians (<a href="?bref=2Thes.3.17">2 Thes 3:17</a>). This indicates that these epistles were penned by someone else—Paul’s amanuensis—prior to his signing off. By contrast, John penned his own epistles (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.4">1 Jn 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.1,7-8,12-14">2:1, 7-8, 12-14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Jn.1.12">2 Jn 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=3Jn.1.9,13">3 Jn 1:9, 13</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=LetterWritingAncient_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Letter Writing, Ancient</a>; <a href="?item=Writing_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Writing</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
<item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Writing">
  <title>Writing</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WRITING</p>
<p class="fl">The process that goes into producing books.</p>
<p>Books have been written for many centuries but have not always been produced in the familiar form in which they are known today. If a book is defined as any written record of thoughts or acts, the production of books goes back to a very early period in the history of civilization. The Sumerians produced written documents and primers on clay tablets as early as 2500 <span class="era">BC</span>. The Sumerian civilization went into decline after its conquest by the Akkadians (2300 <span class="era">BC</span>). In the 21st century <span class="era">BC</span>, however, there occurred a revival of Sumerian culture that produced a number of important literary works, including the first known written codified system of law. Today a rich collection of Sumerian material exists. It includes legal, mythological, and commercial documents as well as written material produced in the process of training scribes. A large collection of cuneiform tablets was found in the library of the Assyrian king Ashurbanipal, which was established in the seventh century <span class="era">BC</span>. The library contained many records of religious and scientific knowledge.</p>
<p>We have many ancient manuscripts of the books of the Bible. As for the books of the Hebrew Bible, scribes used quill, ink, and leather scrolls to make copies of individual books. Some of the scrolls, made of several treated animal hides stitched together, could be as long as 35 to 40 feet (10.7 to 12.2 meters) when unrolled. As scrolls wore out, or if there was a need for copies in various synagogues, Jewish scribes would make additional copies—and they did so with painstaking care. Prior to the Dead Sea Scroll discoveries, museums housed several manuscripts of the Hebrew Bible dated between the eighth and tenth centuries. The Dead Sea Scrolls are dated between 100 <span class="era">BC</span> and <span class="era">AD</span> 100, which makes them a thousand years earlier than these other mauscripts. The Dead Sea Scrolls contain significant portions of the OT. Every book except Esther is represented. The largest portions come from the Pentateuch (especially Deuteronomy—25 manuscripts), the Major Prophets (especially Isaiah—18 manuscripts), and Psalms (27 manuscripts). As for the books of the NT, we have nearly 6,000 manuscripts prior to the time of the printing press (c. 1500). About 200 of these manuscripts date between the early second and late fourth century. Most of the NT manuscripts were written on papyrus or vellum, and all of the NT manuscripts were written in the codex form.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WritingMaterials">Writing Materials</p>
<p class="h3">Clay</p>
<p class="fl">The Sumerian, Babylonian, and Assyrian clay tablets are well known. Baked clay tablets were preserved easily in almost any climate. They were suitable, however, only for a straight-line form of writing such as cuneiform, and were therefore not appropriate for the rounded Aramaic form of Hebrew script.</p>
<p class="h3">Papyrus</p>
<p class="fl">The papyrus rolls of Egypt have been used as a writing surface since the early third millennium <span class="era">BC</span>. The Greeks adopted papyrus around 900 <span class="era">BC</span>, and the Romans adopted its use later. The oldest extant Greek rolls of papyrus date from the fourth century <span class="era">BC</span>. The inner pith of the papyrus plant was called <span class="greek">byblos</span><span class="ital">.</span> From this comes the Greek word <span class="greek">biblion</span> (“book”) and the English word “bible.” The word “paper” is derived from “papyrus.”</p>
<p>Unfortunately, papyrus is perishable, requiring a dry climate for its preservation. That is why few papyri have been discovered anywhere other than in the desert sands of Egypt. Some papyrus fragments have also been found in the caves near the Dead Sea, where the climate is likewise sufficiently dry.</p>
<p class="h3">Potsherds</p>
<p class="fl">Broken pieces of pottery furnished an inexpensive writing material because the supply was so abundant. The Samaria and Lachish ostraca are examples.</p>
<p class="h3">Wood</p>
<p class="fl">Wooden tablets covered with stucco or wax were sometimes used as a writing surface. A NT example is <a href="?bref=Luke.1.63">Luke 1:63</a>.</p>
<p class="h3">Leather, Parchment, and Vellum</p>
<p class="fl">These are all made from animal skins. Leather (tanned skins), the forerunner of parchment, has been in use about as long as papyrus, but it was rarely used because papyrus was so abundant. The ancient Hebrews probably used leather and papyrus for writing materials. The Dead Sea Scrolls were sheets of leather sewed together with linen thread. Metal scrolls also existed (e.g., copper).</p>
<p>Parchment, made in the beginning from sheep and goat skins, began to replace leather as early as the third century <span class="era">BC</span>, though actual parchment codices date from the second century <span class="era">AD</span>. To prepare parchment or refined leather, the hair was removed from the skins and the latter rubbed smooth. The most common form of book for OT and NT documents was evidently a roll or scroll of papyrus, leather, or parchment. The average length of a scroll was about 30 feet (9.1 meters), though the famous Harris Papyrus was 133 feet (40.5 meters) long. Scrolls were often stored in pottery jars (<a href="?bref=Jer.32.14">Jer 32:14</a>) and were frequently sealed (<a href="?bref=Rev.5.1">Rv 5:1</a>).</p>
<p>Vellum had a finer quality than parchment and was prepared from the skins of calves, lambs, or kids. In the fourth century <span class="era">AD</span>, vellum or parchment as a material and the codex as a form became the norm.</p>
<p class="h3">Paper</p>
<p class="fl">Paper, made from wood, rags, and certain grasses, began to replace vellum and parchment as early as the tenth century <span class="era">AD</span> in the Western world, though it was used considerably earlier in China and Japan. By the 15th century, paper manuscripts were common.</p>
<p class="h2" id="KindsofBooks">Kinds of Books</p>
<p class="h3">Scroll</p>
<p class="fl">The scroll is a roll of papyrus, parchment, or leather used for writing a document or literary work. The papyrus scroll of Egypt can be traced as far back as 2500 <span class="era">BC</span>. One of the most famous literary productions of ancient Egypt is the Book of the Dead. Jews used leather scrolls for writing the books of the Old Testament. Most of the scrolls discovered from the Dead Sea area were written on leather, with a few having been written on papyrus.</p>
<p class="h3">Codex</p>
<p class="fl">An important development in the evolution of book production occurred with the advent of the codex in the middle of the first century. A codex was constructed much like our modern books by folding sheets of papyrus or vellum (treated animal hide) in the middle and then sewing them together at the spine. This kind of book was advantageous because it enabled the scribe to write on both sides; it facilitated easier access to particular passages (as opposed to a scroll, which had to be unrolled); and it enabled Christians to bind together all four Gospels or all Paul’s epistles or any other such combination.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientCodexOfPaulSEpistles"/>
<p class="h2" id="WritingUtensilsandInk">Writing Utensils and Ink</p>
<p class="fl">Different kinds of writing implements were used, depending on the writing surfaces in use at various periods of history. Metal chisels and gravers were used for inscribing stone and metal. A stylus was used for writing cuneiform (“wedge-shaped” characters) on clay tablets. For writing on ostraca (potsherds), papyrus, and parchment, a reed was split or cut to act as a brush. In Egypt rushes were used to form a brush. Later, reeds were cut to a point and split like a quill pen. Apparently this was the type of pen or “calamus” used in NT times (<a href="?bref=3Jn.1.13">3 Jn 1:13</a>).</p>
<p>Ink (cf. <a href="?bref=2Jn.1.12">2 Jn 1:12</a>) was usually a black carbon (charcoal) mixed with gum or oil for use on parchment or mixed with a metallic substance for papyrus. It was kept in an inkhorn as a dried substance, on which the scribe would dip or rub his moistened pen. It could be erased by washing (<a href="?bref=Num.5.23">Nm 5:23</a>) or with a penknife, which was also used for sharpening pens and trimming or cutting scrolls (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.23">Jer 36:23</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Hieroglyphics_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hieroglyphics</a>; <a href="?item=Inscriptions_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Inscriptions</a>; <a href="?item=LachishLetters_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Lachish Letters</a>; <a href="?item=LetterWritingAncient_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Letter Writing, Ancient</a>; <a href="?item=Scribe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Scribe</a>; <a href="?item=Writer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Writer</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>
</items>