<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Japheth">
  <title>Japheth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JAPHETH</p>
<p class="fl">One of Noah’s three sons (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.32">Gn 5:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.7.13">7:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.9.18,23,27">9:18, 23, 27</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.10.1-5">10:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.4-5">1 Chr 1:4-5</a>) who, along with his wife, was among the eight human survivors of the great Flood. Because Japheth and his brother Shem acted with respect and modesty in covering their father’s nakedness while he was in a drunken condition (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.20-23">Gn 9:20-23</a>), they were both blessed in Noah’s prophetic pronouncement of <a href="?bref=Gen.9.26-27">Genesis 9:26-27</a>. Of Japheth, Noah said, “God enlarge Japheth, and let him dwell in the tents of Shem; and let Canaan be his slave” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). There are two interpretations of the meaning of this prophecy. Some understand the enlargement of Japheth to be a reference to a great increase in numbers of descendants. “To dwell in the tents of Shem” is understood as Japheth’s sharing in the blessing of Shem. According to this view, there is to be a time when God will work primarily with Shem (the people of Israel), but then, at a later time, Japheth will be brought into connection with the faith of Israel and share in its promises. In this view fulfillment is found in the opening of the gospel to the Gentiles at the inception of the NT church. Others understand the “enlargement of Japheth” to refer to territorial enlargement, and the “dwelling in the tents of Shem” as the conquest of Shemite territory by Japhethites. In this view, fulfillment is found in the Greek and Roman conquests of Palestine.</p>
<p>In the “table of nations” in <a href="?bref=Gen.10.2">Genesis 10:2</a>, Japheth is listed as the father of Gomer, Magog, Madai, Javan, Tubal, Meshech, and Tiras. These are the ancestors of peoples who lived to the north and west of Israel and who spoke what today are classified as Indo-European languages.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Nations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Nations</a>; <a href="?item=Noah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Noah #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>