<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JasharBookof">
  <title>Jashar, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JASHAR, Book of</p>
<p class="fl">This was an ancient Hebrew writing that is no longer extant. It was probably a national songbook containing songs praising the exploits of Hebrew heroes. It is mentioned in the OT account of Joshua’s command to the sun and moon to stand still during the battle with the five kings (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.13">Jos 10:13</a>) and in the account of David’s lament over Saul and Jonathan (<a href="?bref=2Sam.1.17-27">2 Sm 1:17-27</a>). It is also possible that Solomon’s words of dedication of the temple (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.12-13">1 Kgs 8:12-13</a>) were included. According to the Septuagint (Greek translation of the OT), the writer of that passage uses the same language as in <a href="?bref=Josh.10.12-13">Joshua 10:12-13</a> and asks rhetorically if Solomon’s statement were written in the book of “Song.” Some scholars believe that this question may have accidentally dropped out of the Hebrew text since the whole quotation appears in the Septuagint following Solomon’s prayer of <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.14-53">1 Kings 8:14-53</a>. It is also likely that some Hebrew letters may have been transposed so that the Septuagint reads “Song” instead of “Jashar.” If one accepts these assumptions, then <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.12-13">1 Kings 8:12-13</a> would have been part of the Book of Jashar.</p>
<p>It is also possible that the Septuagint rendering, “Book of Song,” is the more correct title. All of the quotations are poetry; the term “Jashar” has never been explained satisfactorily; and “Jashar” has similarities to various Hebrew root forms meaning “to sing.” Hence, some scholars believe that “Book of Song” is a more correct title.</p>
<p>The nature of the book cannot be determined with certainty except to say that it probably contained a wide variety of songs. This is evident as one considers the types of materials contained in the three passages mentioned above. One is an appeal for the prolonging of daylight in order for Israel to complete a military victory; one is an example of David’s literary skill and an expression of the national importance and close friendship of the persons involved; and one is an exclamation extolling God’s supremacy over ritual and nature.</p>
<p>The origin of the Book of Jashar is more clouded in obscurity than is its content. Some believe that it was a written collection of songs dating to the days before the monarchy. Some think that it was an oral tradition dating approximately from the time of Solomon. Others suggest that it was a vital instrument in the establishment of literary archives during the monarchy to preserve the notable events of Israelites. This has led to the suggestion that the Song of Miriam (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.21">Ex 15:21</a>) and the Song of Deborah (Jgs 5) may have been part of the collection.</p>
<p>The book has long interested many people, and this interest has led to various false imitations, false identifications, and false reproductions of it.</p>
  </body>
</item>