<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JebusJebusite">
  <title>Jebus, Jebusite</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEBUS, JEBUSITE</p>
<p class="fl">Walled city, lying on the boundary between Judah and Benjamin, conquered by David; thereafter, it was known as the “city of David,” or ancient Jerusalem. Its occupants were Jebusites (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.16">Jos 18:16</a>). They were one of the several clans or tribes collectively known as Canaanites (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.15-16">Gn 10:15-16</a>). Their land, along with that of their neighbors, was repeatedly promised to the Israelites (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.8">Ex 3:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.13.5">13:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.23.23">23:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.33.2">33:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.11">34:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.13.29">Nm 13:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.7.1">Dt 7:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.20.17">20:17</a>). This promise was partially fulfilled early in the campaign under Joshua (<a href="?bref=Josh.3.10">Jos 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.8">12:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.18.16">18:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Josh.24.11">24:11</a>). It is said that the men of Judah fought against Jerusalem and took it (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.28">18:28</a>). “The Benjamites, however, failed to dislodge the Jebusites, who were living in Jerusalem; to this day the Jebusites live there with the Benjamites” (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.21">Jgs 1:21</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Apparently the city was captured by the men of Judah, but its inhabitants were not destroyed and they later reoccupied the site.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="JebusTheAncientCityOfDavid"/>
<p>Jebus (or Jerusalem) lay on the borderline between two tribes, and this may account for its survival until the time of David. The borders of Judah and Benjamin are thus defined: “The boundary then passed through the valley of the son of Hinnom, along the southern slopes of the Jebusites, where the city of Jerusalem is located. Then it went west to the top of the mountain above the valley of Hinnom, and on up to the northern end of the valley of Rephaim” (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.8">Jos 15:8</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>); “it then goes down the valley of Hinnom, south of the shoulder of the Jebusites, and downward to En-rogel” (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.16">Jos 18:16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The two accounts agree: the survey of Judah follows a westerly direction; the survey of Benjamin moves eastward; both indicate that Jebus lay on the southern slope of the “mountain” north of the valley of Hinnom, the site of East Jerusalem today.</p>
<p>The city’s survival was assured by a constant supply of water, the spring of Gihon, and by strong natural defenses. It was easily defended by steep valleys on three sides: the Kidron on the east, the Hinnom on the south and west. The Jebusites therefore considered their city impregnable. This gave them a certain arrogance and complacency. After the death of Saul, when David was seeking to consolidate the kingdom, the Jebusites scornfully challenged David to capture their stronghold (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.6">2 Sm 5:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.11.5">1 Chr 11:5</a>). As the last remaining Canaanite stronghold in the area, it presented a unique challenge. Joab apparently led the attack up the water shaft and succeeded where previous attempts had failed (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.8">2 Sm 5:8</a>).</p>
<p>For political as well as strategic reasons, David decided to move his capital from Hebron to Jebus. Politically, it lay in neutral territory between Judah and Benjamin and thus aroused no jealousy. Strategically, it was easily defended and more centrally located. The choice proved a wise one. In spite of the fact that Jebus-Jerusalem lies on no waterway or major highway, it has become through the centuries the spiritual capital of the world. Under David and Solomon, it became Israel’s religious center, and today it is of prime importance to the three major monotheistic religions of mankind.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Jerusalem_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jerusalem</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>