<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JehoshaphatPerson">
  <title>Jehoshaphat (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEHOSHAPHAT (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. The fourth king of Judah (872–848 <span class="era">BC</span>), son and successor of Asa (910–869 <span class="era">BC</span>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Jehoshaphat was 35 years of age when he began his reign; he ruled 25 years, during which time he maintained the stability of the Davidic dynasty (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.41-42">1 Kgs 22:41-42</a>). He was contemporary with King Ahab of Israel (874–853 <span class="era">BC</span>), since his first year on the throne corresponds with the fourth year of the reign of Ahab (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.41">41</a>). He was also contemporary with Ahaziah (853– 852 <span class="era">BC</span>), son of Ahab, and his brother Jehoram (852–841 <span class="era">BC</span>), who succeeded Ahaziah when he died childless (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.1.17">2 Kgs 1:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Jehoshaphat is held in high esteem by the Chronicler, along with Hezekiah and Josiah. His successful rule was due to his religious policy. He continued the religious reformation initiated by his father; therefore, the Lord firmly established the kingdom under his control. Everyone in Judah brought tribute to Jehoshaphat, so that he had great riches and honor (<a href="?bref=2Chr.17.1-5">2 Chr 17:1-5</a>). The Chronicler praised Jehoshaphat’s courageous heart, evidenced in his removing the high places and the Asherim from Judah (v <a href="?bref=2Chr.17.6">6</a>). Jehoshaphat is also reported to have closed all the temples of prostitution (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.46">1 Kgs 22:46</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The biblical record informs us that Jehoshaphat reversed his father’s foreign policy. During his reign, Asa warred against Baasha of Israel (908–886 <span class="era">BC</span>), who exterminated the house of Jeroboam I (930–909 <span class="era">BC</span>) and usurped the throne for himself, keeping it for nearly a quarter of a century. The two kingdoms engaged in warfare over the boundaries between the kingdoms. Jehoshaphat, however, discontinued this war and made peace with the king of Israel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.2">1 Kgs 22:2</a>). To confirm this state of peace, he made an alliance with Ahab and married his son and successor, Jehoram, to Ahab’s daughter Athaliah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.8.18">2 Kgs 8:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.18.1-2">2 Chr 18:1-2</a>). In accordance with this alliance Jehoshaphat fought on the side of Ahab in his battle against Aram, which took place at Ramoth-gilead (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.1-53">1 Kgs 22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.18.1-34">2 Chr 18</a>). He also was an ally of Jehoram, the younger son of Ahab, against Mesha the king of Moab (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.4-27">2 Kgs 3:4-27</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">In his domestic reforms Jehoshaphat sent Ben-hail, Obadiah, Zechariah, Nethanel, and Micaiah to teach the law in the cities of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.17.7-9">2 Chr 17:7-9</a>). He is also reported to have organized the use of tribute paid to Judah. The surrounding nations, observing the strength of Jehoshaphat and recognizing the presence of the Lord with him, not only refrained from attacking Judah but even brought tribute to him. He used this tribute to fortify the cities of Judah (vv <a href="?bref=2Chr.17.10-13">10-13</a>). Jehoshaphat also reorganized the army and made arrangements for the defense of the kingdom. He had a standing army in the capital as well as garrisons in the fortified cities. It is evident that the organization centered about the tribal association of Judah and Benjamin (vv <a href="?bref=2Chr.17.14-19">14-19</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">A prophet by the name of Jehu rebuked Jehoshaphat for his alliances with Ahab (<a href="?bref=2Chr.19.1-3">2 Chr 19:1-3</a>). Evidently, Jehoshaphat took this rebuke to heart and ruled Judah wisely. He swept most of the Asherim from the land and determined in his mind to seek God. He is reported to have gone regularly among the people from Beersheba to Mt Ephraim to convert them to the Lord. He appointed judges in each of the fortified cities of Judah and admonished them to judge as the Lord’s representatives. He also appointed Levites, priests, and family heads to handle cases pertaining to the worship of the Lord and to make decisions in disputes arising among citizens (vv <a href="?bref=2Chr.19.4-11">4-11</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">In addition to the fortified cities in Judah, Jehoshaphat placed military forces in the cities of Ephraim that his father, Asa, had taken (<a href="?bref=2Chr.17.1-2">2 Chr 17:1-2</a>). Though his alliances with Phoenicia and Israel were not approved by the prophets and proved dangerous in the long run, they still brought relative peace and temporary prosperity to his realm. He was held in high esteem by the neighboring Philistines and the Arabs (vv <a href="?bref=2Chr.17.10-13">10-13</a>), and it is also evident that Edom submitted to him. He won victory over the Moabites, Ammonites, and Meunites at En-gedi (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.1-30">20:1-30</a>). Wishing to emulate Solomon, he constructed ships at Ezion-geber to go to Tarshish, but this did not prove a successful venture (vv <a href="?bref=2Chr.20.35-37">35-37</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Jehoshaphat died when he was about 60 years of age and was buried with his fathers in the city of David. His son Jehoram became king in his place (<a href="?bref=2Chr.21.1">2 Chr 21:1</a>). His name is listed in Matthew’s genealogy of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.8">Mt 1:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Son of Ahilud who held the position of “recorder” (the Hebrew word may imply an official historian or a spokesman for the king) in the days of David and Solomon (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.16">2 Sm 8:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.20.24">20:24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.3">1 Kgs 4:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.15">1 Chr 18:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Son of Paruah and one of Solomon’s 12 administrative officials who requisitioned food from the people for the king’s household. Each of them arranged provisions for one month of the year. Jehoshaphat was the officer assigned for the tribe of Issachar (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.7,17">1 Kgs 4:7, 17</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Son of Nimshi and the father of Jehu, who exterminated the dynasty of Omri and became king of Samaria around 842–815 <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.2,14">2 Kgs 9:2, 14</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. KJV spelling of Joshaphat in <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.24">1 Chronicles 15:24</a>, a priest during David’s reign. <span class="ital">See</span> #2 (above).</p>
  </body>
</item>