<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Jehoash">
  <title>Jehoash</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEHOASH</p>
<p class="fl">Name of two OT kings, occurring only in the book of 2 Kings. The name means “the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is strong” or “the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> hath bestowed.” Joash, the shorter form of the name, frequently appears in the Kings and Chronicles narratives.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Son of Ahaziah and seventh king of Judah (835–796 <span class="era">BC</span>). Jehoash ascended the throne after the wicked Athaliah had been killed at the command of Jehoiada the priest. As an infant, he was hidden by his aunt Jehosheba in the temple and thus survived the slaughter of the king’s household by Athaliah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.1-3">2 Kgs 11:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.23.10-12">2 Chr 23:10-12</a>). After remaining six years within the temple precinct, Jehoash was declared king at the age of seven and ruled for 40 years (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.21-12.1">2 Kgs 11:21–12:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.24.1-3">2 Chr 24:1-3</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">His major activity during his reign was the renovation of the temple (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.4-5">2 Kgs 12:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.24.4-5">2 Chr 24:4-5</a>). When, by his 23d year, little progress had been made (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.6">2 Kgs 12:6</a>), he revised the taxation schedule, commanded the people of Judah to bring their contributions directly to the Jerusalem temple, and soon restored the Lord’s house to its proper condition (<a href="?bref=2Chr.24.13">2 Chr 24:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">After the death of the priest Jehoiada, Jehoash and Judah forsook the Lord and served the Asherim and the idols (<a href="?bref=2Chr.24.15-18">2 Chr 24:15-18</a>). Not heeding the prophetic warning of divine judgment (v <a href="?bref=2Chr.24.20">20</a>), Jehoash and his people were conquered by the Arameans. Though Jehoash had once been able to avert a siege of Judah by paying tribute to Hazael (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.17-18">2 Kgs 12:17-18</a>), the same strategy did not work a second time. The Arameans plundered Judah and Jerusalem, sending the spoil to Hazael in Damascus (<a href="?bref=2Chr.24.23-24">2 Chr 24:23-24</a>). Jehoash was assassinated by his servants Jozacar (Jozabad/Zabad) and Jehozabad while recuperating from wounds incurred in battle with the Arameans (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.20-21">2 Kgs 12:20-21</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.24.25-26">2 Chr 24:25-26</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Son of Jehoahaz and 13th king of Israel (798–782 <span class="era">BC</span>). Jehoash enjoyed a measure of military success that had eluded his father. No longer subject to punitive military exploits from Hazael of Aram, he was able to establish political stability in the northern kingdom. In fact, he subjugated the southern kingdom of Judah while Amaziah was king in Jerusalem (796–767 <span class="era">BC</span>). The conflict between Amaziah and Jehoash was precipitated mainly by Amaziah. Overconfident with his victories in Edom, Amaziah initiated a military conflict with Israel (<a href="?bref=2Chr.25.17-19">2 Chr 25:17-19</a>). The battle was fought near Beth-shemesh in the Judean Shephelah. King Jehoash routed the army of Judah, captured Amaziah, and moved on to Jerusalem. Destroying the outer wall from the Ephraim Gate to the Corner Gate, he entered the capital city and plundered the treasures of both the palace and the temple (vv <a href="?bref=2Chr.25.21-24">21-24</a>). He was apparently used as an instrument of the Lord to subdue Judah (v <a href="?bref=2Chr.25.20">20</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">A contemporary of Jehoash was Elisha the prophet. In spite of the pervasive wickedness in Israel and the apostasy of the king himself (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.10-11">2 Kgs 13:10-11</a>), Jehoash still sought the counsel of this prophet of the Lord. While Elisha was on his deathbed, Jehoash sought the prophet’s blessing (v <a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.14">14</a>). Elisha assured the king that the Arameans would be defeated by Israel at Aphek and that Israel would enjoy three decisive victories over this same enemy (vv <a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.15-19">15-19</a>). During his 16-year reign, Jehoash achieved political stability in the northern kingdom. Though considered an evil king, he was used as an instrument of judgment against Amaziah of Judah and enjoyed the blessing of Yahweh against Aram.</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>