<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JewelryJewels">
  <title>Jewelry, Jewels</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEWELRY, JEWELS</p>
<p class="fl">Decorated adornments. In the Bible, jewelry was used by both men and women (<a href="?bref=Exod.11.2">Ex 11:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.3.18-21">Is 3:18-21</a>). Items of jewelry were given as presents (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.22,53">Gn 24:22, 53</a>) and were regularly seized as spoil in war (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.25">2 Chr 20:25</a>). Before coinage came into use, jewels were associated with gold and silver as a measure of wealth (<a href="?bref=2Chr.21.3">21:3</a>) or as a standard of value (<a href="?bref=Job.28.16">Jb 28:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.3.15">Prv 3:15</a>).</p>
<p>In the OT a wide variety of jewelry is mentioned—arm bracelets (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.22,30,47">Gn 24:22, 30, 47</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.11">Ez 16:11</a>), ankle ornaments (<a href="?bref=Isa.3.18-20">Is 3:18-20</a>), necklaces (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.42">Gn 41:42</a>), crowns (<a href="?bref=Zech.9.16">Zec 9:16</a>), earrings (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.22">Gn 24:22</a>), nose rings (<a href="?bref=Isa.3.21">Is 3:21</a>), and finger rings (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.42">Gn 41:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.3.10">Est 3:10</a>). In each case a gold or silver mounting was used to hold the precious stones. It would seem that the modern art of faceting was not used but the precious stone was rounded, polished, and sometimes engraved. Many of the precious stones valued in antiquity would hardly be classed as precious today, though they might be classified as semiprecious.</p>
<p>Semiprecious stones were frequently incorporated into necklaces and other pieces of jewelry. Royal headdresses from the graves at Ur near the Persian Gulf give an indication of the skill of jewelers around 2700 <span class="era">BC</span>. Hairbands and pins were necessary parts of hair adornment and have been recovered from numerous Near Eastern archaeological sites. Rings, often with delicately carved stones, were extremely popular, and nose rings were also in use by the middle Bronze Age (see <a href="?bref=Gen.24.47">Gn 24:47</a>). Fine gold chains were frequently worn. A signet ring and a heavy gold chain were decorative symbols of office (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.42">41:42</a>). Bracelets and amulets were worn around the wrist, the upper arm, and the neck. Decorative pins, similar in design and intent to the modern safety pin, were often used to hold clothing together.</p>
<p>An excellent description of women’s clothing and jewelry is found in <a href="?bref=Isa.3.18-23">Isaiah 3:18-23</a> (<span class="sc">nlt</span>), where the prophet warns: “The Lord will strip away their artful beauty—their ornaments, headbands, and crescent necklaces; their earrings, bracelets, and veils of shimmering gauze. Gone will be their scarves, ankle chains, sashes, perfumes, and charms; their rings, jewels, party clothes, gowns, capes, and purses; their mirrors, linen garments, head ornaments, and shawls.”</p>
<p><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=MineralsandMetals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Minerals and Metals</a>; <a href="?item=StonesPrecious_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Stones, Precious</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>