<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JezreelValley">
  <title>Jezreel Valley</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEZREEL VALLEY</p>
<p class="fl">Largest and richest valley in the land of Israel. It was named after Jezreel, and it was apparently the only town on the plain where the Israelites had gained a foothold in the early stages of their conquest (cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.1.27-30">Jgs 1:27-30</a>). The form of the name in later Greek sources is Esdraelon (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.1.8">Jdt 1:8</a>); some scholars have wrongly applied the latter term to the great western plain and the former to the narrow valley leading eastward to Beth-shan. Comparison of <a href="?bref=Josh.17.16">Joshua 17:16</a> with <a href="?bref=Judg.1.27-28">Judges 1:27-28</a> and <a href="?bref=Josh.17.11">Joshua 17:11</a> shows that the Beth-shan area was considered as a separate entity from the valley of Jezreel, which included the cities of Taanach and Megiddo among others (cf. also <a href="?bref=Hos.1.5">Hos 1:5</a>).</p>
<p>The Midianites camped there, between the hill of Moreh and Mt Tabor (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.33">Jgs 6:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.7.1">7:1</a>); Barak defeated the army of Sisera and Jabin there, near Endor (<a href="?bref=Ps.83.9-10">Ps 83:9-10</a>), and later the Philistines gathered there to oppose Saul (<a href="?bref=1Sam.29.1,11">1 Sm 29:1, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.4.4">2 Sm 4:4</a>). Under the monarchy, the valley was an administrative district (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.9">2 Sm 2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.12">1 Kgs 4:12</a>). Another name, perhaps applicable only to the southern half of the valley, is the plain of Megiddo (<a href="?bref=2Chr.35.22">2 Chr 35:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.12.11">Zec 12:11</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfJezreel"/>
<p>The valley figures in the wars of Thutmose III and Amenhotep II, and the towns there, especially Megiddo, were under Egyptian control in the late Bronze Age. The southwestern side was famous as a military assembly ground, probably called Harosheth-haggoyim (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.2,13-16">Jgs 4:2, 13-16</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Palestine_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Palestine</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>