<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Joab">
  <title>Joab</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JOAB</p>
<p class="list">1. Son of Zeruiah, the half sister of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.16">1 Chr 2:16</a>), who, along with his brothers Abishai and Asahel, was well known for his military valor in Judah (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.18">2 Sm 2:18</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.26.6">1 Sm 26:6</a>). According to 2 Samuel, Joab rose to prominence and distinguished himself at the battle of Gibeon when Saul’s troops under Abner were vanquished (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.8-32">2 Sm 2:8-32</a>). Because Abner had slain Joab’s brother Asahel (v <a href="?bref=2Sam.2.23">23</a>), Joab later killed Abner in revenge (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.26-30">3:26-30</a>), despite Abner’s new loyalty to David (vv <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.12-19">12-19</a>). Possibly Joab sensed that Abner would be his rival. Nevertheless, David praised the slain commander as a prince and a great man (vv <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.31-39">31-39</a>) and set a curse on the house of Joab for his insubordination (vv <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.26-29,39">26-29, 39</a>). This incident illumines Joab’s sometimes unscrupulous and ruthless behavior.</p>
<p class="list-text">Joab spearheaded David’s siege of the Jebusite city of Jerusalem, and when David consolidated his reign there, Joab became the commander of the king’s army (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.16">2 Sm 8:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.11.1">11:1</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.11.6-8">1 Chr 11:6-8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.15">18:15</a>). He suppressed a rebellion among the Syrians and Ammonites (<a href="?bref=2Sam.10.7-14">2 Sm 10:7-14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.19.8-15">1 Chr 19:8-15</a>). At Rabbah he not only conquered the city (<a href="?bref=2Sam.11.1-12.31">2 Sm 11–12</a>) but arranged for the death of Uriah the Hittite so that David could take Uriah’s wife, Bathsheba.</p>
<p class="list-text">Joab’s loyalties to David and shrewd control of the army are seen during Absalom’s rebellion (<a href="?bref=2Sam.15.1-37">2 Sm 15</a>). Joab suppressed the conspiracy (ch <a href="?bref=2Sam.18.1-33">18</a>), but ignoring a direct order from David not to kill his son (<a href="?bref=2Sam.18.5">18:5</a>), brutally killed him anyway (vv <a href="?bref=2Sam.18.10-17">10-17</a>). When David mourned, Joab rebuked the king, urging that a crisis with the army was imminent (<a href="?bref=2Sam.19.5-7">19:5-7</a>). This insubordination led David to replace Joab with Amasa as commander (v <a href="?bref=2Sam.19.13">13</a>), but later, at Gibeon, Joab also killed him dishonorably (<a href="?bref=2Sam.20.8-10">20:8-10</a>). Joab’s influence in the army must have been great, since he regained his former role as military commander (<a href="?bref=2Sam.20.23,24">2 Sm 20:23, 24:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.19">1 Kgs 1:19</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">At the end of David’s reign, Joab supported the conspiracy of Adonijah and Abiathar against the throne (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.7">1 Kgs 1:7</a>). David’s distrust of him led the king to warn Solomon specifically about Joab’s repeated treacheries (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.5-9">2:5-9</a>). Solomon had to resolve the problem of an untrustworthy army. Therefore, upon his father’s death, Solomon pursued the conspirators Adonijah (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.23">23</a>), Abiathar (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.26">26</a>), and Joab (v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.28">28</a>). Solomon’s officer Benaiah found Joab at the altar seeking refuge and killed him there (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.28-35">28-35</a>), thus cleansing Solomon’s reign from the wrongdoing of Joab.</p>
<p class="list">2. KJV translation (“Ataroth, the house of Joab”) of Atroth-beth-joab in <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.54">1 Chronicles 2:54</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=AtrothBethJoab_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Atroth-beth-joab</a>.</p>
<p class="list">3. Judahite, Seraiah’s son from the house of Kenaz and forefather of the residents of the valley of craftsmen (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.14">1 Chr 4:14</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Forefather of a clan of Jews who returned to Palestine with Zerubbabel following the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.6">Ezr 2:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.11">Neh 7:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Forefather of a family of which 219 members returned with Ezra to Palestine following the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.9">Ezr 8:9</a>). He is perhaps identifiable with #4 above.</p>
  </body>
</item>