<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Joy">
  <title>Joy</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JOY</p>
<p class="fl">Positive human condition that can be either feeling or action. The Bible uses “joy” in both senses.</p>
<p class="h2" id="JoyasaFeeling">Joy as a Feeling</p>
<p class="fl">Joy is a feeling called forth by well-being, success, or good fortune. A person automatically experiences it because of certain favorable circumstances. It cannot be commanded.</p>
<p>The shepherd experienced joy when he found his lost sheep (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.13">Mt 18:13</a>). The multitude felt it when Jesus healed a Jewish woman whom Satan had bound for 18 years (<a href="?bref=Luke.13.17">Lk 13:17</a>). The disciples returned to Jerusalem rejoicing after Jesus’ ascension (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.52">24:52</a>). Joy was also the feeling of the church at Antioch when its members heard the Jerusalem Council’s decision that they did not have to be circumcised to keep God’s law (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.31">Acts 15:31</a>). Paul mentioned his joy in hearing about the obedience of the Roman Christians (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.19">Rom 16:19</a>). He wrote to the Corinthians that love does not rejoice in wrong but rejoices in the right (<a href="?bref=1Cor.13.6">1 Cor 13:6</a>; see also <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.1">1 Sm 2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.11.9">11:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.18.6">18:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.6.12">2 Sm 6:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.40">1 Kgs 1:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.9.17-22">Est 9:17-22</a>).</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Ps.137.1-6">Psalms 137:1-6</a> shows that the emotion cannot be commanded. The Jews’ captors wanted them to sing in the land of their exile, something they were unable to do. Faraway Jerusalem was their chief joy.</p>
<p class="h2" id="JoyasanAction">Joy as an Action</p>
<p class="fl">There is a joy that Scripture commands. That joy is action that can be engaged in regardless of how the person feels. <a href="?bref=Pr.5.18">Proverbs 5:18</a> tells the reader to rejoice in the wife of his youth, without reference to what she may be like. Christ instructed his disciples to rejoice when they were persecuted, reviled, and slandered (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.11-12">Mt 5:11-12</a>). The apostle Paul commanded continuous rejoicing (<a href="?bref=Phil.4.4">Phil 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.5.16">1 Thes 5:16</a>). James said Christians are to reckon it all joy when they fall into various testings because such testings produce endurance (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.2">Jas 1:2</a>). Joy in adverse circumstances is possible only as a fruit of the Holy Spirit, who is present in every Christian (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.22">Gal 5:22</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=FruitoftheSpirit_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Fruit of the Spirit</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>