<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Jozabad">
  <title>Jozabad</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JOZABAD</p>
<p class="list">1. Benjamite from Gederah and one of the military men who came to David’s support at Ziklag (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.4">1 Chr 12:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2, 3. Leaders and mighty warriors from Manasseh’s tribe who joined David at Ziklag to fight against Saul (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.20">1 Chr 12:20</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. One of the Levites who assisted with the administration of the temple contributions in Jerusalem during King Hezekiah’s reign (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.13">2 Chr 31:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. One of the Levitical chiefs who generously gave animals to the Levites for the celebration of the Passover feast during King Josiah’s reign (<a href="?bref=2Chr.35.9">2 Chr 35:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Levite, the son of Jeshua, and one who helped Meremoth, Eleazar, and Noadiah take inventory of the temple’s gifts and precious metals during the days of Ezra (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.33">Ezr 8:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Priest and one of the six sons of Pashhur who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.22">Ezr 10:22</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. One of the Levites who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.23">Ezr 10:23</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. One of the Levites who assisted Ezra with teaching the people the law during the postexilic period (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.7">Neh 8:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. One of the Levites who relocated to Jerusalem and was put in charge of the work of the temple during the days of Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.16">Neh 11:16</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Alternate rendering for Shimeath’s son in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.21">2 Kings 12:21</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=JozacarJozachar_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jozacar, Jozachar</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>