<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JudahPerson">
  <title>Judah (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JUDAH (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. Fourth of Jacob’s 12 sons (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.23">Gn 35:23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.1">1 Chr 2:1</a>) and the fourth son born to Jacob by Leah, who, overjoyed with the thought of bearing Jacob another son, named him Judah, meaning “praise” (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.35">Gn 29:35</a>). Judah fathered five sons: Er, Onan, and Shelah by Bathshua the Canaanitess (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.3-5">Gn 38:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.3">1 Chr 2:3</a>); and the twins Perez and Zerah by Tamar, his daughter-in-law (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.29-30">Gn 38:29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.4">1 Chr 2:4</a>). He eventually settled his family in Egypt with his father and brothers (<a href="?bref=Exod.1.2">Ex 1:2</a>), although his first two sons, Er and Onan, were divinely killed in Canaan for their disobedience (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.12">Gn 46:12</a>). Judah became the founder of one of Israel’s 12 tribes (<a href="?bref=Num.1.26-27">Nm 1:26-27</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Though reckless in his behavior with Tamar (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.6-30">Gn 38:6-30</a>), Judah showed firm resolve in taking personal responsibility for Benjamin’s safety in Egypt and acting as intercessor for his brothers before Joseph (<a href="?bref=Gen.44.14-18">44:14-18</a>). At the time of Jacob’s blessing, Judah was granted the birthright privileges of the firstborn; the leadership of Jacob’s family would come through Judah’s seed, as would the promised Messiah of Abraham’s covenant (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.8-12">49:8-12</a>). Later, Judah’s family was praised at the time of Ruth’s engagement to Boaz (<a href="?bref=Ruth.4.12">Ru 4:12</a>), and both the Davidic lines of kings (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.1-15">1 Chr 2:1-15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.3.1-24">3:1-24</a>) and Jesus Christ’s ancestors traced their descent from Judah (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.2-3">Mt 1:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.33">Lk 3:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>; <a href="?item=JudahTribeof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judah, Tribe of</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Forefather of a family of Levites who assisted Jeshua, the high priest, with rebuilding the temple during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.9">Ezr 3:9</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg). He is alternately called Hodaviah in <a href="?bref=Ezra.2.40">Ezra 2:40</a> and Hodevah in <a href="?bref=Neh.7.43">Nehemiah 7:43</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Hodaviah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hodaviah #4</a>.</p>
<p class="list">3. One of the Levites who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.23">Ezr 10:23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Benjamite, son of Hassenuah, who was second in command over the city of Jerusalem during the days of Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.9">Neh 11:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. One of the leaders of the Levites who returned with Zerubbabel and Jeshua to Judah after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.8">Neh 12:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. One of the princes of Judah who participated in the dedication of the Jerusalem wall during the postexilic period (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.34">Neh 12:34</a>).</p>
<p class="list">7. One of the priests who played a musical instrument at the dedication of the Jerusalem wall during the days of Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.36">Neh 12:36</a>). He is perhaps identical with #5 above.</p>
<p class="list">8. Joseph’s son, father of Simeon and an ancestor of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.30">Lk 3:30</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>