<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JudeLetterof">
  <title>Jude, Letter of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JUDE, Letter of</p>
<p class="fl">Short, hard-hitting letter to a church being infiltrated by teachers who practiced all types of moral evil. Jude reveals the inner situation of a Jewish-Christian community and also presents some great difficulties for the Christian interpreter.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurposeandTheologicalTeaching">Purpose and Theological Teaching</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">The Letter of Jude states that it was written by “Jude . . . [the] brother of James” (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.1">1:1</a>). Many scholars understand this nomenclature to designate Jude (Greek “Judas”), Jesus’ brother, whose brother James became the leader of the Jerusalem church. But other scholars think that perhaps another Jude wrote it, or some later author wrote it in the spirit of the leader whom he revered. The hypothesis that another Jude wrote it seems unlikely, for the apostle Jude (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.16">Lk 6:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.13">Acts 1:13</a>) is the son of a certain James, not a brother of James; besides, <a href="?bref=Jude.1.17">Jude 1:17</a> appears to distinguish Jude from the apostles. And since there was only one James who was prominent in the early church, James the Lord’s brother, it would be hard to believe that some other Jude would have a brother named James and would use such an identification in the title; it would have been too confusing. The title “brother of James” most likely means that Jude was James of Jerusalem’s brother and therefore Jesus’ brother; he did not use the title “brother of our Lord,” perhaps, as Clement of Alexandria said, out of modesty.</p>
<p>The idea that a later author wrote using Jude’s name presents a major problem: Why would he pick such an obscure name, instead of Paul or Peter or James, and why would he not use a more exalted and authoritative title? We must conclude that, despite the difficulties of date and background, Judas the Lord’s brother wrote this letter.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</p>
<p class="fl">About date, origin, and destination, the letter says nothing directly. Since the content of the faith is clearly fixed (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.3">Jude 1:3</a>) and the recipients have personally heard the apostles (who may have died already, v <a href="?bref=Jude.1.17">17</a>), the date is probably between <span class="era">AD</span> 60 and 100.</p>
<p>Presumably, Jude traveled (with his wife and family) to promote the faith (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.5">1 Cor 9:5</a>). Throughout his travels, he may have established some churches—or, at least, he probably taught at various local churches. It may be that he heard of false teachers infiltrating these churches and was prompted to write them this epistle.</p>
<p>Jude may have written from Galilee in his old age, or perhaps he had returned to Jerusalem. The best guess we can make about the recipients would be that they were members of Jewish-Christian churches in Syria. Still, these locations remain little more than guesses.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientPapyrusManuscriptOfJude"/>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">Three facts about the Letter of Jude make its background difficult to reconstruct. First, it is hard to be sure what type of heresy it was combating. Some scholars believe that this was early Gnosticism, and others that it was simply teaching infiltrated with ethical error. If the heretics were Gnostics, they believed in a hierarchy of angels or demigods. In this case they probably saw Jesus as a lower rung on the way to salvation. Perhaps they also considered God to be the lower creator (the demiurge) and spoke of wanting to serve the true God (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.4">Jude 1:4</a>). This might explain the interest in angels and demons (v <a href="?bref=Jude.1.8">8</a>) and the stress on the unity of God (v <a href="?bref=Jude.1.25">25</a>). But probably these were simply people who had found a way to rationalize immoral behavior and were unwisely mocking the evil powers. There is no clear evidence that they were Gnostic, while there is plenty of evidence that people turned the freedom of the gospel into an excuse for sin (e.g., <a href="?bref=Rom.6.1-23">Rom 6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.1-6.20">1 Cor 5–6</a>). These teachers probably denied Christ by failing to follow his ethical teaching, and their blasphemy of angels (while they themselves were deep in sin) was another ethical sin. Such depravity is enough to explain the letter; however, knowing that doctrinal and ethical error often go hand in hand, we must not discount the possibility that some doctrinal error was also involved.</p>
<p>Second, Jude surprises us by quoting from two apocryphal books, the Assumption of Moses (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.4">Jude 1:4</a>) and 1 Enoch (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.14-15">Jude 1:14-15</a> quotes 1 Enoch 1:9). This fact and other allusions in the book reveal that Jude and probably his readers were well read in Jewish apocryphal literature. Moreover, it also shows that Jude regarded books outside the canon of the OT as transmitting true traditions and authoritative prophecy. That Jude accepted these books is not surprising, since many apocryphal books were used by Jews of that period, alongside the OT, as a type of devotional literature. Early Christians often included apocryphal literature along with canonical books as part of their Bibles (sometimes they would also omit NT books that were not yet considered authentic). The canon of NT Scripture was not firmly established until the third century, long after Jude’s epistle was written.</p>
<p>It is important to realize that while Jude probably believed in the historicity of these citations, the teaching of the letter does not depend on that historicity. Jude wrote about neither Moses nor Enoch but about how one should behave toward authorities (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.8">Jude 1:8</a>) and what God will do to ungodly people (v <a href="?bref=Jude.1.13">13</a>). The citations illustrate Jude’s teaching and probably carried weight with his first readers, but the fact that they are apocryphal should bother us no more than Paul’s quotations from pagan writers or the writer of Hebrews’ allusions to 2 Maccabees (<a href="?bref=Acts.17.1-34">Acts 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.12">Ti 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.35">Heb 11:35</a>). The authority of Scripture rests in the point the author is making.</p>
<p>Third, Jude shows such a close relationship to <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.1-22">2 Peter 2</a> that either Jude is an expansion of 2 Peter 2 or else 2 Peter 2 is an abbreviation of Jude. Words, phrases, and illustrations are essentially identical in the two works. While it is hard to determine who borrowed from whom, probably the author of 2 Peter has adapted the strong denunciations of Jude to the more instructive tone of his work. It would be hard to imagine anyone writing Jude if 2 Peter already existed. Christians should have no problem with this borrowing, for no writer of Scripture believed himself so original that he could not borrow from other Scriptures, from hymns, or from noncanonical literature. It is no more a problem for God to inspire a quotation or adaptation from another writing than for him to inspire a new composition. Indeed, some passages in Scripture are total repetitions of others (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.18.1-50">Ps 18</a> and <a href="?bref=2Sam.22.1-51">2 Sm 22</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeandTheologicalTeaching">Purpose and Theological Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">Jude describes his work in terms of exhortation or encouragement (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.3">Jude 1:3</a>). Obviously he wanted to strengthen the churches against false teachers who were perverting the gospel. Thus, he repeatedly urged the believers to hold fast or guard their purity and the gospel (vv <a href="?bref=Jude.1.3,20-21,24">3, 20-21, 24</a>). Yet he did not want the teachers simply kicked out, for he had hopes that the believers would be able to rescue some from this danger, although the rescue itself would be dangerous work (v <a href="?bref=Jude.1.23">23</a>).</p>
<p>In framing his exhortation the author did not produce any new doctrines; rather, he underlined some old ones: (1) He stressed the ethical nature of the gospel and the need to maintain purity in life and speech. (2) He showed a high regard for salvation through Christ and a strong belief in one God. (3) He demanded respect for authority, both temporal and spiritual (vv <a href="?bref=Jude.1.8-11">8-11</a>). (4) He had a clear apocalyptic belief, stressing the coming last judgment (vv <a href="?bref=Jude.1.14-15">14-15</a>) and affirming that the last days had already come (v <a href="?bref=Jude.1.18">18</a>). (5) He warned of the necessity to persevere in the faith both doctrinally and ethically (vv <a href="?bref=Jude.1.19-21">19-21</a>). (6) He demonstrated zeal to reclaim those who had erred, for they were outside the grace of God (v <a href="?bref=Jude.1.23">23</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Salutation (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.1-2">1:1-2</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The author identifies himself humbly as a servant of Jesus Christ and addresses his letter to the faithful in the church—those who are loved, guarded, and called by God and Christ.</p>
<p class="h3">Called to Hold to the Faith (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.3-4">1:3-4</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Jude had been planning to write these Christians about “the salvation we all share” (v <a href="?bref=Jude.1.3">3</a>). We will never know what instruction he had planned to give, for in the middle of his preparations he heard news that forced him to change his plans. Instead, he penned an epistle in defense of “the faith”—that is, the true apostolic teachings concerning Jesus Christ that all genuine believers embrace. Some people had joined the church, perhaps with ulterior motives, who were dangerous to the church. The Christians must fight hard to keep pure the body of doctrine (meaning ethics as well as theology) that they had received from Jude and the apostles. Jude makes two charges against these false believers: (1) they had perverted God’s grace into licentiousness, perhaps openly flaunting sexual sins as a sign of freedom they had in Christ (cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.6.1-23">Rom 6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.1-6.20">1 Cor 5–6</a>); and (2) they denied the Lord Jesus (by failing to follow his teachings).</p>
<p class="h3">Reminder of God’s Judgment (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.5-7">1:5-7</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Since the recipients were probably Jewish Christians, they had learned the OT and Jewish tradition well. The author chose three illustrations of the results of apostasy: (1) Judgment can come to those once considered as God’s people (as it did to those “saved” from Egypt, <a href="?bref=Exod.32.28">Ex 32:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.11.33-34">Nm 11:33-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.14.29-35">14:29-35</a>). (2) The consequence of apostasy is eternal damnation (as in the case of the fallen angels of 1 Enoch 6–16—these ideas appear in other Jewish traditions as well). (3) Ethical corruption is in fact a type of apostasy and thus merits damnation (as in the case of Sodom—<a href="?bref=Gen.19.1-38">Gn 19</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.4-6">2 Pt 2:4-6</a>). The author stressed the homosexuality of Sodom rather than its injustice, which <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.49">Ezekiel 16:49</a> condemns, so perhaps sexual misbehavior was a problem with the false teachers. These three illustrations drive home the seriousness of the problems that the church was facing.</p>
<p class="h3">Denunciation of the False Teachers (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.8-16">1:8-16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.10-17">2 Pt 2:10-17</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The false teachers claimed to have received revelations in dreams as the basis of their evil behavior. Their sins were (1) sexual impurity (including, but not limited to, homosexuality); (2) rejection of Christ’s authority (as embodied in his ethical teaching); and (3) evil speech about angels (whether good ones, which is probably the case, or evil). This latter practice is shown to be sin by an example from the Assumption of Moses: even an archangel rebuking the devil himself would not use the language these teachers used about angels. But since these people were unspiritual, they were totally ignorant of what they insulted (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.7-16">1 Cor 2:7-16</a>), yet they were experts in bodily sin—like savage animals. Their sin was destroying them.</p>
<p>Therefore, the teachers were just like Cain (the embodiment of violence, lust, greed, and rebellion against God in Jewish tradition), Balaam (who tried to make money by leading people into sin—<a href="?bref=Num.31.16">Nm 31:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.23.4">Dt 23:4</a>), and Korah (who rebelled against God’s authority in Moses—<a href="?bref=Num.16.1-50">Nm 16</a>). They were also dangerous to the believers, for they were turning the meal, which was part of the love feast and Lord’s Table (Eucharist), into an orgy (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.20-22">1 Cor 11:20-22</a>), and would thereby corrupt the practice of the rest of the church. They cared only for themselves and were devoid of real spiritual gifts from God (like waterless clouds or the dead trees of winter, cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.13.6-9">Lk 13:6-9</a>), being ready for the second death (their fate was so sure that it is seen as having already happened). They produced only evil deeds; in this they are like the fallen angels (stars are considered angels in Jewish tradition—1 Enoch 18:13-16; 21:1-10).</p>
<p>The prophecy of Enoch in 1 Enoch 1:9 shows the certainty of their doom. Originally, the prophecy spoke of God coming in judgment, but Jude made it refer to Christ, who for Christians is the coming judge (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.31">Mt 25:31</a>). Christ will come with the angelic hosts and execute justice on sinners for their sins (both evil deeds and evil words). That prophecy pertains to people who grumble or accuse God, as Israel did (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.7-12">Ex 16:7-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.17.3">17:3</a>); it also applies to people who do whatever they desire, are loud-mouthed, yet flatter when it is to their advantage.</p>
<p class="h3">Instructions for the Faithful (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.17-23">1:17-23</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Faithful Christians must remember that the apostles (here meaning the Twelve, not the wider circle of apostles that included Paul, Barnabas, and others) had predicted just such a situation when they were alive: in the last days there would be scoffers, who would do any ungodly act they desired (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.3">2 Pt 3:3</a>). These false teachers are such people. They divide the church, and although they claim to be spiritual and receive dreams, they are totally worldly, for they do not possess the Holy Spirit. The faithful must watch out that they remain in the love of God and do not drift into rebellion as these heretics have. This is done by (1) building themselves up (as opposed to causing divisions) on the basis of the faith, the apostolic teaching, and example; (2) praying in the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Eph.6.18">Eph 6:18</a>), which sets them off from those not having the Spirit; and (3) waiting expectantly for the mercy Jesus would show them in the soon-coming Last Judgment (1 Enoch 27:3-4).</p>
<p>Yet the Christians must still deal with those influenced by the false teaching. While the Greek text here is very uncertain (it is not clear whether Jude had two or three groups in mind), Jude probably intended that the church should act mercifully toward those who were wavering over whether to follow the false teaching, restore those it could from the followers of the false teaching as if snatching them from hell, and while keeping a merciful attitude (a readiness to accept them back quickly if they repented), strictly avoid any social contact with the unrepentant out of fear of God’s judgment.</p>
<p class="h3">Benediction (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.24-25">1:24-25</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Jude closes with a doxology very much like that found in <a href="?bref=Rom.16.25-27">Romans 16:25-27</a>. In the midst of many who have fallen from the faith, God is praised as the one who is able to keep the believers from falling and to bring them safely into his very presence. It is to this one who is alone God our Savior through Jesus Christ (meaning God saves us by means of Jesus) that the four attributes—glory, majesty, dominion, and authority—belong, now and forever.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Apostasy_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Apostasy</a>; <a href="?item=BrothersofJesus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Brothers of Jesus</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>