<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Aaron">
  <title>Aaron</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AARON</p>
<p class="fl">Moses’ brother and Israel’s first high priest. In the books of Exodus, Leviticus, and Numbers, Aaron was Moses’ spokesman and assistant during the Israelites’ exodus from Egypt. Aaron was three years older than Moses and was 83 when they first confronted the pharaoh (<a href="?bref=Exod.7.7">Ex 7:7</a>). Their sister, Miriam (<a href="?bref=Num.26.59">Nm 26:59</a>), must have been the eldest child, old enough to carry messages when the infant Moses was found by the pharaoh’s daughter (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.1-9">Ex 2:1-9</a>). Aaron’s mother was Jochebed and his father was Amram, a descendant of the Kohath family of Levi’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.18-20">Ex 6:18-20</a>).</p>
<p>Aaron and his wife, Elisheba, had four sons (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.23">Ex 6:23</a>), who were to follow him in the priesthood (<a href="?bref=Lev.1.5">Lv 1:5</a>). Two of them, Nadab and Abihu, violated God’s instructions by performing a sacrilegious act while burning incense and were burned to death as a result (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.1-5">Lv 10:1-5</a>). The priesthood was then passed on through the other two sons, Eleazar and Ithamar, who also sometimes failed to carry out God’s instructions precisely (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.6-20">10:6-20</a>).</p>
<p>Aaron was important in the events of the exodus partly because he was Moses’ brother. When Moses tried to avoid becoming Israel’s leader because he couldn't speak well in public, Aaron’s ability as a speaker was recognized and used by God (<a href="?bref=Exod.4.10-16">Ex 4:10-16</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="EventsofAaronsLife">Events of Aaron’s Life</p>
<p class="fl">The Hebrew people were slaves in Egypt at the beginning of Aaron’s life. Raised as an Egyptian by one of the pharaoh’s daughters, Moses had fled into the Midian Desert after killing a cruel Egyptian taskmaster (<a href="?bref=Exod.1.1-2.25">Ex 1–2</a>). When God sent Moses back as a liberator (chs <a href="?bref=Exod.3.1-4.31">3–4</a>), he also sent Aaron out to meet Moses in the desert (<a href="?bref=Exod.4.27">4:27</a>). Moses was a stranger to his people after so many years of exile, so Aaron made contact with Israel’s elders for him (<a href="?bref=Exod.4.29-31">4:29-31</a>). When Moses and Aaron went to see the pharaoh, God told the Egyptian monarch through the two of them to let the Israelites go (<a href="?bref=Exod.5.1">Ex 5:1</a>). When the pharaoh made life even more miserable for the Hebrew slaves, God began to show his power to the Egyptian ruler through a series of miracles (chs <a href="?bref=Exod.5.1-12.51">5–12</a>). God performed the first three miracles through Aaron, using a rod (probably a shepherd’s staff). The pharaoh had his palace sorcerers do similar tricks. After God brought a plague of gnats (<span class="sc">kjv</span> “lice”) over all Egypt, the Egyptian magicians admitted defeat and said, “This is the finger of God!” (<a href="?bref=Exod.8.19">Ex 8:19</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Then God brought on more plagues through Moses, culminating in the deaths of all the Egyptians’ firstborn sons. Aaron was with Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.1-28">12:1-28</a>) when God revealed how he would “pass over” the properly marked homes of the Israelites, sparing their children on the night the Egyptian children died. That event was the origin of the Passover feast still observed by Jews today (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.1-16">13:1-16</a>).</p>
<p>After God led the Israelites to safety and destroyed the Egyptians that followed them, Aaron joined Moses in leading the people on their long wilderness journey to the Promised Land (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.1-6">Ex 16:1-6</a>). Later, battling against Amalek’s army, Aaron helped hold up Moses’ weary arms in prayer to maintain God’s blessing (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.8-16">17:8-16</a>). Although always subordinate to Moses, Aaron seems to have been recognized as an important leader (<a href="?bref=Exod.18.12">18:12</a>). God summoned him to be with Moses when God gave the law on Mt Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.24">19:24</a>). Aaron, along with other representatives of the people, approved God’s laws in the Book of the Covenant (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.1-8">24:1-8</a>). Aaron went with those leaders partway up the holy mountain and saw the vision of the God of Israel (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.9-10">24:9-10</a>). With Hur, he was left in charge when Moses was with God on the mountaintop (vv <a href="?bref=Exod.24.13-14">13-14</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="AaronThePriest"/>
<p>Moses was gone for over a month, and in a moment of weakness, Aaron gave in to the people’s request for an idol to worship. He melted down their gold ornaments to make a golden image of a calf (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.1-4">Ex 32:1-4</a>). At first, Aaron seemed to think he might be doing something acceptable to God (v <a href="?bref=Exod.32.5">5</a>), but things got out of hand and a drunken sex orgy took place around the idol (v <a href="?bref=Exod.32.6">6</a>). God was angry enough to destroy the people, but Moses interceded, reminding God of his promise to multiply Abraham’s descendants (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.7-14">Ex 32:7-14</a>). Moses furiously confronted Aaron about the immorality and idolatry, which Aaron blamed on the people without admitting any guilt of his own (vv <a href="?bref=Exod.32.21-24">21-24</a>). Although the idolators were punished by death (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.25-28">Ex 32:25-28</a>) and the whole camp by a plague (v <a href="?bref=Exod.32.35">35</a>), Aaron was evidently not punished. In a retelling of the events, Moses said that Aaron was in great danger but was spared because he had prayed for him (<a href="?bref=Deut.9.20">Dt 9:20</a>).</p>
<p>In their second year in the wilderness, Aaron helped Moses take a census (<a href="?bref=Num.1.1-3,17-18">Nm 1:1-3, 17-18</a>). Eventually, Aaron may have become jealous of Moses’ position of leadership. Miriam and Aaron began to slander their brother, even though the elderly Moses was by then more humble than any man on earth (<a href="?bref=Num.12.1-4">Nm 12:1-4</a>). God’s anger toward the two was avoided by Moses’ prayer, although Miriam did suffer for her sin (<a href="?bref=Num.12.5-15">12:5-15</a>). Aaron again seems to have escaped punishment entirely. With Moses, Aaron opposed a rebellion at Kadesh (<a href="?bref=Num.14.1-5">14:1-5</a>). He stood with Moses against a later revolt (ch <a href="?bref=Num.16.1-50">16</a>). After a final incident at Meribah, where the Israelites almost revolted again, God accused Moses and Aaron of having failed to take him at his word and denied them entry into the Promised Land (<a href="?bref=Num.20.1-12">20:1-12</a>). Aaron died at the age of 123 on Mt Hor, after Moses took off his elaborate priestly clothes and put them on Aaron’s son Eleazar (<a href="?bref=Num.20.23-29">Nm 20:23-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.33.38-39">33:38-39</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=Exodusthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Exodus, The</a>; <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>; <a href="?item=PriestsandLevites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Priests and Levites</a>; <a href="?item=LeviTribeof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Levi, Tribe of</a>; <a href="?item=AaronsRod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Aaron’s Rod</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>