<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Altar">
  <title>Altar</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ALTAR</p>
<p class="fl">The platform upon which offerings are made to the deity. This may include a ritual sacrifice of animals or a burning of incense before God (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.1-10">Ex 30:1-10</a>). The Hebrew word for altar and the verb “to slaughter” both derive from the same root word; they are terms used in connection with the ritual of sacrificing animals to God as a covering for sin. The Greek terms also point to sacrificing animals. The practice was not unique to Israel but was widely known in the ancient Middle East. Israel’s immediate neighbors, the Canaanites, had their own altars and rituals. The altar was always a raised-up place.</p>
<p>The Bible refers to several altars built by the patriarchs. Noah offered burnt offerings (<a href="?bref=Gen.8.20">Gn 8:20</a>). Abraham built an altar at Shechem (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.7">Gn 12:7</a>), another at Bethel (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.8">Gn 12:8</a>), and one on Mt Moriah (<a href="?bref=Gen.22.9">Gn 22:9</a>). Isaac built an altar at Beersheba (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.25">Gn 26:25</a>), and Jacob at Shechem (<a href="?bref=Gen.33.20">Gn 33:20</a>) and Bethel (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.7">Gn 35:7</a>). Moses built one at Rephidim (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.15">Ex 17:15</a>) and another at Horeb (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.4">Ex 24:4</a>). In each case the altar was built to commemorate an event in which God had helped the offerer.</p>
<p>Two altars were used in the tabernacle. One, measuring 5 by 5 by 3 cubits (7.5 by 7.5 by 4.5 feet; 2.3 by 2.3 by 1.4 meters), was made of acacia wood overlaid with bronze and used for burnt offerings (<a href="?bref=Exod.27.1-8">Ex 27:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.38.1-7">38:1-7</a>). The other, smaller one, the golden altar, was about 18 inches (45 centimeters) square and 3 feet (90 centimeters) high, and was used to burn incense before the veil (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.1-10">Ex 30:1-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.40.5">40:5</a>).</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Exod.20.24-26">Exodus 20:24-26</a>, instructions were given to Israel to make an altar of earth or of uncarved stones, upon which burnt offerings and peace offerings were to be made in every place where God's name was present. This very general prescription seems to have allowed various individuals to build an altar from time to time. Joshua built an altar on Mt Ebal (<a href="?bref=Josh.8.30-31">Jos 8:30-31</a>); the Reubenites, Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh built one in Transjordan (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.10-16">Jos 22:10-16</a>); Gideon built one in Ophrah (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.24">Jgs 6:24</a>); the family of David in Bethlehem (<a href="?bref=1Sam.20.6,29">1 Sm 20:6, 29</a>); David at the threshing floor of Araunah (<a href="?bref=2Sam.24.25">2 Sm 24:25</a>); and Elijah on Mt Carmel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.30">1 Kgs 18:30</a>). Apart from Elijah’s altar these all predated Solomon’s temple.</p>
<p>There were two altars in Solomon’s temple. One was 20 cubits square (about 25 feet; 7.6 meters) and 10 cubits high (about 12.5 feet; 3.8 meters). It was made of bronze and used for burnt offerings. It remained the center of temple worship until the temple was destroyed, although in the days of King Ahaz it was removed from its place to the northern side of the temple at the command of the Assyrian ruler Tiglath-pileser (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.14">2 Kgs 16:14</a>). It was later restored to its proper place by Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.18">2 Chr 29:18</a>). The second, the incense altar, stood in front of the veil. It was made of cedar and overlaid with gold (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.20-22">1 Kgs 6:20-22</a>).</p>
<p>During the exile, when the temple lay in ruins, Ezekiel had a vision of the restored temple in Jerusalem. There was an elaborate altar of burnt offering, rising in three terraces to a height of 10 cubits (17.5 feet; 5.3 meters) and resting on a base about 20 cubits (35 feet; 10.6 meters) square. Although the altar was idealistic, it emphasized the need for atonement in Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.43.13-17">Ez 43:13-17</a>). No reference is made to an incense altar.</p>
<p>Zerubbabel built an altar of burnt offerings (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.2">Ezr 3:2</a>) that Antiochus Epiphanes desecrated with a “desolating sacrilege,” probably an image of Zeus (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.1.54">1 Macc 1:54</a>). There was also an altar of incense. Antiochus Epiphanes carried off the golden altar (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.1.21">1 Macc 1:21</a>) in 169 <span class="era">BC</span>. Both were later restored by Judas Maccabeus (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.4.44-49">1 Macc 4:44-49</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TheAltarForBurntOfferings"/>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TheIncenseAltar"/>
<p>In Christian worship no altar was required, since in the death of Jesus Christ the final sacrifice for sin had been made. There are numerous references to both the altar of burnt offering in the temple (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.23-24">Mt 5:23-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.18-20,35">23:18-20, 35</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.51">Lk 11:51</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.9.13">1 Cor 9:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.18">10:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.13">Heb 7:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.11.1">Rv 11:1</a>) and the altar of incense, both in the earthly temple (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.11">Lk 1:11</a>) and in the heavenly temple (<a href="?bref=Rev.6.9">Rv 6:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.8.5">8:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.9.13">9:13</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>