<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Angel">
  <title>Angel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ANGEL</p>
<p class="fl">Messenger of God or supernatural being, either good or evil, with powers greater than humans possess.</p>
<p>The first kind of angels mentioned in the Bible are cherubim (plural of “cherub,” a Hebrew word). They were celestial beings sent by God to guard the tree of life in the Garden of Eden (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.24">Gn 3:24</a>). They were represented symbolically on the ark of the covenant (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.18-22">Ex 25:18-22</a>), in the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.26.31">Ex 26:31</a>) and temple (<a href="?bref=2Chr.3.7">2 Chr 3:7</a>), and seen by the prophet Ezekiel in a vision of the restored Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Ezek.41.18-20">Ez 41:18-20</a>). Two angels, Gabriel and the chief, or archangel, Michael, are named in the Bible (<a href="?bref=Dan.8.16">Dn 8:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.9.21">9:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.10.13">10:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.19,26">Lk 1:19, 26</a>; <a href="?bref=Jude.1.9">Jude 1:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.12.7-9">Rv 12:7-9</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="AngelOfTheLord"/>
<p>In the Bible, angels are spiritual beings who serve primarily as messengers. The English word “angel” comes directly from a Greek word for messenger. In <a href="?bref=Luke.9.52">Luke 9:52</a>, Jesus sent “messengers” ahead of him. Usually the same word is translated “angel” and is understood to mean a spiritual messenger from God. In the OT also, one Hebrew word can refer either to a human messenger or to a spiritual being. It is not always immediately clear which is meant, especially since angels sometimes appeared in human form. In certain passages, “the angel of God” or a similar phrase may refer to God delivering his own message (see <a href="?bref=Gen.18.2-15">Gn 18:2-15</a>).</p>
<p>Angels appeared to many of God’s people in the Bible to announce good news (<a href="?bref=Judg.13.3">Jgs 13:3</a>), warn of danger (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.15">Gn 19:15</a>), guard from evil (<a href="?bref=Dan.3.28">Dn 3:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.6.22">6:22</a>), guide and protect (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.19">Ex 14:19</a>), nourish (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.14-20">Gn 21:14-20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.4-7">1 Kgs 19:4-7</a>), or instruct (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.38">Acts 7:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.19">Gal 3:19</a>). When Christ came to earth as the Savior, angels heralded his birth (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.8-15">Lk 2:8-15</a>), guided and warned his parents (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.13">Mt 2:13</a>), strengthened him when he was tempted (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.11">Mt 4:11</a>) and in his last distress (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.43-44">Lk 22:43-44</a> in some manuscripts), and observed his resurrection (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.1-6">Mt 28:1-6</a>). Jesus spoke about the guardian angels of little children (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.10">Mt 18:10</a>). Philip was guided by an angel (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.26">Acts 8:26</a>). Apostles were rescued from prison by an angel (<a href="?bref=Acts.5.19">Acts 5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.12.7-11">12:7-11</a>). In a frightening situation, the apostle Paul was encouraged by an angel (<a href="?bref=Acts.27.21-25">Acts 27:21-25</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="AngelsOfTheSevenChurches"/>
<p>The physical appearance of angels in biblical encounters was often unusual enough to distinguish them from ordinary people. The angel who moved the stone from the entrance to Jesus’ tomb had an appearance like lightning and raiment white as snow (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.3">Mt 28:3</a>). Many passages about angels are descriptions of dreams or visions. “Jacob’s ladder” with angels ascending and descending (<a href="?bref=Gen.28.12">Gn 28:12</a>) is an example. In another dream an angel spoke to Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.31.11">Gn 31:11</a>). An angel appeared to Cornelius in a vision (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.1-3">Acts 10:1-3</a>). Major passages of this type include <a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-13">Isaiah 6</a> (the seraphim), much of the book of Ezekiel (the cherubim), and much of Daniel and Zechariah. In the NT, over a third of the references to angels are in the book of Revelation. In most cases there, the angelic beings are glorious or grotesque figures seen in visions and are not to be confused with human persons. The language describing such visions is appropriately mystical, or at least metaphorical and difficult to interpret.</p>
<p>Angelology, or the doctrine of angels, is not a major theme in Christian theology in spite of the many references to angels in the Bible. Angels are included in descriptions of all that God created (<a href="?bref=Ps.148.2">Ps 148:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.16">Col 1:16</a>). There are hints that they witnessed the creation of the world (<a href="?bref=Job.38.7">Jb 38:7</a>). No matter how close to God angels may be, they share with humankind the status of creatures. But as wholly spiritual creatures they are free from many human limitations, such as death (<a href="?bref=Luke.20.36">Lk 20:36</a>). They do not marry (<a href="?bref=Matt.22.30">Mt 22:30</a>), so they could be regarded as sexless. In all their appearances, angels in human form were taken to be men, never women or children. Their ability to communicate in human language and to affect human life in other ways is basic to their role in the Bible. Their power and awesome appearance (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.2-4">Mt 28:2-4</a>) sometimes tempted people to fear or worship them, but the NT does not condone the worship of angels (<a href="?bref=Col.2.18">Col 2:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.22.8-9">Rv 22:8-9</a>). Though angels are stronger and wiser than human beings, their power and knowledge are also limited by God (<a href="?bref=Ps.103.20">Ps 103:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.36">Mt 24:36</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.11-12">1 Pt 1:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.11">2 Pt 2:11</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=CherubCherubim_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cherub, Cherubim</a>; <a href="?item=SeraphSeraphim_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Seraph, Seraphim</a>; <a href="?item=Demon_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Demon</a>; <a href="?item=DemonPossession_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Demon-possession</a>; <a href="?item=Satan_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Satan</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>