<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ArkoftheCovenant">
  <title>Ark of the Covenant</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ARK OF THE COVENANT</p>
<p class="fl">Most important piece of furniture in the wilderness tabernacle (tent-sanctuary) that God instructed Moses to build (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.10-22">Ex 25:10-22</a>). The Hebrew word for ark can also mean “chest” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.9-10">2 Kgs 12:9-10</a>) or “coffin” (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.26">Gn 50:26</a>), but it is not the same word used for Noah’s ark. The ark that Moses had Bezalel make was an oblong chest made of acacia wood (<a href="?bref=Exod.31.1-5">Ex 31:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.37.1-9">37:1-9</a>). The chest measured approximately 45 by 27 by 27 inches (114 by 69 by 69 centimeters), and was overlaid inside and out with gold. It was fitted with two pairs of rings through which poles were slid to make it portable. The ark would also serve as container for the two tablets of the covenant that would be given to Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.16">Ex 25:16</a>). Since the tablets were also called the “testimony,” the ark was sometimes called the “ark of the testimony.” Also in the ark were placed a pot of manna, the miraculous food provided by God (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.33">Ex 16:33</a>), and Aaron’s rod that had budded (<a href="?bref=Num.17.10">Nm 17:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.4">Heb 9:4</a>).</p>
<p>The lid of the ark was called the “mercy seat” or “place of mercy” (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.17">Ex 25:17</a>). It was a slab of gold fitting over the top of the ark and having an importance of its own. Once a year the high priest was to make atonement for the people of Israel by sprinkling the mercy seat with the blood of bulls and goats (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.2-16">Lv 16:2-16</a>). In fact, the English expression “mercy seat” is related to the Hebrew word for “atone.” The lid was called a “seat” because the Lord was considered as enthroned between two cherubim (winged creatures) positioned opposite each other (<a href="?bref=Ps.99.1">Ps 99:1</a>). The Lord spoke to Moses from between the cherubim (<a href="?bref=Num.7.89">Nm 7:89</a>).</p>
<p>The ark was sometimes referred to simply as the ark (<a href="?bref=Exod.37.1">Ex 37:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.31">Nm 3:31</a>), at other times as the “ark of the covenant” (<a href="?bref=Num.4.5">Nm 4:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.4.16">Jos 4:16</a>). The Israelites were thus reminded that the ark’s holiness was not magical but derived from the holy law of God contained inside it. That name also confronted the Israelites with their need to follow the commands God had given in his “covenant.”</p>
<p>Those commands were given by the God of the covenant (or promise) who had rescued Israel from slavery in Egypt and who had promised to be the ever-present God of his people (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.6-7">Ex 6:6-7</a>). Hence the ark was most widely known as the “ark of the covenant.” Sometimes that name was expanded to “the Ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>’s covenant” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.28.18">1 Chr 28:18</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>At times the ark was called “the Ark of God.” It was a visible sign that the invisible God was dwelling in Israel’s midst. It had a devastating and often deadly “holiness.” The people of Beth-shemesh were severely punished after they had treated the ark without proper reverence (<a href="?bref=1Sam.6.19">1 Sm 6:19</a>). A man named Uzzah was killed by the Lord when he touched it with his hand to keep it from tumbling to the ground from a cart (<a href="?bref=2Sam.6.6-9">2 Sm 6:6-9</a>). The ark was dangerous to touch because it was the very symbol of God’s presence. For this reason God commanded that the ark be placed in the Holy of Holies, separated from the rest of the tabernacle (and later the temple) by a heavy veil (<a href="?bref=Exod.26.31-33">Ex 26:31-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.3-5">Heb 9:3-5</a>); no sinful man could look upon the glory of God above the ark and live (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.2">Lv 16:2</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="History">History</p>
<p class="fl">When the Israelites journeyed from Mt Sinai to Canaan, the ark accompanied them in their trek through the desert. It was to be a constant reminder of the holy presence of their God. The ark was spoken of in the accounts of that journey almost as though it were endowed with personal features (<a href="?bref=Num.10.33-36">Nm 10:33-36</a>). Although the wrapping and carrying of the sacred objects were carefully detailed (<a href="?bref=Num.4.1-49">Nm 4</a>), God’s relationship with the ark was so close that the ark seemed to be “alive.”</p>
<p>The ark clearly played a benevolent role during the desert journey. A group of Israelites rebelled and tried to invade Canaan on their own, although neither the ark nor Moses went with them (<a href="?bref=Num.14.44">Nm 14:44</a>). The result was defeat at the hands of their enemies (<a href="?bref=Num.14.45">Nm 14:45</a>). The ark played an important role in the crossing of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Josh.3.13-17">Jos 3:13-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.4.9-10">4:9-10</a>), the conquest of Jericho (<a href="?bref=Josh.6.6-11">Jos 6:6-11</a>), and the life of the Israelites in their new land (<a href="?bref=Josh.8.33">Jos 8:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.20.27">Jgs 20:27</a>). There is no hint of superstitious or magical use of the ark; it was not a fetish, talisman, or charm. Yet it had solemn significance as the container of God’s “testimony” and as the pledge of his presence.</p>
<p>A sharp contrast to the role of the ark in Joshua’s day is found in later times. In the days of Eli and his sons, that is, at the end of the period of the judges, religious life in Israel was at a low ebb. The ark was still venerated but looked upon as a fetish to ensure success or victory automatically. When losing a battle with the Philistines, the Israelites rushed the sacred chest to the battlefield, thereby hoping to gain a victory (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.1-10">1 Sm 4:1-10</a>). But the Lord did not tolerate such flagrant misuse of the ark. He allowed it to be captured by the uncircumcised Philistines (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.11">1 Sm 4:11</a>) and inflicted defeat on Israel and death on the house of the high priest Eli (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.13-22">1 Sm 4:13-22</a>).</p>
<p>At the same time, God vindicated the honor of the ark when it was offered to Dagon, the god of the Philistines. The account of the efforts of the pagan Philistines to get rid of the ark is humorous (<a href="?bref=1Sam.5.1-6.21">1 Sm 5–6</a>). The biblical writer dramatically illustrated that the holy ark could neither be treated superstitiously by God’s people nor mocked by his enemies.</p>
<p>Samuel, a great reformer and prophet, made no attempt to restore the ark to a place of prominence after it was returned to Israel. He allowed it to remain in Kiriath-jearim (<a href="?bref=1Sam.6.21">1 Sm 6:21</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.7.2">7:2</a>). Samuel first had to bring Israel back to obedience to God’s covenant before the ark of the covenant could be of any use. David, described as a king after God’s own heart and chosen to replace the disobedient Saul, exerted efforts to bring the ark back to a prominent place (<a href="?bref=2Sam.6.1-17">2 Sm 6:1-17</a>). It may have been to David’s political advantage to add prestige to his newly established capital, Jerusalem, formerly the Canaanite stronghold of Jebus. But <a href="?bref=Ps.132.1-18">Psalm 132</a> describes David’s concern for the honor of God and for the ark. In a moment of great religious joy and enthusiasm he addressed God directly: “Arise, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and go to thy resting place, thou and the ark of thy might” (v <a href="?bref=Ps.132.8">8</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). To restless David, the ark had also been “restless” as long as Israel had not yet obtained its “rest,” that is, as long as Canaan had not been completely conquered. Some measure of peace had already come during Joshua’s time (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.43-45">Jos 21:43-45</a>), but much remained to be done. By conquering Jebus, David virtually completed the conquest of the Promised Land. Finally the land had rest and the Lord could then “dwell” in his temple, the suitable resting place for the ark. Nevertheless, David’s desire to build a temple for the ark was not granted (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.1-17">2 Sm 7:1-17</a>). He was told that his son Solomon would build a home for the ark and for the Lord. Solomon erected a magnificent temple with a place for the ark in the most holy part, behind the curtains (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.1-11">1 Kgs 8:1-11</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="WhatHappenedToTheArk"/>
  </body>
</item>