<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Azariah">
  <title>Azariah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">AZARIAH</p>
<p class="fl">Very common Jewish name. It appears often in the priestly genealogies and has caused much confusion. The following is one of several possible arrangements:</p>
<p class="list"> 1. Zadok’s son or grandson. According to most translations, Azariah was high priest during Solomon’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.2">1 Kgs 4:2</a>). It is possible, however, that his position should be understood as that of a special counselor or keeper of the royal calendar.</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Nathan’s son, a high official in King Solomon’s court. He was chief officer over the 12 regional administrators (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.5">1 Kgs 4:5</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Amaziah’s son, king of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.21">2 Kgs 14:21</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.1-7">15:1-7</a>), more frequently known as Uzziah. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Uzziah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Uzziah #1</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Ethan’s son, a descendant of Judah (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.8">1 Chr 2:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Jehu’s son, another descendant of Judah (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.38">1 Chr 2:38</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Ahimaaz’s son and Zadok’s grandson (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.9">1 Chr 6:9</a>). If Azariah #1 was indeed a high priest, this Azariah could be identified with him.</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Johanan’s son and Amariah’s father (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.10-11">1 Chr 6:10-11</a>). He is identical with the Azariah of <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.3">Ezra 7:3</a> and <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Esd.1.2">2 Esdras 1:2</a>, whose father (meaning “ancestor”) was Meraioth. The parenthetical note about Solomon’s temple (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.10">1 Chr 6:10</a>) is generally held to go with the Azariah of verse <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.9">9</a> (see #6 above). It is possible, however, that this Azariah served in the temple (built by Solomon) during the reign of Uzziah and is therefore identical with #17 below.</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Hilkiah’s son and Seriah’s father (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.13-14">1 Chr 6:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.1">Ezr 7:1</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Esd.1.1">2 Esd 1:1</a>). Some have identified this Azariah with #10 or #11 below.</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Zephaniah’s son, an ancestor of the singer Heman. Heman sang in the worship ritual instituted by King David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.36">1 Chr 6:36</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Hilkiah’s son or descendant, one of the first priests to settle in Jerusalem after the exile (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.11">1 Chr 9:11</a>; “Seraiah,” <a href="?bref=Neh.11.11">Neh 11:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Oded’s son, a prophet in the days of King Asa of Judah. He encouraged Asa to initiate badly needed reforms in the king’s 15th year (<a href="?bref=2Chr.15.1-15">2 Chr 15:1-15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12, 13. Two sons of King Jehoshaphat of Judah. Along with four of their brothers, they were killed for political reasons by Jehoram, heir to the throne (<a href="?bref=2Chr.21.1-4">2 Chr 21:1-4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">14. Alternate name of Ahaziah, king of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.22.6">2 Chr 22:6</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Ahaziah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ahaziah #2</a>.</p>
<p class="list">15. Jehoram’s son, one of Judah’s military commanders. This Azariah followed Jehoiada the priest in a rebellion that resulted in the execution of Queen Athaliah and the crowning of Joash as king (<a href="?bref=2Chr.23.1">2 Chr 23:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">16. Obed’s son, another of the five commanders in league with Jehoiada against Athaliah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.23.1">2 Chr 23:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">17. High priest in Jerusalem during the reign of King Uzziah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.16-21">2 Chr 26:16-21</a>). He opposed Uzziah’s arrogant attempt to burn incense on the altar. Perhaps the same as #7 above.</p>
<p class="list">18. Johanan’s son, a leader of Ephraim’s tribe. Azariah and other leaders of the tribe, along with the prophet Obed, objected to King Pekah of Israel capturing Judean prisoners and helped secure their release (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.12">2 Chr 28:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">19. Descendant of Kohath and the father of a Levite named Joel. Joel participated in the temple cleansing instituted by King Hezekiah of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.12">2 Chr 29:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">20. Jehallelel’s son. This Azariah, a descendant of Merari, also participated in Hezekiah’s cleansing of the temple (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.12">2 Chr 29:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">21. Zadok’s descendant and high priest during the reign of Hezekiah of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.10,13">2 Chr 31:10, 13</a>). He participated in Hezekiah’s massive religious reforms.</p>
<p class="list">22. Maaseiah’s son, a householder in Jerusalem who participated in Nehemiah’s rebuilding of the wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.23">Neh 3:23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">23. Leader who returned to Judah with Zerubbabel after the Babylonian exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.7.7">Neh 7:7</a>; “Seraiah,” <a href="?bref=Ezra.2.2">Ezr 2:2</a>).</p>
<p class="list">24. Levitical assistant of Ezra who explained to the people passages from the law read by Ezra (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.7">Neh 8:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">25. Priest who signed Ezra’s covenant of faithfulness to God with Nehemiah and others after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.2">Neh 10:2</a>).</p>
<p class="list">26. Participant in the dedication of the rebuilt wall of Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.33">Neh 12:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list">27. Alternate form of Jaazaniah, the name of Hoshaiah’s son, in <a href="?bref=Jer.42.1">Jeremiah 42:1</a> and <a href="?bref=Jer.43.2">43:2</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Jaazaniah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jaazaniah #1</a>.</p>
<p class="list">28. One of the three young Jews taken into captivity with Daniel. In Babylon he was renamed Abednego (<a href="?bref=Dan.1.6-7,11,19">Dn 1:6-7, 11, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.2.17">2:17</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=ShadrachMeshachandAbednego_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>