<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Sackcloth">
  <title>Sackcloth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SACKCLOTH</p>
<p class="fl">Poor quality material or a garment of goat hair usually worn as a symbol of mourning, but also worn by some prophets and captives.</p>
<p>Sackcloth was coarse and probably dark in color (<a href="?bref=Isa.50.3">Is 50:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.12">Rv 6:12</a>). The shape of the garment is disputed. Two views are prominent. One view is that the garment was rectangular, sewn on both sides and one end with spaces left for the head and arms. This shape resembles the grain sacks used by Joseph’s brothers in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.42.25-27,35">Gn 42:25-27, 35</a>) and the sacks used by the Gibeonites (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.4">Jos 9:4</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.11.32">Lv 11:32</a>). A second view is that sackcloth was a small garment resembling a loincloth. Asiatic captives are pictured in such garb. The Hebrew practices of girding the loins with sackcloth (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.31">2 Sm 3:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.15.3">Is 15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.22.12">22:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.4.8">Jer 4:8</a>) and the placing of sackcloth on the loins (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.34">Gn 37:34</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.31">1 Kgs 20:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.48.37">Jer 48:37</a>) support this view, though more than one type of garment could have been made from sackcloth. Sackcloth was associated primarily with mourning (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.34">Gn 37:34</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.27">1 Kgs 21:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.2.10">Lam 2:10</a>). National (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.30">2 Kgs 6:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.1">Neh 9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.37.1">Is 37:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jon.3.8">Jon 3:8</a>) as well as personal crises constituted times for the wearing of sackcloth. Kings (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.27">1 Kgs 21:27</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.30">2 Kgs 6:30</a>), priests (<a href="?bref=Joel.1.13">Jl 1:13</a>), elders (<a href="?bref=Lam.2.10">Lam 2:10</a>), prophets (<a href="?bref=Isa.20.2">Is 20:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.13.4">Zec 13:4</a>), and cattle (<a href="?bref=Jon.3.8">Jon 3:8</a>) all wore sackcloth. Sackcloth was found on the penitent (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.1">Neh 9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.26">Jer 6:26</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.11.21">Mt 11:21</a>) though such usage was not restricted to Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.15.3">Is 15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.49.3">Jer 49:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.31">Ez 27:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Jon.3.5">Jon 3:5</a>). It has been suggested that the coarse fabric produced physical discomfort and was used to inflict self-punishment on the wearer. There is no evidence, however, to support this position.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BurialBurialCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Burial, Burial Customs</a>; <a href="?item=Mourning_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mourning</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>