<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SamuelPerson">
  <title>Samuel (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SAMUEL (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Last of the judges, his name means “name of God” or “his name is El” (El is the name of the God of strength and power). The play on words in <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.20">1 Samuel 1:20</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.2.10">Ex 2:10</a>) is not intended to be an explanation of the meaning of Samuel’s name; Hannah’s words recall only her prayer and the circumstances surrounding her son’s birth.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PersonalHistory">Personal History</p>
<p class="fl">Samuel’s parents were a devout couple who went annually to the sanctuary at Shiloh (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.3">1 Sm 1:3</a>). His father, Elkanah, was a Levite (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.26">1 Chr 6:26</a>) and a resident in Ramah, territory of Ephraim. His mother, Hannah, was unable to bear children early in their marriage. Elkanah had a second wife, Peninnah.</p>
<p>On a visit to Shiloh, Hannah prayed in the sanctuary (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.6-11">1 Sm 1:6-11</a>), vowing that, if the Lord would give her a son, she would dedicate him as a Nazirite (<a href="?bref=Num.6.1-21">Nm 6:1-21</a>) to God’s service for life. The Lord heard Hannah’s prayer and granted her request. She had no other children until after Samuel’s dedication.</p>
<p>When Samuel was presented to Eli and began his service in the sanctuary, he bowed before the Lord and “worshiped the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> there” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.28">1 Sm 1:28</a>). Three ingredients—a feeling of worth, a knowledge of his parents’ love (cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.19">2:19</a>), and a sense of purpose—laid the foundation of his personality and his future accomplishments.</p>
<p>Further proof of Samuel’s valuable early training is evidenced in <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.1-36">1 Samuel 2</a>. Eli’s sons had followed the licentious practices of the pagan religions about them. Eli was old, indulgent, and powerless to restrain them. Samuel neither developed irreverence for Eli nor followed his sons in the path of evil. God determined to judge Eli and his house for their sins. When God announced his purpose to Samuel, Samuel responded with reverence and respect. His personal and spiritual growth indicated that he had been marked out as a future prophet of the Lord.</p>
<p> When everyone did what was right in his or her own eyes (cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.17.6">Jgs 17:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.21.25">21:25</a>), God allowed an adjacent nation to serve as his instrument to chasten his people, until a judge arose to deliver them. When the Philistines again invaded the land (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.1-6.21">1 Sm 4–6</a>), the Israelites mustered their army at Ebenezer, only to be defeated. Believing that the ark of the covenant would guarantee success, they sent to Shiloh for it. The next day the Israelites were again defeated and the ark captured. When this news reached Eli, he fell from his stool and died.</p>
<p>Twenty years elapsed before Samuel’s name is mentioned again (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.2-3">1 Sm 7:2-3</a>). Evidently, following the destruction of Shiloh (cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.7.12-14">Jer 7:12-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.26.6,9">26:6, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.60">Ps 78:60</a>), he lived in Ramah and went on annual preaching missions that included Bethel, Gilgal, and Mizpah, “judging” the people in these places (cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.16.18-22">Dt 16:18-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.17.8-13">17:8-13</a>). Samuel probably also founded “schools of the prophets” during this period. Schools were established at Bethel (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.5">1 Sm 10:5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.3">2 Kgs 2:3</a>), Gilgal (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.38">2 Kgs 4:38</a>), Ramah (<a href="?bref=1Sam.19.20">1 Sm 19:20</a>), and elsewhere (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.5">2 Kgs 2:5</a>), perhaps as a natural outgrowth of Samuel’s ministry.</p>
<p>After a 20-year ministry, Samuel thought it timely to move toward spiritual and national unification. He convened a meeting at Mizpah (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.1-17">1 Sm 7</a>). There, with a symbolic rite expressive of deep humiliation and in keeping with the libations of a treaty, the Israelites poured out water on the ground, fasted, and prayed.</p>
<p>The Philistines mistook the nature of the convocation and decided to attack the defenseless worshipers, who entreated Samuel to pray for them. He offered a sacrifice and the Lord sent a violent thunderstorm, causing the invaders to flee in panic. The pursuing Israelites won a significant victory at Ebenezer (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.12">1 Sm 7:12</a>).</p>
<p>In Samuel’s declining years, the elders rejected his leadership in favor of a king (<a href="?bref=1Sam.8.1-22">1 Sm 8</a>). Following earnest prayer, he received new direction from the Lord, acceded to their request, and later anointed Saul prince over God’s people. Samuel then summoned the Israelites to Mizpah, where God’s choice was made official, and Saul was hailed as king. Following Saul’s victory over Nahash (ch <a href="?bref=1Sam.11.1-15">11</a>), Samuel at Gilgal confirmed Saul’s kingship. Thereafter, Samuel retired to Ramah to train men to carry on his ministry.</p>
<p>Samuel twice had to reprove Saul, first for impatience and disobedience (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.5-14">1 Sm 13:5-14</a>), and then for disobeying the express command of the Lord (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.20-23">15:20-23</a>), who rejected him as king. Samuel was then sent to the home of Jesse in Bethlehem, where he anointed David as the chosen one of the Lord (<a href="?bref=1Sam.16.1-13">16:1-13</a>).</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=1Sam.25.1">1 Samuel 25:1</a> is a brief account of Samuel’s passing, when all Israel gathered together and mourned for him. He was buried in Ramah. The only subsequent mention of Samuel is in <a href="?bref=1Sam.28.1-25">1 Samuel 28</a>. Summoned by the witch of Endor at Saul’s request, Samuel announced that on the following day Saul and his sons would die in battle (vv <a href="?bref=1Sam.28.4-19">4-19</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Character">Character</p>
<p class="fl">Samuel overcame many problems through piety, perseverance, and dedication to the service of the Lord. His overriding concern was for the good of his people. Wise and courageous, he boldly rebuked king, elders, and people when necessary, always from the sure ground of the revealed will of God.</p>
<p>While Samuel served as judge and priest, he was preeminently a prophet. Through his ministry the spiritual life of the Israelites improved. In inaugurating the monarchy, he led the people from tribal disunity to national solidarity. He appointed gatekeepers to the tent of meeting (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.17-26">1 Chr 9:17-26</a>), organized observance of the Passover so memorably that it was still spoken about in Josiah’s day (<a href="?bref=2Chr.35.18">2 Chr 35:18</a>), put into writing how a king and his kingdom should be (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.25">1 Sm 10:25</a>), and penned “The Chronicles of Samuel the Seer” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.29.29">1 Chr 29:29</a>).</p>
<p>Samuel well deserves a place among the great men of faith (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.32">Heb 11:32</a>). He was the last of the judges (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.6,15-17">1 Sm 7:6, 15-17</a>) and the first of the prophets (<a href="?bref=1Sam.3.20">1 Sm 3:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.3.24">Acts 3:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.20">13:20</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=SamuelBooksofFirstandSecond_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Samuel, Books of First and Second</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>