<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Sea">
  <title>Sea</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SEA</p>
<p class="fl">A great body of salty water covering much of the earth.</p>
<p>The seas are mentioned in the very beginning of the Bible. In <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-2">Genesis 1:1-2</a> we read that in the beginning all was shapeless, empty, and dark, “and the Spirit of God was moving over the face of the waters.” Then God spoke and out of the chaos came order. Thus the voice of the Lord is powerful over all the waters of chaos. <a href="?bref=Ps.29.1-11">Psalm 29</a> celebrates this. From the account of the Creation in <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Genesis 1</a>, two things stand out: (1) that the sea, like everything else in earth and heaven, was created by God; and (2) that by the word of God division was made between sea and land. These two facts are amplified in the Bible in a number of ways. <a href="?bref=Ps.33.7">Psalm 33:7</a> speaks of how “He made the oceans, pouring them into his vast reservoirs.” Eloquently, God’s ordaining of the limits of sea and land is expressed in the words of the Lord to Job: “Who shut in the sea with doors, when it burst forth from the womb; . . . and prescribed bounds for it, and set bars and doors, and said, ‘Thus far shall you come, and no farther, and here shall your proud waves be stayed’?” (<a href="?bref=Job.38.8-11">Jb 38:8-11</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>God’s control over the waters of the sea is described when the Bible says that God “trampled the waves of the sea” (<a href="?bref=Job.9.8">Job 9:8</a>). So in his life on earth, Jesus, the God-man, walked on the sea (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.48">Mk 6:48</a>). He also stilled the storm, so that the disciples in awe and wonder asked, “Who then is this, that even wind and sea obey him?” (<a href="?bref=Mark.4.41">Mk 4:41</a>).</p>
<p>The Hebrew people had a healthy respect for the sea and its power. Perhaps because of the lack of good natural harbors, and because they did not control the coastline for much of their history, they were not a seafaring people like the Phoenicians. It is only in the time of Solomon that we read of their having a fleet of their own (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.26">1 Kgs 9:26</a>). The restless sea was to them a picture of the wicked (<a href="?bref=Isa.57.20">Is 57:20</a>). “Breakers rolling upon a beach” (<a href="?bref=Isa.17.13">Is 17:13</a>) or “the roaring of the sea” (<a href="?bref=Isa.5.30">5:30</a>) made them think of forces able to do incalculable harm to men. In <a href="?bref=Dan.7.3">Daniel 7:3</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.13.1">Revelation 13:1</a>, powers hostile to God are pictured as beasts coming up out of the sea.</p>
<p>Yet, as we have seen, God controls the seas. He is able to rescue those who trust in him “out of many waters” (<a href="?bref=Ps.18.16">Ps 18:16</a>). He is able to protect those who go out into the seas (<a href="?bref=Ps.107.23-31">107:23-31</a>). It was always remembered that God had made a way in the sea for his people to pass when they came out of Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.19">Ex 15:19</a>). Psalmists (<a href="?bref=Ps.74.13">Pss 74:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.77.16">77:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.13">78:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.106.9">106:9</a>) and prophets alike (e.g., <a href="?bref=Isa.43.16-17">Is 43:16-17</a>) recalled this. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=DeadSea_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dead Sea</a>; <a href="?item=MediterraneanSea_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mediterranean Sea</a>; <a href="?item=RedSea_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Red Sea</a>; <a href="?item=SeaofGalilee_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sea of Galilee</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>