<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SeirPlace">
  <title>Seir (Place)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SEIR (P<span class="lc">lace</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. Mountain range of Edom extending from the Dead Sea southward to the Gulf of Aqaba. Mt Seir was bordered by the great valley of Arabah on the west and by desert on the east. Seir is the modern Jebel esh-Shera.</p>
<p class="list-text">Seir was formerly inhabited by the Horites, whose defeat to King Kedorlaomer is recorded in <a href="?bref=Gen.14.4-6">Genesis 14:4-6</a>. The Horites were later dispossessed from this region by Esau (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.12">Dt 2:12</a>); however, a remnant of Horite chiefs was listed among the descendants of Esau living in Seir (<a href="?bref=Gen.36.20-30">Gn 36:20-30</a>). As this area was given by the Lord as an inheritance to Esau (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.4">Jos 24:4</a>), the Israelites were warned not to provoke the sons of Esau to war as they passed through Seir on their wilderness travels (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.1-8">Dt 2:1-8</a>). During Israel’s occupation of Palestine, they were drawn into a number of battles against the people of Seir. A band of Simeonites destroyed the Amalekites dwelling in Seir and resettled it with their own people (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.42">1 Chr 4:42</a>). Jehoshaphat, king of Judah (872–848 <span class="era">BC</span>), gained an incredible victory over the allied armies of Ammon, Moab, and Seir (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.10-23">2 Chr 20:10-23</a>). King Amaziah of Judah (796–767 <span class="era">BC</span>) routed an army from Seir in the valley of Salt (<a href="?bref=2Chr.25.11-14">25:11-14</a>). And finally, the prophet Ezekiel pronounced a curse of destruction on the inhabitants of Seir for their antagonism against Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.35.1-15">Ez 35:1-15</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=EdomEdomites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Edom, Edomites</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Place defining part of the northern boundary of the land assigned to Judah’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.10">Jos 15:10</a>). It was positioned west of Kiriath-jearim and northeast of Beth-shemesh. Mt Seir is perhaps the ridge on which the modern town of Saris is built.</p>
  </body>
</item>