<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Serpent">
  <title>Serpent</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SERPENT</p>
<p class="fl">A snake or sea monster. Various words are used in the Bible for serpents or snakes. In general, the serpent belongs to a class of reptiles often characterized by their ability to wound by striking or biting and then poisoning with venom. There are particular kinds of snakes mentioned in the Bible, such as the adder (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.8">Is 11:8</a>) and the viper (<a href="?bref=Acts.28.3">Acts 28:3</a>). “Serpent” also denotes the monstrous sea serpent mentioned in <a href="?bref=Job.26.13">Job 26:13</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.27.1">Isaiah 27:1</a>, and <a href="?bref=Amos.9.3">Amos 9:3</a>.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Gen.3.1">Genesis 3:1</a> the temptation that came to Adam and Eve is described as coming through the serpent, that “shrewdest of all the creatures the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God had made” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). And in consequence of this, he was told, “You will grovel in the dust as long as you live, crawling along on your belly” (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.14">Gn 3:14</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Reference is made in <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.3">2 Corinthians 11:3</a> to the fact that the serpent deceived Eve by his cunning, and <a href="?bref=Rev.12.9">Revelation 12:9</a> speaks of the “ancient serpent, who is called the Devil and Satan, the deceiver of the whole world” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>; see also <a href="?bref=Rev.12.14-15">Rv 12:14-15</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.20.2">20:2</a>).</p>
<p>Most of the biblical references to serpents or snakes allude (in figurative application) to the ability of the snake to bite and to poison with venom (e.g., <a href="?bref=Gen.49.17">Gn 49:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.10.8,11">Eccl 10:8, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.14.29">Is 14:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.19">Am 5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.9.19">Rv 9:19</a>). In <a href="?bref=Ps.58.4-5">Psalm 58:4-5</a> the wicked are likened to snakes. In <a href="?bref=Ps.140.3">Psalm 140:3</a>, people’s tongues are also spoken of as being as sharp as a serpent’s, and their lips as poisonous as vipers. In <a href="?bref=Pr.23.32">Proverbs 23:32</a> it is said that strong drink “bites like a poisonous serpent; it stings like a viper” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). Then in <a href="?bref=Jer.8.17">Jeremiah 8:17</a> the enemies of Israel are spoken of as coming, in God’s judgment against his people, as “poisonous snakes you cannot charm. No matter what you do, they will bite you, and you will die” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Positively, the serpent is seen to have great wisdom as the “craftiest” of creatures. And so we have the words of Jesus to his disciples, “Be wise as serpents and innocent as doves” (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.16">Mt 10:16</a>). But the primary image is negative. The serpent is a symbol of deceit. Thus, Jesus addressed the scribes and Pharisees as “Snakes! Sons of vipers!” (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.33">23:33</a>). John the Baptist also addressed the Pharisees and Sadducees with the words “You sons of snakes!” (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.7">3:7</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>