<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shemaiah">
  <title>Shemaiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHEMAIAH</p>
<p class="list"> 1. Prophet during the reign of Rehoboam, king of Judah (930–913 <span class="era">BC</span>). He warned the king not to go to war against Jeroboam and the ten northern tribes of Israel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.22-24">1 Kgs 12:22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.11.2-4">2 Chr 11:2-4</a>). Five years later he spoke words of comfort to a repentant Rehoboam and people of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.12.5-7">2 Chr 12:5-7</a>). Shemaiah chronicled the life of Rehoboam in a book that has since been lost.</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Son of Shecaniah, the father of six sons and a descendant of David through Rehoboam’s line (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.22">1 Chr 3:22</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Simeonite, father of Shimri and an ancestor of Jehu (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.37">1 Chr 4:37</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Reubenite and a son of Joel (<a href="?bref=1Chr.5.4">1 Chr 5:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Levite and the son of Hasshub, who returned to Jerusalem after the exile (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.14">1 Chr 9:14</a>). He was made a leader in the work of the temple during the days of Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.15">Neh 11:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Son of Galal and the father of Obadiah, a Levite who returned to Jerusalem following the Babylonian captivity (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.16">1 Chr 9:16</a>); called Shammua in <a href="?bref=Neh.11.17">Nehemiah 11:17</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Levite and the leader of his father’s house. Shemaiah was summoned by David to help carry the ark from Obed-edom’s house to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.8-11">1 Chr 15:8-11</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Son of Nethanel and the Levitical scribe who recorded the 24 divisions of the priests during David’s reign in Israel (1000–961 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.24.6">1 Chr 24:6</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Oldest of Obed-edom’s eight sons and the father of sons who served as the gatekeepers of the south gate and storehouse of the sanctuary during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.26.4-7">1 Chr 26:4-7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. One of the Levites sent by King Jehoshaphat of Judah (872–848 <span class="era">BC</span>) to teach the law in the cities of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.17.8-9">2 Chr 17:8-9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Son of Jeduthun and Uzziel’s brother, who was among the Levites chosen by King Hezekiah of Judah (715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>) to cleanse the house of the Lord (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.14-15">2 Chr 29:14-15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. One of the Levites assisting Kore with the distribution of the offerings among his fellow priests living in the priestly cities of Judah during the days of King Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.15">2 Chr 31:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">13. One of the Levitical leaders who generously gave animals to the Levites for the celebration of the Passover feast during King Josiah’s reign (640–609 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.35.9">2 Chr 35:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">14. Son of Adonikam, who returned with Ezra to Judah after the exile during the reign of King Artaxerxes I of Persia (464–424 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.8.13">Ezr 8:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">15. One of the Jewish leaders whom Ezra sent to Iddo at Casiphia to gather Levites and temple servants for the caravan of Jews returning to Palestine from Babylon (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.16-17">Ezr 8:16-17</a>).</p>
<p class="list">16. Priest and one of Harim’s five sons who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.21">Ezr 10:21</a>).</p>
<p class="list">17. Son of another Harim who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.31">Ezr 10:31</a>).</p>
<p class="list">18. Son of Shecaniah and the keeper of the East Gate who repaired a section of the Jerusalem wall under Nehemiah’s direction (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.29">Neh 3:29</a>).</p>
<p class="list">19. Son of Delaiah and a false prophet hired by Tobiah and Sanballat to frighten Nehemiah and hinder him from rebuilding the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.6.10-13">Neh 6:10-13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">20. One of the priests who set his seal on the covenant of Ezra (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.8">Neh 10:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list">21. One of the leaders of the priests who returned with Zerubbabel and Jeshua to Judah after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.6">Neh 12:6</a>).</p>
<p class="list">22. One of the princes of Judah who participated in the dedication of the Jerusalem wall during the postexilic period (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.34">Neh 12:34</a>).</p>
<p class="list">23. Son of Mattaniah, grandfather of Zechariah, and a descendant of Asaph. Zechariah was one of the priests who played a trumpet at the dedication of the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.35">Neh 12:35</a>).</p>
<p class="list">24–25. Two priestly musicians who performed at the dedication of the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.36,42">Neh 12:36, 42</a>).</p>
<p class="list">26. Father of Uriah the prophet from Kiriath-jearim. Like Jeremiah, his contemporary, Uriah spoke words of doom against Jerusalem and Judah during the reign of King Jehoiakim of Judah (609–598 <span class="era">BC</span>), who deplored Uriah’s message and eventually had him killed (<a href="?bref=Jer.26.20-21">Jer 26:20-21</a>).</p>
<p class="list">27. Nehelamite and a Jew deported to Babylon by Nebuchadnezzar, from where he opposed Jeremiah. He sent letters to the priests in Jerusalem that criticized Jeremiah for predicting a long captivity for Judah. Jeremiah exposed Shemaiah as a false prophet and foretold that he and his descendants would not live to see the return to Palestine (<a href="?bref=Jer.29.24-32">Jer 29:24-32</a>).</p>
<p class="list">28. Father of Delaiah, a prince of Judah during the reign of King Jehoiakim (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.12">Jer 36:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">29. A kinsman of Tobit (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Tb.5.14">Tb 5:14</a>); also spelled Shemeliah.</p>
  </body>
</item>