<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shemathe">
  <title>Shema*, the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHEMA*, The</p>
<p class="fl">The declaration “Hear, O Israel, Yahweh our God is one Yahweh” (<a href="?bref=Deut.6.4">Dt 6:4</a>). <span class="hebrew">Shema</span> comes from the first Hebrew word of the verse, <span class="hebrew">shema</span><span class="ital">,</span> “hear.” Verses <a href="?bref=Deut.6.4-9">4-9</a> make up the whole of this foundational biblical truth. While several translations of verse <a href="?bref=Deut.6.4">4</a> are grammatically correct, Jesus’ words in <a href="?bref=Mark.12.29">Mark 12:29</a> correspond most closely to the one given above. Religious Jews recite the Shema three times daily as part of their devotional life; no Sabbath worship is conducted in the synagogue without its proclamation.</p>
<p>Within the Shema is found both a fundamental doctrinal truth and a resultant obligation. There is an urgency connected to the teaching: the word <span class="hebrew">shema</span> demands that the hearer respond with his total being to the fact and demands of this essential revelation.</p>
<p>With regard to the teaching pertaining to the nature of God, the word “one” (<span class="hebrew">echad</span>) designates a compound unity rather than an absolute singular. While the eminent medieval Jewish theologian Maimonides insisted that God was <span class="hebrew">yachid</span> (an absolute singular), the OT does not use this word to define God’s nature. The compound singular word for “one” first occurs in <a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Genesis 2:24</a> where a man and woman, though separate entities, are seen to be one (<span class="hebrew">echad</span>) in marriage. Understandably, Jesus could freely quote <a href="?bref=Deut.6.4">Deuteronomy 6:4</a> without infringing upon the truth of his own deity.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DeuteronomyBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Deuteronomy, Book of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>