<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Sheol">
  <title>Sheol*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHEOL*</p>
<p class="fl">Hebrew term for the place of the dead. In ordinary usage it means “ravine,” “chasm,” “underworld,” or “world of the dead.” In the OT it is the place where the dead have their abode, a hollow space underneath the earth where the dead are gathered in. Synonyms for Sheol are “pit,” “death,” and “destruction” (Abaddon). Sheol is a place of shadows and utter silence. Here all existence is in suspense, yet it is not a nonplace, but rather a place where life is no more. It is described as the Land of Forgetfulness. Those who dwell there cannot praise God (<a href="?bref=Ps.88.10-12">Ps 88:10-12</a>). In Revelation it is called the “bottomless pit” presided over by Abaddon, the prince of the pit (<a href="?bref=Rev.9.11">Rv 9:11</a>).</p>
<p>It is not, however, a place where God is entirely absent; there can be no escape from God even in Sheol (<a href="?bref=Ps.139.8">Ps 139:8</a>). This omnipresence of God is graphically described in Job: “Sheol is naked before God, and Abaddon has no covering” (<a href="?bref=Job.26.6">Jb 26:6</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). A similar thought is expressed in Proverbs: “Sheol and Abaddon lie open before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, how much more the hearts of men!” (<a href="?bref=Pr.15.11">Prv 15:11</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). In both texts Sheol and Abaddon are used interchangeably. Abaddon means literally “destruction,” but in Revelation it is used as a personal name.</p>
<p>In the Bible, death is not a natural occurrence. It violates the principle of life, which is a gift from God. Sheol is therefore not only a place of rest but also of punishment. Korah and his associates who instigated rebellion against Moses were swallowed up by the open pit and perished in Sheol (<a href="?bref=Num.16.30-33">Nm 16:30-33</a>). Fear of death is natural to man; Sheol therefore serves as a symbol of the journey without return (<a href="?bref=Ps.39.12-13">Ps 39:12-13</a>). King Hezekiah of Judah laments on his sickbed: “In the noontide of my days I must depart; I am consigned to the gates of Sheol for the rest of my years” (<a href="?bref=Isa.38.10">Is 38:10</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Sheol, as conceived in the OT, differs from the later doctrine of hell or Hades in that it is the place where all the dead are gathered indiscriminately, both the good and the bad, the saints and the sinners. To die means to be joined to those who have gone before. When a Jew dies, he is “gathered unto his people” (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.25.8,17">Gn 25:8, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.35.29">35:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.49.29">49:29</a>). Beyond Sheol there seemed to be no hope (cf. <a href="?bref=Eccl.9.10">Eccl 9:10</a>). The utter despondency of death is expressed pathetically in the book of Job: “I go whence I shall not return, to the land of gloom and deep darkness, the land of gloom and chaos, where light is as darkness” (<a href="?bref=Job.10.21-22">Jb 10:21-22</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Yet this is not Job’s last word. He also knows of the power of God, which reaches beyond the grave: “For I know that my Redeemer lives . . . ; and after my skin has been thus destroyed, then from my flesh I shall see God” (<a href="?bref=Job.19.25-26">19:25-26</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>The idea that the dead abide in the underworld persists in the OT. The incident in the case of Saul with the medium of Endor (<a href="?bref=1Sam.28.11">1 Sm 28:11</a>) is a good illustration. Samuel is brought “up out of the earth” to be consulted by the king at a time of crisis. Such necromancy was strictly prohibited both by the law of Moses (<a href="?bref=Deut.18.9-11">Dt 18:9-11</a>) and by the king himself (cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.28.3,9">1 Sm 28:3, 9</a>). Apparently, those in the underworld, though separated from the living, were thought to be familiar with the affairs of men.</p>
<p>Sheol is roughly equivalent to the Greek word often found in the NT, <span class="greek">hades</span><span class="ital">,</span> as that which also describes the place of the dead.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DeadPlaceofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dead, Place of the</a>; <a href="?item=Death_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Death</a>; <a href="?item=Hades_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hades</a>; <a href="?item=Hell_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hell</a>; <a href="?item=IntermediateState_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Intermediate State</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>