<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Shepherd">
  <title>Shepherd</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHEPHERD</p>
<p class="fl">One who took complete care of a flock of sheep. His task was to find grass and water for the sheep, to protect them from wild animals (<a href="?bref=Amos.3.12">Am 3:12</a>), to look for and restore those that strayed (<a href="?bref=Ezek.34.8">Ez 34:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.18.12">Mt 18:12</a>), to lead the flock out of the fold each day, and to return the flock to the fold at the close of the day (<a href="?bref=John.10.2-4">Jn 10:2-4</a>).</p>
<p>The figure of the shepherd and his sheep is important in the NT. Jesus is the Good Shepherd who gives his life for the sheep (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.10-14">Mt 18:10-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.34">Mk 6:34</a>; <a href="?bref=John.10.1-42">Jn 10</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.13.20">Heb 13:20</a>). The analogy of the shepherd and the flock finds rich expression in <a href="?bref=Ps.23.1-6">Psalm 23</a>, <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.1-31">Ezekiel 34</a>, and <a href="?bref=John.10.1-42">John 10</a>. God was the Shepherd of Israel (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.24">Gn 49:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.23.1">Pss 23:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.80.1">80:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.11">Is 40:11</a>). When unfaithful shepherds failed Israel, God intervened and appointed his servant David as a faithful shepherd over them (<a href="?bref=Ezek.34.11-16,23-24">Ez 34:11-16, 23-24</a>).</p>
<p>The NT imagery comes from an OT and Palestinian background. In the Jewish economy, the shepherd who tended a flock of sheep or goats held a responsible position. Great flocks had to be moved from place to place, and it was necessary that they be guarded from wild animals and robbers. Because of the fundamental role of shepherding in the ancient world, the word “shepherd” became a common term for a ruler. The kings of Assyria, Babylon, and Egypt were often referred to as shepherds who protected their people. This imagery formed the background for the OT, where the same usage is found. God is pictured as the shepherd of Israel, concerned for every aspect of his people’s welfare. Rulers and leaders of the people are often referred to as shepherds (<a href="?bref=Num.27.17">Nm 27:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.17">1 Kgs 22:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.10.21">Jer 10:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.12.10">12:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.22.22">22:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.1-2">23:1-2</a>).</p>
<p>By the time of Jeremiah, “shepherd” began to be used as a title for the coming Messiah. God himself would provide for his flock (<a href="?bref=Jer.23.3">Jer 23:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.31.10">31:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.34.11-22">Ez 34:11-22</a>) and promised to provide faithful shepherds who showed concern for his people (<a href="?bref=Jer.3.15">Jer 3:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.4">23:4</a>). He explicitly promised that he would be their God and would set the messianic Son of David as shepherd over them (<a href="?bref=Ezek.34.23-24">Ez 34:23-24</a>). In the NT Jesus referred to himself as the promised messianic Shepherd (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.16">Mt 10:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.25.32">25:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.27">Mk 14:27</a>; <a href="?bref=John.10.1-30">Jn 10:1-30</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.13.20">Heb 13:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.25">1 Pt 2:25</a>). <a href="?bref=Eph.4.11">Ephesians 4:11</a> speaks of leaders of the church as shepherds or pastors, and this usage continued in the early church and down until the present day. Paul said they are special people given to the church by God to care for God’s people as a shepherd does his sheep, leading and teaching them in the ways of God. Peter also spoke of the leaders as shepherds; he encouraged them to remain faithful shepherds until the time that the Chief Shepherd, Jesus Christ, appeared (<a href="?bref=1Pet.5.1-4">1 Pt 5:1-4</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>