<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ShittimPlace">
  <title>Shittim* (Place)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SHITTIM* (P<span class="lc">lace</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Site on the plains of Moab where the Israelites made their final Transjordan encampment after defeating Sihon and Og (<a href="?bref=Num.21.21-35">Nm 21:21-35</a>) and prior to their crossing of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Num.25.1">25:1</a>). According to <a href="?bref=Num.33.49">Numbers 33:49</a>, this camp was near the Jordan, spreading from Beth-jeshimoth as far as Abel-shittim. Here Abel-shittim appears to be the full name of the place, while Shittim is the more common abbreviated toponym.</p>
<p>At Shittim, Balak of Moab attempted to thwart the Israelite penetration of Canaan by hiring Balaam to curse the people of God (<a href="?bref=Num.22.1-24.25">Nm 22–24</a>), and later, apparently incited by Balaam’s counsel, Israel “played the harlot” with women from Midian and Moab (<a href="?bref=Num.25.1-5">25:1-5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Num.31.15-16">31:15-16</a>). Israel’s apostasy, participating in idolatrous rites and engaging in ritual prostitution, was punished by Yahweh with the plague at Peor (<a href="?bref=Num.25.1-18">Nm 25:1-18</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.6-8">1 Cor 10:6-8</a>). Moses and Eleazar organized a census of the tribes while encamped at Shittim, and here Joshua was publicly proclaimed as Moses’ successor (<a href="?bref=Num.27.18-22">Nm 27:18-22</a>). Joshua dispatched two spies from Shittim to reconnoiter Jericho (<a href="?bref=Josh.2.1">Jos 2:1</a>); later the Israelites prepared for the river crossing by breaking camp at Shittim and traveling to the Jordan (<a href="?bref=Josh.3.1">3:1</a>).</p>
<p>Outside the Hexateuch the place-name Shittim occurs only in <a href="?bref=Joel.3.18">Joel 3:18</a> and <a href="?bref=Mic.6.5">Micah 6:5</a>. The reference in Joel to the “valley of Shittim” or “wadi of the acacias” seems to be a symbol of barren aridity transformed into well-watered land when Yahweh restores his people in the eschaton, not a literal geographical location. Micah charges the people to remember “what happened from Shittim to Gilgal,” no doubt a reference to the crossing of the Jordan and the covenant promise of a land ultimately realized, as he recites the “saving acts” of Yahweh on Israel’s behalf.</p>
  </body>
</item>