<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SidonPlaceSidonian">
  <title>Sidon (Place), Sidonian</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SIDON (Place), SIDONIAN</p>
<p class="fl">City on the Phoenician coast, between Beirut and Tyre; frequently called Zidon in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>. The present town, Saida, is not regarded as a direct continuation of the ancient city but rather a development of post-Crusader times. The names Sidon and Sidonian appear 38 times in the OT, and Sidon occurs 12 times in the NT.</p>
<p>The relative antiquity of Byblos (Gebal, Jebeil), Tyre, and Sidon may be determined by the “table of nations” (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.1-32">Gn 10</a>), which names Sidon as the firstborn son of Canaan, who was a son of Ham. The territory of the Canaanites extended from Sidon to Gaza and east to the Cities of the Plain.</p>
<p>Sidon is situated 22 miles (35.4 kilometers) north of Tyre, with which it is often associated (e.g., <a href="?bref=Isa.23.1-2">Is 23:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.47.4">Jer 47:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.11.21-22">Mt 11:21-22</a>); both were much concerned with commerce and industry. Sidon was built on a headland that jutted into the sea toward the southwest. It had two harbors, the northern one having inner and outer ports. Sidon was also a center for the manufacture of the purple dye made from the Murex shellfish.</p>
<p>The Bible mentions Sidon several times in connection with the conquest of Palestine. Joshua defeated the northern confederation under Jabin, king of Hazor, and pursued the enemy as far as “Great Sidon” (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.8">Jos 11:8</a>). Joshua also stated that the land of Israel included all of Lebanon, “even all the Sidonians” (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.4-6">13:4-6</a>). The tribal allotment of Asher extended as far north as “Sidon the Great” (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.28">19:28</a>), but Asher did not drive out the inhabitants of Sidon (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.31">Jgs 1:31</a>).</p>
<p>The gods of Sidon are listed among the foreign deities that Israel served (<a href="?bref=Judg.10.6">Jgs 10:6</a>); David’s census included Sidon and Tyre (<a href="?bref=2Sam.24.6-7">2 Sm 24:6-7</a>); and during a famine in the time of Ahab, the prophet Elijah was sent to live at the home of a widow in Zarephath (Sarepta) in Sidon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.17.9">1 Kgs 17:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.25-26">Lk 4:25-26</a>). Sidon is referred to often by the Hebrew prophets (<a href="?bref=Isa.23.2,4,12">Is 23:2, 4, 12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.25.22">Jer 25:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.27.3">27:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.47.4">47:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.8">Ez 27:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.3.4">Jl 3:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.9.2">Zec 9:2</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT, Jesus healed the daughter of a woman of that area (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.21-28">Mt 15:21-28</a>). People came from as far away as Tyre and Sidon to hear Jesus and to be healed by him (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.17">Lk 6:17</a>). On Paul’s voyage to Rome to appear before Caesar, the ship made its first stop at Sidon, where the centurion, Julius, allowed Paul to go ashore to visit friends (<a href="?bref=Acts.27.3">Acts 27:3</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>