<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Sign">
  <title>Sign</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SIGN</p>
<p class="fl">Word connoting a visible event intended to convey meaning beyond that which is normally perceived in the outward appearance of the event.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In a few instances in the OT, “sign” refers to the observances of heavenly bodies in an astrological sense (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.14">Gn 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.10.2">Jer 10:2</a>), or to the “signs and wonders” as marks of the miraculous actions of God within the history of the world (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.34">Dt 4:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.6.22">6:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.10">Neh 9:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.105.27">Ps 105:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.32.20">Jer 32:20</a>). On other occasions, it is used as an insignia of the Mosaic covenant. Thus, the wearing of the law on the wrist and forehead and the keeping of the Sabbath are considered signs of the relationship between Israel and God (<a href="?bref=Deut.6.8">Dt 6:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.11.18">11:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.12,20">Ez 20:12, 20</a>).</p>
<p>The most numerous and significant usages of “sign” appear in relation to the OT prophetic ministry. Beginning with Moses, signs are used to confirm that God has spoken to the prophet. Thus, when Moses received the message of deliverance that he was to bring to the children of Israel in Egypt and the pharaoh, he was given two signs: his staff was changed into a serpent and his hand was afflicted with leprosy (<a href="?bref=Exod.4.1-8">Ex 4:1-8</a>).</p>
<p>Signs and wonders were also used by false prophets. After a sign had been given and had come to pass, the leaders of Israel were to examine the message of the prophet to see if it led the people away from the true worship of God. If it did, the prophet who had given the sign was to be put to death (<a href="?bref=Deut.13.1-5">Dt 13:1-5</a>).</p>
<p>The character of the sign varies and often is miraculous. Some of the great miracles of the OT are prophetic signs—for example, the moving of the shadow back up the steps of Hezekiah’s palace to confirm Isaiah’s prediction that the king would recover from what was a mortal illness (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.8-9">2 Kgs 20:8-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.38.21-22">Is 38:21-22</a>). Often the sign is predictive only, and the people can know whether the prophet has spoken the truth by whether or not the event comes to pass—for example, the prophet’s foretelling the death of both of Eli’s sons on the same day (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.34">1 Sm 2:34</a>; see also <a href="?bref=1Sam.14.10">14:10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.29">2 Kgs 19:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.37.30">Is 37:30</a>). Sometimes the sign was carefully timed, and the recipient was told that the appearance of the sign would show when to act to fulfill the prophetic message (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.7-9">1 Sm 10:7-9</a>). At other times, the events predicted were acted out in the life of the prophet. These symbolic actions demonstrated the truth of the prophet’s message—for example, Isaiah’s nakedness for three years to demonstrate the fate of those who preached trust in Egypt’s power (<a href="?bref=Isa.20.3">Is 20:3</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Ezek.4.3">Ez 4:3</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The NT occurrences are much like those in the OT. There are references to heavenly signs that will occur as indications of the end of time, and those with special knowledge will understand that the end is drawing near (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.3,30">Mt 24:3, 30</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.4,22">Mk 13:4, 22</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.21.11,25-26">Lk 21:11, 25-26</a>). These apocalyptic signs have no astrological connotations as in the OT. There is also mention of the sign as the seal of the covenant between God and Israel in reference to circumcision in <a href="?bref=Rom.4.11">Romans 4:11</a>.</p>
<p>As in the OT, the NT uses of signs are confirmations of the message given by God, and this message comes through the apostolic community to the church. Thus, there is great emphasis on the way God confirms the message of the apostles through their ability to perform signs and wonders (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.43">Acts 2:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.30">4:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.12">5:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.8.13">8:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.14.3">14:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.19">Rom 15:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.2.4">Heb 2:4</a>).</p>
<p>In Matthew, Mark, and Luke, Jesus’ miracles are not called signs. Only in <a href="?bref=Acts.2.22">Acts 2:22</a> does Peter proclaim that Jesus’ message was attested by signs he performed. Rather, Jesus’ miracles are seen as acts of divine power and mercy. When the Jews ask for a sign, they are consistently refused, with the promise that the only sign they will receive is the sign of Jonah (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.38-39">Mt 12:38-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.16.1">16:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.11-12">Mk 8:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.19,30">Lk 11:19, 30</a>), a sign that refers to the death and resurrection of the Christ. As Jonah was in the belly of the whale for three days and three nights, so will the Son of Man be in the heart of the earth for three days (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.40">Mt 12:40</a>).</p>
<p>In the Gospel of John, however, the miracles of Jesus are seen in a strikingly different light and are considered signs. Beginning with the changing of water into wine (<a href="?bref=John.2.1-11">Jn 2:1-11</a>), the miracles are called signs and are intended to lead those who see them to faith (v <a href="?bref=John.2.23">23</a>). Jesus even laments that the people will not believe unless they see signs (<a href="?bref=John.4.48">4:48</a>). John’s purpose in writing his Gospel is to present the signs of Jesus so that those who come to faith may do so through seeing these signs (<a href="?bref=John.20.30">20:30</a>). The signs in the Gospel are expressly chosen because they lend themselves to the development of true faith.</p>
<p>In the Gospel of John, the miracles of Jesus confirm the teaching of Jesus. In the synoptic Gospels, the miracles are seen as acts of mercy and divine power. In John they are carefully selected to demonstrate what Jesus has to tell the world about himself. In this respect, they are a bit like the symbolic actions of Isaiah and Ezekiel in that the action of the speaker dramatizes the message. After Jesus feeds the 5,000 with the five loaves of bread and the two fishes, he announces in the synagogue at Capernaum, “I am the bread of life which came down from heaven” (<a href="?bref=John.6.51">Jn 6:51</a>). He tells them not to labor for the bread of this world that perishes. In much the same way, the healing of the man born blind is bound up with Jesus’ teaching that he is the light of the world (<a href="?bref=John.9.5">9:5</a>). The resurrection of Lazarus prepares the way for Jesus to proclaim that he is the resurrection and the life (<a href="?bref=John.11.25">11:25</a>). In John’s Gospel the signs are not only a demonstration of divine power but also a revelation of Jesus’ divine character. In addition to confirming his divine message, they also proclaim his personhood and mission.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Miracle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Miracle</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>