<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SimeonTribeof">
  <title>Simeon, Tribe of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SIMEON, Tribe of</p>
<p class="fl">One of the 12 tribes of Israel descended from Jacob’s second son. Because of Simeon’s evil deed at Shechem, Jacob foretold that Simeon’s descendants would be dispersed among the other tribes of Israel (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.7">Gn 49:7</a>).</p>
<p>According to the book of Joshua, Simeon’s inheritance was included in Judah’s territory (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.1,9">Jos 19:1, 9</a>). <a href="?bref=Judg.1.3">Judges 1:3</a> points to a close bond between the tribes of Simeon and Judah—they march and fight together as brothers to establish themselves in Canaan. In addition, the list of Levitical towns included Simeon’s with Judah’s (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.9-16">Jos 21:9-16</a>). Inevitably, then, the Simeonites were linked to the kingdom of Judah throughout the period of the monarchy, and its tribal destiny was tied to that of the southern division of the divided monarchy. However, in spite of their minor inheritance within Judah’s tribe, the Simeonites were able to preserve to some extent their own tribal identity, unity, and traditions, as indicated by the keeping of genealogical records, even to the days of Hezekiah, king of Judah (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.24-42">1 Chr 4:24-42</a>).</p>
<p>During Hezekiah’s reign, Simeonites took possession of and settled the Arab areas of Seir (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.24-43">1 Chr 4:24-43</a>) and perhaps the hill country of Ephraim (<a href="?bref=2Chr.15.9">2 Chr 15:9</a>). Although Simeon was Jacob’s second-oldest son, his progeny never achieved a position of prominence in Israel, either before or after the conquest and occupation of Canaan. For example, the tribe apparently provided no judges, and the Song of Deborah contains no references to this group (see <a href="?bref=Judg.5.1-31">Jgs 5</a>). According to <a href="?bref=1Chr.4.28-33">1 Chronicles 4:28-33</a>, Simeon’s tribe settled in the southern extremes of Canaan (called the Negev in Hebrew)—an extensive region, consisting largely of dry, parched land, but with an annual rainfall and perennial springs that ensured fertility in the early summer. This explains why Simeon’s territory is also called “the Negev of Judah,” a phrase that serves to differentiate them from other racial groups occupying parts of southern Canaan (<a href="?bref=1Sam.27.10">1 Sm 27:10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.30.14">30:14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.24.7">2 Sm 24:7</a>).</p>
<p>The genealogies of the Simeonites reveal a certain amount of intermarriage with other Israelite tribes and, indeed, with non-Israelites as well. Shaul, Simeon’s son, was the son of a Canaanite woman (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.10">Gn 46:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.6.15">Ex 6:15</a>). Two of Simeon’s sons (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.25">1 Chr 4:25</a>) bear names of Ishmael’s sons (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.13-14">Gn 25:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.29-30">1 Chr 1:29-30</a>), and Jamin (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.10">Gn 46:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.6.15">Ex 6:15</a>) was a descendant of Ram (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.27">1 Chr 2:27</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT, Simeon’s tribe appears seventh in the list of the tribes who are sealed by God (<a href="?bref=Rev.7.7">Rv 7:7</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>