<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Simon">
  <title>Simon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SIMON</p>
<p class="fl">Greek form of a Hebrew/Aramaic name meaning “God has heard.” Nine men in the NT had this name:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Son of Jona (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.17">Mt 16:17</a>) or John (<a href="?bref=John.1.42">Jn 1:42</a>), Andrew’s brother (v <a href="?bref=John.1.40">40</a>), and surnamed Cephas and Peter (respectively Aramaic and Greek, for “rock,” v <a href="?bref=John.1.42">42</a>) by Jesus. A fisherman of Bethsaida (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.16">Mk 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.44">Jn 1:44</a>), he became an apostle of Jesus and author of two NT letters bearing his name. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=PetertheApostle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Peter, The Apostle</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Brother of Jesus, named with other brothers, James, Joses or Joseph, and Judas (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.55">Mt 13:55</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Leper, perhaps cured by Jesus, in whose house at Bethany Jesus and his disciples were eating when a woman poured an alabaster flask of costly ointment on the Lord’s head. Over the disciples’ objections against the waste of what could have been sold to support the poor, Jesus commended the act as a wonderful thing (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.6-13">Mt 26:6-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.3-9">Mk 14:3-9</a>). From <a href="?bref=John.12.1-8">John 12:1-8</a> it appears that Simon’s house was also the house of Mary, Martha, and Lazarus, but their relationship to Simon is uncertain.</p>
<p class="list">4. Man of Cyrene, a district of North Africa, whom the Romans forced to carry Jesus’ cross (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.32">Mt 27:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.15.21">Mk 15:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.23.26">Lk 23:26</a>). He was the father of Alexander and Rufus (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.21">Mk 15:21</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.16.13">Rom 16:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Apostle of Jesus called a Zealot (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.15">Lk 6:15</a>), presumably because of prior association either with the party of political extremists by that name, who adopted terrorism to oppose the Roman occupation of Palestine, or with one of a number of Jewish groups noted for their zeal for the law. In <a href="?bref=Matt.10.4">Matthew 10:4</a> and <a href="?bref=Mark.3.18">Mark 3:18</a> he is designated the “Cananaean” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>)—from the Aramaic word for “zealot.” He is mentioned again in <a href="?bref=Acts.1.13">Acts 1:13</a> as one of the 11 apostles in Jerusalem after Jesus’ ascension. Otherwise, the NT is silent about him.</p>
<p class="list">6. Pharisee whose treatment of Jesus evoked the parable of the two debtors (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.36-50">Lk 7:36-50</a>). He invited Jesus to eat at his house but withheld courtesies customary for guests and disapproved of Jesus’ acceptance of a “sinner” woman who wet the Lord’s feet with her tears, dried them with her hair, and anointed them with ointment from an alabaster flask. Jesus’ parable contrasted the woman’s act of loving and repentant faith with Simon’s unloving and self-righteous skepticism.</p>
<p class="list">7. Father of Judas Iscariot, the disciple who betrayed Jesus in Gethsemane (<a href="?bref=John.6.71">Jn 6:71</a>; <a href="?bref=John.13.2,26">13:2, 26</a>).</p>
<p class="list">8. Magician (often called Simon Magus) of great repute in Samaria. Impressed by the signs and miracles performed by Philip the deacon-become-evangelist, he joined the crowd of baptized believers. He offered Peter and John money in exchange for the gift of the Holy Spirit, provoking Peter’s emphatic rebuke (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.9-24">Acts 8:9-24</a>). From the association of this incident with his name, the English word “simony” is derived; it denotes the sale or purchase of church positions, or any profiteering from sacred things.</p>
<p class="list">9. Tanner of Joppa. Peter lodged at his house for many days (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.43">Acts 9:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.6,17,32">10:6, 17, 32</a>). On Simon’s housetop, Peter experienced the vision of a great sheet let down from heaven, containing animals and birds prohibited as food in Jewish law (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.15">10:15</a>). Peter later recognized this vision as his preparation for consenting to preach the gospel to the Gentiles (vv <a href="?bref=Acts.10.28-29">28-29</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>