<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SinaSinai">
  <title>Sina*, Sinai</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SINA*, SINAI</p>
<p class="fl">Name of the mountain where God met Moses and gave him the Ten Commandments and the rest of the law. The name applies not only to the mountain itself but to the desert around it (<a href="?bref=Lev.7.38">Lv 7:38</a>), as well as the entire peninsula embraced by the two arms of the Red Sea known as the Gulf of Suez and the Gulf of Aqaba (or Elath).</p>
<p>The name is probably related to Sin (wilderness of) and may even be an alternate spelling (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.16.1">Ex 16:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.17.1">17:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.33.11-12">Nm 33:11-12</a>). Sin is one name of the ancient moon god that desert dwellers worshiped. The mountain is also called Horeb, mostly in Deuteronomy (see also <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.9">1 Kgs 8:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.8">19:8</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.5.10">2 Chr 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.106.19">Ps 106:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.4.4">Mal 4:4</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="SaintCatherineSMonasteryAtTheBaseOfMountSinai"/>
<p>The traditional location of Mt Sinai is among the mountains at the southern end of the Sinai Peninsula. Since at least the fourth century, Christians have venerated Jebel Musa (Mt Moses in Arabic) as the site where God molded the families of Jacob into the nation of Israel. A Greek Orthodox monastery of St Catherine at the base of the 7,500-foot (2,286-meters) peak has been there for over 1,500 years. Other candidates for the holy mountain have been the nearby Jebel Katerina (8,670 feet, or 2,642.6 meters) and Jebel Serbal (6,800 feet, or 2,072.6 meters). Some scholars prefer a northern location near Kadesh-barnea, while others argue for a volcanic mountain across the gulf to the east in ancient Midian or Arabia (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.1">Ex 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.4.25">Gal 4:25</a>).</p>
<p>Most references to Sinai are in Exodus (13 times), Leviticus (5 times), and Numbers (12 times) because these are the books that report the giving of the law and the two-year encampment of the Israelites on the plains adjacent to the mountain. <a href="?bref=Exod.19.1-25">Exodus 19</a> and <a href="?bref=Exod.34.1-35">34</a> especially are replete with references because these are the chapters that describe the encounters between Moses and Yahweh on the two occasions when the law was actually given.</p>
<p>In both the OT and NT, Sinai came to represent the place where God came down to his people. In the blessing of Moses (<a href="?bref=Deut.33.2">Dt 33:2</a>), the song of Deborah (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.5">Jgs 5:5</a>), <a href="?bref=Ps.68.1-35">Psalm 68</a> (vv <a href="?bref=Ps.68.8,17">8, 17</a>), the confession of the Levites in the time of Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.13">Neh 9:13</a>), and the speech of Stephen (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.30,38">Acts 7:30, 38</a>), Sinai was remembered as the scene of that momentous encounter. Paul, in <a href="?bref=Gal.4.21-26">Galatians 4:21-26</a>, spells out an allegory in which Mt Sinai represents the old covenant, slavery, and the present city of Jerusalem. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Paran_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paran</a>; <a href="?item=Shur_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shur</a>; <a href="?item=SinWildernessof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sin, Wilderness of</a>; <a href="?item=CommandmentstheTen_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Commandments, The Ten</a>; <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>; <a href="?item=ZinWildernessof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Zin, Wilderness of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>