<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SinlessnessofChrist">
  <title>Sinlessness of Christ*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SINLESSNESS OF CHRIST*</p>
<p class="fl">The Scripture (quoted here from the <span class="sc">rsv</span>) leaves no question that Christ is regarded as sinless. He is declared to be the perfect Son of God in every respect. His human nature is holy, without any sin. This is repeatedly and explicitly affirmed in unmistakable terms. Paul states that Christ “knew no sin” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.21">2 Cor 5:21</a>). Peter says “he committed no sin; no guile was found on his lips” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.22">1 Pt 2:22</a>); he calls him “righteous” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.3.18">3:18</a>). The writer to the Hebrews says that Christ is “holy, blameless, unstained, separated from sinners” (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.26">Heb 7:26</a>). James speaks of him as “the righteous man” (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.6">Jas 5:6</a>), and John affirms that “in him there is no sin” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.5">1 Jn 3:5</a>). In the Gospels and in the apostolic preaching, Jesus is repeatedly witnessed to as the Holy Son of God, the Holy One of God, the Holy and Righteous One (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.35">Lk 1:35</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.69">Jn 6:69</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.3.14">Acts 3:14</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus was able to ask his enemies with penetrating conviction, “Which of you convicts me of sin?” (<a href="?bref=John.8.46">Jn 8:46</a>). He gives ample evidence of a holy self-consciousness throughout his entire lifetime. Numerous references and inferences are made to his exemption from the unrighteousness of sin and disobedience. He kept the entire law in every detail and in each respect (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.4">Rom 10:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.15">Heb 4:15</a>). Pilate’s wife regarded Jesus as a righteous man, and Pilate himself spoke of him as an innocent man (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.19,24">Mt 27:19, 24</a>). Even Judas realized that he himself had sinned by “betraying innocent blood” (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.4">Mt 27:4</a>).</p>
<p>The issue of Christ’s sinlessness is not confined merely to the fact that he did not commit any sin. There is a deeper theological significance to the question, which has to do with the issue of whether Christ was at all able to sin. Was it even possible for him to sin? This concern has been spoken of in theology as his impeccability (Christ was unable to sin), or on the contrary position, his peccability (Christ was able to sin, even though he did not exercise his will in this direction). The problems on both of these views appear immediately: If Christ was unable to sin, how could he really have been tempted (and we have ample data in Scripture concerning Jesus’ temptations)? If Christ could have sinned, even though he did not do so, does this mean that God can sin (for Christ was in every respect fully the Son of God, the second person of the Trinity)? It is useless to say that Jesus could have sinned with respect to his human nature but not so with respect to his divine nature, because this ignores the indissoluble unity of the person of the God-man. We may not separate the human nature from the divine nature, as though in his humanity he could have acted independently of his divinity. This was, in part, the error of the ancient Nestorian heretics. Whatever the Son of God does, he does with and in his entire divine-human nature.</p>
<p>Essentially, there is no contradiction between being tempted and being unable to sin. Of course, it is difficult for us to imagine how this can be possible. This is because we are sinners and stand within the experiential knowledge of evil. Christ’s person is absolutely unique; we can little imagine how real were his temptations by the devil in the wilderness and throughout his life (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.28,39-46">Lk 22:28, 39-46</a>), even though it was impossible for him to actually sin.</p>
<p>Perhaps an illustration may be helpful. Let us imagine there is an absolutely impregnable fortress that cannot be taken by the enemy as long as the defenses are maintained. (If we may, for the purpose of illustration, let us rule out the terrible destructive forces of modern warfare.) Because the fortress is incapable of being taken by assault and is in reality unconquerable, as long as the defenses are kept up, it does not mean that it cannot be besieged and furiously attacked. So it may be with respect to the reality of Christ’s temptations and his inability to sin as the Holy Son of God.</p>
<p>His temptations were real. Therefore, “we have not a high priest who is unable to sympathize with our weaknesses, but one who in every respect has been tempted as we are, yet without sin. Let us then with confidence draw near to the throne of grace, that we may receive mercy and find grace to help in time of need” (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.15-16">Heb 4:15-16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
  </body>
</item>