<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SongofSolomon">
  <title>Song of Solomon*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SONG OF SOLOMON*</p>
<p class="fl">Short OT book (eight chapters) containing only poetry. Its beautiful poetic passages describe the many dimensions of human love; there is little in this book that is explicitly religious. In addition to the popular title, the book is sometimes referred to as the “Song of Songs.” This is the most literal translation of the short title of the book in the original language and means “the best of all possible songs.” Some writers also entitle the book “Canticles”; this title is based on the name of the Latin version of the book, <span class="ital">Canticum Canticorum.</span></p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Date">Date</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#VariousInterpretations">Various Interpretations</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurposeandTheologicalTeaching">Purpose and Theological Teaching</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">There was an old tradition among the Jews that King Solomon (c. 970–930 <span class="era">BC</span>) wrote the Song of Songs. This view is based on one of several possible translations of the first verse of the Song: “Solomon’s song of songs” (<a href="?bref=Song.1.1">1:1</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). This view could be correct, though there cannot be absolute certainty, for the last words of the verse in the original language could be translated in various ways. An English translation that preserves the ambiguity of the original would be “The song of songs, which is Solomon’s” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>); the last words could mean that Solomon was author, but equally they could indicate that the song was “dedicated to Solomon” or “written for Solomon.” As is often the case with the OT writings, authorship cannot be known with absolute certainty.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Date">Date</p>
<p class="fl">It follows that if the authorship is uncertain, there must also be uncertainty concerning the date at which the song was written. If Solomon was the author, it was written during the latter half of the tenth century <span class="era">BC</span>. If he was not the author, then the song was probably written at a later date. But the contents indicate that the song must have been written and completed at some point during the Hebrew monarchy (before 586 <span class="era">BC</span>). For those who do not accept Solomon as author, the precise date will depend to some extent upon the theory that is adopted concerning the interpretation of the song. If the song is an anthology of Israelite love poetry, then the many poems making up the song would have been written at different dates and gathered together into a single volume toward the end of the Hebrew monarchy.</p>
<p class="h2" id="VariousInterpretations">Various Interpretations</p>
<p class="fl">There are two major difficulties in interpreting this book. First, the song appears to be secular in its present form and God’s name does not appear; the only exception to this statement is in <a href="?bref=Song.8.6">8:6</a>, where some English versions translate the text to show God’s name, though the original text uses the name in an unusual (adjectival) sense. The second problem is that, taken at face value, the song contains only secular poetry of human love. What is the theological significance of love poetry? These and other difficulties have led to a multitude of different interpretations of the song. A brief survey of some of the most significant interpretations will clarify not only the problem of understanding the book but also its content and meaning.</p>
<p class="h3">The Song as an Allegory</p>
<p class="fl">One of the oldest interpretations of the song sees it as an allegory. This view was held by both Jewish and Christian scholars from an early date. The description of human love in the song is seen as an allegory of the love between Christ and the church. Augustine of Hippo (<span class="era">AD</span> 354–430) believed that the marriage referred to in the song was an allegory of the marriage between Christ and the church.</p>
<p>This theory was valued for a long time. It influenced the translators of the <span class="sc">kjv</span>. They added chapter headings to their translations as an aid to readers in understanding the Bible. For example, at the beginning of the first chapter of the Song of Solomon, they wrote, “1. The Church’s love unto Christ, 5. She confesseth her deformity, 7. and prayeth to be directed to his flock.” It is important to stress, however, that the Hebrew text does not mention Christ or the church. The headings represent the understanding of the translators, not the content of the original Hebrew.</p>
<p class="h3">The Song as a Drama</p>
<p class="fl">The view that the song is a drama is also an old one. Those who hold this theory begin by noting that there are several speakers or actors. Perhaps, then, the song is the script of an ancient dramatic play.</p>
<p>This theory has some strong points. In the manuscript of an ancient Greek translation of the OT, headings have been added to the Song of Solomon that identify the speakers. The cast includes bride, bridegroom, and companions. However, the headings were probably not a part of the original Hebrew text. They reflect the interpretation of the early Greek translators.</p>
<p>There is one major difficulty with this theory: there is no clear evidence that drama was a form of art used by the Hebrews. Although drama was common among the Greeks, it does not appear to have been employed in the Near East. It is possible, however, to suggest a slight variation to the drama theory. Perhaps the Song of Solomon is not a drama but simply dramatic poetry, similar to the book of Job. This possibility is more plausible, but it too has difficulties. A story or plot would be expected for either drama or dramatic poetry, but it is not clear that there is a story.</p>
<p>According to one interpretation, the story might go as follows. The song tells the story of true love. A maiden was in love with a shepherd lad. King Solomon, however, fell in love with the maiden and took her to his palace. There he tried to win her love with beautiful words but failed. She remained faithful to the shepherd lad whom she loved. Failing to win her, Solomon released her and allowed her to return to her true lover. The story is beautiful and simple, but it is not easy to see in the text without added headings and explanations. Other interpreters have discerned a quite different story in the Song of Solomon. In conclusion, it is not absolutely clear that there is a single story being told.</p>
<p class="h3">The Song as Reflecting a Fertility Cult</p>
<p class="fl">Some modern scholars claim that the origin of the Song of Solomon is to be found in the fertility cults of the ancient Near East. In ancient fertility cults there was great emphasis on the fertility of the land, which would be seen in bountiful harvests. The cults were designed to ensure that the land remained fertile. They were accompanied by a mythology describing the gods responsible for fertility. This mythology included love poetry about the gods, and the poetry has some similarity to the Song of Solomon.</p>
<p>The theory might go like this: Originally the Hebrews also had a fertility cult. The Song of Solomon contains the love poetry associated with that cult. Later, the mythological references were omitted, so that the present song looks like secular love poetry.</p>
<p>The main difficulty with this theory is the lack of any firm evidence. There is no reference to God or any other gods in the Song of Solomon. There is no reference to a fertility cult or any other kind of cult. If the theory has some validity to it, the evidence no longer exists.</p>
<p class="h3">The Song as a Collection of Poems</p>
<p class="fl">This last, most probable theory of interpretation involves two basic principles. First, the song is to be interpreted literally; it is what it seems to be—poetry celebrating human love. Second, the Song of Solomon is a collection, not a single piece of poetry. Just as the book of Psalms contains songs, hymns, and prayers from many different periods of Israel’s history, so too the Song of Solomon contains poetry from different periods and different authors. The common theme joining all the passages together is human love. Opinions differ concerning where one song ends and the next begins. There may be as many as 29 songs in the book, some consisting of only one verse and others much longer.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="TheSongOfSongsChapter4Niv"/>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeandTheologicalTeaching">Purpose and Theological Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">If the Song of Solomon is primarily an anthology of the poetry of human love, what is its significance as a biblical book? What are its theological implications? First, the presence of the song in the Bible provides a valuable insight concerning human love. The love between a man and a woman is a noble and beautiful thing; it is a gift of God. It is characterized by a certain mystery and cannot be bought. But because human love is a beautiful and noble thing, it can easily be debased. In the modern world, the Song of Solomon provides a proper perspective and a balanced view of human love. Further, a high value of human love is essential. Since human love and marriage are employed in the Bible as an analogy of God’s love for humanity, love in itself must be good and pure.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">The Woman Sings Her Love Song (<a href="?bref=Song.1.2-7">1:2-7</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In each of the songs, the reader is like an eavesdropper listening to the words of love spoken, sometimes privately and sometimes to the beloved one. The opening song is a song of praise, rejoicing in love and delighting in a particular loved one: “Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth—for your love is more delightful than wine” (v <a href="?bref=Song.1.2">2</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). This song, as many others, is characterized by a country setting, here highlighted by a contrast with the city. The young woman is from the country and tanned from working in the open air; it makes her self-conscious among the city women of Jerusalem. But love overpowers self-consciousness, and it is in the country that she will meet her lover.</p>
<p class="h3">The King Converses with the Woman (<a href="?bref=Song.1.8-2.7">1:8–2:7</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In this passage, both the man and the woman are talking, though it is not a conversation in the normal sense. They are talking about each other, rather than to each other, and the beauty of both the man and the woman emerges, not in an abstract sense, but through the eyes of the beholder. Though beauty may perhaps be defined in an abstract sense, the beauty perceived by lovers is of a different kind; it is rooted in the lover’s perception of the loved one and in the relationship of love that acts like a lens to focus that perception.</p>
<p class="h3">A Song of Springtime (<a href="?bref=Song.2.8-13">2:8-13</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This beautiful song describes the young maiden watching her beloved come to her. He calls her to join him in the countryside, where the winter has passed and the new life of spring can be seen in the land. The beauty of young love is here likened to the blossoming forth of fresh life and fragrance that characterizes Palestine in spring.</p>
<p class="h3">The Woman Searches for Her Loved One (<a href="?bref=Song.2.14-3.5">2:14–3:5</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Now the woman sings and a new dimension of her love emerges from the words of her song. Love is full when the partners are together, but separation creates sorrow and loneliness. The words of the maiden evoke the desperation of separated lovers, a desperation that could only be dissipated when she held her lover again and would not let him go (<a href="?bref=Song.3.4">3:4</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The King’s Wedding Procession (<a href="?bref=Song.3.6-11">3:6-11</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The song begins with a description of the approach of the royal wedding procession, a palanquin surrounded by men of war. The king approaches the city for his wedding, and the young girls of the city go out to greet him. The song can be compared with <a href="?bref=Ps.45.1-17">Psalm 45</a>, another wedding song.</p>
<p class="h3">The Woman’s Beauty, Like a Garden (<a href="?bref=Song.4.1-5.1">4:1–5:1</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In sumptuous language, the man describes his maiden’s beauty. To the modern reader, the language is sometimes strange: “your neck is like the tower of David” (<a href="?bref=Song.4.4">4:4</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). But the strangeness lies principally in our unfamiliarity with the ancient metaphors. Nonetheless, much of the language here draws upon the imagery of nature and wildlife, which can be appreciated by all. Again, beauty is not described merely as something aesthetic, for it is intimately tied to the relationship of love: “How delightful is your love, my sister, my bride! How much more pleasing is your love than wine” (v <a href="?bref=Song.4.10">10</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). And again, the maiden’s beauty is not simply to be admired; it is to be given to the beloved. So when the man stops his words of adoration, the woman offers herself to him (v <a href="?bref=Song.4.16">16</a>) and he accepts (<a href="?bref=Song.5.1">5:1</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Woman Speaks of Her Beloved (<a href="?bref=Song.5.2-6.3">5:2–6:3</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In this song, the woman is talking with other women, and the man is not present. As she speaks about her lover, there is a change from words expressing a sense of loneliness and separation (<a href="?bref=Song.5.4-8">5:4-8</a>) to a resurgence of delight as she contemplates her loved one. The sorrow of separation from her beloved is dispelled as she recounts to them the handsomeness of her man (vv <a href="?bref=Song.5.10-16">10-16</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Man Speaks of His Loved One’s Beauty (<a href="?bref=Song.6.4-7.9">6:4–7:9</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This long passage may contain more than a single song; there are words from the man, the maiden, and the female companions. The principal theme is further description by the man of his beloved’s beauty (<a href="?bref=Song.6.4-10">6:4-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.7.1-9">7:1-9</a>), a theme already known from an earlier passage (<a href="?bref=Song.4.1-5.1">4:1–5:1</a>). Each part of the maiden’s body is exquisitely beautiful in the eyes of the one who loves her.</p>
<p class="h3">The Woman and the Man Reflect upon Love (<a href="?bref=Song.7.10-8.14">7:10–8:14</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Both partners speak in this complex passage, which may contain a number of short love songs. While some parts are difficult to interpret (especially <a href="?bref=Song.8.8-14">8:8-14</a>), other verses reveal in the most profound language the meaning of love. Love, that most powerful of all human relationships, creates a sense of mutual belonging and mutual possession: “I belong to my lover, and his desire is for me” (<a href="?bref=Song.7.10">7:10</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). And later, the girl speaks of love with words that convey one of the most powerful understandings of love in the entire Bible: “For love is as strong as death. . . . Many waters cannot quench love; rivers cannot wash it away. If one were to give all the wealth of his house for love, it would be utterly scorned” (<a href="?bref=Song.8.6-7">8:6-7</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=SolomonPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Solomon (Person)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>