<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SonofGod">
  <title>Son of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SON OF GOD</p>
<p class="fl">Term used to express the deity of Jesus of Nazareth as the unique divine Son.</p>
<p>Jesus’ unique sonship is antithetical to concepts of sonship popular in the ancient world. In Hellenism, people believed a man could be a “son of the gods” in many ways: in mythology, by cohabitation of a god with a woman whose offspring was imagined to be superhuman; in politics, by giving generals and emperors high honors in the cult of Roman emperor worship; in medicine, by calling a doctor “son of Asclepius”; and eventually by ascribing to anyone with mysterious powers or qualities the title or reputation of “divine man.”</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheTermintheOldTestament">The Term in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT, certain men who lived before the time of Noah (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.1-4">Gn 6:1-4</a>), “the angels” (including Satan, <a href="?bref=Job.1.6">Jb 1:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.2.1">2:1</a>), and other heavenly beings (<a href="?bref=Ps.29.1">Pss 29:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.82.6">82:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.6">89:6</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span> mg) are called “sons of God.” Israel as a people was the chosen son of God. This corporate sonship became the basis of Israel’s redemption from Egypt: “Israel is my first-born son” (<a href="?bref=Exod.4.22">Ex 4:22</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.31.9">Jer 31:9</a>). Corporate sonship was the context for focus on personal sonship in the divine sanction of David as king: “I will be his father, and he will be my son” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.14">2 Sm 7:14</a>). David’s “adoptive” sonship was by divine decree: “I will proclaim the decree: . . . ‘You are my son; today I have become your Father’ ” (<a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Ps 2:7</a>); and it was the prophetic prototype of the “essential” sonship of Jesus, David’s royal son (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.17">Mt 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.11">Mk 1:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.22">Lk 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.33">Acts 13:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.1.5">Heb 1:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.5.5">5:5</a>). Other messianic prophecies ascribe divine names to the Davidic Messiah: “Immanuel” (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.13-14">Is 7:13-14</a>) and “Mighty God, Everlasting Father” (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.6-7">Is 9:6-7</a>). These are fulfilled in Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.23">Mt 1:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.21.4-10">21:4-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.22.41-45">22:41-45</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheGospels">In the Gospels</p>
<p class="fl">Jesus’ identity as the Son of God is revealed in the Gospels in three distinct ways.</p>
<p>The first is his <span class="ital">eternal, personal sonship.</span> Jesus’ personal sonship is revealed in Peter’s confession, “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God” (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.16">Mt 16:16</a>) and in Jesus’ identification of himself at his trial: “ ‘Are you the Christ, the Son of the Blessed One?’ . . . ‘I am,’ said Jesus” (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.61-62">Mk 14:61-62</a>). In both instances, the issue is his personal being or essence, his eternal identity.</p>
<p>Long before Creation, even from eternity, the Father and the Son enjoyed fellowship with each other. We know this because the Bible tells us so—but not in any great detail. For the most part, the Scriptures are silent about the premundane scene. And yet there are a few verses that lift the veil slightly and give us a glimpse into that sublime, divine relationship that always existed between the Father and the Son.</p>
<p>Of all the books in the Bible, the Gospel of John has the most to say about the relationship between the Father and the Son. It is from John’s inspired pen that we read from the outset, “In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.” This is a rather flat rendering. The Greek conveys something more picturesque: “In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was face to face with God, and the Word was himself God.” Imagine, the Word, who was the preincarnate Son of God, was face to face with God. The expression “face to face” translates the Greek preposition <span class="greek">pros</span> (short for <span class="greek">prosopon pros prosopon</span><span class="ital">,</span> “face to face,” a common expression in koine Greek.) The expression signifies intimate fellowship. The Father and Son enjoyed such an intimate fellowship from eternity. How they must have delighted in each other!</p>
<p>After the Son of God became a man and began his ministry on earth, he referred to the relationship he enjoyed with the Father before the foundation of the world. Jesus spoke of what he had seen and heard together with the Father before coming to earth (see <a href="?bref=John.3.13">John 3:13</a> and <a href="?bref=John.8.38">8:38</a>). Jesus longed to return to that glorious sphere. In his prayer before going to the cross (in ch <a href="?bref=John.17.1-26">17</a>), he asked the Father to glorify him with the glory he had with the Father before the world was (v <a href="?bref=John.17.5">5</a>). Jesus wanted to recapture his primordial equality with the Father—something he had willingly relinquished for the sake of his Father’s plan (see <a href="?bref=Phil.2.6-7">Phil 2:6-7</a>). As he prayed to the Father, a wonderful utterance escaped from his lips: “Father, . . . you loved me before the foundation of the world” (<a href="?bref=John.17.24">Jn 17:24</a>). God’s Son, the unique Son, was the single object of the Father’s love.</p>
<p>The second aspect of Jesus’ sonship is his <span class="ital">nativity sonship.</span> The nativity of Jesus is traced to the direct, spiritual paternity of God. Jesus is the Son of God because his incarnation and birth into the human race was created by the Holy Spirit. In Matthew, Jesus’ conception “is of the Holy Spirit” (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.20">Mt 1:20</a>). He is to be named “Jesus” (meaning Yahweh is salvation) “because he will save his people from their sins” (v <a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">21</a>), and “Immanuel” (God with us) because he is himself the Son of God in human flesh (v <a href="?bref=Matt.1.23">23</a>). In Luke, Jesus’ conception was by the Holy Spirit and the power of the Most High (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.31,35">Lk 1:31, 35</a>), so Jesus was called “the Son of God” (v <a href="?bref=Luke.1.35">35</a>). If the father of Jesus had been the man Joseph, he would have been called “Jesus, the son of Joseph.” Luke’s teaching clearly means that since the Spirit of God was the father of Jesus, this son of the virgin Mary is properly called “Jesus, the Son of God.”</p>
<p>The third aspect is his <span class="ital">messianic sonship.</span> Jesus is the Father’s Son and representative, whose earthly mission is to establish the kingdom of God. At his baptism, he began his mission with the Father’s coronation: “This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased” (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.17">Mt 3:17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Ps 2:7</a>). Jesus received a similar pronouncement from heaven at his Transfiguration (<a href="?bref=Luke.9.35">Lk 9:35</a>). As the messianic Son, Jesus perfectly completed the redeeming work given him to do by his Father.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestamentEpistles">In the New Testament Epistles</p>
<p class="fl">Paul spoke of the essential, ontological sonship of Jesus—not as an isolated fact, but in the context of his redemptive work. It was as God’s Son that Jesus took human nature (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.3">Rom 1:3</a>) and as “the Son of God” that he was resurrected and enthroned in power (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.18">Mt 28:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.4">Rom 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.28">1 Cor 15:28</a>). The Incarnation is spoken of as “God sending his own Son” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.3">Rom 8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.4.4">Gal 4:4</a>) for humanity’s redemption, a redemption that was accomplished “through the death of his Son” (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.10">Rom 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.8.29,32">8:29, 32</a>). As a consequence, believers can have “fellowship with his Son, Jesus Christ our Lord” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.9">1 Cor 1:9</a>), and they can live by faith in “the Son of God” (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.20">Gal 2:20</a>). Paul’s first preaching was “that Jesus is the Son of God” (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.20">Acts 9:20</a>); this was later expounded by Paul in the light of <a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Psalm 2:7</a> (see <a href="?bref=Acts.13.33">Acts 13:33</a>).</p>
<p>In Hebrews, Jesus is “the Son,” who is God’s “firstborn” and personal “heir,” who is creator and sustainer of the universe, and who is the “radiance of God’s glory” (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.2-12">Heb 1:2-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.3.6">3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.5.5">5:5</a>). As the Son, he is the final and eternal High Priest who ascended to heaven and whose mediatorial work remains perfect forever (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.14">4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.6.6">6:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.3,28">7:3, 28</a>). In <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.1-21">1 John 4</a> and <a href="?bref=1Jn.5.1-21">5</a>, belief in Jesus as the incarnate Son of God is essential for salvation; disbelief comes from the spirit of the Antichrist.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Christology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Christology</a>; <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Teachings of</a>; <a href="?item=Messiah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Messiah</a>; <a href="?item=SonofMan_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Son of Man</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>