<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SpiritofJesusChrist">
  <title>Spirit of Jesus Christ</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SPIRIT OF JESUS CHRIST</p>
<p class="fl">The Spirit as identified with Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>The most important development and element in earliest Christian understanding of the Spirit is that the Spirit is now the Spirit of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.7">Acts 16:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.8.9">Rom 8:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.4.6">Gal 4:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.1.19">Phil 1:19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.11">1 Pt 1:11</a>; see also <a href="?bref=John.7.38">Jn 7:38</a>; <a href="?bref=John.15.26">15:26</a>; <a href="?bref=John.16.7">16:7</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.30">19:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.3.1">Rv 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.5.6">5:6</a>). The Spirit is to be identified as the Spirit that bears witness to Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.15.26">Jn 15:26</a>; <a href="?bref=John.16.13-15">16:13-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.32">Acts 5:32</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.3">1 Cor 12:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.2">1 Jn 4:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.5.7-8">5:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.10">Rv 19:10</a>), but also, and more profoundly, as the Spirit that inspired and empowered Jesus himself. This Spirit became available to the believers after Christ’s resurrection.</p>
<p> The apostles John and Paul were quite clear in their writings about Christ becoming spirit through resurrection. The keynote verses penned by John are <a href="?bref=John.6.63">John 6:63</a>; <a href="?bref=John.7.37-39">7:37-39</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.16-18">14:16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=John.20.22">20:22</a>; and <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.24">1 John 3:24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.13">4:13</a>. The critical passages written by Paul are <a href="?bref=Rom.8.9-10">Romans 8:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45">1 Corinthians 15:45</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.17-18">2 Corinthians 3:17-18</a>; and <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.17">1 Corinthians 6:17</a>.</p>
<p>Revelation concerning the Spirit of Jesus is progressive in the Gospel of John. John does not tell us from the beginning that people could not actually receive eternal life until the hour of Christ’s glorification. Throughout the Gospel, Jesus declares to various people that he can give them eternal life if they would believe in him. He promises them the water of life, the bread of life, and the light of life. But no one could really partake of these until after the Lord had risen. As a foretaste, as a sample, they could receive life via the Lord’s words because his words were themselves spirit and life (<a href="?bref=John.6.63">Jn 6:63</a>); however, it was not until the Spirit would become available that believers could actually become the recipients of the divine, eternal life. After the Lord’s discourse in <a href="?bref=John.6.1-71">John 6</a>, Jesus said, “It is the Spirit that gives life, the flesh profits nothing” (v <a href="?bref=John.6.63">63</a>). In the flesh Jesus could not give them the bread of life, but when the Spirit became available, they could have life. Again, Jesus offered the water of life—even life flowing like rivers of living water—to the Jews assembled at the Feast of Tabernacles. He told them to come and drink of him. But no one could, then and there, come and drink of him. So John added a note: “But this he spoke concerning the Spirit, for the Spirit was not yet because Jesus was not yet glorified” (<a href="?bref=John.7.39">7:39</a>). Once Jesus would be glorified through resurrection, the Spirit of the glorified Jesus would be available for people to drink. In <a href="?bref=John.6.1-71">John 6</a>, Jesus offered himself as the bread of life to be eaten by people; and in <a href="?bref=John.7.1-53">John 7</a>, he offered himself as the water of life to refresh men. But no one could eat him or drink him until he became spirit, as was intimated in <a href="?bref=John.6.63">John 6:63</a> and then stated plainly in <a href="?bref=John.7.39">John 7:39</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="CommunityOfTheSpirit"/>
<p>In <a href="?bref=John.14.16-18">John 14:16-18</a>, Jesus went one step further in identifying himself with the Spirit. He told the disciples that he would give them another Comforter. Then he told them that they should know who this Comforter was because he was, then and there, abiding with them and would, in the near future, be in them. Who else but Jesus was abiding with them at that time? Then after telling the disciples that the Comforter would come to them, he said, “I am coming to you.” First he said that the Comforter would come to them and abide in them, and then in the same breath he said that he would come to them and abide in them (see <a href="?bref=John.14.20">14:20</a>). In short, the coming of the Comforter to the disciples was one and the same as the coming of Jesus to the disciples. The Comforter who was dwelling with the disciples that night was the Spirit in Christ; the Comforter who would be in the disciples (after the resurrection) would be Christ in the Spirit.</p>
<p>On the evening of the resurrection, the Lord Jesus appeared to the disciples and then breathed into them the Holy Spirit. This inbreathing, reminiscent of God’s breathing into Adam the breath of life (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.7">Gn 2:7</a>), became the fulfillment of all that had been promised and anticipated earlier in John’s Gospel. Through this impartation, the disciples became regenerated and indwelt by the Spirit of Jesus Christ. This historical event marked the genesis of the new creation. Jesus could now be realized as the bread of life, the water of life, and the light of life. The believers now possessed his divine, eternal, risen life. From that time forward, Christ as spirit indwelt his believers. Thus, in his first epistle John could say, “And hereby we know that he abides in us, by the Spirit whom he gave to us” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.24">1 Jn 3:24</a>), and again, “Hereby we know that we abide in him and he in us, because he has given us of his Spirit” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.4.13">4:13</a>).</p>
<p>The apostles had quite an adjustment to make after Christ’s resurrection. They had become so accustomed to his physical presence that it was difficult for them to learn how to live by his spiritual, indwelling presence. All through the 40 days after his resurrection, from the time the apostles received the inbreathing of the Spirit, Christ was teaching the disciples to make the transfer. He would physically appear and then disappear intermittently. His appearances were very frequent in the beginning and then they steadily diminished. His aim was to guide the apostles into knowing him in his invisible presence. However, this was so new to them that he had to keep appearing to them in order to strengthen and reassure them. But his real desire was to help them live by faith and not by sight. When he appeared to the disciples as they were all together the second time, with Thomas present, he chided Thomas for his unbelief. Then he prounounced this blessing, “Blessed are those who do not see me and yet believe” (<a href="?bref=John.20.29">Jn 20:29</a>).</p>
<p>The apostle Paul was such a “blessed” one. He did not know Christ in the flesh. He knew only the risen Christ (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.15-16">2 Cor 5:15-16</a>). In this regard, he had an advantage over the early apostles. They had a great adjustment to make, but from the very beginning, Paul knew the risen Christ as Spirit. Paul became the forerunner of all those Christians who have never seen Jesus in the flesh and who have come to experience him in the Spirit. Yes, Paul had seen the risen Lord; he was the last one to do so (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.8">1 Cor 15:8</a>). And from that time onward he realized that Jesus was a glorified man, exalted far above all. Paul wrote much concerning this, but his writings did not leave the far-above-all Jesus far away because this was not what Paul experienced. Any experienced Christian should be able to testify that the Christ in the heavens is also the Christ in the heart.</p>
<p>In his writings, Paul often speaks of the Spirit and Christ synonymously. This is evident in <a href="?bref=Rom.8.9-10">Romans 8:9-10</a>. The terms “Spirit of God,” “Spirit of Christ,” and “Christ” are all used interchangeably. The Spirit of God is the Spirit of Christ, and the Spirit of Christ is Christ. In these verses, it is evident that Paul identified the Spirit with Christ because in Christian experience they are absolutely identical. There is no such thing as an experience of Christ apart from the Spirit. The separation and/or distinction does exist in Trinitarian theology—and for very good reasons—but the separation is nearly nonexistent in actual experience. Several of Paul’s statements are written from the vantage point of experience.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45">1 Corinthians 15:45</a>, Paul says that the risen Jesus became life-giving spirit. Notice the verse does not say Jesus became the Spirit, as if the second person of the Trinity became the third, but that Jesus became spirit in the sense that his mortal existence and form were metamorphosed into a spiritual existence and form. Jesus’ person was not changed through the resurrection, only his form. With this changed spiritual form, Jesus regained the essential state of being he had emptied himself of in becoming a man. Before he became a man, he subsisted in the form of God (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.6">Phil 2:6</a>), which form is Spirit and thereby was united to the Spirit (the third of the Trinity), while still remaining distinct. Thus, when the scripture says that the Lord “became life-giving spirit,” it does not mean that the Son became the Holy Spirit. But it does indicate that Christ, via resurrection, appropriated a new, spiritual form (while still retaining a body—a glorified one) that enabled him to commence a new spiritual existence (see <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.18">1 Pt 3:18</a>).</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.1-18">2 Corinthians 3</a>, Paul explains that the NT ministry is a ministry carried out by the Spirit of the living God (v <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.3">3</a>), who is the Spirit that gives life (v <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.6">6</a>). In fact, the whole NT economy is characterized as “the ministry of the Spirit” (v <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.8">8</a>). At the same time, Paul emphasizes that the function of the NT ministry is to bring God’s people to see and experience the glorious Christ (<a href="?bref=2Cor.3.3,14,16-18">3:3, 14, 16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.4.4-6">4:4-6</a>). It is in this context that Paul boldly declares, “The Lord is the Spirit” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.3.17">3:17</a>). He who turns his heart to the Lord is, in effect, turning his heart to the Spirit. lf the Lord were not the Spirit abiding in the believers, how could they turn their hearts to him? And how could they be transformed into the same image? <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.18">Second Corinthians 3:18</a> says, “But we all, with unveiled face mirroring the glory of the Lord, are being transformed into the same image from glory to glory, just as from the Lord-Spirit.” According to the Greek, the last phrase of this verse could be rendered “the Lord, the Spirit” (see <span class="sc">asv</span>) or “the Lord, who is the Spirit” (see <span class="sc">rsv</span>, <span class="sc">niv</span>) because the expression “the Spirit” is in direct apposition to “the Lord” (i.e., it is a further description of the Lord). Thus, the Lord is the Spirit.</p>
<p>In conclusion, when the Scriptures identify the Spirit with Christ and vice versa, the identification is not equivocation. Christ is not the Holy Spirit. Christ and the Spirit are distinct persons of the Trinity, as is affirmed by the overall teaching of the Word. But the Scriptures do identify Christ and the Spirit in the context of Christian experience. It would be accurate to say that Christians experience Christ through his Spirit, the Spirit of Christ. One cannot know Jesus apart from the Spirit or other than through the Spirit.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Resurrection_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Resurrection</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>