<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Succoth">
  <title>Succoth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SUCCOTH</p>
<p class="list">1. Town in the Jordan Valley listed along with other towns as belonging to the tribe of Gad (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.27">Jos 13:27</a>). It is located in the fertile valley called Ghaur Abu ‘Udeidah, known in the Bible as the valley of Succoth (<a href="?bref=Ps.60.6">Pss 60:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.108.7">108:7</a>); it comprises the central portion of the Jordan Valley on the eastern side, between the Wadi Rejeb and the Jabbok River.</p>
<p class="list-text">The place is mentioned for the first time in the account of Jacob’s meeting with Esau, which occurred just south of Penuel. Jacob went from the meeting to Succoth and built some shelters for his cattle, which is given as the explanation for the name of the settlement (<a href="?bref=Gen.33.17">Gn 33:17</a>)—Succoth means “shelters.”</p>
<p class="list-text">Later, the men of Succoth refused to give food to Gideon and his men when they were pursuing the Midianites (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.5-9">Jgs 8:5-9</a>). Upon his return, Gideon made a point of punishing the elders of Succoth (vv <a href="?bref=Judg.8.13-17">13-17</a>). The form of social organization reflected in this passage has suggested that the population was not Israelite at the time of Gideon’s visitation.</p>
<p class="list-text">Finally, Succoth is mentioned with regard to Solomon’s building projects. The metal casting for the important fixtures and implements of the temple was performed in the area between Succoth and Zarethan (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.46">1 Kgs 7:46</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.4.17">2 Chr 4:17</a>). It is possible that Succoth of the monarchical period was destroyed by Shishak of Egypt.</p>
<p class="list-text">It has been proposed that the place-name occurs in two other passages: as the staging area for David’s forces in the battle with Ammon, when the ark and the army were “living in shelters (<span class="hebrew">sukkoth</span>)” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.11.11">2 Sm 11:11</a>), and as the staging area for Ben-hadad’s troops in his war against Samaria (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.12,16">1 Kgs 20:12, 16</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Town in Egypt mentioned as the first station of the Israelites in their exodus from Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.37">Ex 12:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.13.20">13:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.33.5-6">Nm 33:5-6</a>); it appears between Rameses and Etham. </p>
<p class="list-text">Egyptian sources, texts of the Anastasi collection, refer to a place that is most likely the same as biblical Succoth. An Edomite tribe is recorded as bringing their herds in from the desert to pasture them in the Delta, passing by the strong point at <span class="ital">Tkw</span> [Old Egyptian for Succoth] (Papyrus Anastasi VI, 54). The military garrison there was commanded by a “commander” of (archer) troops, and the fort was named after Pharaoh Mernephta (Papyrus Anastasi, VI, 55).</p>
<p class="list-text">Scholarly opinion usually places Succoth at Tell el-Maskhuta, a site near the mouth of the Wadi Tumeilat. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=KeyPlacesintheExodus_Map_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">map</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>