<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Suffering">
  <title>Suffering</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SUFFERING</p>
<p class="fl">Anything causing pain or distress; calamity. From the biblical viewpoint, affliction began with the entrance of sin into the world. Both mankind and all creation were afflicted with “thorns and thistles,” sin, death, and decay (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.3.16-19">Gn 3:16-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.8.18-21">Rom 8:18-21</a>). Because of sin, misery is a common human experience, and our short life is full of trouble (<a href="?bref=Job.14.1-6">Jb 14:1-6</a>). It is impossible for human beings to avoid natural calamity, physical injury, and interpersonal conflict (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.9">2 Chr 20:9</a>), yet God uses affliction to instruct and discipline his people. This aspect of affliction is graphically portrayed by the oppression during the Israelites’ sojourn in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.4.31">Ex 4:31</a>), by their troubles during the period of the judges (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.26-27">Neh 9:26-27</a>), and by their exile in Babylon (<a href="?bref=Isa.26.16">Is 26:16</a>). In Israel’s distress they cried out to God, who delivered them and led them into obedience (<a href="?bref=Jer.10.18">Jer 10:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.5.15-6.3">Hos 5:15–6:3</a>).</p>
<p>The Bible acknowledges that it is difficult to understand the many afflictions of the righteous (<a href="?bref=Ps.34.19">Pss 34:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.37.39">37:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.138.7">138:7</a>). Even the prophet and “Servant of the Lord” (Messiah) were not spared (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.2-12">Is 53:2-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.15.15">Jer 15:15</a>). Jesus Christ bore the griefs and sorrows of humanity as the culmination of the affliction begun by Adam’s sin (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.4-5">Is 53:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.24">1 Pt 2:24</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus indicated that there would be many trials and sorrows for his followers (<a href="?bref=John.16.33">Jn 16:33</a>). Paul taught that entrance to the kingdom of God comes with many tribulations (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.22">Acts 14:22</a>), which must not shake a Christian’s faith (<a href="?bref=1Thes.3.3">1 Thes 3:3</a>). They are to be understood rather as a finishing up of the remainder of Christ’s suffering for his body, the church (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.10-11">2 Cor 4:10-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.24">Col 1:24</a>). The biblical picture indicates that affliction will grow more intense as “the end” approaches (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.9-14">Mt 24:9-14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.3.13">2 Tm 3:13</a>). The forces of Satan will attack in an effort to deceive and destroy the “elect” (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.24">Mt 24:24</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.9-12">2 Thes 2:9-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.20.7-9">Rv 20:7-9</a>). But when Jesus Christ is revealed from heaven in flaming fire, God will afflict those who have afflicted believers and will bring vengeance upon those who have not obeyed the gospel of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.9">Rom 2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.1.5-10">2 Thes 1:5-10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.7-8">2:7-8</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Persecution_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Persecution</a>; <a href="?item=Tribulation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tribulation</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>