<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Synagogue">
  <title>Synagogue</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SYNAGOGUE</p>
<p class="fl">Transliteration of the Greek word <span class="greek">sunagoge</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “a gathering together.” It is used more than 50 times in the NT, mostly for the religious gathering places of Jewish communities in Palestine and throughout the Dispersion. The word <span class="greek">sunagoge</span> is usually the Greek rendering of Hebrew words in the OT that speak of the assembling or assembly of the people.</p>
<p class="h2" id="OriginsandEarlyHistory">Origins and Early History</p>
<p class="fl">It is unknown just how or when the synagogue as an institution first began. One can imagine the situation in Jerusalem after the destruction of the temple by the Babylonians in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. The people who remained in and around the city who wanted to keep true to their faith would have felt the need to meet for worship, where they would continue to teach the law and the message of the prophets. Some think, therefore, that synagogues may have had their origin in such a situation. Jewish people in the various places of the Dispersion would have been aware of a similar need. Jewish elders met together with Ezekiel in exile in Babylon (<a href="?bref=Ezek.8.1">Ez 8:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.14.1">14:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.1">20:1</a>). Yet there is no positive evidence of actual synagogues at this early stage. In <a href="?bref=Neh.8.1-8">Nehemiah 8:1-8</a> the postexilic community gathered in Jerusalem, and Ezra the scribe brought the law, read it from a wooden pulpit, and gave an interpretation so that the people understood the reading. When Ezra blessed the Lord, the people bowed their heads and worshiped. These were the basic elements of what came to be synagogue worship. The first undisputed evidence of a synagogue comes from Egypt in the third century <span class="era">BC</span>. From the first century <span class="era">BC</span> onward, the evidence of synagogues is abundant.</p>
<p class="h2" id="SynagoguesinNTTimes">Synagogues in NT Times</p>
<p class="fl">The Gospels give the impression of many synagogues existing throughout Palestine. Jesus frequently taught in synagogues (e.g., <a href="?bref=Matt.4.23">Mt 4:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.9.35">9:35</a>), especially during his Galilean ministry, but probably in Judea as well. In <a href="?bref=John.18.20">John 18:20</a> are the words of Jesus in his trial before the high priest: “I have spoken openly to the world; I have always taught in synagogues and in the temple, where all Jews come together” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>The Acts of the Apostles refers to synagogues in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.9">Acts 6:9</a>), Damascus (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.2">9:2</a>), Cyprus (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.5">13:5</a>), the Roman province of Galatia (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.14">13:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.14.1">14:1</a>), Macedonia and Greece (<a href="?bref=Acts.17.1,10,17">17:1, 10, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.4">18:4</a>), and Ephesus in the Roman province of Asia (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.8">19:8</a>). Paul made it his practice to go directly to the synagogue and to preach there as long as he was given freedom to do so.</p>
<p class="h2" id="SynagogueWorship">Synagogue Worship</p>
<p class="fl">The Gospels and the Acts of the Apostles give abundant evidence for the meeting of Jewish people on the Sabbath to worship in the synagogue. People also met for worship on the second and fifth days of the week. Luke provides us with the earliest description of a synagogue service. The Mishnah describes the pattern of the synagogue service: the confession of faith, the Shema (which included reciting <a href="?bref=Deut.6.4-9">Deuteronomy 6:4-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.11.13-21">11:13-21</a>; and <a href="?bref=Num.15.37-41">Numbers 15:37-41</a>); prayer (such as the 18 Benedictions); Scripture reading (the reading of the Law was basic, see <a href="?bref=Acts.15.21">Acts 15:21</a>, and was read according to a three-year cycle; the Prophets were also read, but more at random); interpretation (as the knowledge of biblical Hebrew diminished in Palestine, an Aramaic translation of the Scriptures was presented after the reading in Hebrew, and in the Dispersion, a Greek translation); address (following the reading, anyone suitably qualified might address the people, as Jesus and the apostle Paul often did); and blessing.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="RuinsOfAnAncientSynagogueInCapernaum"/>
<p class="h2" id="JudicialFunctions">Judicial Functions</p>
<p class="fl">Administration of justice was also part of the work of the synagogue. Offenders against the law and those whose actions were held to be contrary to Jewish religion were brought before the elders of the synagogue. They might, under extreme circumstances, excommunicate an offender (see <a href="?bref=John.9.22,34-35">Jn 9:22, 34-35</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.42">12:42</a>) or have him scourged. Jesus warned his disciples to be prepared to face either possibility (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.17">Mt 10:17</a>; <a href="?bref=John.16.2">Jn 16:2</a>). Saul, as persecutor of the Christians, had letters addressed to the synagogues at Damascus, giving authority to arrest Christians and bring them bound to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.2">Acts 9:2</a>). In <a href="?bref=Acts.22.19">Acts 22:19</a> he speaks of causing them to be both beaten and imprisoned. Paul himself received the 39 lashes that were administered in the synagogues (<a href="?bref=2Cor.11.24">2 Cor 11:24</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TeachingoftheLaw">Teaching of the Law</p>
<p class="fl">The reading of the Law was of central significance in synagogue worship. The teaching of the Law to people generally, and especially to children, was intimately associated with the synagogue. Either the synagogue building or a school was used.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Organization">Organization</p>
<p class="fl">The NT refers in particular (e.g., <a href="?bref=Mark.5.22">Mk 5:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.14">Lk 13:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.8">Acts 18:8</a>,17) to two appointments in the synagogue: the “ruler of the synagogue,” who was responsible for order and for selection of the Scripture reader; and an attendant (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.20">Lk 4:20</a>), who brought out and put away the Scripture scrolls and also administered corporal punishment to unruly students. Later on, there was a person appointed as leader of the prayers.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Architecture">Architecture</p>
<p class="fl">In structure the synagogue was modeled after the temple. It was built, when possible, on high ground and often constructed so that the people could sit facing the direction of Jerusalem. There was a portable chest for the scrolls of the Law and the Prophets, and a platform for the reading of the Scriptures and for preaching. Men and women sat apart. The scribes loved the “chief seats” facing the people (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.39">Mk 12:39</a>). Many synagogues had ornamentations of vine leaves, seven-branched candlesticks, the paschal lamb, and the pot of manna. Early synagogues also had a genizah, which was a cellar or attic where worn scrolls were put, because, as they bore the name of God, they were too sacred to be destroyed.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>; <a href="?item=RuleroftheSynagogue_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ruler of the Synagogue</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>