<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SyriaSyrians">
  <title>Syria, Syrians</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SYRIA, SYRIANS</p>
<p class="fl">Terms used in the Septuagint and in some English translations to render the names Aram, Arameans.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HistoryoftheArameans">History of the Arameans</p>
<p class="fl">According to the “table of nations” in <a href="?bref=Gen.10.22-23">Genesis 10:22-23</a>, the Arameans were a Semitic group, descendants of Shem. Another genealogy in <a href="?bref=Gen.22.20-21">Genesis 22:20-21</a> makes Aram a descendant of Nahor. According to <a href="?bref=Amos.9.7">Amos 9:7</a>, the Arameans (Syrians) came from Kir, which is linked with Elam in <a href="?bref=Isa.22.6">Isaiah 22:6</a>. The exile of the Arameans to Kir (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.9">2 Kgs 16:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.1.5">Am 1:5</a>) may suggest they were to go back to their original home. The precise origins of this group of people are, however, lost in antiquity. When they emerged clearly into history, they were settled around the central Euphrates from which they were spread out east, west, and north.</p>
<p>The Arameans were traditionally thought to have been established in upper Mesopotamia in the first part of the second millennium <span class="era">BC</span>. Bethuel and Laban were known as Arameans (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.20">Gn 25:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.28.1-7">28:1-7</a>); the home of Bethuel was in Paddan-aram (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.20">25:20</a>). The prophet Hosea recalls the tradition by noting that Jacob fled to “the field of Aram” (<a href="?bref=Hos.12.12">Hos 12:12</a>) or “Aram-naharaim” (Aram of the two rivers), which was the northern part of Mesopotamia between the Euphrates and Tigris Rivers. In the creedal confession in <a href="?bref=Deut.26.5">Deuteronomy 26:5</a>, the Israelite who brought his firstfruits confessed, “My father [probably Jacob] was a wandering Aramean.”</p>
<p>Probably the best early evidence of an Aramean presence in this area comes from Tiglath-pileser I. In his annals of his fourth year (1112 <span class="era">BC</span>), he speaks of a campaign among the “Akhlama, Arameans” in the Middle Euphrates area and the sacking of six Aramean villages in the Mt Bishri area.</p>
<p>The Arameans of upper Mesopotamia became important in biblical history. They set up a number of separate Aramean states, two of which were especially important for the people of Israel—Aram-zobah in the days of David, and Aram-damascus from the days of Solomon onward.</p>
<p>By about 1100 <span class="era">BC</span>, the Aramean tribes had spread throughout Syria and had expanded into northern Transjordan, where they came into conflict with the Israelites. At his peak Hadadezer, king of Aram-zobah, embraced several vassals, such as Damascus, Maacah, and Tob. He was eventually defeated by King David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.3-4">2 Sm 8:3-4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.10.17-19">10:17-19</a>).</p>
<p>Events in Israel and Judah had some bearing on Damascus. After the death of Solomon, when the formerly united kingdom became divided into Judah and Israel, tension arose between the two small states. War broke out between Baasha of Israel and Asa of Judah in the years 890–880 <span class="era">BC</span>. Asa sought aid from Ben-hadad I of Damascus (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.18">1 Kgs 15:18</a>). Lands in Transjordan changed hands several times. The successors of Omri of Israel—namely Ahab, Ahaziah, Jehoram, Jehu, Jehoahaz, and Jehoash—had many conflicts with Damascus. Ahab fought Ben-hadad and his 32 allies who besieged Samaria (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.1">20:1</a>), but Israel defeated him. A second time Ben-hadad entered Israelite territory and reached Aphek (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.20.26">20:26</a>), but he was again defeated and captured. As a consequence of his defeat and for the price of his release, he was obliged to make bazaars available in Damascus for Israelite trade. After three years of peace between Israel and Damascus, hostilities broke out again and resulted in a battle in the region of Ramoth-gilead in which Ahab was killed (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.29-37">22:29-37</a>). Aram-damascus was eventually defeated by King Jehoash of Israel (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.25">2 Kgs 13:25</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="SyriaaftertheCollapseoftheArameanKingdoms">Syria after the Collapse of the Aramean Kingdoms</p>
<p class="fl">After the collapse of Aram-damascus in 733–732 <span class="era">BC</span>, the political character of the whole region changed. Over the centuries that followed and on into Christian times, the region passed under the control of several great powers and no independent Aramean state survived. When Assyria collapsed in 612–609 <span class="era">BC</span>, the region came under Babylonian control, but only for a comparatively short period. With the rise of Cyrus the Persian, the Syrian region was quickly overrun by Persian armies. Palestine, Asia Minor, and Egypt were absorbed into the Persian Empire at the same time.</p>
<p>The next significant political change that affected the region came with the appearance of Philip of Macedon in 360 <span class="era">BC</span>. His son Alexander the Great (336–323 <span class="era">BC</span>) consolidated Greek power throughout western Asia and as far as the borders of India. On his death in 323 <span class="era">BC</span>, at the age of 33, the control of western Asia passed to Alexander’s generals. General Seleucus I (312–280 <span class="era">BC</span>) controlled the southern half of Asia Minor, the region of Syria, Mesopotamia, and eastward to the borders of India. Syria thus fell under the influence of Hellenist rulers, the Seleucids, who founded a new capital at Antioch.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientSiteOfDuraEuroposInSyria"/>
<p>Further west, Rome was rising to power and cast her eyes eastward. It was General Pompey who overcame Mithridates, the young king of Pontus, and moved to crush the remnants of the kingdom of the Seleucids. The western parts of Syria were formed into a Roman province in 64 <span class="era">BC</span>. Pompey finally moved into Palestine, which came under Roman control in 63 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The Roman province of Syria included Cilicia, a strip of territory in the southeastern corner of Asia Minor. The northern boundary reached to the Euphrates River. The boundary then swung south well to the east of Damascus and then turned west about halfway down the Dead Sea and continued west to the Mediterranean Sea. Syria was bound to the west by the Mediterranean up to the Gulf of Alexandretta, where it turned west. The province of Syria and Cilicia (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.23,41">Acts 15:23, 41</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.21">Gal 1:21</a>) was governed by an imperial legate (<span class="ital">legatis</span>) who commanded a strong force of legionary troops. One such governor, Quirinius, governed Syria at the time of the census of Caesar Augustus; this census brought Joseph and Mary to Bethlehem for the birth of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.2">Lk 2:2</a>).</p>
<p>In the following centuries the population of Damascus was Christianized, and Christianity spread throughout the Roman province of Syria, giving rise to the Old Syrian Church, which remains to this day. It has left a remarkable legacy of Christian literature written in Syriac (Aramaic). The old Aramaic language remained, though a modified alphabet was used to write it.</p>
<p>It was the rise of Islam in the seventh century <span class="era">AD</span> that brought about a considerable weakening of the Syrian church, although it has never been completely destroyed. Scattered communities of Aramaic-speaking people still survive in parts of Syria, and numerous remains of Christian churches have been brought to light as a result of modern archaeological work.</p>
<p class="h2" id="LanguageandCulture">Language and Culture</p>
<p class="fl">Aramaic was the language of the Arameans, of which numerous inscriptions have been discovered. The Aramaic script was adapted for use by the Israelites, and the language became the international language for diplomacy and administration all over the Near East. It was the <span class="ital">lingua franca</span> of the Persian period from Egypt to India and was widely spoken in Palestine in Jesus’ day. The words “<span class="ital">talitha cumi</span>” (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.41">Mk 5:41</a>) and “<span class="ital">marana tha</span>” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.22">1 Cor 16:22</a>) are Aramaic.</p>
<p>Excavations in many sites have provided a good idea of the Aramean architecture, sculpture, pottery, and other arts. The religion of the Arameans was polytheistic. The people adopted many foreign deities as well. The principal Aramean deity was the ancient west Semitic storm god Hadad. In the days of Ahaz of Judah, the Damascus cult was forced on the people of Jerusalem when an altar based on a Damascus model was placed in the temple (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.10-13">2 Kgs 16:10-13</a>). Arameans exiled to Samaria by the Assyrian ruler Sargon brought foreign Aramean cults with them (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.24-34">17:24-34</a>).</p>
<p>Through the centuries that followed the disappearance of the Aramean states, the Aramaic language has survived. The Christian form of Aramaic, Syriac, has left behind a vast legacy of literature, histories, theologies, commentaries, treatises, and translations, which have been carefully preserved in ancient monastic libraries, particularly in northern Syria, northern Iraq, and southern Turkey.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Aramaic_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Aramaic</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="ABedouinInSyria"/>
</body>
</item>