<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HaranPlace">
  <title>Haran (Place)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HARAN (P<span class="lc">lace</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">City of northern Mesopotamia, first mentioned in <a href="?bref=Gen.11.31">Genesis 11:31</a> as the destination of Terah, Abraham’s father, in migrating from Ur of the Chaldees, and his home until his death. At age 75, Abraham was commanded by God to move to a land that God had for him (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.1-4">Gn 12:1-4</a>). There were relatives who remained in Haran, however, to whom Jacob, Abraham’s grandson, fled in fear of Esau (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.42-43">27:42-43</a>). Jacob stayed in Haran many years while serving his Uncle Laban and acquiring Leah and Rachel as wives, as well as many sheep and goats, servants, camels, and donkeys (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.43">30:43</a>).</p>
<p>This “city of Nahor” (<a href="?bref=Gen.11.27-29">Gn 11:27-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.24.10">24:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.27.43">27:43</a>) was established in the third millennium <span class="era">BC</span>, and its location on a branch of the Euphrates soon made it an important commercial center. Perhaps the ancient trade route that linked Damascus, Nineveh, and Carchemish passed by Haran. Ezekiel mentions trade between Haran and Tyre (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.23">Ez 27:23</a>). Haran was an Aramean city and was famous for its worship of the lunar Sin and Nikkal. This system was an offspring of the cult found in Sumerian Ur. Sin and his consort Nikkal were revered not only here but throughout Canaan and even in Egypt. The cult persisted past NT times, its temple finally being destroyed by Mongols in the 13th century <span class="era">AD</span>. It is little wonder that God commanded Abraham to leave this seat of idolatry. Modern Harran preserves the ancient cuneiform spelling of the name (cf. <span class="sc">kjv</span> “Charran,” <a href="?bref=Acts.7.2,4">Acts 7:2, 4</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>