<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HebrewsLettertothe">
  <title>Hebrews, Letter to the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HEBREWS, Letter to the</p>
<p class="fl">One of the most profound and enigmatic books in the NT. The identity of its author, the time of its writing, and the people and place to which it was sent are all shrouded in mystery. Yet, in spite of the uncertainty, Hebrews remains one of the most timely and relevant books in the Bible. Some 300 years ago John Owen, the English Puritan, appropriately remarked: “No doubt the Epistle next in importance to Romans is this to the Hebrews.” The letter is both doctrinal and practical, theological and pastoral. In short, it builds a compelling case for the superiority of Christianity. Hebrews also reflects the impassioned concern of a pastor’s heart. Those who have experienced God’s ultimate work of grace in Christ are urged to hold fast to God’s final word of revelation in his Son.</p>
<p>Unlike most other NT epistles, Hebrews does not begin like a letter. There is no introductory salutation, the writer is not identified, and no mention is made of those to whom the document is addressed. The author characterizes the work as a “word of exhortation” (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.22">13:22</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), which suggests a sermon or oral homily (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.13.15">Acts 13:15</a>). Nonetheless, its conclusion is that of a conventional letter (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.22-25">Heb 13:22-25</a>). Some have detected a gradual transition in the document from an essay to a more specifically epistolary form (cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.2.1">2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.1">4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.13.22-25">13:22-25</a>). The evidence thus suggests that the author may have cast the original homiletic “word of exhortation” into letter form when the need to communicate in writing with his Christian friends became urgent.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Date">Date</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#OriginandDestination">Origin and Destination</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Purpose">Purpose</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">Who wrote the book is not directly stated in the letter. Since the late second century, various authorities have linked the document with the apostle Paul. Clement of Alexandria (d. 220) theorized that Paul wrote the letter in Hebrew for Jews and that Luke translated it into Greek. However, this suggestion has not been widely received by modern scholars. Clement’s pupil Origen (d. 254) stated more generally that the thoughts of the letter are Pauline but that the style is unlike that of the known writings of the apostle. Other early authorities, such as Jerome (d. 419) and Augustine (d. 430), persuaded that canonicity demanded apostolic authorship, likewise affirmed that Paul was the author.</p>
<p>Yet a number of factors argue against the Pauline authorship of Hebrews. The anonymity of the letter is contrary to the consistent pattern of Paul’s introduction in the opening salutation of his letters. Moreover, <a href="?bref=Heb.2.3">Hebrews 2:3</a> indicates the writer was discipled by eyewitnesses of the Lord. Yet Paul insists that his knowledge of Christ was gained from a firsthand encounter with the risen Christ (cf. <a href="?bref=Gal.1.12">Gal 1:12</a>). F. F. Bruce evaluates the authorship of Hebrews as follows: “We may say with certainty that the thought of the epistle is not Paul’s, the language is not Paul’s, and the technique of OT quotations is not Paul’s.”</p>
<p>Early Christian tradition suggests that Barnabas may have written Hebrews. According to Tertullian (d. 220), many early authorities believed that Barnabas was responsible for the letter. <a href="?bref=Acts.4.36">Acts 4:36</a> (<span class="sc">asv</span>) speaks of him as a “son of exhortation” (cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.13.22">Heb 13:22</a>). Furthermore, as a Levite, Barnabas would have been familiar with the Jewish sacrificial ritual so prominent in the letter.</p>
<p>Luther was the first to suggest that Hebrews may have been penned by Apollos, “an excellent man of learning, who had been a disciple of the apostles and learned much from them, and who was very well versed in Scripture.” As a native of Alexandria (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.24">Acts 18:24</a>), Apollos would have been familiar with the typological interpretation evident in Hebrews. Clearly Apollos was the sort of man who was qualified to write Hebrews.</p>
<p>Other names have been suggested as possible authors. Calvin surmised that either Luke or Clement of Rome was responsible for the letter. It is noted that the Greek of Hebrews resembles the language and style of the third Gospel and Acts. Others theorize that Hebrews may have been written by Silas, a Jewish Christian from Jerusalem who would have been thoroughly familiar with the Levitical ritual. Silas is described as one of “the church leaders” (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.22">Acts 15:22</a>). He was a coworker with Paul in the gentile mission, and apparently was known in Rome as well as in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=1Pet.5.12-13">1 Pt 5:12-13</a>).</p>
<p>In conclusion, it is probable that the author of Hebrews was a second-generation Jewish Christian, a master of classical Greek whose Bible was the Septuagint, conversant with first-century Alexandrian philosophy, and a creative apologist for the Christian faith. As to the identity of that author, we can affirm no more than Origen in the third century: “But as to who actually wrote the Letter, God alone knows.”</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientPapyrusManuscriptOfTheBookOfHebrews"/>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">The very early title of the letter, “To Hebrews,” suggests that the book concerns Jewish Christians living in the Dispersion. The letter itself offers a few hints of the historical circumstances surrounding its composition. Not long after becoming Christians, the readers of the letter were exposed to severe persecution (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.32-36">Heb 10:32-36</a>). During their trial, the new believers endured imprisonment, confiscation of personal property, and public ridicule. Yet the persecution had not been fatal; they had not yet been called upon to lay down their lives in martyrdom (<a href="?bref=Heb.12.4">12:4</a>). Amid the excitement of their newfound faith in Christ, they had demonstrated practical concern and love by ministering to fellow believers in need (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.10">6:10</a>) and comforting others who had been harassed for their faith (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.34">10:34</a>).</p>
<p>But since the time of those earlier trials, the readers had made little progress in Christian maturity (<a href="?bref=Heb.5.11-13">5:11-13</a>). Moreover, in the face of a new wave of persecution, and despondent over an apparent delay in the Lord’s coming, the believers had begun to waver and abandon hope. Indeed, they threatened to renounce Jesus Christ and to revert back to the security of the Jewish religion that enjoyed the protection of Roman law.</p>
<p>Thus we read that because of the strange, new teachings of certain Judaizers who sought to draw them back to their former religion (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.9">13:9</a>), the wavering believers had neglected to assemble together (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.25">10:25</a>) and had lost confidence in their spiritual leaders (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.17">13:17</a>). Faced with the possibility that these Jewish Christians might abandon their faith altogether, the writer sternly warns them of the tragic consequences of renouncing the Son (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.4-6">6:4-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.26-31">10:26-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.13.12-19">13:12-19</a>) and urges them to renew their commitment to Christ, God’s foremost and final revelation.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Date">Date</p>
<p class="fl">Lacking firm information as to the author and recipients of the letter, no certainty exists as to the date of the writing. We have noted that the author of Hebrews, and probably his readers as well, had been discipled by those who were personally acquainted with Jesus (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.3">2:3</a>). Further evidence in the letter suggests that Paul probably was not alive. Timothy, Paul’s younger associate, was still living (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.23">13:23</a>).</p>
<p>The absence of any mention in Hebrews of the destruction of the Jerusalem temple is significant for dating the letter. In terms of his argument that the old covenant had passed away and the legal priesthood had been superseded, the writer would scarcely have omitted mention of the temple’s destruction had he written the letter later than <span class="era">AD</span> 70. <a href="?bref=Heb.9.6-10">Hebrews 9:6-10</a> and <a href="?bref=Heb.10.1-4,11-14">10:1-4, 11-14</a> plainly suggest that the Jewish sacrifices were still being offered. Hence, it may be supposed with some degree of certainty that the letter was written prior to <span class="era">AD</span> 70. If it was written after Paul’s death, that would put it after <span class="era">AD</span> 67, the traditional date of his execution. Thus, Hebrews may have been written in the period <span class="era">AD</span> 67–70.</p>
<p class="h2" id="OriginandDestination">Origin and Destination</p>
<p class="fl">The place from which Hebrews was written is also uncertain. Some manuscripts of the letter bear the subscription “written from Rome” or “written from Italy.” Such notations are educated deductions drawn from the statement “The Christians from Italy send you their greetings” (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.24">13:24</a>). Most probably this indicates that the writer is extending greetings to a church in Italy on behalf of Italian Christians associated with him in another land, possibly Asia. Nevertheless, we cannot locate the point of origin with any certainty.</p>
<p>It has been suggested that the letter was written to a group of Jewish converts to Christianity. Yet the precise community to which it was sent is a matter of debate. Opinions vary from Judea to Spain. Tradition has it that Hebrews was directed to Jewish Christians living in Palestine. But against a Palestinian destination it may be argued: (1) the readers had had no personal contact with Jesus (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.3">2:3</a>), an unlikely event for mid-first-century residents of Palestine; (2) the statement in <a href="?bref=Heb.12.4">12:4</a> that his readers had not yet given their lives could hardly be said of Palestinian Christians of the period; (3) the generosity of the believers (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.34">10:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.13.16">13:16</a>) was inconsistent with the poverty of the Jerusalem church; and (4) the general tone of the letter is Hellenistic rather than rabbinical.</p>
<p>Other proposals for the destination of Hebrews include (1) Caesarea, on the supposition of Lukan authorship; (2) Syrian Antioch or Cyprus, assuming Barnabas wrote the letter; (3) Ephesus, in the light of the conversion of many Jews during Paul’s ministry in that city; (4) Colosse, noting certain similarities between the Colossian heresy and the false beliefs of the “Hebrews”; and (5) Alexandria, because of the apparent influence of the philosopher Philo Judaeus in the letter.</p>
<p>The thesis that Hebrews was directed to a group of Jewish Christians in Rome has found favor with a number of scholars. Arguments in support of a Roman destination include the following facts: (1) The letter was first known in Rome no later than <span class="era">AD</span> 96. (2) <a href="?bref=Rom.11.13,18">Romans 11:13, 18</a> suggests that the church at Rome consisted of a Jewish-Christian minority. (3) References to persecution and suffering endured by the readers (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.32-33">Heb 10:32-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.12.4">12:4</a>) are consistent with known repressive measures exacted by the Roman authorities. (4) There is a good possibility that saints who “come from Italy” would convey greetings to their brethren in Rome. (5) The Jewish community in Rome preserved certain features of nonconformist or sectarian Judaism that would explain several notable similarities between the theology and praxis of the Qumran community and that expressed in Hebrews.</p>
<p>It is likely that the letter was addressed to a small subgroup within a local church. The exhortation in <a href="?bref=Heb.5.12">5:12</a> (<span class="sc">rsv</span>)—“by this time you ought to be teachers”—hardly would have been relevant to an entire congregation. <a href="?bref=Heb.13.7,24">Hebrews 13:7, 24</a> lends further support to the theory that the letter was sent to a small group, perhaps to a “house church” within a larger assembly.</p>
<p>Tentatively, one might conclude that the addressees were converts from Judaism who dwelt in the Dispersion. Hence they were familiar with OT Judaism and were acquainted with the religious philosophy of the Greek world. Possibly the readers comprised a house fellowship that tended to disassociate itself from the parent group (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.25">10:25</a>). The existence of such house churches in Rome is confirmed by <a href="?bref=Rom.16.5,14-15">Romans 16:5, 14-15</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Purpose">Purpose</p>
<p class="fl">In response to the threat that his Jewish-Christian friends might renounce Christianity and revert to Judaism, the writer by a “word of exhortation” (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.22">13:22</a>) communicated to them the finality of the Christian revelation. He sought also to inform his despondent, vacillating readers that Christ, the object of God’s final revelation, is vastly superior to the greatest of Judaism’s heroes. The author, in addition, affirmed the heavenly and eternal character of the salvation secured by Christ. Whereas the legal sacrificial system was powerless to effect the remission of sin, Christ the eternal High Priest “is able, once and forever, to save everyone who comes to God through him” (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.25">7:25</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>In short, the writer commended to his readers the need for patient endurance amid the persecution and sufferings to which the heirs of eternal salvation are inevitably exposed. Just as Jesus, the forerunner of our faith, suffered and patiently endured in anticipation of eternal reward, so ought harassed, oppressed believers “take a new grip with your tired hands and stand firm on your shaky legs” (<a href="?bref=Heb.12.12">12:12</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>) in anticipation of their reception in that eternal “kingdom that cannot be destroyed” (<a href="?bref=Heb.12.28">12:28</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>The author’s final purpose for writing was to proclaim the fearful judgment that awaits those who repudiate Jesus Christ. Since “our God is a consuming fire” (<a href="?bref=Heb.12.29">12:29</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>), “what makes us think that we can escape if we are indifferent to this great salvation” (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.3">2:3</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>)?</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="fl">Next to Romans, Hebrews is the most doctrinal book in the NT. The writer develops a series of weighty arguments to demonstrate the superiority of the gospel of Christ to the religion of Judaism. Since Jesus is final both as to his person and his work, Christianity is the ultimate and normative faith. The book’s particularism runs counter to the spirit of the modern world.</p>
<p class="h3">The Superiority of the Son to Former Revelation (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.1-4">1:1-4</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The writer acknowledges that God revealed himself to the prophets of old in many ways—through dreams, visions, audible speech, and mighty acts. But “in these last days” (the advent of the end times, cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.9.26">9:26</a>) God spoke finally and definitively through his own Son (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.2">1:2</a>). Central to the argument is the fact that in one way or another the prophets received an eternal word from God. Yet given the intimate relation of the Son to the Father, God’s latest revelation has come forth from the very depths of his own being.</p>
<p>Identification of the Son as the pinnacle of divine revelation leads to a concise but profound statement of Christ’s person and his cosmic work. The Son reflects the glory of God in that the sum of the divine attributes brilliantly shine through his person. Moreover, he bears the very image and stamp of God’s nature (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.3">1:3</a>), as the wax bears the impress of the seal. Jesus as God’s final word of revelation is truly the divine and eternal Son of God. Christ’s excellence is further displayed in the fact that he is the mighty agent through whom the universe was created (v <a href="?bref=Heb.1.2">2</a>) and by whom the cosmic order is sustained (v <a href="?bref=Heb.1.3">3</a>). In the moral realm he has wrought the purification of sins and now sits enthroned on God’s right hand (cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.8.1">8:1</a>). God’s pleasure toward the Son is seen in that he has appointed Christ heir and head of all (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.2">1:2</a>). His name is surpassed by none save God the Father (v <a href="?bref=Heb.1.4">4</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Superiority of the Son to Angels (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.5-2.18">1:5–2:18</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Angels enjoyed an exalted status in biblical and postbiblical Judaism. Traditionally the Jews believed that angels praised God upon his throne, mediated God’s revelation to men, attended to God’s will, and gave succor to the people of God. Angels were far superior to men in power and knowledge. According to the Jewish Apocrypha, angels ruled the stars and were responsible for the rise and fall of civilizations. In Qumran thought, angelic beings would engage in a final cosmic struggle with Belial and the forces of evil at the end of the age.</p>
<p>Against this background the writer of Hebrews argues that the Son is vastly superior to the angels. To prove his point, the author assembles a string of well-known OT texts and applies them directly to the Son. God never said of any angel, “Today I have become your Father” (<a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Ps 2:7</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Yet just such a claim was made on behalf of the Son (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.5">Heb 1:5</a>). When the Son incarnated himself in the world, he received the obedient worship of angels (v <a href="?bref=Heb.1.6">6</a>). His is the sovereignty and the eternality and the majesty at God’s right hand (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.1.8,11-12">8, 11-12</a>). By contrast, angels are “only servants” (v <a href="?bref=Heb.1.14">14</a>) that rank below the Son in dignity and might.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Heb.2.1-4">Hebrews 2:1-4</a> the writer parenthetically warns his wavering congregation of the danger of drifting away from the truth of God. If disobedience to the law mediated by angels resulted in stern punishment, how much more severe would be God’s judgment on those who trampled under foot the revelation delivered by the Son? If God’s saving grace in Christ is neglected, retribution will surely follow (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.3">2:3</a>).</p>
<p>The mention of angels turns the writer’s mind to Jesus’ humiliation and exaltation (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.5-18">2:5-18</a>). <a href="?bref=Ps.8.1-9">Psalm 8</a>, a song about the smallness and yet the significance of man, is applied to the experience of Jesus. In assuming human flesh and blood, Jesus was made “for a little while . . . lower than the angels” (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.7">Heb 2:7</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). But subsequent to the completion of his earthly work, he was elevated above the angels and crowned with the glory and honor of heaven (v <a href="?bref=Heb.2.9">9</a>). The theological implications of Christ’s descent and ascent are carefully spelled out: Christ descended to earth (1) to bring many children to glory (v <a href="?bref=Heb.2.10">10</a>), (2) to destroy the devil (v <a href="?bref=Heb.2.14">14</a>), (3) to deliver his people from the bondage of death (v <a href="?bref=Heb.2.15">15</a>), and (4) to make an offering on the cross for the sins of the people (v <a href="?bref=Heb.2.17">17</a>). He ascended to heaven (1) to intercede on our behalf as a faithful High Priest (v <a href="?bref=Heb.2.17">17</a>), and (2) to succor those who are sorely tempted (v <a href="?bref=Heb.2.18">18</a>). The perfect summary of Christ’s person and work is given in <a href="?bref=Heb.2.9">Hebrews 2:9</a>: “What we do see is Jesus, who ‘for a little while was made lower than the angels’ and now is ‘crowned with glory and honor’ because he suffered death for us. Yes, by God’s grace, Jesus tasted death for everyone in all the world” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Superiority of the Son to Moses and Joshua (<a href="?bref=Heb.3.1-4.13">3:1–4:13</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Jewish Christians contemplating reversion to Judaism surely believed that Moses was one of the greatest figures in Israel’s history. So esteemed was the one who led Israel out of Egypt through the wilderness and who gave them the Law that there was no one in Israel’s history so honored as Moses. Yet the author of Hebrews argues that Moses, though faithful to his calling, was but a servant in the house of God. Jesus, by contrast, was not a servant but a Son; he was not a mere dweller in the house but the very builder of the structure. Jesus, therefore, far transcends the revered figure of Moses.</p>
<p>Practical implications are drawn from Jesus’ superiority to Moses. From <a href="?bref=Ps.95.7-11">Psalm 95:7-11</a> the writer rehearses the tragic experience of Israel under Moses during the desert wanderings (<a href="?bref=Heb.3.7-19">Heb 3:7-19</a>). Throughout the 40-year wilderness experience the people hardened their hearts and rebelled against God. In turn God was provoked by their stubbornness and swore that those who sinned would never enter the rest he was going to provide (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.3.10-11,18">10-11, 18</a>). The writer thus argues that if disobedience to God under Moses had serious consequences, forsaking Christ will be much more perilous. Hence the wavering Christians are urged to watch lest due to an evil, unbelieving heart they should fall away from the living God (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.12">12</a>). Nothing short of steadfast persistence will lead to the attainment of the heavenly goal (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.14">14</a>).</p>
<p>Joshua, likewise, was regarded as a great leader of Israel. Yet because of disobedience, the people under Joshua’s leadership failed to enter the rest that God had planned. That rest spoken of corresponds to the Sabbath rest of God (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.3-4">4:3-4</a>), and is a concept closely related to salvation. It is a spiritual reality that is achieved by turning from our own empty works and trusting in the finished work of Christ (v <a href="?bref=Heb.4.10">10</a>). The author reminds the readers that “there is a special rest [a Sabbath rest] still waiting for the people of God” (v <a href="?bref=Heb.4.9">9</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>), one that only Christ can provide. Christians not only benefit from this Sabbath rest in the present age but anticipate its full realization in the age to come. One of the chief means of ensuring entry into the Sabbath rest of salvation is the Word of God (v <a href="?bref=Heb.4.12">12</a>). The living and powerful Word penetrates the innermost depths of the soul, reveals our impoverished condition, and strengthens the trusting heart.</p>
<p class="h3">The Superiority of the Priesthood of the Son (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.14-7.28">4:14–7:28</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Almost half of Hebrews is devoted to the priesthood of Jesus Christ. The writer goes to great lengths to demonstrate that the revered Aaronic priestly system has been superseded by the High Priest “in the line of Melchizedek” (<a href="?bref=Heb.5.6">5:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.6.20">6:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.11">7:11</a>). This central theme had been anticipated earlier when Christ was referred to as “our merciful and faithful High Priest before God” who has made atonement for sins (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.17">2:17</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Hebrews makes the claim that Jesus’ priesthood is the ultimate ground of the believers’ confidence (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.14-16">4:14-16</a>). On three counts Jesus surpasses the old legal priestly order. First, he is an <span class="ital">exalted</span> high priest (v <a href="?bref=Heb.4.14">14</a>). The Jewish high priest climbed the mount to enter the temple sanctuary. But Jesus, our great high priest, has ascended to heaven itself and entered the sanctuary on high. He ministers in no earthly tabernacle but in the very presence of God. Second, Jesus is an <span class="ital">empathetic</span> high priest (v <a href="?bref=Heb.4.15">15</a>a). Fully God and fully man, Jesus suffers along with his people in their trials and afflictions. From heaven’s perspective he knows fully what his people are called upon to endure. He “feels” our hurts, and he does so perfectly. Finally, Jesus is a <span class="ital">sinless</span> high priest (v <a href="?bref=Heb.4.15">15</a>b). Day in and day out (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.27">7:27</a>), year in and year out, the Levitical priests were required to bring sacrifices for their own sins. Yet Jesus had no sin that needed cleansing, for “he is holy and blameless, unstained by sin” (v <a href="?bref=Heb.7.26">26</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). In view of Jesus’ priestly perfections, sorely tempted Christians are urged to come to the throne of grace to receive mercy and find grace to help in time of need (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.16">4:16</a>).</p>
<p>For those not convinced that Jesus was indeed a legitimate priest, two prerequisites for priesthood are detailed. First, if the high priest is to represent humanity before God, he must be taken from among men (<a href="?bref=Heb.5.1-2">5:1-2</a>). And second, he must be called by God to high priestly office, as was Aaron (v <a href="?bref=Heb.5.4">4</a>). Christ has fully satisfied these qualifications. From <a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Psalms 2:7</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.110.4">110:4</a> it is shown that Jesus did not take this office upon himself but was appointed by God (<a href="?bref=Heb.5.5-6">Heb 5:5-6</a>). Moreover, from the obedience that he had to learn (v <a href="?bref=Heb.5.8">8</a>) and from the agony of the Gethsemane experience (v <a href="?bref=Heb.5.7">7</a>) it is clear that Jesus was in every way a man. Nevertheless, Hebrews makes it perfectly clear that Jesus was not a priest after the order of Aaron but a high priest in the line of Melchizedek (v <a href="?bref=Heb.5.10">10</a>).</p>
<p>After introducing the theme of Christ as a Melchizedekian high priest, the writer recalls that his readers were not ready for such advanced teaching. Although not new converts (<a href="?bref=Heb.5.12">5:12</a>), his friends had remained spiritually immature and sluggish. Hence the writer issues the challenge to press on to Christian maturity, to be ready for the solid food of advanced teaching.</p>
<p>In his digression the writer warns not only against spiritual immaturity but also against “apostasy.” The question now arises whether the author’s apostasy teaching in <a href="?bref=Heb.6.4-8">Hebrews 6:4-8</a> and <a href="?bref=Heb.10.26-31">10:26-31</a> contradicts the NT doctrine of the perseverance of the saints. Undoubtedly it does not. Some authorities hold that those addressed were not true Christians, hence the issue is not one of apostasy. It is possible, like Judas Iscariot or Simon Magus (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.9-24">Acts 8:9-24</a>), to possess considerable knowledge of the gospel and fall short of personal commitment. But the writer makes it quite clear that in the case of his addressees he is persuaded otherwise (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.9">Heb 6:9</a>). The most reasonable view is that in these two hortatory passages the writer advances a hypothetical argument warning his friends of the utter seriousness of reverting back to Judaism. That is, if a falling away were to occur, renewal would be impossible unless Christ were to die a second time. The writer sums up the point of these difficult passages with the words “It is a terrible thing to fall into the hands of the living God” (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.31">10:31</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Nevertheless, followers of Christ may confidently lay hold of God’s promises, confirmed by solemn oath, to see them through their trials (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.13-18">6:13-18</a>). God may be trusted to hold the believer fast.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Heb.7.1-28">Hebrews 7</a> contains an intricate argument for the superiority of Christ’s priesthood over the old legal order. Melchizedek, the ancient priest-king of Salem (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.18-20">Gn 14:18-20</a>), is regarded as a primordial type of Christ. He is “king of righteousness” and “king of peace” (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.2">Heb 7:2</a>). The solemn priest from Salem has figuratively what Christ possesses actually: neither mother nor father, neither beginning nor end of life (v <a href="?bref=Heb.7.3">3</a>). Melchizedek is shown to be superior to Abraham on three counts: (1) Melchizedek blessed the patriarch (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.7.1,7">1, 7</a>); (2) he accepted tithes from Abraham (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.7.2-6">2-6</a>); and (3) Melchizedek lives on since the OT nowhere mentions his death (v <a href="?bref=Heb.7.8">8</a>). It follows that since Levi was in the loins of Abraham as seed (v <a href="?bref=Heb.7.10">10</a>), Melchizedek is superior to the Levitical priests. And inasmuch as Christ is a priest in the likeness of Melchizedek (v <a href="?bref=Heb.7.15">15</a>), it follows that the Son of God is more excellent than the old legal priesthood.</p>
<p>The result is that the old Levitical priesthood has been superseded by the priesthood of Christ. The demise of the old order was inevitable, for its repetitive animal sacrifices could never effect spiritual perfection (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.11">7:11</a>). It was a system characterized by weakness and uselessness (v <a href="?bref=Heb.7.18">18</a>). By contrast, Christ’s priesthood is indestructible, eternal, uninterrupted, efficacious, final, and perfect (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.7.16,21,24-27">16, 21, 24-27</a>). Forgiveness and reconciliation is possible only through Christ, our great High Priest.</p>
<p class="h3">The Superiority of the Priestly Work of the Son (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.1-10.39">8:1–10:39</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Since Christ’s priestly office far excels the old order, it follows that his priestly ministration is superior to all that has gone before. The theme of Christ as high priest in a better sanctuary is introduced (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.1-5">8:1-5</a>). The writer utilizes Plato’s distinction between the ideal form in heaven and the imperfect copy on earth to argue that the Levitical sanctuary and sacrifices are mere shadows of the heavenly realities: (1) Christ ministers in the true tent that is the heavenly sanctuary (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.8.2,5">2, 5</a>); (2) he discharges his high priestly service in the very presence of the Father, which results in a far more effective ministry (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.8.1,6">1, 6</a>); and (3) his oblation on the cross was the ultimate sacrifice (v <a href="?bref=Heb.8.3">3</a>). How unreasonable it is that his Christian readers should go back to the old Jewish priestly system!</p>
<p>Christ is the minister of a new and better covenant (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.6-13">8:6-13</a>). The old covenant established by God with the nation’s fathers was not to be despised; nevertheless, it had become ineffectual and obsolete (v <a href="?bref=Heb.8.13">13</a>). Indeed, the prophet Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.31-34">Jer 31:31-34</a>) foresaw the new covenant that God would inaugurate with his people. This new covenant sealed by Christ involves (1) the immediate work of the Holy Spirit on the mind and heart (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.10">Heb 8:10</a>); (2) a personal and intimate knowledge of God (v <a href="?bref=Heb.8.11">11</a>); and (3) the full absolution of sins (v <a href="?bref=Heb.8.12">12</a>). This new and better covenant has been established on the work of Christ, the great High Priest.</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Heb.9.1-28">9</a> gives a detailed comparison of the efficacy of priestly service under the old and new covenants. The Levitical priests ministered in a material sanctuary on earth (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.9.1-5">1-5</a>). Features of the tabernacle and its furnishings are described to highlight their obsolescence. More important, however, is the character of the sacrificial ritual conducted in the earthly sanctuary. The Jewish priests in their daily service were not permitted to enter the Holy of Holies, which contained the ark of the covenant and the mercy seat—the place of propitiation of sins (v <a href="?bref=Heb.9.6">6</a>). The high priest alone could enter the Holy of Holies, and then but once a year on the Day of Atonement, and only after sacrificing for his own sins (v <a href="?bref=Heb.9.7">7</a>). The inaccessibility of the Holy of Holies signified that access to the presence of God had not been opened. The presence of the curtain symbolized that the people had no way to the throne of God, the priests had no way, and the high priest had a limited way and only once a year. Moreover, the sacrifices brought by the Jewish priests could not purify the conscience but merely dealt with external ritual cleansing (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.9.9-10">9-10</a>). A truly effectual sacrifice must await “the time of reformation” (v <a href="?bref=Heb.9.10">10</a>).</p>
<p>Christ’s priestly ministration is shown to be far more efficacious. First, the Christian’s High Priest has brought a better sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.11-14">9:11-14</a>), and here we arrive at the heart of the message of Hebrews. Employing the imagery of the tabernacle, the author demonstrates that Christ our High Priest has accomplished what the Jewish priests failed to do. He entered the heavenly Holy of Holies, not repeatedly, but <span class="ital">once</span> for all, thereby effecting a completed redemption (v <a href="?bref=Heb.9.12">12</a>). Christ brought to the altar, not the blood of bulls and goats, but his own life’s blood. The Lord did not merely lay down a material body, but he presented himself to God through the eternal Spirit (v <a href="?bref=Heb.9.14">14</a>). Christ’s better sacrifice thus goes beyond cleansing of the flesh to the purification of the defiled conscience.</p>
<p>Second, Christ through his death has instituted a better covenant (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.15-23">9:15-23</a>). The teaching of <a href="?bref=Heb.8.6-13">Hebrews 8:6-13</a> is developed further. The old covenant was sealed with the blood of calves and goats (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.19">9:19</a>). But the new covenant was ratified with the blood of Christ, God’s own Son. The new covenant thus could accomplish what the old covenant merely foreshadowed—forgiveness and cleansing of sins (v <a href="?bref=Heb.9.22">22</a>).</p>
<p>Third, Christ ministers in a better tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.24-28">9:24-28</a>). Our Lord entered, not into a merely earthly sanctuary, but into the holy place of heaven, there to represent us (v <a href="?bref=Heb.9.24">24</a>). Access to the throne is not limited to one day per year, for he is continually in the presence of the Father. Nor is it necessary that repeated sacrifices be made. Christ’s single sacrifice on the cross has conquered sin once and for all (v <a href="?bref=Heb.9.26">26</a>). In sum, as regards the sanctuary, the covenant, and the sacrifices, the Christian’s High Priest is vastly superior to the old Jewish order.</p>
<p>In order to drive home these crucial points, the writer in chapter <a href="?bref=Heb.10.1-39">10</a> expands on the theme of the absolute finality of Christ’s high priestly work. The earlier argument concerning the futile character of the Levitical sacrifices (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.6-14">9:6-14</a>) is repeated for emphasis (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.1-4">10:1-4</a>). The Mosaic ceremonial legislation called for repetitive sacrifices, which could never perfect the worshiper (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.1">1</a>). Instead of purifying one’s life, they served only as a yearly reminder of sin (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.3">3</a>) until Christ should come.</p>
<p>The writer discovers in <a href="?bref=Ps.40.6-8">Psalm 40:6-8</a> a prediction that the eternal Christ would become man for the purpose of offering himself as the ultimate sacrifice for sin (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.5-10">Heb 10:5-10</a>). Once again the sanctifying power of Christ’s single self-oblation is emphasized (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.10">10</a>). The vivid contrast is again drawn between the ineffective ministry of the Jewish priests who stand during the daily ritual (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.11">11</a>), and the effectual single sacrifice of Christ, who is now seated at the right hand of God (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.12">12</a>). Since Jesus “by that one offering . . . perfected forever all those whom he is making holy” (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.14">14</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>), nothing can be added to what the seated Sovereign has accomplished (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.18">18</a>).</p>
<p>In view of the manifest superiority of Christ’s priestly office and work, the struggling Christians are exhorted to appropriate the means of grace at their disposal (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.19-39">10:19-39</a>). In the midst of trials and persecution they should remember that Christ has effectively opened the way to God (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.10.19-20">19-20</a>). They are summoned to come to God in faith with hearts cleansed by Christ’s sacrifice (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.22">22</a>). Those tempted to revert to legal religion should hold fast and support one another in love (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.10.23-24">23-24</a>). The means of grace afforded by corporate worship should not be neglected (v <a href="?bref=Heb.10.25">25</a>). In short, the wavering Jewish Christians are summoned to renewed endurance and fidelity to their Lord (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.10.26-31">26-31</a>). What God has promised to his people he will surely make good.</p>
<p class="h3">The Superiority of the Life of Faith (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.1-12.29">11:1–12:29</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The discussion of faith and endurance as the solution to despondency (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.36-38">10:36-38</a>) prompts a fuller consideration of the faith theme. Faith is a prominent concept in the book of Hebrews, as attested by the fact that the word occurs some 35 times in the letter. The Pauline idea of faith as the means of legal justification is adapted to the particular circumstances of the threatened Jewish Christians. The concept of faith is broader in this book than the strictly saving faith discussed by Paul, in that it leads to spiritual salvation (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.39-40">11:39-40</a>). Faith is the power by which heaven’s unseen realities are laid hold of to satisfy the soul. Faith enables the Christian disciple to view the world and interpret the flow of history from the divine perspective. Faith is the means of victory over the world of sin and woe. Through faith the believer approaches the throne of grace (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.16">4:16</a>) with the confidence and assurance that God will enable him to overcome.</p>
<p>The victory faith affords is amply illustrated from the history of God’s OT people. Abel, Enoch, and Noah in the primal history; Abraham, the father of faith; Moses, the leader of the young nation; and many valiant prophets and martyrs serve as living memorials to faith’s overcoming power. And yet God has something better in store for his sanctified people, the church (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.40">11:40</a>): the reality of the living Christ.</p>
<p>Yet the greatest model of steadfast endurance in suffering is Jesus, “the Originator and Perfecter of our faith” (<a href="?bref=Heb.12.2">12:2</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg). When surrounded with trials, the Christian needs to recall Christ, who in anticipation of the heavenly crown endured the cross and its shame. The Christian’s trials are trivial compared with what Jesus Christ was called upon to suffer (v <a href="?bref=Heb.12.3">3</a>). Moreover, for the people of God, suffering and persecution prove to be disguised blessings. The rod of discipline confirms our status as children of the living God (vv <a href="?bref=Heb.12.5-10">5-10</a>). But beyond this, the sovereign God is able to transform the Christian’s suffering into inestimable blessing (v <a href="?bref=Heb.12.11">11</a>). Hence the wavering saints should strive for spiritual wholeness and maturity, taking care lest they be overtaken by bitterness and resentment (v <a href="?bref=Heb.12.15">15</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Final Exhortations and Benediction (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.1-25">13:1-25</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The writer in his closing words challenges his Christian friends to be faithful to the tasks that lie at hand. They are to show continued love to the brethren, to extend hospitality to strangers, to uphold the sanctity of marriage, to be content with what they now possess, and to be obedient to their spiritual leaders (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.1-7">13:1-7</a>).</p>
<p>The readers are warned against the trickery of the Judaizers, who would lead them astray from Jesus Christ, the one who remains “the same yesterday, today, and forever” (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.8">13:8</a>). Spiritual determination is strengthened by recalling the example of Christ, who “suffered outside the city gates” for their salvation (v <a href="?bref=Heb.13.12">12</a>). As the people of God, they are challenged to follow Christ “outside the camp,” bearing abuse for him (v <a href="?bref=Heb.13.13">13</a>). Patient endurance is possible when the Christian realizes that he has no enduring city here (v <a href="?bref=Heb.13.14">14</a>). His goal is the heavenly Jerusalem, the eternal city of God.</p>
<p>The anonymous letter to the unknown “Hebrews” closes with a glorious benediction. The Christian’s God is described as the great “God of peace” (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.20">13:20</a>), and Jesus is “the great Shepherd of the sheep,” who established a new and eternal covenant and then rose triumphant from the dead. And the promise is made to the trusting soul that the triune God would “equip you with all you need for doing his will” (v <a href="?bref=Heb.13.21">21</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>The letter to the Hebrews is rich in doctrinal teaching. It discloses more about the historical Jesus than any other NT letter. It alone explains the atoning work of Christ under the rubric of the Melchizedekian priest. The letter’s discussion of repentance, justification, sanctification, and perseverance makes it a mine of salvation teaching. Its explication of old and new covenants, impending judgment, and the world to come make a significant contribution to Christian theology. And the letter’s teaching on faith, endurance, and the practical Christian combine to make Hebrews one of the most important documents God has given to the church.</p>
  </body>
</item>