<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hezekiah">
  <title>Hezekiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HEZEKIAH</p>
<p class="list">1. King of Judah from 715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>. The account of Hezekiah’s reign is in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.1-20.21">2 Kings 18:1–20:21</a>, <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.1-32.33">2 Chronicles 29:1–32:33</a>, and <a href="?bref=Isa.36.1-39.8">Isaiah 36:1–39:8</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Chronology">Chronology</p>
<p class="fl">Hezekiah succeeded to Judah’s throne at 25 and ruled for 29 years (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.2">2 Kgs 18:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.1">2 Chr 29:1</a>). His mother was Abi (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.2">2 Kgs 18:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.29.1">2 Chr 29:1</a>; “Abijah,” a longer form), a daughter of Zechariah. The chronology of Hezekiah’s reign is difficult to establish with certainty. The Bible says the Assyrian siege of Samaria, capital of the northern kingdom of Israel, began in the fourth year of his reign and that Samaria fell in the sixth year (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.9-10">2 Kgs 18:9-10</a>), which would make his reign begin about 728 <span class="era">BC</span> and end about 699 <span class="era">BC</span>. Assyrian king Sennacherib besieged the fortified Judean cities during Hezekiah’s 14th year (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.13">2 Kgs 18:13</a>), which would have been 714 <span class="era">BC</span>. Assyrian records, however, indicate that Sennacherib came to the Assyrian throne in 705 <span class="era">BC</span> and that his Judean campaign took place in 701 <span class="era">BC</span>. The most generally accepted solution to the discrepancy is that Hezekiah came to the throne in 715 <span class="era">BC</span>, probably after a co-regency with his father, Ahaz, that began in 728 <span class="era">BC</span>. That solution harmonizes with the statement that Sennacherib’s siege took place in the 14th year of Hezekiah’s reign, or 701 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HezekiahsReligiousReforms">Hezekiah’s Religious Reforms</p>
<p class="fl">Hezekiah came to the throne at a critical juncture in Judah’s history. Sargon II had taken Samaria in 722 <span class="era">BC</span>, and Judah was militarily weakened from wars and raids by surrounding nations during the reign of Ahaz. Perhaps motivated by warnings to the northern kingdom delivered by the prophets Amos and Hosea that punishment would come if Israel did not turn back to God, Hezekiah began his religious reforms soon after becoming king.</p>
<p>In the first month of his reign, Hezekiah opened the temple doors and repaired them. He brought the Levites together and ordered them to sanctify themselves and the temple and to reinstate the religious ceremonies that had long been neglected. Hezekiah brought sacrifices, and the priestly temple service was restored (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.1-36">2 Chr 29</a>).</p>
<p>Hezekiah then sent invitations throughout Judah and Israel for the Passover celebration in Jerusalem (held a month later than the prescribed time because the priests and people could not be ready earlier). It was hoped that religious unification would be a prelude to political reunification of the northern kingdom of Israel and the southern kingdom of Judah. However, most of the northern tribes mocked the Judean messengers who brought the invitations, and only a few persons from the tribes of Asher, Manasseh, and Zebulun went to Jerusalem for the celebration (<a href="?bref=2Chr.30.1-27">2 Chr 30</a>).</p>
<p>After the Passover observance, the worshipers set about destroying the high places and altars. They broke the pillars and cut down the Asherim throughout Judah and Benjamin, and also went into Ephraim and Manasseh (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.1">2 Chr 31:1</a>). Hezekiah even smashed the bronze serpent that Moses had made (<a href="?bref=Num.21.6-9">Nm 21:6-9</a>), for it had become an object of worship and was identified with a serpent deity, Nehushtan (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.4">2 Kgs 18:4</a>). Because of his sweeping reforms, later generations said of Hezekiah, “There was never another king like him in the land of Judah, either before or after his time” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.5">2 Kgs 18:5</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheAssyrianThreat">The Assyrian Threat</p>
<p class="fl">Hezekiah knew that Assyria’s growing international dominance was a serious threat to his kingdom, but following his father’s policy of submission, Hezekiah did not attempt any resistance at first.</p>
<p>The inscriptions of the Assyrian king Sargon II record his victorious campaign in 711 <span class="era">BC</span> against a revolt by Aziru, king of Ashdod, who requested help from Egypt and Judah. Perhaps a prophecy received by Isaiah warned Hezekiah not to interfere with the Ashdod siege (<a href="?bref=Isa.20.1-6">Is 20</a>), and so no punitive action was taken against Judah by Assyria. Sargon died in 705, and his son Sennacherib came to the throne. This triggered widespread rebellion throughout the Assyrian provinces. Hezekiah withheld tribute from the new Assyrian ruler and, taking advantage of the confused situation, made raids against the Philistines (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.8">2 Kgs 18:8</a>). After subduing rebellious elements in the East, Sennacherib began his campaign against the “land of Hatti” (the Assyrian name for the western countries) in 701 <span class="era">BC</span>. In preparation Hezekiah repaired Jerusalem’s city wall, raised towers on it, built another wall outside it, and strengthened the Millo in the City of David. He also stockpiled abundant quantities of weapons and shields (<a href="?bref=2Chr.32.5">2 Chr 32:5</a>). Knowing the necessity of an adequate water supply for a city under siege, Hezekiah had a 1,777-foot (542-meter) tunnel cut through solid rock from the spring of Gihon to the Siloam Pool to bring water into the city and to prevent the Assyrians from gaining access to the spring water outside the city (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.20">2 Kgs 20:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.32.3-4">2 Chr 32:3-4</a>). The Siloam inscription, carved inside the tunnel itself, records the completion of that remarkable conduit and is one of the oldest preserved examples of the Hebrew language.</p>
<p>Sennacherib invaded Palestine and, after an extensive campaign, put down the rebellion there. That campaign is well documented in Assyrian records, including a description of his siege on Jerusalem in 701, and this documentation is supplemented by the biblical account (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.13-19.37">2 Kgs 18:13–19:37</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.32.1-22">2 Chr 32:1-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.36.1-37.38">Is 36–37</a>). Sidon, the cities of Phoenicia, and the immediate neighbors of Judah (including Byblos, Arnon, Moab, Edom, and Ashdod) submitted to the Assyrians. Resistant Philistine cities were also taken. Sennacherib laid siege against Ekron, whose king, Padi (a loyal subject of Sennacherib), had been taken prisoner by his own subjects and turned over in chains to Hezekiah. A large Egyptian and Ethiopian army failed to relieve the Ekronites, who were defeated by the Assyrians in the vicinity of Eltekah. Ekron was captured, and Padi was recalled to his throne by Sennacherib.</p>
<p>Sennacherib then turned his attention to the fortified cities of Judah and took them one by one (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.13">2 Kgs 18:13</a>). Assyrian records claim that he captured 46 walled cities and countless villages, including Lachish and Debir (southwest of Jerusalem), 200,150 people, homes, cattle, and flocks without number. While Lachish was still under siege, Hezekiah saw that it was hopeless to resist and sent word to Sennacherib offering to surrender and pay whatever tribute he would impose. The Assyrian ruler demanded an enormous tribute of 300 talents of silver (800 talents according to Assyrian records, either an exaggerated figure or computed by a different standard) and 30 talents of gold. In order to pay that tribute, Hezekiah took all the silver in the temple and the royal treasuries, and stripped the gold from the temple doors and doorposts (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.14-16">2 Kgs 18:14-16</a>). This treasure was sent to Sennacherib along with other gifts that, according to the Assyrian account, included some of Hezekiah’s own daughters as concubines.</p>
<p>The account in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.17-19.37">2 Kings 18:17–19:37</a> raises the question of whether there was another invasion of Judah at a later date, or whether this passage gives additional details about the invasion of 701. Although Hezekiah had already submitted and paid tribute, these verses describe further Assyrian demands. Those who believe it was a single invasion suggest that this is an account of the Assyrian deputation sent by Sennacherib to demand Jerusalem’s surrender while Lachish was still under siege. The deputation included the Tartan, Rabsaris, and Rabshakeh (titles of court officials rather than personal names). They warned the citizens that their God was no more able to save them than the gods of other cities defeated by the Assyrians. In distress Hezekiah sent word to the prophet Isaiah, who assured the king that Sennacherib would hear a rumor and return to his own land and there die by the sword (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.1-7">2 Kgs 19:1-7</a>). Shortly afterward Sennacherib received word of Babylon’s revolt in his eastern provinces, so he departed at once without taking Jerusalem. Assyrian records do not claim that Jerusalem was taken but only say that Hezekiah was “shut up in Jerusalem like a bird in a cage.” Judah’s surrounding neighbors celebrated their deliverance and brought gifts of gratitude to Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.32.23">2 Chr 32:23</a>).</p>
<p>Later, the Assyrian king heard that Tirhakah, king of Ethiopia, was advancing against him, so he sent another threatening message to Hezekiah, probably to warn him against making an alliance with Tirhakah. Hezekiah took the matter before the Lord and received word from Isaiah that the Assyrian king would return the same way he came and that Jerusalem would be untouched. Soon afterward, in a miraculous intervention by God, 185,000 Assyrian troops were killed, and the Assyrian monarch abandoned his plans to conquer Hezekiah. That embarrassing calamity understandably is not mentioned by the Assyrian records. In 681 Sennacherib was killed by two of his sons as Isaiah had predicted (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.7,37">2 Kgs 19:7, 37</a>).</p>
<p>Sometime prior to 701, Hezekiah became seriously ill, and Isaiah told him to prepare for death. The king earnestly prayed for an extension of life, and God promised him 15 more years as well as deliverance from the Assyrians. Hezekiah asked Isaiah for a sign that he would be healed, and a shadow cast by the sun moved backward 10 steps contrary to its normal direction (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.1-11">2 Kgs 20:1-11</a>).</p>
<p>Sometime after his recovery Hezekiah received a delegation with presents from Merodach-baladan of Babylon, ostensibly to congratulate Hezekiah on his return to health. The real object of the visit was probably to enlist Hezekiah as an ally in a conspiracy being formed against Assyria. The king showed the Babylonian envoys all the gold, silver, and other valuables he possessed. This act brought a warning from Isaiah that the day would come when all those treasures would be carried away to Babylon (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.12-19">2 Kgs 20:12-19</a>).</p>
<p>Hezekiah lived the remainder of his life in peace and prosperity. It may have been during this time that he encouraged literary efforts in Judah, which included copying some of Solomon’s proverbs (<a href="?bref=Pr.25.1-29.27">Prv 25–29</a>). Upon his death in 686, he was succeeded by his son Manasseh, who probably had become co-regent 10 years earlier.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=King_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">King</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. KJV form of Hizkiah, Neariah’s son, in <a href="?bref=1Chr.3.23">1 Chronicles 3:23</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Hizkiah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hizkiah #1</a>.</p>
<p class="list">3. Head of a family of exiles (the sons of Ater), 98 of whose descendants returned from the Babylonian exile with Zerubbabel (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.16">Ezr 2:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.21">Neh 7:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.10.17">10:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Ancestor of the prophet Zephaniah, possibly King Hezekiah himself (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.1">Zep 1:1</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>