<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hittites">
  <title>Hittites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HITTITES</p>
<p class="fl">Biblical people who figure largely in the promises of a land for the descendants of Abram and the children of Israel. Once unknown to secular history and thought to be a mythical people by some critics of Bible history, information about the Hittites has been uncovered by archaeologists and historians, and they now are known to have had an empire centered in Asia Minor. They were of sufficient military strength to challenge the armies of Egypt under the vainglorious Ramses II and fought him to a standstill at Kadesh on the Orontes.</p>
<p>For the most part, the biblical references do not suggest that the Hittites were more than a minor group, but the association of Hittite kings and Egypt with Solomon’s trade in horses and their involvement in the conflicts of Syria and Israel in the divided monarchy indicate that the Hittites were a people of great consequence.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Geography">Geography</p>
<p class="fl">The Hittite Empire had its center in Anatolia (Asia Minor, modern Turkey), with its capital at Hattusas (modern Baghazkoy) at the bend of the Halys River (present Kizil Irmak). The empire at times extended over a much larger area without definite boundaries since it included city-states that were dependencies of the Anatolian kingdom, related to it by treaties but otherwise not a part of it. Because of their presence in Palestine-Syria, the Hittites made their influence felt in Egypt and are well known from the art and inscriptions of that country. The presence of Hittites in Palestine is widely attested in the Bible, and the power of the Hittites in Palestinian cities like Hebron is indicated in patriarchal times.</p>
<p class="h2" id="History">History</p>
<p class="fl">The Hittites (also known as Hattians) were one of several groups of peoples, thought to be neither Semitic nor Indo-European, who occupied the Anatolian plateau in the third millennium <span class="era">BC</span>. In the late part of this millennium Indo-Europeans overran the area and assumed political power.</p>
<p>History in the true sense, that is, based on written records, begins in Anatolia around 1900 <span class="era">BC</span> with the arrival of Assyrian traders. These merchants established themselves in various cities and corresponded with their homeland using cuneiform tablets. Numbers of these records have been found near Kayseri. These mention the struggle among Hittite principalities for supremacy in Anatolia and refer to a King Anittas, who is known from Hittite sources of later date.</p>
<p>During the 15th century <span class="era">BC</span>, the dominance of the Hurrians was broken by the campaigns of the Egyptian king Thutmose III, but another Hurrian kingdom, Mitanni, soon became prominent in western Asia. Mitanni presented a threat to the Hittites, but with the arrival of an ambitious and energetic monarch, Suppiluliuma I (c. 1380–1340 <span class="era">BC</span>), there came a resurgence of Hittite vitality and the strength of the empire. This was the time of the writing of the Amarna letters, with their testimony of the confused situation in Palestine-Syria.</p>
<p>Suppiluliuma carried out a brilliant military expedition against Mitanni and then, by combining force with diplomatic genius, forged for himself a buffer zone of vassal city-states, which were bound to him by treaties, copies of which were found in the Hittite archives.</p>
<p>During the first half of the 14th century, the languor of Amenhotep III and the religious preoccupation of Akhenaten had allowed the Asiatic empire of Egypt to dwindle away into a memory. But with the beginning of the 19th dynasty, the Egyptians became concerned about regaining what was lost. The contest for Palestine-Syria reached its climax with the famous battle at Kadesh on the Orontes, where the initial advantage was won by Hittite chariots. Ramses II celebrated the battle as a victory, although he barely escaped with his life. The Hittite king, Muwatallis, also claimed a triumph, but in political terms the battle was inconclusive. The next Hittite king after him, Hattusilis III, signed a treaty with Ramses II in the 21st year of the reign of the Egyptian king; the pact was confirmed by the marriage of the daughter of Hattusilis to Ramses II.</p>
<p>Around the middle of the 13th century <span class="era">BC</span>, the Hittites were threatened from the west by the Ahhiyawa, possibly to be associated with the Achaeans and the Sea Peoples (see <a href="?item=PhilistiaPhilistines_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Philistia, Philistines</a>). It was a wave of the Sea Peoples that brought the Hittite Empire to an end around 1190 <span class="era">BC</span> and surged along the eastern Mediterranean coast until it was finally stopped in the Nile Delta by Ramses III.</p>
<p>In northern Syria, independent city-states continued to be ruled by kings who bore Hittite names and erected monuments inscribed with Hittite hieroglyphs. The Assyrians continued to refer to the area as the Land of Hatti, and the OT speaks of these rulers of principalities as “kings of the Hittites.” These little kingdoms were soon placed under Assyrian tribute and became Assyrian provinces in the reigns of Shalmaneser V and Sargon II, the rulers who also put an end to the northern kingdom of Israel by conquering Samaria in 721 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="LanguagesandLiterature">Languages and Literature</p>
<p class="fl">In the texts found at Boghazkoy, eight different languages were employed. Of these, only two, Hittite and Akkadian, were used for official royal records. Akkadian was the lingua franca of the empire and was also the main language of the Amarna tablets. Hurrian is the only other language in which complete texts were written. The other languages occur mostly in short passages in Hittite religious documents, and one is identified only by some technical terms.</p>
<p>There were eight languages: (1) Hittite, also called Nesite, was recognized by B. Hrozny as having affinities with Indo-European. This proposal met with skepticism among scholars for a while, but it has been proved beyond question. (2) Hattic (Hattian), the language of the aboriginal people of Anatolia, is used for speeches of the priests in the performance of the cultic ritual relating to the Hittite pantheon. (3) Luwian is another Indo-European language, closely related to Hittite. (4) Palaic, a little-known language, is also Indo-European. (5) Hurrian appears in many ritual texts. Fragments of a Hurrian translation of the Epic of Gilgamesh were found. One of the Amarna tablets, written by Tushratta, king of Mitanni, to Amenhotep III, was in Hurrian. Also represented are (6) the Aryan language of the Mitanni rulers, (7) Akkadian, and (8) Sumerian. In addition to the cuneiform script, the Hittites used hieroglyphs, which have been found inscribed on stone and lead.</p>
<p>The Hittite archives contained texts of official documents, such as treaties, laws, instructions, annals of the kings, letters, and other historical records. There was much religious literature, including myths, legends, epics, incantations, rituals, omens, prayers, and descriptions of festivals and their celebration.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ThePeople">The People</p>
<p class="fl">The diversity of language characteristic of Hittite civilization is paralleled by the great mixture of ethnic backgrounds, particularly over the geographic range covered by the empire. The physical appearance of the Hittites is known from their own reliefs and from representation on Egyptian monuments. Their own depictions show the Hittites with unattractive faces, heavy coats, tall pointed caps, and shoes with turned-up toes.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Religion">Religion</p>
<p class="fl">The Hittites had a pantheon of deities, known by name from the inscriptions and by appearance from the reliefs. Gods may be identified by a weapon or tool carried in the right hand, a symbol in the left hand, wings or similar appurtenances, or the sacred animal on which a divinity may stand.</p>
<p>A principal god was the weather god, whose sacred animal was the bull. Out of the multiplicity of local cults, there arose an official pantheon, headed by the sun goddess, Arinna, who was the supreme deity of the state and of the king. The treaties of the Hittites typically have a long list of divinities who served as witnesses to the treaty and oath.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HittitesandtheBible">Hittites and the Bible</p>
<p class="fl">The name “Hittite(s)” occurs nearly 50 times in the OT but does not appear in the NT. If one includes the occurrences of the name of Heth, the father of the Hittites, there are more than 60 citations in the Bible. Most have to do with the presence of Hittites in Canaan. Their progenitor and eponym, Heth, is listed second among the sons of Canaan in the “table of nations” (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.15">Gn 10:15</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.13">1 Chr 1:13</a>). Most of the references to the “sons of Heth” appear in the narrative of the purchase of the cave of Machpelah by Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.23.1-20">Gn 23</a>).</p>
<p>The OT references to Hittites include <a href="?bref=Gen.26.34">Genesis 26:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.27.46">27:46</a> (Hittite women); <a href="?bref=Gen.49.29-32">49:29-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.50.13">50:13</a> (Ephron); <a href="?bref=Exod.33.2">Exodus 33:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.13.29">Numbers 13:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.7.1">Deuteronomy 7:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.20.17">20:17</a> (their destruction); <a href="?bref=Josh.11.3">Joshua 11:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.8">12:8</a> (occupants of Canaan); <a href="?bref=1Sam.26.6">1 Samuel 26:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.11.1-12.31">2 Samuel 11–12</a> (Uriah, a warrior under David); <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.20">1 Kings 9:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.29">10:29</a> (laborers or traders under Solomon); <a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.1">11:1</a> (wife of Solomon); <a href="?bref=Ezra.9.1">Ezra 9:1</a> (foreigners); <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.3,45">Ezekiel 16:3, 45</a> (Jerusalem’s ancestors).</p>
  </body>
</item>