<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hivites">
  <title>Hivites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HIVITES</p>
<p class="fl">Name of a pre-Israelite group living in Canaan. Though not yet discovered/rated archaeologically or from secular history as a people, they were regarded as emerging from a son of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.17">Gn 10:17</a>) and as inhabiting areas of the Lebanon Mountains (<a href="?bref=Judg.3.3">Jgs 3:3</a>) and Mt Hermon (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.3">Jos 11:3</a>). They are referred to frequently as a group dispossessed by Israel (<a href="?bref=Josh.12.8">Jos 12:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.11">24:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.20">1 Kgs 9:20</a>) but who managed to survive into the kingdom period (<a href="?bref=2Sam.24.7">2 Sm 24:7</a>) and lived at that time near Tyre as well as in other possible areas. Some scholars think that an error in copying, involving the changing of the letters <span class="ital">r</span> (resh) to <span class="ital">w</span> (waw) was responsible for the origin of the name Hivite from Horite.</p>
<p>Others have suggested a scribal confusion of names, since Zibeon is called a Hivite in <a href="?bref=Gen.36.2">Genesis 36:2</a> and a Horite in verses <a href="?bref=Gen.36.20">20</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.36.29">29</a>. In several cases the Septuagint gives “Horite” in place of the Masoretic Text “Hivite” (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.2">Gn 34:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.9.7">Jos 9:7</a>). Other passages in the Septuagint read “Hittite” rather than “Hivite” (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.3">Jos 11:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.3.3">Jgs 3:3</a>).</p>
<p>The overlapping or equivalence of Hivite and Horite in <a href="?bref=Gen.36.1-43">Genesis 36</a> probably indicates some relationship between the two peoples (cf. Ishmaelites and Midianites in <a href="?bref=Gen.37.27-28,36">Gn 37:27-28, 36</a>). Perhaps both Horites and Hivites are related to the Hurrians, who are well attested archaeologically.</p>
<p>The fact that there are some 25 occurrences of the name “Hivite(s)” in the OT, nearly one-third of which come in Joshua, makes it probable that they were a distinct people. Aside from Hivites in Palestine, they also appeared in Edomite territory (<a href="?bref=Gen.36.2">Gn 36:2</a>). OT references to Hivites include Hamor (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.2">Gn 34:2</a>), the men of Gibeon (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.7">Jos 9:7</a>), the northern Hivites (<a href="?bref=Judg.3.3-8">Jgs 3:3-8</a>), and those who lived near Tyre (<a href="?bref=2Sam.24.7">2 Sm 24:7</a>). During the reign of Solomon, the Hivites and other foreign inhabitants of the land were made slaves; that is, they were put under forced labor (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.20-21">1 Kgs 9:20-21</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.8.7">2 Chr 8:7</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>