<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Holofernes">
  <title>Holofernes</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HOLOFERNES</p>
<p class="fl">According to the book of Judith, the chief Assyrian general under King Nebuchadnezzar (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.2.4">Jdt 2:4</a>) who was ordered by the king to “go and attack the whole west country” (v <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.2.6">6</a>). He ravaged the nations one after another (vv <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.2.21-27">21-27</a>) and his huge army spread terror wherever it went (v <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.2.28">28</a>). He destroyed “all the gods of the land, so that all nations should worship Nebuchadnezzar only, and all their tongues and tribes should call upon him as god” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.3.8">3:8</a>). When Holofernes made a determined effort to seize Bethulia (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.7.1-32">7:1ff</a>.), the forces of Israel rallied and took up their weapons. The desperate Jews were about to surrender when the beautiful widow Judith asked permission of the leaders of the Jews to go to Holofernes (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.8.32-34">8:32-34</a>). The permission was given and Judith called upon God to deliver her people (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.9.2-14">9:2-14</a>). She “made herself very beautiful” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.10.4">10:4</a>) and went to meet Holofernes “to give him a true report” (v <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.10.13">13</a>). Holofernes came under the spell of the beautiful Judith, and on the fourth day of her visit he made a banquet and Judith was invited (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.12.10-11">12:10-11</a>). Holofernes became drunk, and when all the servants had left, Judith took his sword and severed his head from his body and carried it back to Bethulia in a bag and showed it to the leaders of Israel. Jubilant Israelites attacked the leaderless Assyrians, who fled in panic. Led by Judith, the Jews joined in celebration and praise and offered thanksgiving in Jerusalem. This story of defeated pride has been a favorite theme of artists, including Donatello and Dante.</p>
  </body>
</item>