<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hoshea">
  <title>Hoshea</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HOSHEA</p>
<p class="list">1. Original name of Joshua, the son of Nun and Moses’ successor, before his name was changed by Moses (<a href="?bref=Num.13.8,16">Nm 13:8, 16</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=JoshuaPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Joshua (Person) #1</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Son of Elah and the last of the 20 kings of the northern kingdom of Israel (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.1-6">2 Kgs 17:1-6</a>). He reigned for nine years (732–723 <span class="era">BC</span>) before being taken captive by the Assyrians. In the later years of the northern kingdom, Assyria (under the rule of Tiglath-pileser III) had gained control of most of the Middle East and had reduced the scope of the northern kingdom to Ephraim, Issachar, and the half of Manasseh west of the Jordan.</p>
<p class="list-text">Earlier, the northern kingdom, under Pekah (740–732 <span class="era">BC</span>), entered into an alliance with Rezin of Damascus (Syria) and attempted to coerce King Ahaz of Judah (735–715 <span class="era">BC</span>) to join them in action against Tiglath-pileser (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.5">2 Kgs 16:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.7.1-6">Is 7:1-6</a>). Assyria came to Judah’s aid, and at this point Hoshea was one of a group of conspirators who assassinated Pekah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.30">2 Kgs 15:30</a>). Tiglath-pileser rewarded Hoshea by making him king over the remnant of the northern kingdom. Hoshea ruled only as a vassal of Assyria and paid heavy tribute, remaining loyal to Assyria until the death of Tiglath-pileser in 727 <span class="era">BC</span>. When Shalmaneser V succeeded to the throne of Assyria, he did not trust Hoshea’s loyalty and marched against him, thereby continuing the forced annual tribute (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.3">2 Kgs 17:3</a>). In a short time Hoshea attempted to assert independence. He withheld tribute and entered into negotiations with So, king of Egypt (v <a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.4">4</a>), finding a favorable response, because Egypt would be in a precarious position if Assyria were to control Palestine. Therefore, Egypt was quite willing to support Hoshea in his resistance to Assyria in the hope that Samaria would remain a buffer between Egypt and Assyria. Soon, Shalmaneser directed his army against Samaria (724 <span class="era">BC</span>), and Hoshea discovered that the alliance with Egypt was of little value. Hoshea was taken prisoner, and Assyria apparently besieged Samaria for three years. The city fell in 722 <span class="era">BC</span>, and Sargon II, who had succeeded Shalmaneser about 726 <span class="era">BC</span>, deported many Israelites to various places in Assyria, thus ending the northern kingdom.</p>
<p class="list">3. Son of Azaziah and one of King David’s officers set over the Ephraimites (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.20">1 Chr 27:20</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. One who set his seal on Ezra’s covenant (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.23">Neh 10:23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Eighth-century prophet of Israel better known as Hosea. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=HoseaPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hosea (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=HoseaBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hosea, Book of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>