<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HostHostofHeaven">
  <title>Host, Host of Heaven*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HOST, HOST OF HEAVEN*</p>
<p class="fl">Hebrew expressions found frequently in the OT and literally meaning “army” and “army of the skies.” “Host” is basically a military term, occurring nearly 500 times in the OT, and can mean “army” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.17">2 Kgs 18:17</a>), “angels,” “heavenly bodies,” or “creation.”</p>
<p>The phrase “host of heaven” has various applications in the Bible. Ancient writers sometimes referred symbolically to the sun, moon, and stars as an army (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.19">Dt 4:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.5.20">Jgs 5:20</a>). In the astrological cults of antiquity, it was believed that celestial bodies were animated by spirits and thus constituted a living army that controlled heavenly destiny. The worship of the host of heaven was one of the earliest forms of idolatry, and was common among the Israelites in their times of regression from serving God (<a href="?bref=Jer.19.13">Jer 19:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.42">Acts 7:42</a>). Although warned against such pagan beliefs (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.19">Dt 4:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.17.3">17:3</a>), the Israelites fell into the practice of worshiping heavenly bodies, particularly during the Assyrian and Babylonian periods (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.16">2 Kgs 17:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.3-5">21:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.33.3-5">2 Chr 33:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.8.2">Jer 8:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.5">Zep 1:5</a>). The corrective to this pagan practice is belief in the Lord as the Creator of heaven and earth, the Almighty, the one who marshaled the heavenly bodies at his command and ordained them to perform a special function (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.14-19">Gn 1:14-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.2.1">2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.6">Neh 9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.33.6">Pss 33:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.103.21">103:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.148.2">148:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.26">Is 40:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.45.12">45:12</a>).</p>
<p>God is frequently called “the Lord God of hosts,” that is, of the celestial armies (<a href="?bref=Jer.5.14">Jer 5:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.38.17">38:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.44.7">44:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.12.5">Hos 12:5</a>). The heavenly host includes angels or messengers who are associated with the Lord’s work in heaven and on earth. God presides over a heavenly council composed of angels or “sons of God” (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.26">Gn 1:26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.19">1 Kgs 22:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.1.6">Jb 1:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.82.1-8">Ps 82</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-13">Is 6</a>) whose messengers are sent from the Lord’s council to accomplish his purpose (<a href="?bref=Gen.28.12-15">Gn 28:12-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.13">Lk 2:13</a>).</p>
<p>Though the hosts are sometimes understood as the stars or angels, the tribes of Israel are also called “the host of the Lord.” The “host of heaven” in <a href="?bref=Dan.8.10-11">Daniel 8:10-11</a> appears to be figurative language referring to Israel, “the holy people,” and God, the King of Israel, is called “the Prince of the host.”</p>
<p>The Greek words translated “host” occur only twice in the NT (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.13">Lk 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.42">Acts 7:42</a>). “Lord of hosts” is used by Paul and James (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.29">Rom 9:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.5.4">Jas 5:4</a>) as a title for the Lord. The term expresses God’s sovereign might and majesty in history, but the precise identification of the “hosts” that stand at his command is uncertain.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=HostsLordof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hosts, Lord of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>