<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Humility">
  <title>Humility</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HUMILITY</p>
<p class="fl">A condition of lowliness or affliction in which one experiences a loss of power and prestige. Outside of biblical faith, humility in this sense would not usually be considered a virtue. Within the context of the Judeo-Christian tradition, however, humility is considered the proper attitude of human beings toward their Creator. Humility is a grateful and spontaneous awareness that life is a gift, and it is manifested as an ungrudging and unhypocritical acknowledgment of absolute dependence upon God.</p>
<p>In biblical literature there is not a clear distinction between humility and meekness or patience. In early stages of Israel’s history, the humble were identified as the poor, the afflicted, and the powerless. The Lord delivers the humble but brings down the proud (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.7">1 Sm 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.22.28">2 Sm 22:28</a>). Before the power and glory of God, the patriarch Abraham confessed that he was but dust and ashes (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.27">Gn 18:27</a>). Israel began as a nation subjected to slavery and knew themselves as a people chosen not because of numerical strength or material wealth but because of God’s love (<a href="?bref=Deut.7.7-8">Dt 7:7-8</a>). By attributing the source of all wealth and power to the Lord, those two major sources of human pride and arrogance are brought under control (cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.9.23-24">Jer 9:23-24</a>).</p>
<p>The humble poor are the constant concern of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.6,11">Ex 23:6, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.15.4,7">Dt 15:4, 7</a>). Consequently, the humility of the poor became the symbol of the righteous God-fearer (<a href="?bref=Num.12.3">Nm 12:3</a>). In the development of the concept of humility in the OT, humility is nearly equated with righteousness and is identified, along with justice and mercy, as the requirement of God (<a href="?bref=Mic.6.8">Mi 6:8</a>). In the Psalms particularly, “the afflicted” is almost a technical term for the righteous (<a href="?bref=Ps.22.26">Pss 22:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.25.9">25:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.147.6">147:6</a>).</p>
<p>In addition, humility is the appropriate response of the sinner in the presence of the holiness of God. The prophet Isaiah, confronted by the glory of God in the temple, cried, “My destruction is sealed, for I am a sinful man” (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.5">Is 6:5</a>). Thus humility became more of a character trait than a term that reflected a state of material poverty or affliction. It became a concept reflective of the essence of piety and godliness expected of all people who have God as their Lord.</p>
<p>Only rarely in the NT does humility refer to an objective condition of poverty, affliction, or oppression.The humility motif is developed in connection with Jesus as Messiah. The religious ideal of humility that the OT attributed to the coming King certainly applied to Jesus (<a href="?bref=Zech.9.9">Zec 9:9</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.21.4-5">Mt 21:4-5</a>). As Son of God, Jesus took no thought for himself but lived a life of obedience and trust in God the Father. The apostle Paul attributed to the incarnate Son of God a self-emptying by which he “humbled himself” and took on the form of a servant (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.5-8">Phil 2:5-8</a>). Jesus’ character exhibited no pride or arrogance.</p>
<p>Though bold in the face of hypocrisy and unflinching in his repudiation of pretentious religion, Jesus was “gentle and humble in heart” (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.29">Mt 11:29</a>). He could, therefore, issue a severe warning against desire for status and openly rebuke the Pharisees for their violence against the poor and oppressed (<a href="?bref=Luke.14.11">Lk 14:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.12">Mt 23:12</a>). At the same time, he was humble before those whose servant and helper he had become (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.27">Lk 22:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.45">Mk 10:45</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.20.28">Mt 20:28</a>). The highest dignity of Jesus and his willingness to accept the cross in submission to the Father’s will are one. So his teaching on poverty of spirit rang true as a testimony of his own life. He ascribed all glory to his Father and lived in total dependence upon him (<a href="?bref=John.5.19">Jn 5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.38">6:38</a>; <a href="?bref=John.7.15">7:15</a>; <a href="?bref=John.8.28,50">8:28, 50</a>; <a href="?bref=John.14.10,24">14:10, 24</a>). By washing his disciples’ feet, he assumed the role of servant with no loss of dignity or self-worth. And he set forth such service as a model of a life that finds happiness in preferring others over one’s self (<a href="?bref=John.13.1-20">Jn 13:1-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.1-4">Phil 2:1-4</a>).</p>
<p>Consequently, disciples of Jesus are also summoned to a life of humility. Turning their backs on status, security, and success, Christians seek an opportunity to gain themselves in serving others. Humility, thus, is the all-embracing life principle by which love seeks the good of others, and thus fulfills the law (cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.12.10">Rom 12:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.13.8-10">13:8-10</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>