<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hypocrisy">
  <title>Hypocrisy</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HYPOCRISY</p>
<p class="fl">The act of pretending to be what one is not, especially the false appearance of being religious or virtuous. Our modern understanding of the word “hypocrisy” is determined by its use in the NT, especially by Jesus. In both the NT and subsequent understandings the term most often meant deceit, misrepresenting the truth, or claiming virtues or qualities one does not possess.</p>
<p>In contrast to its consistently negative meaning in the Bible, hypocrisy as first used by the Greeks was a neutral word. In its verb form it meant “to explain, to interpret, or to expound.” Although the noun “hypocrisy” could mean “answer,” the other noun form, “hypocrite,” almost always meant “actor” and probably came from the verb meaning “to expound.”</p>
<p>Originally, a hypocrite could be a speaker or actor who interpreted the words of a poet or the music of a composer. The actor, or hypocrite, tried to make intelligible for his audience what the poet or composer had written. On a larger scale the hypocrite could be one actor among others in a drama performed on a stage. A good hypocrite faithfully interpreted his assigned role, while an undesirable hypocrite interpreted his role poorly. Because of the word’s essential neutrality, accompanying words were necessary to set its direction.</p>
<p>In Hellenistic times (c. 325–125 <span class="era">BC</span>), the world was commonly viewed as a stage and all human conduct as the art of acting. One’s role and script were written for him by his familial, cultural, and religious environment and could be performed either successfully or poorly. When used in this sense, hypocrisy did not carry the idea of pretense or sham. Nevertheless, there are instances where the term “hypocrite” was used to describe a person who performed life’s role deceptively. The image presented to the public was only a mask behind which the true and different self lay hidden.</p>
<p>The Gospels often use the terms “hypocrisy” (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.28">Mt 23:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.15">Mk 12:15b</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.1">Lk 12:1</a>) and “hypocrite” (<a href="?bref=Matt.7.5">Mt 7:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.51">24:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.42">Lk 6:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.15">13:15</a>) to record the conflict between Jesus and his opponents. With respect to the Pharisees and Sadducees, Jesus detected a blatant contrast between their outward forms of righteousness and their failure to embrace the more substantive aspects of righteousness: mercy, justice, humility, forgiveness, and love toward the unlovely (<a href="?bref=Luke.11.38,42">Lk 11:38, 42</a>). They hid their failure in this matter behind pious pretense (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.1-13">Mk 7:1-13</a>). Inwardly they were full of greed and wickedness (<a href="?bref=Luke.11.39">Lk 11:39</a>). Hypocrisy defines the one who presents an outward appearance of righteousness but who is inwardly marked by wickedness (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.28">Mt 23:28</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus condemned hypocrisy because it distorts God’s righteous command. Rather than pursue an authentic inward holiness, the hypocrites distorted righteousness into a rigid mold whose chief usefulness was exhibition before people (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.2-7">Mt 23:2-7</a>). Their idea of righteousness revealed a warped conception of God and a perverse understanding of how he reconciles sinners to himself (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.15">Lk 16:15</a>). The hypocrites, who claimed to interpret God to humans, actually misrepresented him. Consequently, their falsification led sinners away from God rather than toward reconciliation with him (<a href="?bref=Luke.11.52">Lk 11:52</a>). Hypocrites not only keep others from entering the kingdom of God, they refrain from going in themselves (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.13">Mt 23:13</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>