<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="KingdomofGodKingdomofHeaven">
  <title>Kingdom of God, Kingdom of Heaven</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">KINGDOM OF GOD, KINGDOM OF HEAVEN</p>
<p class="fl">The sovereign rule of God, initiated by Christ’s earthly ministry and consummated when the kingdom of the world becomes the kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ (<a href="?bref=Rev.11.15">Rv 11:15</a>).</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Introduction">Introduction</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#OldTestamentBackground">Old Testament Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Introduction">Introduction</p>
<p class="fl">According to the testimony of the first three Gospels, the proclamation of the kingdom of God was Jesus’ central message. Matthew summarizes the Galilean ministry with the words “Jesus traveled throughout Galilee teaching in the synagogues, preaching everywhere the Good News about the Kingdom” (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.23">Mt 4:23</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The Sermon on the Mount is concerned with the righteousness that qualifies people to enter the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.20">5:20</a>). The collection of parables in <a href="?bref=Matt.13.1-58">Matthew 13</a> and <a href="?bref=Mark.4.1-41">Mark 4</a> illustrate the “mystery” of the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.11">Mt 13:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.11">Mk 4:11</a>). The establishment of the Lord’s Supper looks forward to the establishment of the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.29">Mt 26:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.25">Mk 14:25</a>).</p>
<p>The NT reports two different forms of the expression: “the kingdom of God” and “the kingdom of the heavens.” The latter is found only in Matthew, but Matthew also has “the kingdom of God” four times (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.28">Mt 12:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.19.24">19:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.21.31,43">21:31, 43</a>). “The kingdom of heaven” is a Semitic phrase that would have been meaningful to Jews but not to Greeks. The Jews, out of reverence for God, avoided uttering the divine name, and contemporary literature gives examples of substituting the word “heaven” for God (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.3.18,50">1 Macc 3:18, 50</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.4.10">4:10</a>; see <a href="?bref=Luke.15.18">Lk 15:18</a>).</p>
<p>The key to an understanding of the kingdom of God is that the basic meaning of the Greek word <span class="greek">basileia</span><span class="ital">,</span> as also of the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">malkut</span><span class="ital">,</span> is rule, reign, dominion. We frequently find in the OT the expression “in the year of the kingdom of . . . ,” meaning in the year of the reign of a given king (e.g., <a href="?bref=1Chr.26.31">1 Chr 26:31</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.3.2">2 Chr 3:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.15.10">15:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.7.1">Ezr 7:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.8.1">8:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.2.16">Est 2:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.10.7">Jer 10:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.52.31">52:31</a>). When we read that Solomon’s kingdom was firmly established (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.12">1 Kgs 2:12</a>), we are to understand that his authority to reign was settled. To “turn the kingdom of Saul over to [David]” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.23">1 Chr 12:23</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>) indicates that the authority that had been Saul’s was given to David. As a result of having received legal authority, David became king. This abstract idea of <span class="hebrew">malkut</span> is evident when it is found in parallelisms with such ideas as power, might, glory, and dominion (<a href="?bref=Dan.4.34">Dn 4:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.7.14">7:14</a>).</p>
<p>When <span class="hebrew">malkut</span> is used of God, it almost always refers to his authority or to his rule as the heavenly King. “They will talk together about the glory of your kingdom; they will celebrate examples of your power. . . . For your kingdom is an everlasting kingdom. You rule generation after generation” (<a href="?bref=Ps.145.11,13">Ps 145:11, 13</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Further, if a king rules, there must be a realm or sphere over which he reigns. This is also called <span class="hebrew">malkut</span><span class="ital">.</span> “So the realm of Jehoshaphat was quiet, for his God gave him rest round about” (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.30">2 Chr 20:30</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>; see <a href="?bref=Esth.3.6">Est 3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.10.7">Jer 10:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.9.1">Dn 9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.11.9">11:9</a>).</p>
<p>This same twofold use of <span class="greek">basileia</span> is found in the NT. In fact, <span class="greek">basileia</span> could be translated by the expression “kingly power” in <a href="?bref=Luke.23.42">Luke 23:42</a> (<span class="sc">niv</span> mg) and by “kingship” in <a href="?bref=John.18.36">John 18:36</a>. When a nobleman went into a far country to get a “kingdom” (<a href="?bref=Luke.19.12">Luke 19:12</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>) he went to the governing authority to get an appointment as king. When Jesus said, “My kingship is not of this world” (<a href="?bref=John.18.36">Jn 18:36</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), he did not mean to say that his rule has nothing to do with the world but rather that his kingship—his dominion—does not come from man but from God. Therefore, he rejects the use of worldly fighting to gain his ends.</p>
<p>This central meaning of <span class="greek">basileia</span> makes it easy to understand many sayings in the Gospels. In the Lord’s Prayer the petition “Thy kingdom come” (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.10">Mt 6:10</a>) is a prayer for God to manifest his reign so that his will may be done on earth as it is in heaven. When we read that we are to “receive the kingdom of God like a child” (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.15">Mk 10:15</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), we must open our hearts and lives to the rule of God.</p>
<p>Also in the NT are sayings about being <span class="ital">in</span> the kingdom or of <span class="ital">entering</span> the kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.11">Mt 8:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.47">Mk 9:47</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.23-25">10:23-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.28">Lk 13:28</a>). There is no philological or theological objection to understanding “the kingdom of God” first as the divine reign or rule and second as the sphere of blessing in which that reign is experienced.</p>
<p class="h2" id="OldTestamentBackground">Old Testament Background</p>
<p class="fl">The expression “the kingdom of God” is not found in the OT, but the idea appears throughout the prophets. God is frequently spoken of as the King, both of Israel (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.18">Ex 15:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.23.21">Nm 23:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.33.5">Dt 33:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.43.15">Is 43:15</a>) and of all the earth (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.15">2 Kgs 19:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.29.10">Pss 29:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.47.2">47:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.93.1-2">93:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.96.10">96:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.97.1-9">97:1-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.99.1-4">99:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.145.11-13">145:11-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.6.5">Is 6:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.46.18">Jer 46:18</a>). Although God is not the earthly King of Israel, other references speak of a day when God shall become King and shall rule over his people (<a href="?bref=Isa.24.23">Is 24:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.33.22">33:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.52.7">52:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Obad.1.21">Ob 1:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.15">Zep 3:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.14.9-11">Zec 14:9-11</a>).</p>
<p>This brief summary of God’s kingship provides the outline for the entire OT concept. While God is King over all the earth, he is in a special way King over his people, Israel. God’s rule is therefore something realized in Israel’s history. However, it is only partially and imperfectly realized. Israel again and again rebelled against the divine sovereignty. Furthermore, Israel was constantly plagued by wars with its pagan neighbors in which it was not always victorious. Again, there are evils in nature and the physical world that often bring suffering to God’s people. Therefore, the prophets look forward to a day when God’s rule will be fully experienced, not by Israel alone, but by all the world. The main emphasis of the prophets is on hope, the establishing of God’s perfect rule in the world.</p>
<p>The prophets describe the final establishment of God’s kingdom in terms of a theophany—a divine visitation (<a href="?bref=Mic.1.3-4">Mi 1:3-4</a>). Zechariah foresees a “Day of the Lord” when all nations will be gathered in battle against Jerusalem, when the Lord will go forth and fight against those nations (<a href="?bref=Zech.14.3,5">Zec 14:3, 5</a>). Israel will be visited by the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.29.6">Is 29:6</a>) and delivered from its enemies (<a href="?bref=Isa.35.4">35:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.59.20">59:20</a>). God’s coming will also mean judgment (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.21">2:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.26.21">26:21</a>). This final coming of God will mean the salvation of the Gentiles as well as of Israel (<a href="?bref=Zech.2.10-11">Zec 2:10-11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.66.18-24">Is 66:18-24</a>).</p>
<p>Behind this language is a distinct theology of “the God who comes.” It is a fact widely recognized in contemporary OT theology that the God of the OT is not a nature god, like the gods of other peoples, but a God of history—a God who visits his people in history to bless or to judge them. God visited Israel in Egypt to deliver them from bondage and to constitute them as his people. The rescue from Egypt was not merely an act of deliverance; it was an act through which God made himself known and through which Israel was to know and serve him. </p>
<p>Because God has visited his people again and again in their history, he must finally come to them in the future to judge wickedness and to establish his kingdom. Israel’s hope is thus rooted in history, or rather in the God who works in history. God will finally break into history in a glorious theophany to establish his rule in all the earth. The source of the kingdom is not history itself but God.</p>
<p>While the prophets visualize the kingdom as coming from God, the kingdom is always on earth. The divine irruption into the natural order is not designed to accomplish its destruction but to make way for a new, perfect order arising out of the old, imperfect one. The prophets do not present a single consistent picture of the new order. Sometimes the new order is described very much in this-worldly terms. “The terraced vineyards on the hills of Israel will drip with sweet wine” (<a href="?bref=Amos.9.13">Am 9:13</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). On the other hand, God will create new heavens and a new earth (<a href="?bref=Isa.65.17">Is 65:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.66.22">66:22</a>), where there will be untroubled joy, prosperity, peace, and righteousness. The final visitation of God will mean the redemption of the world, for a redeemed earth is the scene of the kingdom of God. The prophets look forward again and again to the deliverance of creation “from the bondage to decay.” The description is often couched in simple physical terms. The wilderness will become fruitful (<a href="?bref=Isa.32.15">32:15</a>); the desert will blossom (<a href="?bref=Isa.35.2">35:2</a>); sorrow and sighing will flee away (v <a href="?bref=Isa.35.10">10</a>). The burning sands will be cooled and the dry places become springs of water (v <a href="?bref=Isa.35.7">7</a>); peace will return to the animal world so that all injury and destruction are done away with (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.6">11:6</a>). All this results because the earth becomes full of the knowledge of God (v <a href="?bref=Isa.11.9">9</a>).</p>
<p>Such language is not mere poetry but reflects a profound theology of creation. Humans as creatures were made to dwell on the earth, and the earth shares in human destiny. The main point is that creation as such is good and not a hindrance to true spirituality, as was often true in Greek thought. Redemption always includes redemption of the earth, which then becomes the blessed environment God intended it to be. Salvation does not mean deliverance from creaturehood, for this is not an evil thing but an essential and permanent element of true, human existence. Salvation does not mean escape from bodily creaturely existence, as in some Greek thought. On the contrary, ultimate redemption will mean the redemption of the whole person. The emergence of the doctrine of bodily resurrection is a reflection of this theology of creaturehood. The corollary of this is that creation in its entirety must share in the blessing of redemption.</p>
<p>A distinctive element in prophetic eschatology is the tension between history and eschatology. That is, as the prophets looked into the future, they saw an immediate historical judgment as well as a more remote eschatological visitation. For Amos, the Day of the Lord is both the immediate judgment of Israel by the Assyrians and a final eschatological salvation. Joel sees an imminent historical visitation of drought and locusts, but beyond this he sees the eschatological Day of the Lord. Zephaniah sees an imminent Day of the Lord in some undesignated historical visitation (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.2-18">Zep 1:2-18</a>), but beyond it he sees the salvation of the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Zeph.3.9">3:9</a>). The same God who acts in history to bless and judge his people will act at the end of history in an eschatological act of judgment and salvation. The prophets do not sharply distinguish between these two days, for it is one and the same God who is concerned to judge and save his people.</p>
<p>The eschatological hope of the prophets is always an ethical hope. That is to say, the prophets are not interested in the future for its own sake but for the impact of the future on the present. The prophetic predictions were given that, in light of future judgment and salvation, Israel might be confronted in the present by the will of God. “Prepare to meet your God as he comes in judgment, you people of Israel” (<a href="?bref=Amos.4.12">Am 4:12</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>) might well be taken as the keynote of all the prophets.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="h3">The Synoptic Gospels</p>
<p class="fl">Jesus’ teachings about the kingdom of God embodied the same contrast between the present order and the future age as that of the prophets, and he expressed it in the idiom “this age and the age to come.” This fact is obscured in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>, which translates the word for “age” by “world.” These are, however, two different concepts. A rich man asked Jesus what he must do to inherit eternal life (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.17">Mk 10:17</a>). The context makes it clear that he was asking about eschatological life—the life of the resurrection (<a href="?bref=Dan.12.2">Dn 12:2</a>). Jesus speaks of the difficulty of entering the kingdom of God. (The parallel passage in <a href="?bref=Matt.19.23-24">Matthew 19:23-24</a> has both “kingdom of God” and “kingdom of heaven,” proving that they are interchangeable terms.) In their reaction the disciples ask, “Then who can be saved?” Jesus’ answer contrasts the lot of his disciples “in this time” with the “age to come” (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.29-30">Mk 10:29-30</a>) when they would inherit eternal life. It is clear from this passage that in some sense the kingdom of God, the kingdom of heaven, salvation, and eternal life all belong to the age to come. So far as this saying is concerned, God’s people will not experience eternal life until they do so in the new age.</p>
<p>Matthew alone records the expression “the close of the age.” This age will be terminated by the coming of the Son of Man (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.3">Mt 24:3</a>) and by the judgment of humanity (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.39-42">13:39-42</a>). Then the righteous will be separated from the wicked (v <a href="?bref=Matt.13.49">49</a>). The same expression occurs in the promise of the risen Jesus assuring his disciples of his presence until the consummation of the age (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.20">28:20</a>). It follows that if this age is to come to its consummation, it must be followed by another age—the age to come.</p>
<p>The eschatological kingdom will be inaugurated by an apocalyptic event—the glorious coming of the Son of Man. This is made clear by two of the parables about the kingdom of God. In the parable of the tares, “the Son of man will send his angels, and they will gather out of his kingdom all causes of sin and all evildoers, and throw them into the furnace of fire” (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.41-42">Mt 13:41-42</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The parable of the sheep and goats reflects the same eschatology. When the Son of Man comes in his glory, he will sit on his glorious throne to judge the nations, separating the sheep from the goats. The righteous—the sheep—are to “inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world”; and entrance into the kingdom is synonymous with entrance into life (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.31-46">25:31-46</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>The eschatological character of the kingdom of God is seen also in the other two parables of <a href="?bref=Matt.25.1-46">Matthew 25</a>. “The kingdom of heaven shall be compared to ten maidens who took their lamps and went to meet the bridegroom” (v <a href="?bref=Matt.25.1">1</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). However, five of them were foolish and did not provide an adequate supply of oil for their lamps. Thus they were late for the wedding and were excluded from the wedding feast—a symbol of the eschatological kingdom—while those properly prepared entered the kingdom. In the same way the two faithful servants who had been “faithful over a little” were granted to “enter into the joy of your master” (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.25.21,23">21, 23</a>), while the unfaithful servant was excluded from the kingdom and cast into outer darkness.</p>
<p>Jesus almost never showed any interest in descriptions of the eschatological kingdom, but it is clear that its coming was constantly in his thoughts. The pure in heart will see God (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.8">Mt 5:8</a>). The harvest will take place and the grain will be gathered into the barn (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.30,39">13:30, 39</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.29">Mk 4:29</a>). Jesus frequently used the metaphor of a feast or table fellowship to describe life in the eschatological kingdom. He will drink wine again with his disciples in the kingdom of God. They will eat and drink at Jesus’ table in the kingdom (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.30">Lk 22:30</a>). People will be gathered from all corners of the earth to sit at a table with the OT saints (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.11-12">Mt 8:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.29">Lk 13:29</a>). The consummation is likened to a wedding feast (<a href="?bref=Matt.22.1-14">Mt 22:1-14</a>) and a banquet (<a href="?bref=Luke.14.16-24">Lk 14:16-24</a>). All of these metaphors picture the restoration of communion between God and people, a union that had been broken by sin.</p>
<p>In most of the sayings cited to illustrate the future character of the kingdom, “kingdom” refers to the eschatological order—the eschaton, the age to come. However, when Jesus taught his disciples to pray “Thy kingdom come” (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.10">Mt 6:10</a>), he was not referring to the new eschatological order; he was referring to the kingdom as God’s kingly rule, his reign. It is a prayer that God will effectively establish his sovereign rule in the world.</p>
<p>In his teaching about the kingdom of God as the apocalyptic consummation, Jesus does not differ essentially from the OT prophets. The most distinctive element in Jesus’ teaching—indeed, the fact that characterizes his entire mission and message—is the fact that in some real sense of the word, the kingdom of God has come in history in an utterly unexpected way. This sets Jesus’ teaching apart from all contemporary Jewish thought.</p>
<p>This is seen first of all in his repeated teaching that his mission is a fulfillment of the OT messianic prophets. Mark summarizes Jesus’ message with the words “The Kingdom of God is near! Turn from your sins and believe this Good News!” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.15">Mk 1:15</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). This saying can have one of two meanings. It may refer to the imminent coming of the apocalyptic kingdom. Matthew summarizes the message of John the Baptist with nearly the same words: “Turn from your sins and turn to God, because the Kingdom of Heaven is near” (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.2">Mt 3:2</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The Baptist expounds what he means by the approach of the kingdom of God: “He is ready to separate the chaff from the grain with his winnowing fork. Then he will clean up the threshing area, storing the grain in his barn but burning the chaff with never-ending fire” (v <a href="?bref=Matt.3.12">12</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). John proclaimed an apocalyptic act; “unquenchable fire” can mean no strictly historical event but only an apocalyptic judgment. John expected Jesus to be the one in whom the cosmic event expected by the prophets would be carried out.</p>
<p>It is possible that this was also Jesus’ meaning. However, another interpretation is possible that is better supported by the actual course of his mission: “The time is fulfilled.” The messianic promises of the prophets were not only about to be fulfilled; they were actually in process of fulfillment in his mission. In Jesus, God was visiting his people. The hope of the prophets in some real sense was being realized.</p>
<p>The meaning of this can be seen in Luke’s introduction of Jesus’ ministry. Luke selects an event that occurred in Nazareth later in Jesus’ ministry (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.16-21">Lk 4:16-21</a>) and places it at the beginning of his Gospel in order to sound this note of fulfillment. Jesus read from Isaiah a promise that looked forward to the messianic salvation: “The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, for he has appointed me to preach Good News to the poor. He has sent me to proclaim that captives will be released, that the blind will see, that the downtrodden will be freed from their oppressors, and that the time of the Lord’s favor has come” (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.4.18-19">18-19</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Then Jesus astonished his audience by the assertion “This Scripture has come true today before your very eyes!” (v <a href="?bref=Luke.4.21">21</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Here was an amazing claim. John the Baptist had announced an apocalyptic visitation of God that would mean the fulfillment of the eschatological hope and the consummation of the messianic age. Jesus proclaimed that the messianic promise was actually being fulfilled in his person. This is no apocalyptic kingdom but a present salvation. In these words Jesus did not proclaim the imminence of the apocalyptic kingdom. Rather, he boldly announced that the kingdom of God had come. The presence of the kingdom was a happening, an event, the gracious action of God. This was no new theology or new idea or new promise; it was a new event in history.</p>
<p>The note of fulfillment is again sounded in Jesus’ answer to the question about fasting. “Do wedding guests fast while celebrating with the groom? Of course not. They can’t fast while they are with the groom” (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.19">Mk 2:19</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The marriage feast had become a metaphor in Judaism for the messianic consummation. In these words Jesus announced the presence of the messianic time of salvation. It would be a contradiction in terms for the disciples to fast when they were enjoying the blessings of the messianic age. The time of fulfillment had come.</p>
<p>A saying found in different contexts in Matthew and Luke touches this central note of the fulfillment in history of the OT hope: “Blessed are the eyes which see what you see! For I tell you that many prophets and kings desired to see what you see, and did not see it, and to hear what you hear, and did not hear it” (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.23-24">Lk 10:23-24</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.13.16-17">Mt 13:16-17</a>). Both Matthew and Luke associate this saying with the kingdom of God, and both agree that the hope of former generations has become an object of experience. Many prophets and kings looked forward to something, but they looked in vain, for it did not come to them. What they longed for has now come, and this can be nothing less than the promised messianic salvation.</p>
<p>Fulfillment in history is again asserted in Jesus’ answer to John’s question about the one who is to come (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.2-3">Mt 11:2-3</a>). “The deeds of the Christ” (Messiah) were not the deeds John had announced. Wicked rulers like Herod were not being judged in fire. Instead, Jesus was helping people, not bringing an apocalyptic kingdom. Jesus replied in words that echo the promise of the messianic salvation in <a href="?bref=Isa.35.5-6">Isaiah 35:5-6</a>: “Go and tell John what you hear and see: the blind receive their sight and the lame walk, lepers are cleansed and the deaf hear, and the dead are raised up, and the poor have the gospel preached to them” (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.4-5">Mt 11:4-5</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). In these words Jesus claimed that the blessings of the messianic salvation are present. There was indeed reason for John’s perplexity, for the fulfillment was not taking place along expected lines. The apocalyptic consummation did not appear to be on the horizon. The point of Jesus’ answer was that fulfillment was taking place without the eschatological consummation. Therefore, Jesus pronounced a special blessing upon those who were not offended by the character of the messianic fulfillment (v <a href="?bref=Matt.11.6">6</a>). The fulfillment was indeed taking place, but not the apocalyptic consummation.</p>
<p>The most unambiguous statement of the presence of the kingdom is found in the words about the binding of Satan. One of Jesus’ most characteristic acts was the exorcism of demons—deliverance from satanic power. The Pharisees admitted his power but attributed it to Satan. Jesus replied, “If Satan casts out Satan, he is divided against himself; how then will his kingdom stand? . . . But if it is by the Spirit of God that I cast out demons, then the kingdom of God is come upon you” (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.26,28">Mt 12:26, 28</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Here the verb has the clear meaning “to come, to arrive” (cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.9.30">Rom 9:30</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.10.14">2 Cor 10:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.3.16">Phil 3:16</a>). Here is a clear affirmation that the kingdom of God has come among men.</p>
<p>In explanation Jesus said, “Or how can one enter a strong man’s house and plunder his goods, unless he first binds the strong man? Then indeed he may plunder his house” (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.29">Mt 12:29</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The strong man is Satan; this “present evil age” (<a href="?bref=Gal.1.4">Gal 1:4</a>) is his “house”; his “goods” are demon-possessed men and women. Jesus has invaded the strong man’s house to snatch away from him men and women whom he has in his power, and this is the work of the kingdom of God. The kingly reign of God has come into history in the person of Jesus before the apocalyptic consummation when Satan will be destroyed, to render Satan a preliminary defeat. Jesus has already “bound” Satan (i.e., curbed his power). This has been accomplished by the presence of the kingdom of God in the mission of Jesus.</p>
<p>A similar saying is found in <a href="?bref=Luke.10.18">Luke 10:18</a>. Jesus had sent a band of his disciples on a preaching mission. Like Jesus, they were to proclaim the nearness of the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.9">Lk 10:9</a>). They, too, were to exorcize demons. When they returned to Jesus to report their success, Jesus said, “I saw Satan fall like lightning from heaven” (v <a href="?bref=Luke.10.18">18</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). This again is metaphorical language that asserts that in the mission of Jesus’ disciples, as well as in Jesus himself, Satan has fallen from his place of power. Both “binding” and “falling” are metaphors that describe the same truth: the victory of the kingdom of God over Satan.</p>
<p>Here is the element that sets Jesus apart from the OT and from all of contemporary Judaism. The prophets conceived of the kingdom being established by a heavenly supernatural being (<a href="?bref=Dan.7.1-28">Dn 7</a>) or ruled by a powerful Davidic messianic king (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.1-21">Is 9</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1-16">11</a>). The fulfillment of the messianic hope is everywhere in the prophets an eschatological hope. The same is true of the Jewish writers who despaired of history and cast all hope into the future.</p>
<p>In contrast to all that had gone before him, Jesus proclaimed the kingdom of God as an event taking place in his own person and mission. God had again assumed the initiative; God was acting. No first-century Jew had any idea of the kingdom of God coming into history in the person of an ordinary man—a teacher who was meek and lowly.</p>
<p>The presence of the kingdom is further seen in the fact that the rule of God, present in Jesus, is a gift to be received. This is also true of the kingdom in its eschatological consummation, where the kingdom is freely inherited by the righteous (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.34">Mt 25:34</a>). In answer to the young man’s question about inheriting eternal life (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.17">Mk 10:17</a>), Jesus spoke of entering the kingdom (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.10.23-24">23-24</a>) and receiving the gift of eternal life (v <a href="?bref=Mark.10.30">30</a>) as though they were synonymous. The kingdom is a gift that the Father is pleased to bestow upon the little flock of Jesus’ disciples (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.32">Lk 12:32</a>).</p>
<p>If God’s eschatological rule brings to his people the blessings of that kingdom, and if God’s kingdom is his rule invading history before the eschatological consummation, then we may expect God’s rule in the present to bring a preliminary blessing to his people. This fact is reflected in numerous sayings. The kingdom is something to be sought here and now (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.33">Mt 6:33</a>) and to be received as children receive a gift (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.15">Mk 10:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.18.16-17">Lk 18:16-17</a>). Although it is present in an unexpected form, the kingdom of God in Jesus’ person is like a hidden treasure or a pearl of great price whose possession outranks all other goods (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.44-46">Mt 13:44-46</a>). The gift of the kingdom is also seen in that the deaf hear, the blind see, lepers are cleansed, and the poor have good news preached to them (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.5">11:5</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">John’s Gospel</p>
<p class="fl">In the Gospel of John the concept of eternal life takes the place of the kingdom of God in Jesus’ teaching. The kingdom of God is mentioned twice (<a href="?bref=John.3.3,5">Jn 3:3, 5</a>), and it is placed in connection with eternal life. The kingdom of God is here the eschatological kingdom, and eternal life is the life of the kingdom. Thus, as the kingdom of God in the synoptic Gospels is both future and present, so eternal life is both the life of the age to come (<a href="?bref=John.12.25">12:25</a>) and also a present blessing (<a href="?bref=John.3.16">3:16</a>, etc.).</p>
<p class="h3">Acts</p>
<p class="fl">In Acts it seems the earliest disciples generally failed to understand Jesus’ message about the kingdom of God as a present spiritual blessing. They gathered together to await the coming of the eschatological kingdom to Israel (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.6">Acts 1:6</a>). Acts relates that the disciples continued to preach the kingdom of God, but usually it is an eschatological blessing (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.12">8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.14.22">14:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.19.8">19:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.20.25">20:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.28.23,31">28:23, 31</a>). However, the last two references make the kingdom of God synonymous with the gospel about Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>One important theme in Acts is linked to that of the kingdom of God. On the Day of Pentecost, Peter announces that God has seated Jesus at his right hand in fulfillment of <a href="?bref=Ps.110.1">Psalm 110:1</a> (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.33-35">Acts 2:33-35</a>). In the Psalms this is a prophecy of the enthronement of the Davidic king in Jerusalem. Peter asserts that this prophecy is now fulfilled in the heavenly reign of Jesus. Therefore, he has been made both Lord and Christ (Messiah). These are interchangeable terms, “Lord” meaning absolute sovereign, “Christ” meaning the messianic king.</p>
<p class="h3">Paul’s Writings</p>
<p class="fl">Paul carried further this theme of the heavenly rule of Christ, the anointed King. The kingdom is both an eschatological inheritance (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.9">1 Cor 6:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.50">15:50</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.21">Gal 5:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.5">Eph 5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.2.12">1 Thes 2:12</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.1.5">2 Thes 1:5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.4.1,18">2 Tm 4:1, 18</a>) and a present blessing into which believers now enter (<a href="?bref=Rom.14.17">Rom 14:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.13">Col 1:13</a>). The key to this is the interchangeable character of lordship and messianic kingship. Jesus is now exalted as Lord over all (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.11">Phil 2:11</a>), and even as his lordship is invisible, it will become manifest to all at his second coming. In the same way, he has been enthroned as messianic King by virtue of his resurrection and heavenly session, and he must reign as King until he has put all his enemies under his feet (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.25">1 Cor 15:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.22">Eph 1:22</a>). The last enemy to be destroyed is death.</p>
<p class="h3">Revelation</p>
<p class="fl">The central message of the Revelation to John is the consummation of God’s redemptive purpose, when the kingdom of this world becomes the kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ (<a href="?bref=Rev.11.15">Rv 11:15</a>). Revelation pictures the plight of a persecuted church in a hostile world, but it assures the church that Christ has already won a victory over the powers of evil (<a href="?bref=Rev.5.5">5:5</a>), by virtue of which he can finally destroy them (<a href="?bref=Rev.19.11-20.14">19:11–20:14</a>). Again, the last enemy to be destroyed is death (<a href="?bref=Rev.20.13-14">20:13-14</a>). Revelation closes with a highly symbolic picture of the kingdom of God (chs <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-22.21">21–22</a>) when God comes to dwell among his people, and “they shall see his face” (<a href="?bref=Rev.22.4">22:4</a>). Thus the NT ends: divine order is restored to a disordered world. This is the kingdom of God.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Teachings of</a>; <a href="?item=King_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">King</a>; <a href="?item=Parable_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Parable</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="TheMysteryOfTheKingdom"/>
  </body>
</item>