<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="UnpardonableSinthe">
  <title>Unpardonable Sin*, the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">UNPARDONABLE SIN*, The</p>
<p class="fl">Attributing to Satan what is actually the work of the Holy Spirit as demonstrated through Jesus Christ. This sin is blasphemy against the Holy Spirit.</p>
<p>The unpardonable sin must be defined by its context, which is found in <a href="?bref=Matt.12.31-32">Matthew 12:31-32</a> and <a href="?bref=Mark.3.28-30">Mark 3:28-30</a>. In these passages, Jesus had just cast a demon from a man who was blind and mute. Incontrovertible evidence of the power of God had just occurred. But the Pharisees, with stubborn unbelief, credited this display of God’s power to Beelzebul, the devil (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.24">Mt 12:24</a>). Several Scriptures reveal that many Jews had expressed the same kind of fallacious opinion, namely, that Jesus was performing miracles by the power of the devil (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.34">Mt 9:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.11.18">11:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.33">Lk 7:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.14-20">11:14-20</a>; <a href="?bref=John.7.20">Jn 7:20</a>; <a href="?bref=John.8.48,52">8:48, 52</a>; <a href="?bref=John.10.20">10:20</a>). A group of Jews, mostly Pharisees, were guilty of attributing to the devil what was the work of the Spirit demonstrated through the Lord Jesus. They committed <span class="ital">the</span> unpardonable sin when they said that Jesus’ actions, performed by the power of the Holy Spirit, originated from Beelzebul, the devil. Put simply, they sinned grievously by boldly characterizing Jesus’ work as coming from the devil. Interestingly, many Jews perpetuated this false characterization about Jesus long after his death. They did not deny that he did miracles; they said he did miracles by the power of the devil.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WhatIsnttheUnpardonableSin">What Isn’t the Unpardonable Sin</p>
<p class="fl">The unpardonable sin is not Israel’s rebellion against God, even though this rebellion resulted in the eternal judgment of thousands and a temporary elimination of God’s blessing. The “sin unto death” mentioned by John (<a href="?bref=1Jn.5.16-17">1 Jn 5:16-17</a>) is not the unpardonable sin. It would be impossible for a person who has redemption and the forgiveness of sin (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.7">Eph 1:7</a>), cleansing for present and future sin (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.7">1 Jn 1:7</a>), and eternal life (<a href="?bref=John.3.16">Jn 3:16</a>) to commit an unpardonable sin. But those who commit the “sin unto death” are all Christians. <a href="?bref=1Jn.5.16">First John 5:16</a> says the person who commits the “sin unto death” is a “brother” in Christ.</p>
<p>The unpardonable sin is not rejection of the Lord Jesus, until the rejecter dies in his unbelief. Such a sin will not be forgiven throughout eternity, but it is not the same sin as that which Jesus condemned with these words: “Anyone who blasphemes against me, the Son of Man, can be forgiven, but blasphemy against the Holy Spirit will never be forgiven, either in this world or in the world to come” (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.32">Mt 12:32</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Numerous passages repeat the warning that unbelief in the Savior results in eternal death (<a href="?bref=John.3.18,36">Jn 3:18, 36</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.5.12">1 Jn 5:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.20.15">Rv 20:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.8">21:8</a>), but these Scriptures do not directly speak of the unpardonable sin. Jesus asserted that a person could be an unbeliever in him, even to the degree of speaking against him, yet not be guilty of the unpardonable sin.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=JustificationJustified_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Justification, Justified</a>; <a href="?item=SinuntoDeath_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sin unto Death</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>