<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Uzziel">
  <title>Uzziel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">UZZIEL</p>
<p class="list">1. Youngest of the sons of Kohath of Levi’s tribe, who became the head of the Uzzielite division of the Kohathites (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.18">Ex 6:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.19,27,30">Nm 3:19, 27, 30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.26.23">1 Chr 26:23</a>). He was Aaron’s uncle, and his sons, Mishael and Elzaphan, carried Nadab and Abihu out of the camp when they rebelled against Aaron’s authority (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.22">Ex 6:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.10.4">Lv 10:4</a>). Several of his descendants were significant during Israel’s history, including Amminadab, who officiated over David’s transfer of the ark to Jerusalem, and Micah and Isshiah, who were chiefs among the Levites during the reign of Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.10">1 Chr 15:10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.20">23:20</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Son of Ishi who was one of the leaders of the Simeonite warriors who defeated the Ammonites at Seir during the reign of Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.42">1 Chr 4:42</a>). As a result of defeating the Amalekites, who had not been defeated earlier by Saul or David, the Simeonites inherited the land.</p>
<p class="list">3. Benjaminite clan chief who is listed as the son of Bela, the son of Benjamin (<a href="?bref=1Chr.7.7">1 Chr 7:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Son of Heman of the Levite clan of Asaph (<a href="?bref=1Chr.25.4">1 Chr 25:4</a>). A variant name is Azarel (v <a href="?bref=1Chr.25.18">18</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg).</p>
<p class="list">5. Levite who participated in the reconsecration of the temple under Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.14">2 Chr 29:14</a>), listed as the son of Jeduthun.</p>
<p class="list">6. Goldsmith who worked on rebuilding the gates of Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.8">Neh 3:8</a>). His name indicates that he was likely a priest who had the responsibility of making and repairing the temple instruments and vessels (cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.29">1 Chr 9:29</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>