<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WillofGod">
  <title>Will of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WILL OF GOD</p>
<p class="fl">Important NT term indicating God’s choice and determination, emanating from desire.</p>
<p>Paul used a Greek word in <a href="?bref=Eph.1.5,9">Ephesians 1:5, 9</a>, and <a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">11</a> that conveys the idea of desire, even heart’s desire. The word is usually translated as “will”—“the will of God.” But the English word “will” sublimates the primary meaning. The Greek word <span class="ital">(</span><span class="greek">thelema</span><span class="ital">)</span> is primarily an emotional word and only secondarily is it volitional. “God’s will” is not so much “God’s intention” as it is “God’s heart’s desire.” God does have an intention, a purpose, a plan. It is called <span class="greek">prothesis</span> in Greek (see <a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">Eph 1:11</a>), and it literally means “a laying out beforehand” (like a blueprint). This plan was created by God’s counsel (called <span class="greek">boule</span> in Greek, <a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">Eph 1:11</a>). However, behind the plan and the counsel was not just a mastermind but a heart—a heart of love and of good pleasure. Therefore, Paul talked about “the good pleasure of God’s heart” (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.5">Eph 1:5</a>). Paul also said, “He made known to us the mystery of his heart’s desire, according to his good pleasure which he purposed in him” (v <a href="?bref=Eph.1.9">9</a>). Indeed, God operated all things according to the counsel of his heart’s desire or will (v <a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">11</a>).</p>
<p>The impetus of God’s eternal purpose came from a heart’s desire, and that heart’s desire was to have many sons and daughters made like his only Son (see <a href="?bref=Rom.8.26-28">Rom 8:26-28</a>). In love, he predestined many people to participate in this—not by their own merits but by virtue of being in the Son (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.4-5">Eph 1:4-5</a>). Notice how often in <a href="?bref=Eph.1.1-23">Ephesians 1</a> Paul speaks of the believers’ position “in him.” Outside of him (the Son), no one could be a son or daughter of God and no one could be pleasing to the Father. The many sons and daughters owe all their divine privileges to the Beloved, as ones graced in him and selected in him (v <a href="?bref=Eph.1.6">6</a>). Thus, predestination and election are issues of God’s will.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ElectElection_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Elect, Election</a>; <a href="?item=Predestination_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Predestination</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>