<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Woman">
  <title>Woman</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WOMAN</p>
<p class="fl">Man’s companion created by God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HerCreation">Her Creation</p>
<p class="fl">Genesis provides two accounts of the creation of the first man and woman. In the first, <a href="?bref=Gen.1.26-28">Genesis 1:26-28</a>, God created humans in his image, as male and female. Hence, the female shares with the male the image of God, reflects his power and majesty on earth, and is commanded to multiply and bring dominion to the earth. From <a href="?bref=Gen.1.26-28">Genesis 1:26-28</a> there is no suggestion of inferiority of the female to the male, nor is there any suggestion of her submission to his dominance. Rather, they are pictured together, the male and the female, as the representation of their Maker.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Gen.2.20-25">Genesis 2:20-25</a> is the second portrayal of the creation of the first woman. In <a href="?bref=Gen.2.1-25">Genesis 2</a> the male was made before the female, a point that seems to give him some precedence. This may not be pressed too far, however, as the pattern in the creation texts is to move progressively from the lesser to the finer work! Yet it is because of his prior creation that the male is given the prerogative to name the female (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.23">Gn 2:23</a>). In Semitic thought, the giving of names signifies dominion or ownership. This means that Adam’s naming of his wife was an act of lordship. However, the name that he gives her is the equivalent to his own, meaning the male affirmed her equality with him. Paradoxically, then, this hierarchical relationship is also a relationship of equals.</p>
<p>The situation in <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Genesis 1</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.2.1-25">2</a> reveals a balanced relationship between the man and the woman who were the parents of all mankind: two persons who were altogether equal in status as coheirs of the mystery of the image of God and yet who dwell in a delicate one-to-one relationship in which one is the leader of the other. In Eden before the fall, this delicate balance was possible.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HerDownfallandPlight">Her Downfall and Plight</p>
<p class="fl"><a href="?bref=Gen.3.1-24">Genesis 3</a>, the story of the fall of mankind, speaks of the breaking of the delicate balance between the man and the woman and the ensuing struggles that have been passed down through the ages. In God’s words to the woman, he announced the pain that would accompany her childbearing (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.16">Gn 3:16</a>) and the conflict of interests that would affect her relationship with her husband: “Your desire will be for your husband, and he will rule over you” (<span class="sc">niv</span>). The Hebrew term “desire” <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">teshuqah</span><span class="ital">)</span> in the <a href="?bref=Gen.3.1-24">Genesis 3</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.4.1-26">4</a> passages is not a sexual longing but a desire to control, to master, to be in charge (the use of <span class="hebrew">teshuqah</span> meaning sexual desire is seen in <a href="?bref=Song.7.10">Sg 7:10</a>). Consequently, after the fall, the desire of woman has been to dominate her husband. Her determination to reject his leadership in their relationship of equals is a breaking of the balance in their relationship. For his part, the man tends to tyrannize the woman.</p>
<p>To the women who attempt to dominate their husbands, the apostle Paul says, “Wives, submit to your husbands as to the Lord” (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.22">Eph 5:22</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Her natural inclination needs transformation, so that she can submit to her husband as she submits to the Lord. For, Paul argues, the husband is to the wife as Christ is to the church (v <a href="?bref=Eph.5.23">23</a>). The husbands who tend to dominate their wives also need transformation so that they can love their wives, “just as Christ loved the church and gave himself up for her” (v <a href="?bref=Eph.5.25">25</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). By these words, the apostle Paul was presenting a means whereby couples could regain the bliss in their relationship that was the mark of Eden before the fall. Paul’s citation of <a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Genesis 2:24</a> in <a href="?bref=Eph.5.31">Ephesians 5:31</a> is a case in point: here a couple may regain the original oneness that God intended for them. The relationship of equal persons in a hierarchy of responsiveness is stated in the context of mutual submission, which is a mark of their greater submission to the Lord Jesus.</p>
<p class="h2" id="HerRoleinLifeaccordingtotheBible">Her Role in Life according to the Bible</p>
<p class="fl">A woman is a person in every respect as a man; she shares in the image of God and has the potential of varied ranges of response to culture, community, and life about her. It is a fact of Scripture that women are regularly associated with, and find their sense of worth in, childbearing. Yet the same Scriptures show that the nature of woman is not exhausted by associations with childbearing: she has her own identity in the community, in the church, and before the Lord in the whole of her life, not just when (or if) she bears and nourishes a child. Further, the biblical concept of childbearing always involves the husband, who is her partner at conception, at her side during delivery, and partner with her in the ongoing task of nourishing the child.</p>
<p>The image of the woman as the childbearer begins with the promise of God in <a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Genesis 3:15</a>, where he announced the ultimate victory over the evil one, Satan, by the offspring of the woman. This promise respecting the offspring of the woman became the universal blessing of God upon woman as the childbearer. Ultimately, through one born of a woman, there would come the final deliverance. There is a sense in which each birth experience is a participation in the continuity of this promise (see <a href="?bref=1Tim.2.15">1 Tm 2:15</a> and its possible relationship to this continuity of women, salvation, and childbearing).</p>
<p>Further, in the culture of the OT world, a woman’s genuine worth was solely, or largely, perceived in terms of childbearing. Yet it is not in childbearing alone that she finds worth and dignity before God. For the woman, as for the man, the issue of faith in the Lord is central. A woman who has a household of children but no faith in God might regard herself as a fulfilled person. Yet her care of her children is no substitute for piety to God. A woman who has no children, and perhaps no husband, may have her full identity and worth in her relationship with the God in whose image she is made and whose tasks she is commissioned by him to do. The gifts of God in a woman’s life may lead her to find opportunities in the community to express her devotion to God. Women apparently had the same opportunities as men to take a Nazirite vow (<a href="?bref=Num.6.2">Nm 6:2</a>; see also ch <a href="?bref=Num.30.1-16">30</a>).</p>
<p>Certain notable women in the Bible led lives of public service. Miriam, the sister of Moses and Aaron (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.20-21">Ex 15:20-21</a>), was a prophetess, musician, and national leader (<a href="?bref=Num.12.1-16">Nm 12</a>). Long after her time, God spoke through his prophets of the gift he had given to Israel in the person of the national leader Miriam (<a href="?bref=Mic.6.4">Mi 6:4</a>). There were other magnificent women who had exemplary lives: Deborah, the prophetess of God and the only named woman judge of Israel (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.1-5.31">Jgs 4–5</a>); Esther, the Hebrew queen of Xerxes who saved her people from the rash acts of the Persian king, a result of a frightful conspiracy; and Huldah, the prophetess who was the agent of the Lord’s word to Josiah at the inception of his revival (<a href="?bref=2Chr.34.22-28">2 Chr 34:22-28</a>). Huldah’s reception and transmission of the word of the Lord is the more remarkable because she was a contemporary with Jeremiah and Zephaniah. In this case God chose to speak through a woman.</p>
<p>In the NT, certain women were noted for their public ministries: the daughters of Philip, Phoebe, Priscilla, Junias, Tryphena, Tryphosa, Persis, Euodia, and Syntyche. These women mark the beginning of the fulfillment of Joel’s prophecy of a day in which women as well as men would be the instruments of the outpouring of the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-29">Jl 2:28-29</a>). Women such as Sarah, Ruth, and Hannah exercised their faith in God in the context of the home and family as well. And preeminently there is Mary, mother of Jesus, in whom the ideal of womanhood is conjoined to the fulfillment of the ancient promise to Eve that she would one day be the great victor over the enemy of mankind.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Eve_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eve</a>; <a href="?item=Man_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Man</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>