<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WrathofGod">
  <title>Wrath of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WRATH OF GOD</p>
<p class="fl">A term for God’s displeasure with human beings and their sinful actions. The word “wrath” is a concept represented by many different words and idioms in the original languages of the Bible, all of which express the notion of justifiable anger for unjust actions.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT God is said to be angry with nations, sinners, and even with his covenant people. God’s anger is first expressed toward the covenant community of Israel for having refused to believe his word about entering into the Promised Land. After they had been rescued from Egypt, had received the Ten Commandments and the covenant, and had seen his glory (<a href="?bref=Num.11.10">Nm 11:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.12.9">12:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.22.22">22:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.32.10-14">32:10-14</a>), they still disbelieved. Consequently, God in his wrath condemned the Israelites to wander in the wilderness until they died. The major reason for the Lord’s anger in the OT was that his own people constantly broke the covenant. They provoked him by their idolatry (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.15">Dt 2:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.25">4:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.9.7-8,19">9:7-8, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.2.14">Jgs 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.9">1 Kgs 11:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.9,15">14:9, 15</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.18">2 Kgs 17:18</a>), by their mixing paganism with the worship of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.10-17">Is 1:10-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.20">Jer 6:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.6.6">Hos 6:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.21-27">Am 5:21-27</a>); by their wanton rebellion (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.46">1 Kgs 8:46</a>), their unbelief (<a href="?bref=Num.11.33">Nm 11:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.14.11,33">14:11, 33</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.95.10-11">Ps 95:10-11</a>), and their disregard for his concern for love, justice, righteousness, and holiness (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.22-24">Ex 22:22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.15-17">Is 1:15-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.7-12">Am 5:7-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.3.1">Mi 3:1</a>).</p>
<p>The wrath of God also extends to all humanity (<a href="?bref=Nah.1.2">Na 1:2</a>). The concept of the Day of the Lord was developed by the prophets to warn Israel and the nations that no one can escape the righteous expression of God’s wrath (<a href="?bref=Amos.5.18-20">Am 5:18-20</a>). The Day of the Lord is the day of his wrath (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.15">Zep 1:15</a>).</p>
<p>The OT presents the concept of the wrath of God in balance with three other doctrines: his forbearance, his love, and his readiness to forgive. First, God is patient. The Hebrew word for “patient” is related to the word for “wrath” and means “length of wrath”; that is, God does not quickly become angry. He is longsuffering (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6">Ex 34:6</a>). Second, God is full of compassion and fidelity (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6">Ex 34:6</a>). Even when his children sin against him, he is like a father who is full of compassion and love. He is always faithful to his children. Third, he is ready to forgive those who sin against him when they atone for and are cleansed from their sins (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6">Ex 34:6</a>). The pleasure of his love is so much greater than his wrath (<a href="?bref=Ps.30.5">Ps 30:5</a>). Micah prayed that the Lord may soon forgive and restore his people on the ground that he cannot be angry forever (<a href="?bref=Mic.7.18">7:18</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.89.46">Ps 89:46</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.3.5">Jer 3:5</a>). In <a href="?bref=Ps.103.8-13">Psalm 103:8-13</a>, the psalmist likens God’s love and forgiveness to that of a father who does not harbor his anger continually, nor does he vex his children with discipline, so great is his love for those who fear him.</p>
<p>The purpose of God’s wrath is not to destroy humanity (<a href="?bref=Hos.11.9">Hos 11:9</a>). His wrath is neither a vindictive, emotional overreaction, nor is it unpredictable. In his wrath he sovereignly imposes limits on nations (Babylon, Assyria) and disciplines his own people with the desired end that they return to him (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.13-14">Jl 2:13-14</a>). The OT presentation of the Day of the Lord doesn’t end with God’s anger; it concludes with the restoration of the earth, when the whole earth will be filled with knowledge of God (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.9">Is 11:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.2.14">Hb 2:14</a>) and wickedness will be no more (<a href="?bref=Isa.65.25">Is 65:25</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The NT also teaches the wrath of God side by side with the doctrine of his grace, love, and forbearance (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.7">Mt 3:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.21.23">Lk 21:23</a>; <a href="?bref=John.3.36">Jn 3:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.18">Rom 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.6">Eph 5:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.14.10">Rv 14:10</a>). Those who do not profess faith in the risen Christ remain in their sins and will be subject to God’s wrath, whereas those who believe in him are delivered from God’s wrath (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.3">Eph 2:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.10">1 Thes 1:10</a>). The good news of the NT is that Jesus has come to deliver us from the wrath of God (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.9">Rom 5:9</a>). Those who have been delivered are reconciled with God (v <a href="?bref=Rom.5.10">10</a>) because they no longer are under condemnation (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.1">8:1</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Death_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Death</a>; <a href="?item=Hell_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hell</a>; <a href="?item=Judgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judgment</a>; <a href="?item=LastJudgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Last Judgment</a>; <a href="?item=Love_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Love</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>