<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Rachel">
  <title>Rachel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">RACHEL</p>
<p class="fl">Beautiful younger daughter of Laban; she was the favorite wife of Jacob. He first met her as he arrived at Haran in Paddan-aram. There he assisted her by attending to the needs of Rachel’s father’s sheep, removing a stone from the mouth of a well in order to water them (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.10">Gn 29:10</a>). Jacob loved Rachel exceedingly and agreed to work seven years for Laban in return for her hand in marriage. His seven years’ service seemed like only a few days because of his great love for her. Laban deceptively reneged on his bargain and required Jacob to marry Leah, his older, less attractive daughter, before finally giving him Rachel for his wife. Unlike Leah, Rachel was barren in the early years of her marriage to Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.1">30:1</a>). Consequently, she gave her servant, Bilhah, to Jacob in order to have children. Thus, through this commonly accepted ancient custom, Dan and Naphtali were born. In time, Rachel herself conceived and bore Joseph (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.30.22-25">22-25</a>). After this, Jacob took his wives, children, and possessions away from Haran.</p>
<p>Somewhere between Bethel and Bethlehem, Rachel died while giving birth to Benjamin (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.16,19">Gn 35:16, 19</a>). Jacob set up a pillar over her tomb there, a landmark known even in the days of Saul (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.2">1 Sm 10:2</a>). Rachel and Leah are highly regarded as those who built up the house of Israel (<a href="?bref=Ruth.4.11">Ru 4:11</a>). In <a href="?bref=Jer.31.15">Jeremiah 31:15</a>, Rachel is pictured as crying for her children being carried off into captivity. Later, Matthew recalls Jeremiah’s words in Herod’s slaughter of the male infants (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.18">Mt 2:18</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Jacob_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jacob #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>