<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="RahabPerson">
  <title>Rahab (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">RAHAB (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Heroine of the battle of Jericho (<a href="?bref=Josh.2.1-6.27">Jos 2–6</a>). Soon after Moses’ death, God told Joshua that he and the people were to cross the Jordan and occupy the land of promise. Before the crossing, however, Joshua sent two spies into the land to reconnoiter the opposition, in particular the fortified city of Jericho. Upon entering the city, the spies found their way quickly to Rahab’s house, which was perhaps an inn and/or a brothel. She apparently was a prostitute.</p>
<p>News of the arrival of spies was not long in reaching the king of Jericho, who quite naturally demanded that Rahab divulge their whereabouts. She cleverly admitted seeing them but insisted that they had left the city at nightfall. Actually, the spies were hiding under the stalks of flax on the roof of her house. When the king’s search party left Jericho to hunt the spies, Rahab confessed to the spies the reason for her complicity with the Israelites’ cause. She feared the God of the Jews, believing that he would surely give them victory (<a href="?bref=Josh.2.11">Jos 2:11</a>).</p>
<p>For her help, the spies agreed to save Rahab and her family. The sign was to be a cord of scarlet thread hanging from her window, the same avenue the spies used to escape the city. Rahab and her family were indeed the only survivors of the subsequent battle. They were led to safety, on Joshua’s command, by the very men Rahab had saved.</p>
<p>Rahab became the wife of Salmon and mother of Boaz, and thus an ancestor of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.5">Mt 1:5</a>). Rahab is listed, along with Moses, David, Samson, and Samuel, as an example of faith (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.31">Heb 11:31</a>). Her deed is an example of good works and justification (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.25">Jas 2:25</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ConquestandAllotmentoftheLand_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Conquest and Allotment of the Land</a>; <a href="?item=JoshuaBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Joshua, Book of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>