<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ramah">
  <title>Ramah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">RAMAH</p>
<p class="list">1. One of the cities located in the territory allotted to Benjamin’s tribe for an inheritance, listed between Gibeon and Beeroth (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.25">Jos 18:25</a>). In the proximity of this town, Rachel, Jacob’s wife, was buried (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.18">Mt 2:18</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.35.16-21">Gn 35:16-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.31.15">Jer 31:15</a>). Ramah, positioned near Bethel, was the place where Deborah judged Israel (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.5">Jgs 4:5</a>). This city was a temporary resting place for a Levite and his concubine traveling north from Bethlehem (<a href="?bref=Judg.19.13">19:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">During the period of the divided kingdom (930– 722 <span class="era">BC</span>), King Baasha of Israel (908–886 <span class="era">BC</span>) fortified Ramah. From Ramah, Baasha was able to prevent an invasion of King Asa’s (910–869 <span class="era">BC</span>) Judean army. Baasha later abandoned the city and hurried his army north to repulse a Syrian offensive led by King Ben-hadad I (c. 885 <span class="era">BC</span>). Asa dismantled Ramah’s military fortifications, using the material to build the towns of Geba and Mizpah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.17-22">1 Kgs 15:17-22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.16.1-6">2 Chr 16:1-6</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The cities of Geba, Ramah, and Gibeah formed the route taken by the Assyrian army during Sennacherib’s military incursion into Judah (c. 701 <span class="era">BC</span>) against King Hezekiah and Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Isa.10.29">Is 10:29</a>). Later King Nebuchadnezzar used Ramah as a place of detainment for the Jews being deported to Babylon. Here Nebuzaradan, the captain of the guard, released Jeremiah from among the captives (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.1">Jer 40:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Following the Babylonian captivity, inhabitants of Ramah returned with Zerubbabel to Palestine and rebuilt this city (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.26">Ezr 2:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.30">Neh 7:30</a>). Some suggest that the postexilic town of Ramah was another Benjaminite town located farther west near the coastal plain (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.33">Neh 11:33</a>). The site of Ramah is identified with the modern village of er-Ram, five miles (8 kilometers) north of Jerusalem.</p>
<p class="list">2. City in the Negev marking the southern extremity of the territory allotted to the tribe of Simeon within Judah’s inheritance (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.8">Jos 19:8</a>); also called Ramoth of the Negev (<a href="?bref=1Sam.30.27">1 Sm 30:27</a>) and Baalath-beer (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.8">Jos 19:8</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.4.33">1 Chr 4:33</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=BaalathBeer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Baalath-beer</a>.</p>
<p class="list">3. Town defining the boundary of the territory assigned to Asher’s tribe for an inheritance, mentioned between Sidon and Tyre (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.29">Jos 19:29</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. One of 19 fortified cities given to Naphtali’s tribe for a possession, mentioned between Adamah and Hazor (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.36">Jos 19:36</a>). Its location is identifiable with the modern town of er-Rameh, about 11 miles (17.7 kilometers) northwest of the Sea of Galilee.</p>
<p class="list">5. Home of Samuel’s parents, Elkanah and Hannah; the birthplace of Samuel (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.19">1 Sm 1:19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.11">2:11</a>); and later his home (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.17">7:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.16.13">16:13</a>). Samuel judged Israel from Ramah, Bethel, Gilgal, and Mizpah (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.17">7:17</a>). Saul first met Samuel at this city (<a href="?bref=1Sam.9.6-10">9:6-10</a>). Here the elders of Israel petitioned Samuel to appoint a king for them (<a href="?bref=1Sam.8.4">8:4</a>), and later this city provided David a place of refuge from King Saul (<a href="?bref=1Sam.19.18-20.1">19:18–20:1</a>). Samuel was buried at Ramah (<a href="?bref=1Sam.25.1">25:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.28.3">28:3</a>). Ramah is alternately called Ramathaim-zophim in <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.1">1 Samuel 1:1</a>.</p>
<p class="list">6. Abbreviated name for Ramoth-gilead (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.8.29">2 Kgs 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.22.6">2 Chr 22:6</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=RamothGilead_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ramoth-gilead</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>