<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="RamothGilead">
  <title>Ramoth-Gilead</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">RAMOTH-GILEAD</p>
<p class="fl">City lying in the Transjordan area of Gilead and probably identifiable with Tell Ramith, although the site of Tell el-Husn has also been suggested. Initially, biblical references pertain to Ramoth in Gilead (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.43">Dt 4:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.20.8">Jos 20:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.38">21:38</a>), while later it is called Ramoth-gilead. Combined names were used to avoid confusion with cities of the same name in other locations.</p>
<p>Ramoth-gilead, a possession of the tribe of Gad, first appears in the biblical narrative as one of three Transjordan cities of refuge (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.43">Dt 4:43</a>) later included in the six cities of refuge for all Israel (<a href="?bref=Josh.20.8">Jos 20:8</a>). It was allotted to the Merarites as one of 48 Levitical cities (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.38">21:38</a>) and was most likely located along the King’s Highway, which transversed that area.</p>
<p>During the time of Solomon, Ramoth-gilead enjoyed a place of prominence as the central city in his sixth administrative district and the residence of Ben-geber, chief officer of that district (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.13">1 Kgs 4:13</a>). After the division of the kingdom, this border town was taken by the Arameans and became a site of contention between Israel and Aram. King Ahab’s final battle began with his desire to retake Ramoth-gilead. In seeking to convince his ally Jehoshaphat, king of Judah, to support him in this maneuver, he produced many prophets who spoke favorable and victorious words to the king (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.1-53">1 Kgs 22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.18.1-34">2 Chr 18</a>). Unconvinced, Jehoshaphat inquired of the word of the Lord through Micaiah, a prophet of the Lord, who warned of impending disaster. The message was ignored and Ahab was killed at Ramoth-gilead. Ahab’s son Joram also fought with Aram here and was wounded in battle (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.8.29">2 Kgs 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.22.6">2 Chr 22:6</a>; also called Ramah). Shortly thereafter, Elisha sent one of the sons of the prophets to Ramoth-gilead, where he anointed Jehu to be king over Israel (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.1-14">2 Kgs 9:1-14</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CitiesofRefuge_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cities of Refuge</a>; <a href="?item=LeviticalCities_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Levitical Cities</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>