<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Ransom">
  <title>Ransom</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">RANSOM</p>
<p class="fl">Price for redeeming or liberating slaves, captives, property, or life. Jesus described his entire ministry as one of service in giving his life as a ransom for many (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.28">Mt 20:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.45">Mk 10:45</a>). Hence, “ransom” is closely linked to such terms as “redemption” and “salvation,” to the satisfaction Christ made in atonement for sin.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="ToWhomWasTheRansomPaid"/>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT God provided various regulations for his covenant people whereby life and property could be “redeemed,” “bought back,” or “set free” by payment of ransom (cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.25.1-27.34">Lv 25–27</a>). Ransom involved a price paid as a substitute for that which was redeemed or set free.</p>
<p>The OT uses three different Hebrew words for ransom or redemption. Only when there is a clear indication of the payment of a price are these terms translated by “ransom.” But even when another term, such as “redemption,” is used in English translation, a ransom price is usually implied.</p>
<p>One of the Hebrew terms (<span class="hebrew">kopher</span>) means a “cover” or a “covering.” It was a replacement payment made in exchange for punishment. A ransom could be paid to redeem the life of the owner of an ox that had gored a person to death (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.30">Ex 21:30</a>). A half-shekel ransom price was required by God for each Israelite at census taking to prevent a plague (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.12">30:12</a>), and this “atonement money” was an offering to the Lord for use in the tabernacle service. A murderer could not be ransomed, and anyone who found safety in a city of refuge could not be taken back by ransom (<a href="?bref=Num.35.31-32">Nm 35:31-32</a>). It was impossible to avoid death by paying a ransom (<a href="?bref=Ps.49.7-9">Ps 49:7-9</a>). But in a few instances the term takes on the meaning of a “bribe” or “hush money” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.12.3">1 Sm 12:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.6.35">Prv 6:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.12">Am 5:12</a>).</p>
<p>A second Hebrew word-family for “ransom” and “redemption” is related to <span class="hebrew">go’el</span><span class="ital">.</span> <span class="hebrew">Go’el</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning a “reclaimant” or “redeemer,” derives from the root meaning of the Hebrew term “to restore, repair, deliver, rescue.” The term refers to God’s family-law regulations that place various obligations on a relative or kinsman (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.25-55">Lv 25:25-55</a>). The kinsman had the right and duty of redeeming by ransom any family property that a person was compelled to sell (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.25-34">Lv 25:25-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.4-6">Ru 4:4-6</a>); of ransoming a relative who was compelled by poverty to sell himself as a slave to a stranger or sojourner (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.47-55">Lv 25:47-55</a>); and of acting as avenger of the blood of a dead relative, thus enforcing the claim for satisfaction for shedding his blood (<a href="?bref=Num.35.19-27">Nm 35:19-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.20.3-5">Jos 20:3-5</a>). The kinsman was also obligated to marry the wife of a dead brother who had died without leaving children so that the kinsman might raise up seed and the brother’s name not be forgotten in Israel (<a href="?bref=Ruth.3.9-13">Ru 3:9-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.1-12">4:1-12</a>). In a general sense the <span class="hebrew">go’el</span> was a “vindicator” or “redeemer”; a familiar example is Job’s cry for God to vindicate him (<a href="?bref=Job.19.25">Jb 19:25</a>). In the highest sense, God is the kinsman and <span class="hebrew">go’el</span> of Israel, redeeming them from the bondage of Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.5-7">Ex 6:5-7</a>), from captivity in Babylon, and from distress in general (<span class="hebrew">go’el</span> occurs 13 times in <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-46.13">Is 40–46</a>). Thus Israel is called “the ransomed of the Lord” (<a href="?bref=Isa.35.10">Is 35:10</a>), having been “redeemed without money” (<a href="?bref=Isa.52.3">52:3</a>). In such contexts, however, the cost is indicated in terms of God’s might and power.</p>
<p>The OT uses a third Hebrew word (<span class="hebrew">pidyon</span>) from the area of commercial law for ransom or payment. Since God spared the firstborn in Israel at the time of Passover, the first offspring of every womb belonged to God, and the oldest male was redeemed by ransom (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.12-15">Ex 13:12-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.20">34:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.27.27">Lv 27:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.18.15-17">Nm 18:15-17</a>). Later the entire tribe of Levi was set aside as priestly substitutes for the firstborn. Since there were 273 more firstborn than Levites, a payment of five shekels was paid in ransom for each (<a href="?bref=Num.3.40-46">Nm 3:40-46</a>). This term was also used for the price paid to ransom a slave from slavery (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.15">Dt 15:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.18">24:18</a>); a slave concubine could also be ransomed (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.8-11">Ex 21:8-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.19.20">Lv 19:20</a>). God motivates these provisions by his own ransoming of Israel as slaves in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.15">Dt 15:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.18">24:18</a>). This Hebrew term is also applied to God’s deliverance of Israel from Egypt (<a href="?bref=Deut.7.8">Dt 7:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.9.26">9:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.13.5">13:5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.7.23">2 Sm 7:23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.17.21">1 Chr 17:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.42">Ps 78:42</a>) and from Babylonian captivity (<a href="?bref=Isa.35.10">Is 35:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.51.11">51:11</a>). Sometimes God ransoms without reference to a specific occasion (<a href="?bref=Hos.7.13">Hos 7:13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.21.8">Dt 21:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.1.10">Neh 1:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.27">Is 1:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.31.11">Jer 31:11</a>). God also ransoms from the grave (<a href="?bref=Hos.13.14">Hos 13:14</a>), from iniquities (<a href="?bref=Ps.130.8">Ps 130:8</a>), and from troubles (<a href="?bref=Ps.25.22">25:22</a>). This deliverance always implies some sort of payment or cost, such as “the mighty power” or “strong hand” of God needed for the redemption.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the NT there is just one family of words used for ransom. The term basically means “to loose” or “to set free.” It denotes releasing, redeeming, or liberating on payment of the ransom price. The translation “ransom” is restricted to approximately eight instances where there is a clear reference to the payment of some sort of price. The translators of the Septuagint restricted their use of this Greek word to those instances where the three Hebrew terms clearly meant ransom payment.</p>
<p>The most important occurrence in the NT is Jesus’ description of his death “as a ransom for many” (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.28">Mt 20:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.45">Mk 10:45</a>). Three features stand out in Jesus’ words: his service is one of ransom; his self-sacrifice is the ransom price; and his ransom is substitutionary in character. “He gave his life to purchase freedom for everyone” (<a href="?bref=1Tim.2.6">1 Tm 2:6</a>). Jesus Christ “gave his life to free us from every kind of sin” (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.14">Ti 2:14</a>). The ransom price was “the precious blood of Christ,” who was an unblemished lamb (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.18-19">1 Pt 1:18-19</a>), thus linking Christ’s self-sacrifice to the sacrifices of the OT that pointed to him. The blood of goats and calves was not able to save, but an eternal redemption was obtained by Christ’s blood (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.12">Heb 9:12</a>). In heaven the redeemed sing the new song to the Lamb whose blood ransomed them (<a href="?bref=Rev.5.9">Rv 5:9</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.14.3-4">14:3-4</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Atonement_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Atonement</a>; <a href="?item=RedeemerRedemption_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Redeemer, Redemption</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>