<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="RebeccaRebekah">
  <title>Rebecca*, Rebekah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">REBECCA*, REBEKAH </p>
<p class="fl">Daughter of Bethuel and the wife of the patriarch Isaac. Her name, which means “well fed” or “choice,” appears 31 times in Genesis (primarily in chs <a href="?bref=Gen.24.1-27.46">24–27</a>) and once in <a href="?bref=Rom.9.10">Romans 9:10</a>.</p>
<p>Rebekah’s father was Bethuel, who in turn was the son of Milcah and Nahor, Abraham’s brother (<a href="?bref=Gen.22.20-23">Gn 22:20-23</a>). Abraham was her great-uncle and eventually, of course, her father-in-law. Laban, the father of Leah and Rachel, was her brother. Thus her son Jacob married his two cousins, who were sisters.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Gen.24.1-67">Genesis 24</a> is the account of the successful search by Abraham’s servant for a wife for Isaac. He went to Aram-naharaim (northwest Mesopotamia) in obedience to Abraham, who did not want his son to marry a local Canaanite. In answer to the servant’s prayer, Rebekah not only gave a drink to the man but also watered his camels. After a certain amount of hospitality was extended and payment was made, Rebekah willingly went to meet her new husband.</p>
<p>Rebekah bore twins, Esau and Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.20-27">25:20-27</a>). She preferred Jacob, the younger, over Esau and was a party to the deception of her husband in securing the right of the firstborn for Jacob. Disguising Jacob to feel, look, and smell like Esau the outdoorsman was her idea. She also prepared Isaac’s favorite dish in order to facilitate the event (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.5-17">27:5-17</a>).</p>
<p>Scripture records little more of her life but does report that she was buried next to her husband in the cave of Machpelah near Mamre (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.31">49:31</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Isaac_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Isaac</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>