<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Reconciliation">
  <title>Reconciliation</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">RECONCILIATION</p>
<p class="fl">Restoration of friendly relationships and of peace where there had previously been hostility and alienation. Ordinarily, it also includes the removal of the offense that caused the disruption of peace and harmony. This was especially so in the relation of God with humanity, when Christ removed the enmity existing between God and mankind by his vicarious sacrifice. The Scripture speaks first of Christ’s substitutionary death in effecting reconciliation of God with sinners; of sinners appropriating this free gift by faith; the promised forgiveness and salvation that become the sinners’ possession by grace; and finally reconciliation with God (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.10">Rom 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.19">2 Cor 5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.2.16">Eph 2:16</a>).</p>
<p>The term <span class="greek">katalassein</span> (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.10">Rom 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.19">2 Cor 5:19</a>) signifies first of all the reconciliation of God with the world, expressing God’s initial change of heart toward sinners. The problem is not rightly addressed by questioning whether the unchanging God ever changes his mind; the situation rather is one where an altered relationship now exists between God and sinners by Christ’s interposing sacrifice on behalf of fallen humanity. The point of the reconciliation is that God, for Christ’s sake, now feels toward sinners as though they had never offended him. The reconciliation is complete and perfect, covering mankind both extensively and intensively—that is, all sinners and all sin. The cause of rupture between God and sinners has now been healed, a truth wholly independent of humanity’s mood or attitude. While sinners were still the objects of God’s just wrath, Christ, in full harmony with the gracious will of his heavenly Father, interposed himself for their sakes, for the restoration of harmony.</p>
<p>So basic is this truth that without objective reconciliation there is no thought of salvation, of regeneration, of faith, of Christian life. The initiative in reconciliation, moreover, is all on God’s side; through his Word, the gospel, God reveals to sinners that he is fully reconciled with them because of Christ.</p>
<p>The vicarious atonement or redemption of Christ underlies God’s reconciling activity. Reconciliation took place not by God’s exercise of divine fiat or decree of power but through Christ interposing himself as the people’s substitute for the law’s condemnation. Thus the vicarious atonement is the key to understanding reconciliation as scripturally conceived and taught. Christ “became sin for us”; he assumed the full obligations of the law, perfectly fulfilling it and fully bearing the guilt and punishment. Sins and guilt were laid on him; his righteousness attained under the law was imputed to mankind.</p>
<p>The human predicament, simply and precisely, was the human inability to change or rectify in any way the broken, hostile relationship existing between humanity and God. Christ was the bridge. To carry out his substitutionary mission was the purpose of his incarnation. His sacrificial suffering and death, sealed by his triumphant resurrection, achieved mankind’s redemption (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.25">Rom 4:25</a>). Christ suffered death not as the common lot of all people but as the wages of sin.</p>
<p>His vicarious satisfaction for all sins is the central teaching of the Scripture. Everything literally depends upon the fact that the turning point for humanity came from God, who was working out reconciliation with the world through Christ. This is not simply an imagined or piously conceived idea, something presented as true by deeply concerned and thoughtful people, but a reality that happened (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.6">Is 53:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.21">2 Cor 5:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.12-14">Heb 9:12-14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.19">1 Pt 1:19</a>). It was God’s solution for the grievous, hostile state that existed between a righteous, angry God and sinful, offending people.</p>
<p>The Scripture never loses sight of the sweeping extent of Christ’s work, the atonement for the sins of all people (<a href="?bref=John.3.16">Jn 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.2">1 Jn 2:2</a>). Christ is the sinners’ shield from and before the just wrath of God. Nor was it merely by God’s accepting it as sufficient that Christ’s atonement availed; it was in fact and in truth the adequate and full payment (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.28">Mt 20:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">Rom 3:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.26-28">Heb 7:26-28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.2.6">1 Tm 2:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.2">1 Jn 2:2</a>).</p>
<p>The gospel, therefore, is the message that informs the sinner of God’s reconciliation with sinners through Christ and powerfully persuades the sinner to accept this truth in faith, or as the apostle Paul puts it: “For God was in Christ, reconciling the world to himself, no longer counting people’s sins against them. This is the wonderful message he has given us to tell others. We are Christ’s ambassadors, and God is using us to speak to you. We urge you, as though Christ himself were here pleading with you, ‘Be reconciled to God!’ ” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.19-20">2 Cor 5:19-20</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
  </body>
</item>