<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Regeneration">
  <title>Regeneration*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">REGENERATION*</p>
<p class="fl">Spiritual rebirth producing a new beginning. It describes the new life of the believer in Christ (<a href="?bref=Titus.3.5">Ti 3:5</a>) and the new order that will begin at Christ’s return (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.28">Mt 19:28</a>). It occurs in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> of the Bible in only these two places. This does not mean, however, that the concept is unimportant. A variety of other words and figures are used frequently by the biblical writers to describe the same inner renewal of the heart.</p>
<p>Secular writers also speak of regeneration. For the Stoic philosophers, it meant a return to a former state of existence. They referred to the yearly cycle of the seasons as a regeneration. For the biblical writers, however, regeneration means a renewal on a higher level. It is a radically new beginning rather than a mere restoration of previous conditions. This renewal involves a mighty change in the person. It is a work of the Holy Spirit, breaking the dominion of sin and implanting proper attitudes and desires. The regenerated person freely and joyously does the will of God. The ultimate goal of regeneration is the creation of a new heaven and earth that will be totally righteous and without sin (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.13">2 Pt 3:13</a>). The present working of the Holy Spirit in the believer is a foretaste of this future cosmic regeneration (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.13-14">Eph 1:13-14</a>). The new heavens and earth are still future. But God’s renewal of his people, foreseen by the OT prophets, is already a reality (<a href="?bref=Isa.65.17">Is 65:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.66.22">66:22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.3.13">2 Pt 3:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1">Rv 21:1</a>).</p>
<p>The believer now possesses a new life from God through the process of spiritual birth. Christians are born of God (<a href="?bref=John.1.12-13">Jn 1:12-13</a>). And it is only through this spiritual birth that one may participate in the kingdom of God and receive his Spirit. Those born into God’s family reflect his righteous character (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.29">1 Jn 2:29</a>). They are freed from habitual sin (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.9">3:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.5.18">5:18</a>). In <a href="?bref=Jas.1.18">James 1:18</a> this process of birth is attributed to the power of the Word of God.</p>
<p>Extending this metaphor for regeneration, Jesus taught Nicodemus about the absolute necessity of being born again, or born from above, as a prerequisite to entering the kingdom of God. Those who are thus reborn possess a living hope (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.3">1 Pt 1:3</a>). Again, this new birth is brought about through the power of the Word of God (v <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.23">23</a>).</p>
<p>The initial experience of regeneration is followed by a continuing renewal in the life of the Christian. The newborn are to desire the pure milk of the Word of God in order to grow (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.2">1 Pt 2:2</a>). Paul commands an ongoing transformation by the renewing of the mind (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.2">Rom 12:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.23">Eph 4:23</a>). The new person remains in a process of constant renewal (<a href="?bref=Col.3.10">Col 3:10</a>), and the inner self is renewed daily (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.16">2 Cor 4:16</a>).</p>
<p>The present result of the new birth is a new person or new creation for whom old things are replaced by new (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.17">2 Cor 5:17</a>). It is this new creation, rather than superficial participation in religious practices, that is the goal of the Christian life (<a href="?bref=Gal.6.15">Gal 6:15</a>). It involves laying aside the old nature (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.22">Eph 4:22</a>) and putting on the new nature (v <a href="?bref=Eph.4.24">24</a>). In the final analysis, however, this is never the result of human effort alone. We are God’s workmanship (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.10">2:10</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Atonement_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Atonement</a>; <a href="?item=Conversion_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Conversion</a>; <a href="?item=RedeemerRedemption_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Redeemer, Redemption</a>; <a href="?item=Repentance_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Repentance</a>; <a href="?item=Salvation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Salvation</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="YouMustBeBornAgain"/>
  </body>
</item>