<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Repentance">
  <title>Repentance</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">REPENTANCE</p>
<p class="fl">Literally a change of mind, not about individual plans, intentions, or beliefs, but rather a change in one’s attitude about God. Such repentance accompanies saving faith in Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.21">Acts 20:21</a>). It is inconsistent and unintelligible to suppose that anyone could believe in Christ yet not repent. Repentance is such an important aspect of conversion that it is often stressed rather than saving faith, as when Christ said that there is joy in heaven among the angels over one sinner who repents (<a href="?bref=Luke.15.7">Lk 15:7</a>). The apostles described the conversion of the Gentiles to Christ as God granting them “repentance unto life” (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.18">Acts 11:18</a>). Evangelical repentance and faith in Christ are in fact inseparable, though a convert may be aware of one aspect more than another.</p>
<p>Such penitence is not an isolated act but a disposition of the mind, providing a spur for behavior that accords with God’s declared will. Recognition of daily sins and shortcomings provides the occasion for renewed acts of penitence and for fresh exercises of faith in Christ. One of the deepest and most noteworthy expressions of such penitence is David’s account of his adultery with Bathsheba (<a href="?bref=Ps.51.1-19">Ps 51</a>). Whole churches are, on occasion, called to repent (<a href="?bref=Rev.2.5">Rv 2:5</a>). <a href="?bref=2Cor.7.1-16">Second Corinthians 7</a> contains an interesting and full description of such corporate repentance involving the elements of sorrow for sin and a determined resolve to forsake old sinful ways and to behave properly. While repentance is often accompanied by deep feelings, it is not equivalent to such feelings but is rooted in convictions about the sinner’s own need before a holy God.</p>
<p>Both John the Baptist (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.2">Mt 3:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.4">Mk 1:4</a>) and Christ (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.15">Mk 1:15</a>) were preachers of repentance, calling not the righteous but sinners to repent. And in accordance with the Great Commission (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.44-49">Lk 24:44-49</a>), the apostles continued the same kind of preaching—beginning with Peter’s preaching on the Day of Pentecost (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.1-47">Acts 2</a>), with noteworthy results. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Confession_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Confession</a>; <a href="?item=Conversion_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Conversion</a>; <a href="?item=Forgiveness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Forgiveness</a>; <a href="?item=Regeneration_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Regeneration</a>; <a href="?item=Salvation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Salvation</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="CanGodRepent"/>
  </body>
</item>