<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NaphtaliTribeof">
  <title>Naphtali, Tribe of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NAPHTALI, Tribe of</p>
<p class="fl">One of the 12 tribes of Israel that migrated from Egypt to Canaan, ultimately settling in northern Canaan in the high country of Galilee.</p>
<p>During the period of the Israelite exodus from Egypt, Naphtali’s tribe is mentioned only incidentally. Acting as the leader of the tribe, Ahira, Enan’s son (<a href="?bref=Num.2.29">Nm 2:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.7.28">7:28</a>), helped conduct the census of Naphtali (<a href="?bref=Num.1.15">1:15</a>) as Israel prepared for the prospect of war. The first census records 53,400 men ready for war (vv <a href="?bref=Num.1.42-43">42-43</a>), whereas a later census taken near the end of their desert sojourning records 45,400 men capable of battle (<a href="?bref=Num.26.48">26:48</a>). When Moses sent the 12 spies to search out the land of Canaan, Nahbi, Vophsi’s son, represented Naphtali’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Num.13.14">13:14</a>). Other significant activities involving Naphtali’s tribe during the wilderness wanderings include the position of encampment around the tabernacle while in the desert (<a href="?bref=Num.2.29">2:29</a>); the distribution of the land, in which Pedahel, Ammihud’s son, represented Naphtali in the ceremony of choosing lots (<a href="?bref=Num.34.28">34:28</a>); and the ratification of the covenant at Shechem (<a href="?bref=Deut.27.13">Dt 27:13</a>). Finally, like the rest of the tribes, Naphtali was the recipient of a blessing from Moses (<a href="?bref=Deut.33.23">Dt 33:23</a>).</p>
<p>The tribal inheritance of Naphtali was located on the eastern side of upper Galilee, bordered on the south by Zebulun and by Asher on the west (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.34">Jos 19:34</a>). Within its borders were several Levitical cities (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.6">Jos 21:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.62">1 Chr 6:62</a>) and a city of refuge, Kedesh (<a href="?bref=Josh.20.7">Jos 20:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.76">1 Chr 6:76</a>). Though they successfully occupied the region, they did not initially drive out the Canaanites (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.33">Jgs 1:33</a>). They did, however, subjugate the inhabitants of the Canaanite cities Beth-shemesh and Beth-anath to forced labor. As a result of their location, they were involved in some major conflicts with the indigenous population and foreign invaders. The most significant of these was the war with Jabin, king of Hazor. Barak, son of Abinoam, from Kedesh in Naphtali joined Deborah, the prophetess, and together they led the tribes of Zebulun and Naphtali against the Canaanites (chs <a href="?bref=Judg.4.1-5.31">4–5</a>). Along with the tribes of Asher, Zebulun, and Manasseh, the tribe of Naphtali was also called by Gideon into battle against the Midianites (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.35">6:35</a>).</p>
<p>During the united monarchy, the tribe of Naphtali sent troops to Hebron, demonstrating their support of David’s kingship over all of Israel (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.34">1 Chr 12:34</a>). Naphtali’s continued allegiance to the Davidic dynasty was evidenced in their support of Solomon’s administrative system. Ahimaaz of Naphtali’s tribe was one of 12 officers who administered the various regional districts for the king; this same Ahimaaz also married Basemath, the daughter of Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.15">1 Kgs 4:15</a>).</p>
<p>The history of the tribe during the divided monarchy is sketchy, and references to Naphtali occur in the contexts of military conflicts. During the reign of Asa in Judah, Baasha, king of Israel, sought to build a fortress at Ramah on the central Benjamite plateau. Feeling threatened, Asa encouraged Ben-hadad of Syria to attack the northern kingdom. The Syrian monarch complied, and the brunt of his attack was felt by Naphtali’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.16-24">1 Kgs 15:16-24</a>). Baasha withdrew his troops from the Benjamite plateau only to encounter the powerful onslaught of the Syrian army. The other major foreign power to exert its influence in the region of Naphtali was Assyria, particularly during the reign of Tiglath-pileser III. During the rule of Pekah in Israel and Rezon in Syria, this Assyrian monarch came and captured Gilead, Galilee, and Naphtali (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.29">2 Kgs 15:29</a>) in 732 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>According to the prophet Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.1">Is 9:1</a>), though the Lord had made Naphtali’s land contemptible, he would make it glorious once again. Matthew sees the fulfillment of this prophecy in the person of Christ, who brought the message of God’s kingdom to the Jews living in the region of Naphtali’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.13-15">Mt 4:13-15</a>). In the book of Revelation (<a href="?bref=Rev.7.6">Rv 7:6</a>), 12,000 members of Naphtali’s tribe are included among the sealed multitude of Israel.</p>
  </body>
</item>