<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Nathanael">
  <title>Nathanael</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NATHANAEL</p>
<p class="fl">Jew from Cana of Galilee whom Jesus called to be a disciple (<a href="?bref=John.1.45-50">Jn 1:45-50</a>; <a href="?bref=John.21.2">21:2</a>). Initially skeptical when Philip described Jesus as the fulfillment of the whole OT (<a href="?bref=John.1.45-46">1:45-46</a>), Nathanael proclaimed Jesus to be the Son of God and the King of Israel (v <a href="?bref=John.1.49">49</a>) after an astonishing personal encounter.</p>
<p>The fact that the only NT references to Nathanael occur in the Gospel of John has led some scholars to identify him with several personalities appearing in the synoptic Gospels. Because his call appears with those of Andrew, Peter, and Philip, some have speculated that he was one of the 12, possibly Bartholomew. Three pieces of evidence are cited in support of this position: (1) the name Bartholomew is patronymic (literally “son of Tolmai”) and would be accompanied by another name; (2) each of the Synoptic lists of the 12 apostles place Bartholomew after Philip (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.2-4">Mt 10:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.16-19">Mk 3:16-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.14-16">Lk 6:14-16</a>), paralleling the call of Nathanael after Philip in John’s account; and (3) Bartholomew’s name does not appear in the fourth Gospel.</p>
<p>A second position identifies Nathanael as James, the son of Alphaeus. According to this view, Jesus’ comment in <a href="?bref=John.1.47">John 1:47</a> should read “Behold, Israel [not “an Israelite”] indeed, in whom is no guile!” Israel is the name God gave to Jacob, and the NT form of Jacob is James. John addressed James, the son of Alphaeus, as Nathanael in order to distinguish him from others who had become prominent in the early church.</p>
<p>Two less plausible identifications equate Nathanael with either Matthew or Simon the Cananaean. The first is precariously founded on the similar etymologies of the names Matthew (“gift of Yahweh”) and Nathanael (“Yahweh has given”). The second identifies the two on the basis of the common hometown of Cana.</p>
<p>In the final analysis, Nathanael was most likely a disciple who was not a member of the 12 and was known only to John. This suggestion conforms to early patristic evidence. In the fourth Gospel, Nathanael serves as a symbol for the true Jew who overcomes initial skepticism to believe in Christ. This is confirmed by three observations: (1) his initial reaction to Jesus parallels that of others who believed in the Law and the Prophets (<a href="?bref=John.7.15,27,41">Jn 7:15, 27, 41</a>; <a href="?bref=John.9.41">9:41</a>); (2) Jesus’ perception of Nathanael under a fig tree (<a href="?bref=John.1.48">1:48</a>) identifies the latter’s devotion to the Torah (in rabbinic literature the proper place to study the Torah is under a fig tree); and (3) Jesus identifies Nathanael with Jacob, the father of the Israelite nation. In <a href="?bref=Gen.25.1-32.32">Genesis 25–32</a>, Jacob is certainly sly and cunning in his dealings with Esau and Laban. <a href="?bref=John.1.51">John 1:51</a> strengthens the ties between Nathanael and Jacob by presenting the imagery of angels ascending and descending, reminiscent of Jacob’s dream, and by locating the event in Galilee close to Bethel and Jabbok, the sites of Jacob’s experiences. Nathanael is thus a symbol of the pious Israelite for whom Christ came. His response typifies what the fourth Evangelist understands as the appropriate response of the true Israelite to Jesus—from initial skepticism to faith (cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.9.6">Rom 9:6</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ApostleApostleship_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Apostle, Apostleship</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>