<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NazariteNazirite">
  <title>Nazarite*, Nazirite</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NAZARITE*, NAZIRITE </p>
<p class="fl">Person who was either chosen or consecrated for life or for a set period of time to complete a vow to God. The Nazirite (Nazarite) devoted himself to self-imposed discipline in order to perform some special service (<a href="?bref=Num.6.1-21">Nm 6:1-21</a>).</p>
<p>Israelite tradition viewed the Nazirite as consecrated for life. Samson was the ancient hero of the Nazirites. He was “consecrated to God” through the vow of his mother (<a href="?bref=Judg.13.5">Jgs 13:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.16.17">16:17</a>) and remained under that vow to the “day of his death” (<a href="?bref=Judg.13.7">13:7</a>). As long as Samson’s hair was not cut, he was able to receive the Spirit of the Lord and thereby perform amazing physical feats.</p>
<p>Early Nazirite vows may have been associated with holy-war ceremonies. Combatants were consecrated to God and perhaps wore long hair (<a href="?bref=Judg.13.5">Jgs 13:5</a>). The prophet Samuel did not cut his hair because of his mother’s vow that no razor would touch his head (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.11">1 Sm 1:11</a>); the Septuagint adds that he was not to drink wine. The Nazirite vow of uncut hair was associated with being consecrated to God’s service and was especially common during the charismatic days of Israel’s early leaders.</p>
<p>Naziritism developed into a ritual for those who sought to consecrate themselves temporarily to God. During the period of consecration, the devotee abstained from drinking wine, allowed his hair to grow, and avoided all contact with dead bodies.</p>
<p>Uncut hair symbolizes strength and life. Perhaps this is the intended meaning of <span class="hebrew">nazir</span> when used to describe Joseph in the blessing of Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.26">Gn 49:26</a>) and in the blessing of Moses (<a href="?bref=Deut.33.16">Dt 33:16</a>). Vineyards that were not pruned in sabbatical or jubilee years were said to be <span class="hebrew">nazir</span><span class="ital">.</span></p>
<p>In later times, touching or coming in close proximity to a dead body was the most serious offense against the vow. Should anyone die in his presence, a Nazirite became impure. Such a contaminated Nazirite was expected to shave his “defiled head” on the day of cleansing. Next, he would bring two young pigeons to the priest, who would offer one as a sin offering. And finally, he must bring a male lamb for a guilt offering (<a href="?bref=Num.6.9-12">Nm 6:9-12</a>). Because of this defilement, the Nazirite had to begin his days of separation again.</p>
<p>At the end of his period of separation he “desecrated” himself through a ceremony: he offered a sacrifice for sin and a communion sacrifice, then he shaved his head and burnt the hair. Thereafter, the Nazirite returned to his normal life and could drink wine (<a href="?bref=Num.6.13-21">Nm 6:13-21</a>).</p>
<p>Paul completed a similar vow at Cenchrea in NT times (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.18">Acts 18:18</a>) and, then again, along with four other Nazirites in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.23-24">Acts 21:23-24</a>). In the Talmud the period of time for the consecration was usually 30 days. It was customary for the wealthy to aid poor Nazirites in the purchase of their offerings. During the Maccabean period, the Nazirites were unable to complete their rites because the temple was profaned (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.3.49-51">1 Macc 3:49-51</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>