<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Neighbor">
  <title>Neighbor</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NEIGHBOR</p>
<p class="fl">Concept apparently limited in the OT period and late Judaism to one’s fellow Israelite, or member of the covenant, and extended by Jesus to include anyone encountered in life.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Although it is never explicitly limited as such, the prominent connotation of “neighbor” in the OT is that of a fellow member of the covenant community; that is, another Israelite (see <a href="?bref=Lev.6.1-7">Lv 6:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.19.1-37">19</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.15.2-3">Dt 15:2-3</a>). In <a href="?bref=Lev.19.18">Leviticus 19:18</a>, a passage often quoted in the NT, the Israelite is commanded to “love your neighbor as yourself.” In <a href="?bref=Lev.19.34">19:34</a>, it is explicitly stated that such love should also be shown to the foreigner (or “sojourner”) passing through the land. If “neighbor” (v <a href="?bref=Lev.19.18">18</a>) implied a more encompassing notion, such as “mankind” or “fellow man,” there presumably would have been no need to include the further stipulation in verse <a href="?bref=Lev.19.34">34</a>. “Neighbor” was therefore probably taken to mean one’s immediate neighbor, the fellow Israelite.</p>
<p>Within the covenant community, love of neighbor involved certain responsibilities explicitly set forth in the law. The neighbor was to be treated fairly (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.5-15">Ex 22:5-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.2-7">Lv 6:2-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.19.9-18">19:9-18</a>) and respected (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.16">Ex 20:16</a>), as were his belongings (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.17">Ex 20:17</a>). To foster such just and merciful relationships within the covenant community, the neighbor was to be thought of as a “brother” (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.25">Lv 25:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.22.1-4">Dt 22:1-4</a>). What one did to one’s neighbor was to be returned in kind (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.19-23">Lv 24:19-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.19.11-19">Dt 19:11-19</a>).</p>
<p>The grave importance attached to treatment of the neighbor is understandable when seen as part of one’s wider relationship with God and was considered something that could affect significantly the divine-human relationship (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.1-7">Lv 6:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.19.1-37">19</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.25.17">25:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.10-13">Dt 24:10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.12.1-8">Ps 12</a>). Israelites were to treat their neighbors in the same loving way they had themselves been treated by God (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.21">Ex 22:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.25.35-38">Lv 25:35-38</a>).</p>
<p>The importance of the neighbor relationship within the covenant community is also demonstrated by the fact that when such responsibilities were ignored, a societal breakdown or national turmoil followed (<a href="?bref=Deut.28.15-68">Dt 28:15-68</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.4.1-3">Hos 4:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.2.6-7">Am 2:6-7</a>). That the Israelites often did neglect love for neighbor, particularly the neighbor in need, is a contributing cause for the divine punishment of the exile (<a href="?bref=Jer.5.7-9">Jer 5:7-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.7.1-15">7:1-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.9.2-9">9:2-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.4.1-3">Hos 4:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.2.6-7">Am 2:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.10-13">5:10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.4-6">8:4-6</a>). The mere fact that proper love of neighbor was also part of Israel’s hope for the messianic age to come (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.34">Jer 31:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.3.10">Zec 3:10</a>) also points to its common neglect within the OT covenant community.</p>
<p class="h2" id="InLateJudaism">In Late Judaism</p>
<p class="fl">From the exilic experience, Israel recognized that divine blessing was conditional somewhat on justice and love exercised toward one another (<a href="?bref=Zech.8.14-17">Zec 8:14-17</a>). The identity of the “neighbor” was debatable, however. Several factors suggest that “neighbor” was limited in this period to the fellow Israelite and the proselyte (gentile convert to Judaism). Evidence from rabbinic material excludes Samaritans and the Gentiles living in the land from being considered “neighbors” and thus worthy of love. Within the Jewish Essene community at Qumran, the “neighbor” to be respected and treated fairly was restricted to one’s fellow community members. Finally, when Jesus recalls, “You have heard that it was said, ‘You shall love your neighbor and hate your enemy’” (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.43">Mt 5:43</a>), he is quoting only partially from the OT (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.18">Lv 19:18</a>—“You shall love your neighbor”). The last phrase (“and hate your enemy”) reflects the contemporary Jewish feeling toward outsiders; that is, God did not require love toward those considered “enemies” but only toward fellow countrymen.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Jesus differed dramatically from his Jewish contemporaries by eradicating the limitations on the neighbor to be loved. In contrast to those who would limit love to one’s fellow countrymen, Jesus advocated extending the obligation reserved for the neighbor to the enemy as well (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.43-48">Mt 5:43-48</a>), and in so doing, he destroyed the distinction between neighbor and enemy altogether.</p>
<p>On another occasion, a scribe asked Jesus what was the greatest commandment given by God (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.28-31">Mk 12:28-31</a>). In response, Jesus cited <a href="?bref=Deut.6.5">Deuteronomy 6:5</a> concerning the nature of God and man’s obligation to love God with his entire being: heart, soul, and mind. Of significance is that Jesus did not stop there but linked with this a second commandment to “love your neighbor as yourself” (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.18">Lv 19:18</a>). Some scholars suggest that this dramatic and close association of love of God and love of neighbor originated with Jesus. If Jesus was the first to tie these commands together (see <a href="?bref=Matt.22.37">Mt 22:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.29-31">Mk 12:29-31</a>), it reveals our Lord’s own understanding of the relation of these two obligations; proper love for neighbor derives from love for God, and conversely, love for God is inseparable from meeting the needs of a neighbor in love.</p>
<p>The debate in Jesus’ time was not over how to properly treat a neighbor but who, in fact, was the neighbor. Jesus is asked this very question by an expert of the law (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.29">Lk 10:29</a>). Jesus had complimented the lawyer for his clear understanding of what was required to inherit eternal life, namely, love of God and love of neighbor. Luke suggests that the lawyer asked the further qualifying question in order to “justify himself,” that is, justify his actual behavior of limited love toward his fellow man. Jesus chose not to respond directly but through the use of a parable, in this case, the familiar parable of the Good Samaritan (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.10.30-35">30-35</a>).</p>
<p>In order to open the lawyer’s eyes to the tragic shortsightedness of his question, Jesus related an everyday story of a man traveling the treacherous road from Jerusalem down to Jericho, a road particularly plagued by robbers. The traveler is robbed, stripped, beaten, and left half dead. To this point, the lawyer might have assumed Jesus was offering an example of who constitutes a “neighbor”—a fellow Jew in need. Jesus proceeds, however, to introduce two figures, a priest and a Levite who, in an academic discussion, could have argued quite ably on who is the neighbor God calls one to love. The lawyer would no doubt have anticipated such experts in the law to act rightly toward the victim. In contrast, the priest and Levite, upon seeing the man in need, respond by “passing by on the other side.” Unable to determine whether the victim was dead or barely alive, and possibly not wanting to risk uncleanness, the experts of the law pass by, thus violating the greatest of the commandments just identified by the lawyer (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.25-28">10:25-28</a>).</p>
<p>Enter a Samaritan—a figure especially despised by the Jews. Viewed as heretics by the Jewish religious authorities, the Samaritans were disqualified in rabbinic circles from being considered a “neighbor” and thus worthy of love. In fact, previous centuries had witnessed the slaughter of many Samaritans by Jewish rulers, and animosity clearly existed between the two peoples (see <a href="?bref=John.4.9">Jn 4:9</a>). While the lawyer listening to the parable would have expected the priest and Levite to act justly toward the victim, he must have been surprised that a hated Samaritan would show compassion and thus fulfill the greatest commandment. Jesus intentionally spelled out the extent of the Samaritan’s compassion (immediate care in dressing wounds, transport to the inn, care for the victim there and extended care in paying for care by others while he is away, <a href="?bref=Luke.10.34-35">Lk 10:34-35</a>) to such a degree that the lawyer would have no doubt as to the genuineness of the Samaritan’s love. The irony of the story is that one not considered worthy to be called “neighbor” by Jews was precisely the one who showed himself to be “neighbor” to the victim (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.10.36-37">36-37</a>).</p>
<p>The parable, like the statement in <a href="?bref=Matt.5.43-48">Matthew 5:43-48</a>, reveals Jesus’ own understanding of “neighbor” and what “love of neighbor” demands. Jesus sets no limitation on who qualifies as the neighbor commanded by God to be loved.</p>
<p>The forcefulness and power of Jesus’ teachings on the love of neighbor and its relationship to one’s love for God are demonstrated by a similar emphasis within the early church. Paul on two occasions called the love of neighbor the fulfillment of the entire law (<a href="?bref=Rom.13.8-10">Rom 13:8-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.14">Gal 5:14</a>), while James referred to the same commandment as “the royal law” (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.8">Jas 2:8</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>