<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NethaneelNethanel">
  <title>Nethaneel*, Nethanel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NETHANEEL*, NETHANEL</p>
<p class="fl">Common OT name spelled Nethaneel in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>.</p>
<p class="list-space"> 1. Zuar’s son and the prince of Issachar’s tribe at the start of Israel’s wilderness wanderings (<a href="?bref=Num.1.8">Nm 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.2.5">2:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.10.15">10:15</a>), who represented his kinsmen at the altar’s dedication (<a href="?bref=Num.7.18,23">7:18, 23</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Judahite, the fourth son of Jesse and David’s brother (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.14">1 Chr 2:14</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. One of the priests assigned to blow a trumpet before the ark in the procession led by David when the ark was moved to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.24">1 Chr 15:24</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Levite and the father of Shemaiah, the scribe who recorded the 24 divisions of priests founded during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.24.6">1 Chr 24:6</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Korahite Levite and Obed-edom’s fifth son in David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.26.4">1 Chr 26:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. One of the princes sent by King Jehoshaphat to teach the law in the cities of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.17.7">2 Chr 17:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. One of the Levitical chiefs who generously gave animals to the Levites for the celebration of the Passover feast during King Josiah’s reign (<a href="?bref=2Chr.35.9">2 Chr 35:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Priest and one of Pashhur’s six sons who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.22">Ezr 10:22</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Head of Jedaiah’s priestly family during the days of Joiakim, the high priest, in postexilic Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.21">Neh 12:21</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. One of the priestly musicians who performed at the dedication of the Jerusalem wall during Nehemiah’s day (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.36">Neh 12:36</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>