<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NewCreationNewCreature">
  <title>New Creation*, New Creature*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NEW CREATION*, NEW CREATURE*</p>
<p class="fl">Concept of redemption developed throughout the OT and NT to its final consummation in the second coming of Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>The most fundamental truth of the Bible is that God is the Creator of heaven and earth, who sustains and controls everything (e.g., <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Gn 1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.33.6-11">Pss 33:6-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.104.1-35">104</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.6.25-32">Mt 6:25-32</a>). The most basic consideration about men and women is that they are creatures made in God’s image (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-2.25">Gn 1–2</a>). Accordingly, the Bible’s message of salvation is unintelligible apart from what it teaches about God as Creator. The true nature and perversity of humanity’s sin stem from the fact that they “worshiped and served created things rather than the Creator” (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.25">Rom 1:25</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). God is Redeemer because he is Creator. By the same token, the objects of God’s saving activity are his rebellious creatures who, along with the entire created order, are cursed with futility and decay (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.17-18">Gn 3:17-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.8.20-21">Rom 8:20-21</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The tie between creation and salvation is especially prominent in the latter part of Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-66.24">Is 40–66</a>). The prophet surveys the grandeur of the final redemption God will accomplish for Israel. Repeatedly the perspective on this promised eschatological deliverance is that God is the Creator of heaven and earth and of Israel in particular (see also the full statement of <a href="?bref=Isa.40.12-31">40:12-31</a>; e.g., <a href="?bref=Isa.44.24">44:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.45.18">45:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.48.13">48:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.51.16">51:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.64.8">64:8</a>).</p>
<p>In this context, expectation centers on “the new heavens and the new earth” (<a href="?bref=Isa.65.17">65:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.66.22">66:22</a>). This reference to the new creation gives the broadest conceivable scope to the eschatological salvation prophesied by Isaiah. God’s work of renewal and restoration at the end parallels his work of creation in the beginning (<a href="?bref=Isa.48.12">48:12</a>). What God will do in bringing all things to their consummation is of the same order of magnitude as what he did in calling them into existence out of nothing. At the same time, the new creation concept reveals that the end-time salvation promised to Israel has universal and cosmic proportions. The underlying hope is the ultimate entrance of the faithful from among the nations, as well as in Israel, into the bliss of the eternal, new creation order. These themes from Isaiah are taken up and developed by the NT writers, and are integral to their message.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheNewCreationandChrist">The New Creation and Christ</p>
<p class="fl">The NT ties together creation and redemption. Several writers either parallel or in other ways relate the saving work of Christ to his activity at creation (<a href="?bref=John.1.3">Jn 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.15-18">Col 1:15-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.1.2-3">Heb 1:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.3.14">Rv 3:14</a>). What he has done at the end, in “the fullness of time” (<a href="?bref=Gal.4.4">Gal 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.10">Eph 1:10</a>), “in these last days” (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.2">Heb 1:2</a>), roots in what he did in the beginning. The redemption accomplished by Christ is a work of new creation.</p>
<p>This association of the new creation with Christ’s work is unmistakable when Paul designates Christ as the “last Adam” and “second man” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45-47">1 Cor 15:45-47</a>; cf. v <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.22">22</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.14">Rom 5:14</a>). This description has close affinities with “Son of Man,” a self-designation of Jesus. Paul’s use of the last Adam designation is obviously intended to heighten the contrast between Adam and Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.1-32">Rom 1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-58">1 Cor 15</a>). In antithesis to Adam, who through his disobedience brought into the world sin and the consequent condemnation of death, Christ by his obedience has established righteousness, resulting in justification and life.</p>
<p>Paul discloses something of the full range and implications of the Adam-Christ contrast in <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.42-49">1 Corinthians 15:42-49</a>. He contrasts the believer’s present bodily existence, in its weakness and mortality, with the body to be received at the resurrection. He sums up this contrast: the one body is “natural,” the other is “spiritual.” Adam and Christ exemplify these two bodies, the natural and the spiritual. At the same time, however, Adam and Christ are brought into view as whole persons. They are the representatives of others and heads over contrasting orders of life. Adam, the first man, is representative head of the natural earthly order of existence, made subject to corruption and death by his sin (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.12-19">Rom 5:12-19</a>). Christ, the second and last Adam, is the representative head over the spiritual, heavenly order, characterized by life, power, and glory. Ultimately, the contrast in this passage is between two successive world orders, creation and its consummation (new creation), each beginning with an Adam.</p>
<p>Two other points also bear on the new creation gospel of Paul and the other NT writers. First, the believer’s resurrection is fully dependent on the resurrection of Christ, who, as the last Adam, became life-giving Spirit in resurrection (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45">45</a>). The controlling emphasis is on the unity between the resurrection of Christ and that of believers (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.12-20">1 Cor 15:12-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.18">Col 1:18</a>). In the NT proclamation, the resurrection of Christ is the great redemptive counterpart to creation (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.17">Rom 4:17</a>). According to the NT, the new creation is a present reality, dating from the resurrection of Christ. Second, in stating that the last Adam became life-giving Spirit, <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45">1 Corinthians 15:45</a> points to the unity that exists between the exalted Christ and the Holy Spirit in their life-giving activity. The Holy Spirit is the power of the new creation (cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.6.5">Heb 6:5</a>). Where the Spirit is at work as the gift of the glorified Christ, the new creation is present.</p>
<p>The new creation is the eschatological fulfillment promised and anticipated in the OT. As such it has already been inaugurated and realized by the work of Christ (the last Adam), particularly by his death and resurrection, and will be consummated at his return. The interval in between receives its fundamental character from the coexistence of the two creations; the new has begun, while concurrently the old continues to pass away (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.31">1 Cor 7:31</a>). The concept of new creation closely parallels that of the kingdom of God. According to the synoptic Gospels, it is the central theme of Jesus’ proclamation. Tied to his own person and work in its coming, the kingdom is announced by him as both present (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.28">Mt 12:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.13.11,16-17">13:11, 16-17</a>) and future (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.11">Mt 8:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.25.34">25:34</a>). In terms of the two-age distinction, coined by contemporary Judaism to express its eschatological expectations and taken over by Jesus and the early church (e.g., <a href="?bref=Matt.12.32">Mt 12:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.21">Eph 1:21</a>), the new creation is the longed-for “age to come.” “New creation” serves to indicate the comprehensive nature of this eschatological reality; redemption involves nothing less than the renewal of all things (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.5">Rv 21:5</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheNewCreationandtheChurch">The New Creation and the Church</p>
<p class="fl">Salvation, according to the NT, is from beginning to end a matter of union with Christ and sharing in all the benefits resulting from his once-for-all redemptive work. Accordingly, because Christ died and was raised, anyone in Christ is already a participant in the new ceation order (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.15">2 Cor 5:15</a>). The reference is not only personal but cosmic, as seen from the context with its correlative emphasis on the reconciliation and its scope (vv <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.17-19">17-19</a>).</p>
<p>In the only other NT occurrence of the expression “new creation” (<a href="?bref=Gal.6.15">Gal 6:15</a>), the perspective is cosmic as well as individual. The new creation, in which neither circumcision nor uncircumcision matters, stands in opposition to the world, to which the believer has been crucified with Christ (<a href="?bref=Gal.6.14">Gal 6:14</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Col.2.20">Col 2:20</a>). “When anyone is united to Christ, there is a new world; the old order is gone, and a new order has already begun” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.17">2 Cor 5:17</a>, <span class="sc">neb</span>).</p>
<p>Resurrection is not only a future hope for believers but a present reality; they have already been raised with Christ (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.5-6">Eph 2:5-6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Col.2.12-13">Col 2:12-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.1">3:1</a>). Consequently, believers are “created in Christ Jesus for good works” (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.10">Eph 2:10</a>). Further, the church is the new covenant reality of “the new man,” made up of Israel and the nations (v <a href="?bref=Eph.2.15">15</a>). As such, its members are already being renewed inwardly (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.16">2 Cor 4:16</a>) by the Lord-Spirit according to the glorified image of the last Adam (<a href="?bref=2Cor.3.18">2 Cor 3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.4.4-6">4:4-6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.8.29">Rom 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.24">Eph 4:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.10">Col 3:10</a>). And they will bear this same image bodily at his return (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.49">1 Cor 15:49</a>). The deepest motive for holy living is not gratitude for the forgiveness of sin but the determination of the believer’s existence as a new creature. The ethics of the NT are new creation ethics (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.2">Rom 12:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.2.20">Col 2:20</a>).</p>
<p>The new creation is not only a present reality but a future hope. For the new creation, too, the church lives “by faith, not by sight” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.7">2 Cor 5:7</a>). Reminiscent of Isaiah’s expectation, believers are looking to Christ’s return for “new heavens and a new earth in which righteousness dwells” and where sin and its effects are nothing more than memories (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.13">2 Pt 3:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-4">Rv 21:1-4</a>).</p>
<p>This hope raises the question of the relationship between this final, eternal order and the original creation. The picture of destruction by burning (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.10-12">2 Pt 3:10-12</a>) and some of the images in <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-27">Revelation 21</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.22.1-21">22</a> (e.g., no sun, moon, night; cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.6.12-14">6:12-14</a>) seem to suggest an absolute disjunction. Other passages, however, interpret this as imagery. With all the radical differences before and after the resurrection, the natural and spiritual bodies (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.44">1 Cor 15:44</a>) are not distinct from each other as bodies. This body, sown in corruption, dishonor, and weakness, will be raised up incorruptible, glorious, and powerful. And what holds true for the believer’s body also holds for creation. The anxious longing and groaning of the entire (nonpersonal) creation is not for annihilation but that it may be set free from bondage to futility and decay and may share in the glorious freedom of the children of God, which will be revealed in the redemption (resurrection) of the body (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.19-23">Rom 8:19-23</a>). The new creation is not merely a return to conditions in the beginning but a renewed creation, the consummation of God’s purposes set from before the beginning and realized, despite man’s sin and its destructive effects, by the redemption in Christ, the last Adam. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=AdamPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Adam (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=Creation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Creation</a>; <a href="?item=EternalLife_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eternal Life</a>; <a href="?item=ManOldandNew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Man, Old and New</a>; <a href="?item=New_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New</a>; <a href="?item=NewHeavensandNewEarth_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">New Heavens and New Earth</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>