<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Night">
  <title>Night</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">NIGHT</p>
<p class="fl">Word in Scripture denoting that time of darkness from dusk until dawn when no light of the sun is visible. For example, Joseph took Mary and Jesus to Egypt by night (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.14">Mt 2:14</a>). The shepherds were keeping watch over their flocks at night (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.8">Lk 2:8</a>). Nicodemus came to see Jesus at night (<a href="?bref=John.3.2">Jn 3:2</a>). An angel from the Lord came and opened the prison doors at night in order to let the disciples out (<a href="?bref=Acts.5.19">Acts 5:19</a>).</p>
<p>According to <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Genesis 1</a>, the day-night cycle was instituted by God and “night” was the name given to the period of darkness (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.5">Gn 1:5</a>). Later, God put the lights in the expanse of the heavens, appointing the sun to rule or dominate the day, and the moon, the lesser light, to dominate the night (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.1.16-18">16-18</a>). The covenant of the Lord is the basis of the regularity of the rotation of day and night.</p>
<p>The night in OT times was apparently divided into three periods or “watches.” The latter name originated with the changing of the guard at these times. Gideon’s 300 men blew their trumpets and broke their pitchers at the beginning of the middle watch (<a href="?bref=Judg.7.19">Jgs 7:19</a>). Although no references in the OT give the limits of these three periods, night was considered to begin at sunset, and consequently the periods may have been 6:00 to 10:00 <span class="sc">pm</span>, 10:00 <span class="sc">pm</span> to 2:00 <span class="sc">am</span>, and 2:00 to 6:00 <span class="sc">am</span>.</p>
<p>Later, according to the Roman calculation of time, night was divided into four watches. Some historians think they began at 9:30 <span class="sc">pm</span>, at midnight, at 2:30 <span class="sc">am</span>, and at 5:00 <span class="sc">am</span>. Others think that the nighttime period between 6:00 <span class="sc">pm</span> and 6:00 <span class="sc">am</span> was divided equally into four periods, the first beginning at 6:00 <span class="sc">pm</span>, the second at 9:00 <span class="sc">pm</span>, the third at midnight, and the fourth at 3:00 <span class="sc">am</span>. <a href="?bref=Mark.13.35">Mark 13:35</a> contains the popular designations for these four watches, namely late in the day (early evening), midnight, the cock-crowing, and early in the morning.</p>
<p>Apparently, <a href="?bref=Matt.14.25">Matthew 14:25</a> and <a href="?bref=Mark.6.48">Mark 6:48</a> follow the Roman calculation when they locate Jesus’ walking on the water at about the fourth watch of the night.</p>
<p>A specialized use of the word “night” along with the word “day” emphasizes the continuance of activity. For example, the man with an unclean spirit is said to have been in the mountains and in the tombs “night and day” (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.5">Mk 5:5</a>). Paul refers to his having labored, working night and day, so as not to be a burden to the church (<a href="?bref=1Thes.2.9">1 Thes 2:9</a>). Later in the same book he refers to his continuous praying night and day (<a href="?bref=1Thes.3.10">3:10</a>).</p>
<p>Along with this literal usage of the word “night,” there is also a figurative or metaphorical usage. In some references it refers to divine judgment (<a href="?bref=Amos.5.8-9">Am 5:8-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.3.6">Mi 3:6</a>). Jesus uses “night” to refer to death (<a href="?bref=John.9.4">Jn 9:4</a>). Once the night (death) comes, time for working is over.</p>
<p>Paul compares this present age (soon to be over with) to the night that is almost gone (<a href="?bref=Rom.13.12">Rom 13:12</a>). Again, Paul speaks of himself and his readers as children of the light and of the day, not the night and darkness (<a href="?bref=1Thes.5.5">1 Thes 5:5</a>). In this context he links night with separation from God, sin, intemperance, careless living, as well as spiritual blindness and ignorance, especially regarding the Lord’s return.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Day_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Day</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>