<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Sabbath">
  <title>Sabbath</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SABBATH</p>
<p class="fl">Comes from a Hebrew word that means “cease” or “desist.” The Sabbath was a day (from Friday evening until Saturday evening in Jesus’s time) when all ordinary work stopped. The Scriptures relate that God gave his people the Sabbath as an opportunity to serve him and as a reminder of two great truths in the Bible: Creation and redemption.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The relationship between Creation and the Sabbath is first expressed in <a href="?bref=Gen.2.2-3">Genesis 2:2-3</a>. God “ceased” his work in Creation after six days and then “blessed” the seventh day and “declared it holy.” In the fourth commandment (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.8-11">Ex 20:8-11</a>), God’s “blessing” and “setting aside” of the seventh day after Creation (the words used are the same as those in Genesis) form the basis of his demand that people should observe the seventh day as a day of Sabbath rest.</p>
<p>The idea of God resting from his work is surprising. It’s clear in <a href="?bref=Exod.31.17">Exodus 31:17</a>, where the Lord tells Moses how he was refreshed by his day of rest. The Bible often speaks of God the creator as a manual laborer. No doubt it is presented in clear human terms in Exodus to reinforce the fact that people must follow the pattern their Creator has set for them. One day’s rest in seven is necessary for individuals, families, households, and even animals (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.10">Ex 20:10</a>).</p>
<p>The Sabbath’s setting in the biblical account of Creation implies that it is meant for all people and not just for Israel. The inclusion of the Sabbath law in the Ten Commandments underlines this important truth. The Ten Commandments occupied a special place in OT law. Of all of God’s instructions, these were spoken by his audible voice (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.1">Ex 20:1</a>), written by his finger (<a href="?bref=Exod.31.18">31:18</a>), and placed in the ark, within the tabernacle, which was at the heart of Israel’s worship (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.16">25:16</a>). The NT also confirms the strong impression that the Ten Commandments embody principles that are permanently valid for all people in all places at all times. Whether or not Sunday is recognized as the Christian Sabbath, one has to accept the central principle of this biblical teaching as far as the Sabbath is concerned. God’s instructions require people to observe a regular weekly break from work.</p>
<p>Redemption is the second main strand of the Bible’s Sabbath teaching. It is also in one of the Ten Commandments list. The Sabbath law (already noted in <a href="?bref=Exod.20.8-11">Ex 20:8-11</a>) reappears in <a href="?bref=Deut.5.12-15">Deuteronomy 5:12-15</a>, but a different reason is attached to its observance: “Remember that you were once slaves in Egypt and that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God brought you out with amazing power and mighty deeds. That is why the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God has commanded you to observe the Sabbath day” (v <a href="?bref=Deut.5.15">15</a>).</p>
<p>The differences between these two accounts of the fourth commandment are important. The first (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.1-26">Ex 20</a>) is addressed, <span class="ital">through</span> Israel, to all people as created beings. The second (<a href="?bref=Deut.5.1-33">Dt 5</a>) is directed <span class="ital">to</span> Israel as God’s redeemed people. So the Sabbath is God’s signpost, pointing not only to his goodness toward all people as their Creator but also to his mercy toward his chosen people as their Redeemer.</p>
<p>There is another significant note in Deuteronomy regarding the Sabbath’s work-ban: “On that day no one in your household may do any kind of work. This includes you, your sons and daughters, your male and female servants, your oxen and donkeys and other livestock, and any foreigners living among you. All your male and female servants must rest as you do” (<a href="?bref=Deut.5.14">Dt 5:14</a>). All the OT’s covenant teaching has a practical concern for others. The Israelite family had to show the same loving concern to those who served them, as God had shown them when in slavery in Egypt. The Sabbath was the ideal moment to practice this expression of love. Jesus was especially eager to rescue this humanitarian side of Sabbath observance from the mass of cruel regulations that threatened it in his day (see, e.g., <a href="?bref=Mark.3.1-5">Mk 3:1-5</a>).</p>
<p>The OT develops this humanitarian theme further with the provision for a “sabbatical year”  (see <a href="?bref=Exod.23.10-12">Ex 23:10-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.25.1-7">Lv 25:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.15.1-11">Dt 15:1-11</a>; also the regulations for the “year of jubilee” in <a href="?bref=Lev.25.8-55">Lv 25:8-55</a>). Every seventh year the land was to lay fallow and be uncultivated (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.4">Lv 25:4</a>). It needed a regular rest just like the people it fed. The primary purpose of this law was kindness: “But you, your male and female slaves, your hired servants, and any foreigners who live with you may eat the produce that grows naturally during the Sabbath year. And your livestock and the wild animals will also be allowed to eat of the land’s bounty” (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.25.6-7">6-7</a>). <a href="?bref=Deut.15.1-11">Deuteronomy 15:1-11</a> extends the same humanitarian principle into the world of commerce. All debts within God’s redeemed community were to be canceled during the sabbatical year. For the greedy who might be tempted to refuse a loan if the sabbatical year was imminent, the law added a warning and a promise: “Do not be mean-spirited and refuse someone a loan because the year of release is close at hand. If you refuse to make the loan and the needy person cries out to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, you will be considered guilty of sin. Give freely and willingly, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God will bless you in everything you do” (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.9-10">Dt 15:9-10</a>).</p>
<p>Observing the sabbatical year was obviously a great test of the people’s obedience to God and of their willingness to depend on him for their livelihood.</p>
<p>Regarding the seventh day, the OT law codes sustain the work-ban by defining what may and may not be done by God’s people on the Sabbath day. The bans were not meant to rule out all activity. Their aim was to stop regular, everyday work, because if God had set aside the Sabbath (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.11">Ex 20:11</a>), the most obvious way of disrespecting it was to treat it just like any other day. Rules were spelled out in specific terms that the farmer (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.21">34:21</a>), the salesman (<a href="?bref=Jer.17.27">Jer 17:27</a>), and even the housewife (<a href="?bref=Exod.35.2-3">Ex 35:2-3</a>) would understand.</p>
<p>The details may seem unimportant, but obedience to the Sabbath law was seen as the main test of the people’s allegiance to the Lord. It was made quite clear that willful disobedience was a capital offense (<a href="?bref=Exod.35.2">Ex 35:2</a>), and the fate of the person found gathering wood in defiance of Sabbath regulations showed that this was not a vain threat (<a href="?bref=Num.15.32-36">Nm 15:32-36</a>).</p>
<p>With so many rules and regulations (and with the death penalty overhanging all), the Sabbath easily could have become a day of fear—a day when the people were more afraid of committing an offense than worshiping the Lord and enjoying a weekly rest. But the Sabbath was intended to be a blessing, not a burden. Above everything else, it was a weekly sign that the Lord loved his people and wanted to draw them into an ever-closer relationship with himself. Those who valued that relationship enjoyed the Sabbath, calling it a delight (<a href="?bref=Isa.58.13-14">Is 58:13-14</a>). Nowhere does the OT express its sheer joy in Sabbath worship more powerfully than in <a href="?bref=Ps.92.1-15">Psalm 92</a>, which has the title “A Song for the Sabbath.”</p>
<p>The later prophets, were, however, far from blind to the darker side of human nature. They knew that a great deal of Sabbath observance was a sham. Many people treated the Sabbath more as holiday than holy day, an opportunity for self-indulgence rather than delighting in the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.58.13">Is 58:13</a>). Some greedy tradesmen found its restrictions very annoying (<a href="?bref=Amos.8.5">Am 8:5</a>).</p>
<p>As God’s spokesmen, the prophets were not afraid of exposing such neglect and abuse (<a href="?bref=Ezek.22.26">Ez 22:26</a>). Isaiah said that those who worship on Sabbath with unrepentant hearts are sickening to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.10-15">Is 1:10-15</a>). Jeremiah said that Jerusalem’s Sabbath breaking was the symptom of its rebellion, and will bring destruction on the city (<a href="?bref=Jer.17.27">Jer 17:27</a>). Ezekiel warned the people that the Lord’s judgement was certain because they had neglected the Sabbath for so long, yet he had been very patient with them (<a href="?bref=Ezek.20.12-24">Ez 20:12-24</a>).</p>
<p>When judgment fell (in the exile to Babylon, 586 <span class="era">BC</span>), the surviving remnant of the nation took the lesson to heart. Sabbath keeping was one of the few distinctive marks faithful Jews could retain in a foreign land, so it became extremely meaningful. Prompted by prophets like Ezekiel, who set out rules for Sabbath worship in the rebuilt temple at Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Ezek.44.24">Ez 44:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.17">45:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.46.3">46:3</a>), the returning exiles were more careful than their predecessors in observing the Sabbath day under the leadership of men like Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.31">Neh 10:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.13.15-22">13:15-22</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Before the first century, some Jews in Palestine developed a lot of rules for promoting the Sabbath. Unfortunately, it led to such complexities and legalistic details that the main purpose of the Sabbath was lost.</p>
<p>Jesus had many confrontations with the Jewish religious leaders over Sabbath observances. From their perspective, Jesus was a Sabbath breaker and therefore a lawbreaker. Jesus, however, never saw himself as a Sabbath breaker. He went to synagogue regularly on the Sabbath day (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.16">Lk 4:16</a>). He read the lesson, preached, and taught (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.21">Mk 1:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.10">Lk 13:10</a>). He clearly accepted the principle that the Sabbath was an appropriate day for worship.</p>
<p>He collided with the Pharisees where their tradition departed from biblical teaching. He made this clear when defending his disciples by using Scripture. They had been accused of breaking the Sabbath tradition by walking through grainfields and breaking off heads of wheat (which fell into the category of “harvesting,” according to the Pharisees; <a href="?bref=Mark.2.23-26">Mk 2:23-26</a>). He followed this up with a remark that took his hearers straight back to God’s Creation purpose for the Sabbath: “The Sabbath was made to benefit people, and not people to benefit the Sabbath” (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.27">Mk 2:27</a>).</p>
<p>Rabbinic tradition had exalted the institution above the people it was meant to serve. By making it an end in itself, the Pharisees had effectively robbed the Sabbath of one of its main purposes.</p>
<p>More than anything else, Jesus’s Sabbath healings clashed with rabbinic restrictions. The OT does not forbid cures on the Sabbath day, but the rabbis labeled all healing as work which must be avoided on the Sabbath unless life was at risk. Jesus fearlessly exposed the cruelty and absurd inconsistencies to which this attitude led. He asked his opponents how could it be right to circumcise a baby or lead an animal to water on the Sabbath day (which tradition allowed) but wrong to heal a chronically handicapped woman and a crippled man, even if their lives were not in immediate danger (<a href="?bref=Luke.13.10-17">Lk 13:10-17</a>; <a href="?bref=John.7.21-24">Jn 7:21-24</a>). He taught that the Sabbath was a particularly appropriate day for acts of mercy (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.4-5">Mk 3:4-5</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus, the man from heaven, claimed that he was Lord of the Sabbath (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.28">Mk 2:28</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.12.5-8">Mt 12:5-8</a>). Just as God kept working, despite his Creation rest, to sustain the world in his mercy, so Jesus would continue to teach and to heal on the Sabbath day (<a href="?bref=John.5.2-17">Jn 5:2-17</a>). But one day his redemptive work would be complete, and then the Sabbath’s purpose as a sign of redemption would be accomplished.</p>
<p>Paul understood the meaningfulness of Jesus’s death and resurrection regarding Sabbath observance. He didn’t ban all observance of the Jewish Sabbath. Indeed, he attended many Sabbath synagogue services himself in his evangelistic travels (see, e.g., <a href="?bref=Acts.13.14-16">Acts 13:14-16</a>). Jewish Christians who insisted on keeping up their Sabbath practices were free to do so, provided they respected diverging opinions (<a href="?bref=Rom.14.5-6,13">Rom 14:5-6, 13</a>). But he resisted any suggestion that observing the Jewish calendar was necessary for salvation (<a href="?bref=Gal.4.8-11">Gal 4:8-11</a>). Paul considered the Sabbath to be a shadow, while Christ himself is the reality of that shadow (<a href="?bref=Col.2.17">Col 2:17</a>).</p>
<p>The writer of the Letter to the Hebrews explains how the twin biblical “sabbath themes” of creation and redemption find their joint fulfillment in Christ. He showed how both relate to the present and future rest that Christians can and do enjoy in Jesus (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.1-11">Heb 4:1-11</a>).</p>
<p>God intends all his people to share his promised rest (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.1">Heb 4:1</a>). He showed this intention clearly when he brought Israel to the Promised Land, but that did not mark the complete fulfillment of his promise which is in heaven. Christ has already entered there. He is resting from his work, just as God did after the Creation. And because of his redeeming work, he invites all those who believe in him to share that same “sabbath rest” now (v <a href="?bref=Heb.4.9">9</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=LordsDaythe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Lord’s Day, The</a>; <a href="?item=SabbathDaysJourney_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sabbath Day’s Journey</a>; <a href="?item=CommandmentstheTen_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Commandments, The Ten</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>