<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Satan">
  <title>Satan</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SATAN</p>
<p class="fl">Spirit being who opposes God and seeks to frustrate his plans and lead his people into rebellion.</p>
<p>Satan is rarely mentioned in the OT. He is pictured as an angel who acts as the heavenly prosecutor (<a href="?bref=Job.1.6-12">Jb 1:6-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.2.1-7">2:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.3.1-2">Zec 3:1-2</a>). As such, he is called “the satan” or “the accuser,” and there is nothing in the context to indicate that the angel is evil. It is not until the late OT period that Satan appears as a tempter: in <a href="?bref=1Chr.21.1">1 Chronicles 21:1</a>, the story of <a href="?bref=2Sam.24.1">2 Samuel 24:1</a> is retold with Satan (used for the first time as a proper name) substituted for God and pictured as an evil figure. The OT, then, has no developed doctrine of Satan but contains the raw material from which the later doctrine came. (Some people see Lucifer of <a href="?bref=Isa.14.12">Is 14:12</a> as a reference to Satan, but the context is clearly referring to the king of Babylon; it is therefore unlikely that any reference to Satan was intended.)</p>
<p>The Jews further developed the idea of Satan during the intertestamental period, also calling him Belial, Mastema, and Sammael. Three differing conceptions appear. First, the Satan of the OT reappears in the roles of tempting people, of accusing them in heaven before God, and of hindering God’s saving plan (Jubilees 11:5; 17:16; Assumption of Moses 17; 1 Enoch 40:7). Second, the Dead Sea Scrolls present Satan (Belial) as the leader of the evil forces and attacker of the righteous. This development was probably influenced by the evil god of Zoroastrian religion. But unlike the Zoroastrian idea, the scrolls never present two gods but rather one God who has created both Belial and the Prince of Light (who is sure to win in the end, for God is with him). Third, in this literature Satan is often identified with OT stories from which his name was originally absent: he lusted after Eve and therefore caused the fall (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.2.24">Wisd of Sol 2:24</a>), he controls the angels who fell in <a href="?bref=Gen.6.1-4">Genesis 6:1-4</a> (Jubilees 10:5-8; 19:28), or he is a fallen angel himself (2 Enoch 29:4).</p>
<p>The NT has a developed portrayal of Satan, and he comes with a whole list of names: Satan (Hebrew for “accuser”), devil (the Greek translation of Satan), Belial, Beelzebul, the Adversary, the Dragon, the Enemy, the Serpent, the Tester, and the Wicked One. Satan is pictured as the ruler of a host of angels (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.41">Mt 25:41</a>) and the controller of the world (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.6">Lk 4:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.18">Acts 26:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.4.4">2 Cor 4:4</a>), who especially governs all who are not Christians (<a href="?bref=Mark.4.15">Mk 4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=John.8.44">Jn 8:44</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.10">Acts 13:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.13">Col 1:13</a>). He is opposed to God and seeks to alienate all people from God; therefore, he is an especially dangerous foe of Christians (<a href="?bref=Luke.8.33">Lk 8:33</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.5">1 Cor 7:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.8">1 Pt 5:8</a>), who must steadfastly resist him and see through his cunning (<a href="?bref=2Cor.2.11">2 Cor 2:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.6.11">Eph 6:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.4.7">Jas 4:7</a>). Satan works his evil will by tempting persons (<a href="?bref=John.13.2">Jn 13:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.3">Acts 5:3</a>), by hindering God’s workers (<a href="?bref=1Thes.2.18">1 Thes 2:18</a>), by accusing Christians before God (<a href="?bref=Rev.12.10">Rv 12:10</a>), and by controlling the evil persons who resist the gospel (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.9">2 Thes 2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.2.9,13">Rv 2:9, 13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.13.2">13:2</a>).</p>
<p>Most importantly, however, the NT teaches us that this being, who has been evil from the beginning (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.8">1 Jn 3:8</a>), has now been bound and cast out of heaven through the ministry of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.18">Lk 10:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.12.1-18">Rv 12</a>). While Satan is still a dangerous enemy, Jesus himself prays for us and has given us the powerful weapons of prayer, faith, and the efficacy of his blood. Satan can still cause physical illness when allowed by God (<a href="?bref=2Cor.12.7">2 Cor 12:7</a>), and persons can be delivered over to him for punishment (<a href="?bref=1Cor.5.5">1 Cor 5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.1.20">1 Tm 1:20</a>). Satan will always be under God’s control, who will eventually destroy him (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.20">Rom 16:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.20.10">Rv 20:10</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Angel_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Angel</a>; <a href="?item=Demon_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Demon</a>; <a href="?item=DemonPossession_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Demon-possession</a>; <a href="?item=Lucifer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Lucifer</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>