<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Savior">
  <title>Savior</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SAVIOR</p>
<p class="fl">One who delivers or rescues. The term “savior” is most frequently applied to God and Jesus Christ in the Bible. Understanding that Jesus is the Savior is a key truth to appropriate oneself of the biblical message. <span class="translatorCheckGreek">Versions of the English Bible use “savior” in the OT to translate various forms of the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">yasha‘</span><span class="ital">,</span> which means “to save,” “to deliver,” or “to rescue.” Most frequently it is used to translate the participle of the verb, <span class="hebrew">moshia‘</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “the one who saves.”</span><span class="translatorCheckTargetLanguage">Used in this way, “savior” is found 13 or 14 times in the OT, depending upon the version.</span></p>
<p>The term “savior” in its basic understanding of someone who delivers or rescues is illustrated in <a href="?bref=Deut.22.27">Deuteronomy 22:27</a>, where the law anticipated a situation when no deliverer was near in time of need. <span class="hebrew">Moshia‘</span> is also used for individuals, as both Othniel and Ehud are called “deliverers” (<a href="?bref=Judg.3.9,15">Jgs 3:9, 15</a>) and <a href="?bref=Neh.9.27">Nehemiah 9:27</a> speaks of the judges collectively as deliverers sent by God. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.5">Second Kings 13:5</a> reports that the Lord gave Israel a savior in reference to their deliverance from the Arameans. Some have identified this deliverer with King Jeroboam II of Judah; others with a foreign king, quite often Zakir of Hamath. But the text does not clearly indicate who this savior might have been. The point of the text is that God sent this deliverer for his people. The majority of references in the OT refer to God himself as Israel’s savior, and even when other individuals are so termed, it is clearly stated that God sent them or raised them up. Israel understood that God was their savior and declared this in songs of praise (<a href="?bref=Ps.17.7">Pss 17:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.106.1-12">106:1-12</a>) and cries for help (<a href="?bref=Jer.14.8">Jer 14:8</a>). David said this of God: “He is my stronghold, my refuge and my savior” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.22.3">2 Sm 22:3</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Quite often the psalmists refer to the Lord as their <span class="translatorCheckTargetLanguage">“help” or “salvation” (<a href="?bref=Ps.27.9">Pss 27:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.38.22">38:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.42.5,11">42:5, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.65.5">65:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.68.19">68:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.79.9">79:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.85.4">85:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.26">89:26</a>; all rendered “Savior” by the <span class="sc">niv</span>).</span> The exodus was undoubtedly the greatest example of deliverance for Israel and secured their knowledge of God as the savior. The psalmist, in remembrance of Israel’s sin of making a golden calf, proclaims, “They forgot God, their savior, who had done such great things in Egypt” (<a href="?bref=Ps.106.21">Ps 106:21</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.63.11">Is 63:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.13.4-6">Hos 13:4-6</a>). In Isaiah, where “savior” is a frequent title for God, the term is used to emphasize his uniqueness. God alone is seen as savior, in contrast to foreign gods and idols: “I, even I, am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and apart from me there is no savior. I have revealed and saved and proclaimed—I, and not some foreign god among you” (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.11-12">Is 43:11-12</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Isaiah further states that God would show himself as savior by the future blessing and restoration of Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.26">49:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.60.16">60:16</a>). The designation “savior” is not directly applied to the Messiah in the OT, but a passage like <a href="?bref=Zech.9.9">Zechariah 9:9</a> indicates that God’s Anointed One would be a deliverer. Several <?oxy_comment_start author="jeffreygonzales" timestamp="20230901T191727+0200" comment="MT: fictitious"?>apocryphal<?oxy_comment_end?> books use the term “savior” for God, some in lofty titles like “everlasting Savior” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Bar.4.22">Bar 4:22</a>) or “the eternal Savior of Israel” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=3Macc.7.16">3 Macc 7:16</a>). This later usage also illustrates the idea of God as the one who is able to save Israel.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="SignOfTheFishASpecialInsigniaOfJesusNames"/>
<p>The Greek literature uses <span class="translatorCheckGreek"><span class="greek">soter</span> (“savior,” “deliverer” from the verb <span class="greek">sozo</span> “to save,” “to rescue”)</span> for both gods and humans. For example, at one point Herodotus refers to the Athenians as the “saviors” of Greece (<span class="ital">Persian Wars</span> 7.139.5). In the Septuagint <span class="translatorCheckGreek"><span class="greek">soter</span> (“savior”)</span> is used to render various forms of the Hebrew <span class="translatorCheckGreek"><span class="hebrew">yasha‘</span> (“to save”).</span><span class="translatorCheckTargetLanguage"><span class="greek">Soter</span> occurs 24 times in the NT and is exclusively applied to God and Jesus Christ (to God 8 times and to Christ 16 times). Out of the 24 NT occurrences of <span class="greek">soter</span><span class="ital">,</span> ten are in the Letters and five in 2 Peter.</span> Dependence upon the OT can be seen in <a href="?bref=Luke.1.47">Luke 1:47</a>, where Mary praises God as Savior in her hymn of praise. Jesus’ name (Greek for Joshua) means “the Lord is salvation” and was given in anticipation of his function as the Savior (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">Mt 1:21</a>). As the Savior, Jesus completes God’s plan for a promised deliverer (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.23">Acts 13:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.4">Ti 3:4</a>), provides redemption for humanity (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.13-14">Ti 2:13-14</a>), and is the hope of the believer (<a href="?bref=Phil.3.20-21">Phil 3:20-21</a>). Inherent in the term “savior” is the concept of one who saves or delivers from danger to a position of safety. Jesus has delivered the believer from sin and death into immortality and life (<a href="?bref=2Tim.1.10">2 Tm 1:10</a>). While Jesus never refers to himself as Savior (<span class="greek">soter</span>), he is announced as such by the angels at his birth (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.11">Lk 2:11</a>), confessed as such by those who heard his words (<a href="?bref=John.4.42">Jn 4:42</a>), and proclaimed as Savior by the early church (<a href="?bref=Acts.5.31">Acts 5:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.23">13:23</a>). Salvation is central to the mission of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.19.10">Lk 19:10</a>). Paul teaches that Christ is the Savior of the church in the present (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.23">Eph 5:23</a>) and future (<a href="?bref=Phil.3.20">Phil 3:20</a>).</p>
<p>Savior, as a title, is applied to God in the Pastoral Epistles and clearly represents God as Savior of all persons (<a href="?bref=1Tim.2.3">1 Tm 2:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.4.10">4:10</a>). The Pastorals also clearly designate Jesus as Savior (<a href="?bref=2Tim.1.10">2 Tm 1:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.6">Ti 3:6</a>), in some instances also declaring that he is God the Savior (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.13">Ti 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.4-6">3:4-6</a>). Savior is used as a title for Jesus Christ throughout 2 Peter (e.g., <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.20">2 Pt 2:20</a>). John, in his first letter, uses it to describe Jesus as the Savior sent by the Father to save the world (<a href="?bref=1Jn.4.14">1 Jn 4:14</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Salvation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Salvation</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>