<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Scribe">
  <title>Scribe</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SCRIBE</p>
<p class="fl">Reference in early OT times to those employed for their ability to record information in writing. After the exile, scribes were a class of scholars who taught, copied, and interpreted the Jewish law for the people. They appear in the Gospels primarily as opponents of Jesus.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ScribesBeforetheExile">Scribes Before the Exile</p>
<p class="fl">The ability to read and write was not widespread in ancient Israel, and professional secretaries were needed in the various aspects of public life. This appears to be the earliest biblical notion of the term “scribe” and has no particular religious connotation. Scribes were employed to keep accounts or put in writing legal information (<a href="?bref=Jer.32.12">Jer 32:12</a>), military data (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.11">2 Chr 26:11</a>), other public documents (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.14">Jgs 8:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.50.1">Is 50:1</a>), or personal correspondence (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.18">Jer 36:18</a>). These secretaries were essential to royal administrations, and it is frequently mentioned of a chief scribe who functioned as a court recorder (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.3">1 Kgs 4:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.24.11">2 Chr 24:11</a>), as an adviser (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.16-17">2 Sm 8:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.18">2 Kgs 18:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.12">22:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.27.32">1 Chr 27:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.36.3">Is 36:3</a>), and as a financial overseer (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.3-4">2 Kgs 22:3-4</a>). Secretaries or scribes were associated with the priesthood as well, serving as recorders for temple affairs (<a href="?bref=1Chr.24.6">1 Chr 24:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.13-15">2 Chr 34:13-15</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="ScribesAftertheExile">Scribes After the Exile</p>
<p class="fl">With the <?oxy_comment_start author="jeffreygonzales" timestamp="20230901T105405+0200" comment="revival"?>restoration<?oxy_comment_end?> of Judaism under Ezra and Nehemiah, the term “scribe” begins to be associated more narrowly with those who gathered together, studied, and interpreted the Torah (Jewish law). They became a separate occupation of teachers, able to preserve accurately the law of Moses and interpret it to meet the conditions after the exile. In the beginning of this period, Ezra appears as the ideal “scribe who studied and taught the commands and laws of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to Israel” (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.11">Ezr 7:11</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). In Ecclesiasticus, the scribe is portrayed as one who, because of his diligent study of the Law, the Prophets, and Writings (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.38.24-34">Ecclus 38:24ff</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.39.1">39:1</a>), is able to deeply understand the hidden meanings of texts (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.39.2-3">39:2-3</a>), and therefore is able to serve as judge and counsel for the people and the state (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.38.33">38:33</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.39.4-8">39:4-8</a>). Because of his invaluable place in a society governed by the Torah, the scribe is worthy of praise and great respect throughout the generations (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.39.9">39:9</a>). By the second century <span class="era">BC</span>, the scribes were a rather distinct class in Jewish society. From then and onwards, they became closely linked with the rise of the Pharisees, and most scribes were affiliated with them (see the close connection in the NT: <a href="?bref=Matt.5.20">Mt 5:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.12.38">12:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.15.1">15:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.7.5">Mk 7:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.7">Lk 6:7</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TrainingandStatus">Training and Status</p>
<p class="fl">Initially, scribes where trained within priestly families which shared the same occupation. These groups guaranteed the regulation and perpetuation of the position (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.55">1 Chr 2:55</a>). Later, the training became open to members of all classes, with the eventual result, by Jesus’ time, of scribes from families of non-priests being far more numerous and influential. Training began at an early age under the personal supervision of a teacher (rabbi), who gave instructions in all matters pertaining to the law and its interpretation. Since the written law of Moses could not directly address the conditions after the exile, the Scribe’s skills became a significant contribution. The  “oral law” that they established, was regarded as equal to the written law and equally binding for those desiring to please God (see <a href="?bref=Mark.7.6-13">Mk 7:6-13</a>). This important function, lying at the heart of Jewish life, explains the participation of the scribes in the Sanhedrin. The Sanhedrin, in order to make legal decisions in line the law, obviously needed their presence. The scribes, consequently, were the only members outside the aristocratic high priests and elders to be represented in this Jewish supreme court (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.57">Mt 26:57</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.43,53">Mk 14:43, 53</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.22.66">Lk 22:66</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.23.9">Acts 23:9</a>). Being the authoritative instructors of the law both within the temple (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.46">Lk 2:46</a>) and within the various synagogues of Judea and Galilee (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.17">5:17</a>), as well as prominent members of the Sanhedrin, the scribes were greatly respected within the Jewish community. They wore special robes (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.38">Mk 12:38</a>) with memorial fringes at the bottom and phylacteries, or “prayer boxes,” hanging from the arms (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.5">Mt 23:5</a>). Such attire made their presence obvious and caused the common people to rise or bow when they passed (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.38">Mk 12:38</a>). They were respectfully called “rabbi” or “master” (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.7">Mt 23:7</a>) and were given the place of honor during worship and social affairs (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.2">Mt 23:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.39">Mk 12:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.46">Lk 20:46</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheScribesinJesusDay">The Scribes in Jesus’ Day</p>
<p class="fl">During Jesus’ ministry, the scribes mainly appeared as those paying extremely close attention to legal observance. Luke refers to the scribes as “<?oxy_comment_start author="jeffreygonzales" timestamp="20230901T110437+0200" comment="lawyers?"?>men of law<?oxy_comment_end?>”, thereby describing to his gentile listeners and readers the scribes’ chief function as interpreters of the Jewish law. Often, scribes were critical of Jesus, accusing him of violating the law on numerous occasions: when he forgave sins (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.1-3">Mt 9:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.17-26">Lk 5:17-26</a>), when he broke the way they thought Sabbath was to be observed, both through work (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.1-2">Lk 6:1-2</a>) and healing (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.6.6-11">6-11</a>), when they noticed he wasn’t  following their ceremonial washings (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.2-5">Mk 7:2-5</a>), and ignoring their practice of fasting (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.33-39">Lk 5:33-39</a>). Not surprisingly, they especially disapproved of Jesus’ practice of <?oxy_comment_start author="jeffreygonzales" timestamp="20230901T150700+0200" comment="spending time with"?>mingling<?oxy_comment_end?> with the unclean and outcasts of Jewish society (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.16-17">Mk 2:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.15.1-2">Lk 15:1-2</a>). They are frequently found attempting to trick Jesus with questions about the law (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.5">Mk 7:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.28,35">12:28, 35</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.53">Lk 11:53</a>; <a href="?bref=John.8.3-4">Jn 8:3-4</a>). They demanded that Jesus make his identity clear (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.38">Mt 12:38</a>) and reveal the source of his authority to perform miracles (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.22">Mk 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.1-4">Lk 20:1-4</a>). Despite the fact that a small number of them did accept Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.19">Mt 8:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.13.52">13:52</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.32">Mk 12:32</a>; <a href="?bref=John.3.1-2">Jn 3:1-2</a>), they usually were hostile toward him. It was also due to his rising popularity among the people, which posed a threat to their own authority (<a href="?bref=Matt.7.29">Mt 7:29</a>) <?oxy_comment_start author="jeffreygonzales" timestamp="20230901T114422+0200" comment="and, as they believed, to the safety of the city"?>and to the safety of the city<?oxy_comment_end?> <?oxy_comment_start author="jeffreygonzales" timestamp="20230901T114606+0200" comment="The referenced Bible verses do not directly relate to the safety of the city, (especially if the events took place *during* feasts.)"?>(<a href="?bref=Matt.21.15">Mt 21:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.11.18">Mk 11:18</a>)<?oxy_comment_end?>. Another major contributing factor to their opposition to Jesus was how he exposed their hypocrisy and corruption. In his reprimands to the them and to the Pharisees, Jesus openly accused them of seeking public recognition (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.5-7">Mt 23:5-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.38-39">Mk 12:38-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.43">Lk 11:43</a>). They outwardly appeared to be outwardly correct and holy, but were corrupt in their hearts (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.25-28">Mt 23:25-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.39-41">Lk 11:39-41</a>). Jesus also attacked the principle of oral law taught by the scribes, declaring that it was a “heavy burden” that the scribes themselves didn’t even follow themselves (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.2-4,13-22">Mt 23:2-4, 13-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.46">Lk 11:46</a>). They emphasized minor points of the law, yet were also guilty of ignoring the more important concerns of justice, mercy, and faith (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.23-24">Mt 23:23-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.40">Mk 12:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.42">Lk 11:42</a>). They regarded themselves as the descendants of the prophets, but Jesus told them that they would have killed the prophets if they had lived in their day (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.29-36">Mt 23:29-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.9-19">Lk 20:9-19</a>).</p>
<p>Therefore, it is not surprising that the scribes were eager to get rid of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.1">Mk 14:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.53">Lk 11:53</a>). His more flexible interpretation of the law posed a clear threat to their position and authority within the community. The scribes joined forces with their normal opponents (the high priesthood) to plot Jesus’ arrest (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.43">Mk 14:43</a>). When Jesus appeared before them and the rest of the Sanhedrin, they participated in constructing a case against him worthy of death (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.57-66">Mt 26:57-66</a>). When taking Jesus before Herod, they stood by and shouted their accusations with the others (<a href="?bref=Luke.23.10">Lk 23:10</a>). Finally, they participated with other members of the Sanhedrin in mocking Jesus on the cross (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.41-43">Mt 27:41-43</a>). Prior to the destruction of Jerusalem in <span class="era">AD</span> 70, the scribes continued with the other elements of the Sanhedrin to oppose the early Christian church, and they helped get Stephen <?oxy_comment_start author="jeffreygonzales" timestamp="20230901T151408+0200" comment="“martyred” or “murdered”"?>killed for his faith<?oxy_comment_end?> (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.12-14">Acts 6:12-14</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>; <a href="?item=Pharisees_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Pharisees</a>; <a href="?item=Writer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Writer</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>