<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SpiritofGod">
  <title>Spirit of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">SPIRIT OF GOD</p>
<p class="fl">Description of God in action, God in motion. The word “spirit” (Hebrew, <span class="hebrew">ruach</span><span class="ital">;</span> Greek, <span class="greek">pneuma</span>) is the word used from ancient times to describe and explain the experience of divine power working in, upon, and around people.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">There are three basic meanings evident in the use of “spirit” from the earliest Hebrew writings: It was a wind from God, it was the breath of life, and it was a spirit of ecstasy.</p>
<p>First, it was a wind from God (the same Hebrew word translated “Spirit” in <a href="?bref=Gen.1.2">Gn 1:2</a>) that caused the waters of the Flood to go down (<a href="?bref=Gen.8.1">8:1</a>). A wind from God blew locusts over Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.10.13">Ex 10:13</a>) and quail over the camp of Israel. The blast of his nostrils separated the waters of the Red Sea at the exodus (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.21">14:21</a>).</p>
<p>Second, it was the breath of God that made man a living being (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.7">Gn 2:7</a>). It is one of the earliest perceptions of Hebrew faith that humans live only because of the stirring of the divine breath or spirit within them (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.3">Gn 6:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.33.4">Jb 33:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.34.14-15">34:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.104.29-30">Ps 104:29-30</a>). Later, a clearer distinction was drawn between divine Spirit and human spirit, and between spirit and soul, but at the earliest stage these were all more or less perceived to be the same manifestations of the divine power, the source of all life—animal as well as human (<a href="?bref=Gen.7.15,22">Gn 7:15, 22</a>; see <a href="?bref=Eccl.3.19-21">Eccl 3:19-21</a>).</p>
<p>Third, there were occasions when this divine power seemed to overtake and possess an individual fully, so that his or her words or actions far transcended those of normal behavior. Such a person was clearly marked as an agent of God’s purpose and given respect. This was apparently how leaders were recognized in the pre-monarchy period—Othniel (<a href="?bref=Judg.3.10">Jgs 3:10</a>), Gideon (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.34">6:34</a>), Jephthah (<a href="?bref=Judg.11.29">11:29</a>), and the first king, Saul (<a href="?bref=1Sam.11.6">1 Sm 11:6</a>), as well. In the same way, the earliest prophets were those whose inspiration came in ecstasy (<a href="?bref=1Sam.19.20-24">1 Sm 19:20-24</a>).</p>
<p>In the earlier stages of Hebrew thought, ecstatic experience was seen as the direct effect of divine power. This was true even when the ecstasy was recognized as evil in character, as in the case of Saul’s seizure by the Spirit (<a href="?bref=1Sam.16.14-16">1 Sm 16:14-16</a>). A spirit from God could be for evil as well as for good (see <a href="?bref=Judg.9.23">Jgs 9:23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.19-23">1 Kgs 22:19-23</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">In the Writings of the Prophets</p>
<p class="fl">For Isaiah, the spirit was that which characterized God and distinguished him and his actions from human affairs (<a href="?bref=Isa.31.3">Is 31:3</a>). Later, the adjective “holy” appeared to distinguish the Spirit of God from any other spirit, human or divine (<a href="?bref=Ps.51.11">Ps 51:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.63.10-11">Is 63:10-11</a>).</p>
<p>The problem of false prophecy emphasized the danger of assuming that every message delivered in ecstasy was the word of the Lord. Therefore, the content of the message delivered was tested, as well as the character of the prophet’s life, but not the degree or quality of inspiration (see <a href="?bref=Deut.13.1-5">Dt 13:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.18.22">18:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.14">Jer 23:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.3.5">Mi 3:5</a>). This sense of a need to differentiate between true and false inspiration and to distinguish the word of God from the any ecstatic message supposed from God may help to explain the otherwise puzzling reluctance of the major eighth- and seventh-century <span class="era">BC</span> prophets to attribute their inspiration to the Spirit.</p>
<p class="h3">In the Exilic and Postexilic Writings</p>
<p class="fl">In exilic and postexilic literature, the role of the Spirit is narrowed to two major functions: that of the prophetic Spirit and that of the Spirit of the age to come.</p>
<p>The later prophets again spoke of the Spirit in explicit terms as the inspirer of prophecy (see <a href="?bref=Ezek.3.1-4,22-24">Ez 3:1-4, 22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.5">Hg 2:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.4.6">Zec 4:6</a>). As they looked back to the preexilic period, these prophets freely attributed the inspiration of “the former prophets” to the Spirit as well (<a href="?bref=Zech.7.12">Zec 7:12</a>).</p>
<p>This tendency to exalt the Spirit’s role as the inspirer of prophecy became steadily stronger in the period between the OT and NT, until in rabbinic Judaism the Spirit was almost exclusively the inspirer of the prophetic writings now regarded as Scripture.</p>
<p>The other understanding of the Spirit’s role during exilic and postexilic times was that the Spirit would be the manifestation of the power of God in the age to come. That end-time hope of divine power causing a final cleansing and a renewed creation is rooted principally in Isaiah’s prophecies (<a href="?bref=Isa.4.4">Is 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.32.15">32:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.44.3-4">44:3-4</a>). Isaiah speaks of someone anointed by the Spirit to accomplish complete and final salvation (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.2">11:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.42.1">42:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.61.1">61:1</a>). Elsewhere, the same longing is expressed in terms of the Spirit being freely distributed to all Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.39.29">Ez 39:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-29">Jl 2:28-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.12.10">Zec 12:10</a>) in the new covenant (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.31-34">Jer 31:31-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.36.26-27">Ez 36:26-27</a>).</p>
<p>In the period prior to Jesus, the understanding of the Spirit as the Spirit of prophecy and as the Spirit of the age to come had developed into the widespread dogma that the Spirit was no longer to be experienced in the present. The Spirit had been known in the past as the inspirer of prophetic writings, but after Haggai, Zechariah, and Malachi, the Spirit had withdrawn (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.4.44-46">1 Macc 4:44-46</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.9.27">9:27</a>; 2 Bar 85:1-3; see also <a href="?bref=Ps.74.9">Ps 74:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.13.2-6">Zec 13:2-6</a>). The Spirit would be known again in the age of the Messiah, but in the interim the Spirit was absent from Israel.</p>
<p>The consequence of this accepted absence of the Spirit was that the Spirit in practice became less important then the law. The Spirit was the inspirer of the law, but since the Spirit could no longer be experienced directly, the law became the sole voice of the Spirit. It was this increasing dominance of the law and its authoritative interpreters that provided the background for the mission of Jesus and the initial spread of Christianity.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">If we are to understand the NT’s teaching on the Spirit, we must recognize both its continuity and discontinuity with the OT. At many points NT usage cannot be fully understood except against the background of OT concepts or passages. For example, the ambiguity of <a href="?bref=John.3.8">John 3:8</a> (“wind,” “Spirit”), <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.8">2 Thessalonians 2:8</a> (“breath”), and <a href="?bref=Rev.11.11">Revelation 11:11</a> (“breath of life”) takes us back to the basic Hebrew meanings of “spirit.” <a href="?bref=Acts.8.39">Acts 8:39</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.17.3">Revelation 17:3</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.21.10">21:10</a> reflect the same conception of the Spirit that we find in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.12">1 Kings 18:12</a>, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.16">2 Kings 2:16</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ezek.3.14">Ezekiel 3:14</a>. The NT writers generally share the rabbinic view that Scripture has the authority of the Spirit behind it (see <a href="?bref=Mark.12.36">Mk 12:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.28.25">Acts 28:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.3.7">Heb 3:7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.1.21">2 Pt 1:21</a>). The principal continuity is that the NT brings the fulfillment of what the OT writers looked forward to. At the same time, Christianity is not simply fulfilled Judaism. Jesus’s coming and his giving of his Spirit to live within his believers marks off the new faith as something new and distinct.</p>
<p class="h3">The Spirit of the New Age</p>
<p class="fl">The most striking feature of Jesus’s ministry and of the message of the earliest Christians was their conviction and proclamation that the blessings of the new age were already present, that the end-time Spirit had already been poured out. With the exception of the Essenes at Qumran, no other group or individual within the Jewish religion of that time had dared to make such a bold claim. The prophets and the rabbis looked for a messianic age yet to come, and the apocalyptic writers warned of its imminent arrival, but none thought of it as already present. Even John the Baptist spoke only of one about to come and of the Spirit’s operation in the imminent future (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.8">Mk 1:8</a>). But for Jesus and first-century Christians, the longed for hope was a living reality, and the claim carried with it the exciting sense of being in “the last days.” Without some recognition of that end-time dimension of the Christians’ faith and life, we cannot understand this teaching on the Spirit and the experience of the Spirit.</p>
<p>Jesus clearly thought of his teachings and healings as fulfillment of the prophetic hope (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.41-42">Mt 12:41-42</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.13.16-17">13:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.17.20-21">Lk 17:20-21</a>). In particular, he saw himself as the one anointed by the Spirit to provide salvation (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.3-6">Mt 5:3-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.11.5">11:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.17-19">Lk 4:17-19</a>). Jesus also understood his exorcisms as the effect of the power of God and as manifestations of the end-time rule of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.27-28">Mt 12:27-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.22-26">Mk 3:22-26</a>). The Gospel writers, especially Luke, emphasize the end-time character of Jesus’s life and ministry by stressing the role of the Spirit in his birth (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.18">Mt 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.35,41,67">Lk 1:35, 41, 67</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.25-27">2:25-27</a>), his baptism (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.9-10">Mk 1:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.38">Acts 10:38</a>), and his ministry (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.1">Mt 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.12.18">12:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.12">Mk 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.1,14">Lk 4:1, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.21">10:21</a>; <a href="?bref=John.3.34">Jn 3:34</a>).</p>
<p>The Christian church began with the in-breathing of the Holy Spirit on the day of Christ’s resurrection (<a href="?bref=John.20.22">Jn 20:22</a>), followed by the outpouring of the Spirit at Pentecost “in the last days.” The overwhelming experience of vision and inspired utterance was taken as definite proof that the new age prophesied by Joel had now arrived (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.2-5,17-18">Acts 2:2-5, 17-18</a>). Similarly, in Hebrews the gift of the Spirit is spoken of as “the powers of the age to come” (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.4-5">Heb 6:4-5</a>). More striking still is Paul’s understanding of the Spirit as the guarantee of God’s complete salvation (<a href="?bref=2Cor.1.22">2 Cor 1:22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.5">5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.13-14">Eph 1:13-14</a>), and as the first installment of the believer’s inheritance of God’s kingdom (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.15-17">Rom 8:15-17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.9-11">1 Cor 6:9-11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.42-50">15:42-50</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.4.6-7">Gal 4:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.16-18,21-23">5:16-18, 21-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.13-14">Eph 1:13-14</a>). Again, the Spirit is here thought of as the power of the age to come, as that power (which will characterize God’s rule at the end of time) already shaping and transforming the lives of believers.</p>
<p>For Paul, this means also that the gift of the Spirit is only the beginning of a lifelong process that will not end until the believer’s whole person is brought under the Spirit’s power (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.11,23">Rom 8:11, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.44-49">1 Cor 15:44-49</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.18">2 Cor 3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.1-5">5:1-5</a>). It also means that the present experience of faith is one of lifelong tension between what God has already begun to bring about in the believer’s life and what has not yet been brought under God’s grace (<a href="?bref=Phil.1.6">Phil 1:6</a>). It is this tension between life “in the Spirit” and life “in the flesh” (see <a href="?bref=Gal.2.20">Gal 2:20</a>) that is painfully expressed in <a href="?bref=Rom.7.24">Romans 7:24</a> and <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.2-4">2 Corinthians 5:2-4</a>.</p>
<p class="h3">The Spirit of New Life</p>
<p class="fl">Since the Spirit is the mark of the new age, it is not surprising that the NT writers understood the gift of the Spirit to be that which brings an individual into the new age. John the Baptist described the way the coming one would baptize with the Holy Spirit and with fire (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.11">Mt 3:11</a>). According to <a href="?bref=Acts.1.5">Acts 1:5</a> and <a href="?bref=Acts.11.16">11:16</a>, this imagery was taken up by Jesus, and the promise is seen as fulfilled at Pentecost—the outpouring of the Spirit here being understood as the risen Christ’s action in drawing his disciples into the new age (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.17,33">Acts 2:17, 33</a>).</p>
<p>It seems to be one of Luke’s aims in the book of Acts to highlight the central importance of the gift of the Spirit in conversion-initiation—it is that decisive “gift of the Holy Spirit” that makes one a Christian (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.38-39">Acts 2:38-39</a>). People could have been followers of Jesus on earth, but it was only when they received the gift of the Spirit that they could be said to have “believed in the Lord Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.16-17">11:16-17</a>). When the Spirit’s presence was manifested in and upon a person’s life, that was recognized by Peter as proof enough that God had accepted that person, even though he or she had not yet made any formal profession of faith or been baptized (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.44-48">10:44-48</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.15-18">11:15-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.15.7-9">15:7-9</a>). Apollos was already radiant with the Spirit (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.25">18:25</a>). That’s why, even though his knowledge of “the way of God” was slightly defective (vv <a href="?bref=Acts.18.24-26">24-26</a>), he apparently was not required to supplement his “baptism of John” with Christian baptism. However, the 12 so-called disciples at Ephesus proved by their very ignorance of the Spirit that they were not yet disciples of the Lord Jesus (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.1-6">19:1-6</a>). Paul asked these 12 men, “Did you receive the Holy Spirit when you believed?” (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.2">19:2</a>).</p>
<p>This accords with Paul’s emphasis in his letters. Belief and reception of the Spirit go together: to receive the Spirit is to begin the Christian life (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.2-3">Gal 3:2-3</a>); to be baptized in the Spirit is to become a member of the body of Christ (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.13">1 Cor 12:13</a>); to “have the Spirit of Christ” is to belong to Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.9-11">Rom 8:9-11</a>); to receive the Spirit is equivalent to becoming a child of God (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.14-17">Rom 8:14-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.4.6-7">Gal 4:6-7</a>). The Spirit so characterizes the new age and the life of the new age that only the gift of the Spirit can bring a person into the new age to experience the life of the new age. Because the Spirit is distinctively and in particular the life-giver; the Spirit indeed <span class="ital">is</span> the life of the new age (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.2,6,10">Rom 8:2, 6, 10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45">1 Cor 15:45</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.6">2 Cor 3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.25">Gal 5:25</a>).</p>
<p>In just the same way in John’s writings, the Spirit is characteristically the life-giving Spirit (<a href="?bref=John.6.63">Jn 6:63</a>), the power from above, the seed of divine life that produces the new birth (<a href="?bref=John.3.3-8">Jn 3:3-8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.9">1 Jn 3:9</a>), and a river of living water that brings life when one believes in Christ (<a href="?bref=John.7.37-39">Jn 7:37-39</a>; so also <a href="?bref=John.4.10,14">4:10, 14</a>). Or again, reception of the Spirit in <a href="?bref=John.20.22">John 20:22</a> is depicted as a new creation similar to <a href="?bref=Gen.2.7">Genesis 2:7</a>. Consequently, in <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.24">1 John 3:24</a> and <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.13">4:13</a>, possession and experience of the Spirit count as one of the “tests of life” listed in that letter.</p>
<p class="h3">Manifestations of the Spirit</p>
<p class="fl">It will be clear from what has already been said that when the first Christians, like the ancient Hebrews, spoke of the Spirit, they were thinking of experiences of divine power. In the NT, as in the OT, “Spirit” is the word used to explain the experience of new life and vitality (see above), of liberation from legalism (e.g., <a href="?bref=Rom.8.2">Rom 8:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.17">2 Cor 3:17</a>), of spiritual refreshing and renewal (cf. e.g., <a href="?bref=Isa.32.15">Is 32:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.29">Ez 39:29</a> with <a href="?bref=John.7.37-39">Jn 7:37-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.5">Rom 5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.13">1 Cor 12:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.3.5-6">1 Tm 3:5-6</a>). It is important to realize how wide a range of experiences were attributed to the Spirit: ecstatic experiences (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.24">Acts 2:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.43-47">10:43-47</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.19.6">19:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.10.10">10:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.22.17">22:17</a>—“in ecstasy”; <a href="?bref=2Cor.12.1-4">2 Cor 12:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.1.10">Rv 1:10</a>), emotional experiences (e.g., love—<a href="?bref=Rom.5.5">Rom 5:5</a>; joy—<a href="?bref=Acts.13.52">Acts 13:52</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.6">1 Thes 1:6</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Gal.5.22">Gal 5:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.1-2">Phil 2:1-2</a>), experiences of illumination (<a href="?bref=2Cor.3.14-17">2 Cor 3:14-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.17-18">Eph 1:17-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.6.4-5">Heb 6:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.20-21">1 Jn 2:20-21</a>), and experiences producing moral transformation (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.9-11">1 Cor 6:9-11</a>). Likewise, when Paul speaks of spiritual gifts, called <span class="greek">charismata</span> in Greek (acts or words that bring divine grace to concrete expression), he evidently has a wide range of actual events in mind: inspired speech (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.8-10">1 Cor 12:8-10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.5">1 Thes 1:5</a>), miracles and healings (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.9">1 Cor 12:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.5">Gal 3:5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.2.4">Heb 2:4</a>), and various acts of service and help, of counsel and administration, and of aid and mercy (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.7-8">Rom 12:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.28">1 Cor 12:28</a>).</p>
<p>Although we talk of the Spirit in terms of experience, we should not overemphasize particular experiences or manifestations, as though earliest Christianity consisted of a sequence of mountaintop experiences or spiritual highs. There clearly were such experiences, indeed a wide range of experiences, but no one experience is singled out to be sought by all (except prophecy). There is no distinctively second (or third) experience of the Spirit in the NT, and Paul warned against overvaluing particular manifestations of the Spirit (<a href="?bref=1Cor.14.6-19">1 Cor 14:6-19</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.12.1-10">2 Cor 12:1-10</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.8.11-13">Mk 8:11-13</a>). Where particular experiences are valued, it is as manifestations of a more sustained experience, particular expressions of an underlying relationship (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.6.3-5">Acts 6:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.24">11:24</a>—“full of the Spirit”; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.18">Eph 5:18</a>). What we are in touch with here is the vigor of the experiences of earliest Christianity. If the Spirit is the breath of the new life in Christ (cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.9-10,14">Ez 37:9-10, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.20.22">Jn 20:22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.45">1 Cor 15:45</a>), then presumably the analogy extends further, and the experience of the Spirit is like the experience of breathing: one is not conscious of it all the time, but if one is not conscious of it, at least sometimes, something is wrong.</p>
<p class="h3">The Fellowship of the Spirit</p>
<p class="fl">It was out of this shared experience of the Spirit that the earliest Christian community grew and developed, for this is what “the fellowship [<span class="greek">koinonia</span> in Greek] of the Spirit” properly means: common participation in the same Spirit (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.1">Phil 2:1</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.2.42">Acts 2:42</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.4-9">1 Cor 1:4-9</a>). It was the gift of the Spirit that brought those in Samaria, Caesarea, and elsewhere effectively into the community of the Spirit (Act 8, 10). So also, it was the experience of the one Spirit that provided the unifying bond in the churches of Paul’s mission (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.13">1 Cor 12:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.3-4">Eph 4:3-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.1-2">Phil 2:1-2</a>). Here we see the real importance of the divine manifestations of the Spirit for Paul: it is out of the diversity of these particular manifestations that the body of Christ grows in unity (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.4-8">Rom 12:4-8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.12-17">1 Cor 12:12-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.4-16">Eph 4:4-16</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>