<items release="1.6">
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AaronThePriest">
  <title>Aaron the Priest</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Aaron the Priest</p>
<p class="box-first">Because it marked the beginning of the priesthood in Israel, the consecration of Aaron to his office was both instructive and solemn. Nothing was left to human ingenuity; all was precisely commanded of God. There were three ceremonies: washing, clothing, and anointing. When the tabernacle was finished, Aaron and his sons were set apart to the priesthood by washing (to signify purification), clothing with official garments (for beauty and glory), and anointing with oil (to picture the need of empowering by the Spirit; cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.28.1-43">Ex 28</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.40.12-15">40:12-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.1-36">Lv 8</a>). Aaron thus became the first high priest, serving nearly 40 years. The character of his office was hereditary; this is attested to by his sons’ wearing his garments when they succeeded to the office of high priest (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.29-30">Ex 29:29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.20.25-28">Nm 20:25-28</a>). Although all priests were anointed with oil, the anointing of Aaron and his successors was distinct from that of the ordinary priests (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.7">Ex 29:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.40.12-15">40:12-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.12">Lv 8:12</a>). Because the priesthood was inherited, all subsequent priests had to trace their ancestry back to Aaron (<a href="?bref=Ezra.7.1-5">Ezr 7:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.5">Lk 1:5</a>). Also, a sharp distinction was always drawn between the family of Aaron and the rest of the Levites (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.3.5">Nm 3:5</a>). Thus, the high priest was designated as the anointed priest in a special sense (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.3-4">Lv 4:3-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.20-22">6:20-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.21.10">21:10</a>).</p>
<p>Because of Aaron’s priestly role, the NT looks upon him as prefiguring the Messiah of Israel. Jesus Christ was appointed High Priest (<a href="?bref=Heb.3.1-2">Heb 3:1-2</a>) in the same way God chose Aaron (<a href="?bref=Heb.5.1-5">Heb 5:1-5</a>), but he was described as a greater high priest than Aaron (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.11-28">Heb 7:11-28</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AbominationOfDesolation">
  <title>Abomination of Desolation</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Abomination of Desolation</p>
<p class="box-first">Phrase used in Daniel, 1 Maccabees, Matthew, and Mark to designate a detestable object of pagan idolatry so loathsome to God that he would enact desolating judgment.</p>
<p>In Daniel’s vision of coming abomination, a detestable object would be set up in the temple in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Dan.11.31">Dn 11:31</a>) 1,290 days after the beginning of a period of sacrilege (<a href="?bref=Dan.12.11">Dn 12:11</a>), thus destroying the temple’s holiness and rendering it unclean by ceremonial and ethical standards. In 1 Maccabees it is recorded that the Syrian Antiochus Epiphanes invaded Palestine (167 <span class="era">BC</span>) and erected a desolating sacrilege, probably a statue of Zeus, upon the altar of burnt offering in the temple (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.1.54">1 Macc 1:54</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus used the phrase “abomination of desolation” in answering the disciples’ questions concerning the destruction of the temple and the general course of the age until his return (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.1-31">Mt 24:1-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.1-27">Mk 13:1-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.21.5-28">Lk 21:5-28</a>). In alluding to the Daniel passages, Jesus predicted that something analogous to the destruction by Antiochus would occur. Jesus applied the prediction and fulfillment of Daniel’s prophecy in part to the coming Roman desecration, which did take place in <span class="era">AD</span> 70. Jesus warned that the erection of the abomination of desolation (“desolating sacrilege,” <span class="sc">rsv</span>) was a signal to flee the city of Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.15-16">Mt 24:15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.14">Mk 13:14</a>).</p>
<p>The Greek version of the book of Ezekiel sometimes used “lawlessness” in place of abomination, leading to the association of “man of lawlessness” (man of abomination) with the detestable sacrilege of the Antichrist (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.3">2 Thes 2:3</a>). A similar theme is reflected in the book of Revelation, where the image of the creature or beast from the sea symbolizes the power of the forces of evil demanding obedience and submission (<a href="?bref=Rev.13.1-10">Rv 13:1-10</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Antichrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Antichrist</a>; <a href="?item=DanielBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Daniel, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=Abomination_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Abomination</a>.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AbrahamsBosom">
  <title>Abraham’s Bosom</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Abraham’s Bosom</p>
<p class="box-first">Figure of speech probably derived from the Roman custom of reclining on one’s left side at meals with the guest of honor at the bosom of his host (cf. <a href="?bref=John.13.23-25">Jn 13:23-25</a>). It was used by Jesus in the story of Lazarus as a description of paradise (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.22-23">Lk 16:22-23</a>). In rabbinical writings, as well as <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=4Macc.13.17">4 Maccabees 13:17</a>, righteous people were thought to be welcomed at death by Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. Jesus, probably aware of this, was also alluding to the “messianic banquet,” an image he used a number of times. Thus, in the world to come, the godly poor like Lazarus would not only be welcomed by Abraham but would occupy the place of honor next to him at the banquet.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Heaven_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Heaven</a>; <a href="?item=Paradise_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paradise</a>.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AbrahamTheFriendOfGod">
  <title>Abraham, the Friend of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Abraham, the Friend of God</p>
<p class="box-first">Referred to as the “friend of God” (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.7">2 Chr 20:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.23">Jas 2:23</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>), Abraham played an important role in Hebrew history. Through Abraham’s life, God revealed a program of “election” and “covenant,” which culminated in the work of Jesus Christ. God said to Abraham, “All the families of the earth will be blessed through you” (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.3">Gn 12:3</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Centuries later, the apostle Paul explained that the full import of God’s promise was seen in the preaching of the gospel to all nations and the response of faith in Christ, which signifies believers from all families of the earth as sons of Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.6-9">Gal 3:6-9</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AhabsFailure">
  <title>Ahab’s Failure</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Ahab’s Failure</p>
<p class="box-first">The Bible’s evaluation of Ahab is based not on his accomplishments as a warrior or politician but on his failure to lead Israel in devotion to God. He was worse than all the previous kings of Israel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.28-30">1 Kgs 16:28-30</a>), and his marriage to Jezebel and the introduction of Baal worship “did more to provoke the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, to anger than all the kings of Israel who were before him” (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.31-33">1 Kgs 16:31-33</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AhazsLackOfFaith">
  <title>Ahaz’s Lack of Faith</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Ahaz’s Lack of Faith</p>
<p class="box-first">Ahaz’s lack of trust in God seems to have stemmed from his complete rejection of the Mosaic or traditional Jewish faith rather than from the dangerous political situation. The book of 2 Chronicles describes him as erecting images for the Baals (deities who represented the god Baal, a Canaanite fertility deity). Ahaz is also described as engaging in human sacrifice by offering his sons in pagan worship. The chronicler cites such practices as God’s reason for the invasion by Israel and Syria (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.5">2 Chr 28:5</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AhithophelTheBetrayer">
  <title>Ahithophel the Betrayer</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Ahithophel the Betrayer</p>
<p class="box-first">Ahithophel was surely in David’s mind in <a href="?bref=Ps.41.9">Psalm 41:9</a>, “Even my best friend, the one I trusted completely, the one who shared my food, has turned against me” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). In the NT the similarity of Judas to Ahithophel is seen by Jesus’ use of <a href="?bref=Ps.41.9">Psalm 41:9</a> to describe his own situation (<a href="?bref=John.13.18">Jn 13:18</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AmenAndAmen">
  <title>Amen and Amen</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Amen and Amen</p>
<p class="box-first">Two uses of “amen” by the early church focused special attention on Jesus Christ. In <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.20">2 Corinthians 1:20</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.1.7">Rv 1:7</a>) “amen” is used almost as an equivalent to “yes.” Jesus is viewed as God’s means of saying yes to us, fulfilling his promises. Jesus is also viewed as our means of saying yes to God; through Jesus the “amen” response of believers is presented for the glory of God. In <a href="?bref=Rev.3.14">Revelation 3:14</a>, “the Amen” is used as a title of Christ to emphasize his reliability and the truth of what he says (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.65.16">Is 65:16</a>).</p>
<p>The use of “amen” in the Gospels, however, is entirely different from its use in the OT, the early church, or anywhere else in Jewish literature. Excluding <a href="?bref=Matt.6.13">Matthew 6:13</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) and <a href="?bref=Mark.16.20">Mark 16:20</a> (both passages with textual uncertainty), all of the 100 occurrences of “amen” are spoken by Jesus and always precede what is said rather than coming after as a response. In the synoptic Gospels (Mt, Mk, Lk) the form is always “Amen, I say to you”; in John it is always the doubled form “Amen, amen, I say to you” (<a href="?bref=John.3.3,5">Jn 3:3, 5</a>, etc.). That unique use of “amen” stresses both the authority with which he taught and his majesty: Jesus’ words come with absolute certainty and are binding on all.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AnEternalInheritance">
  <title>An Eternal Inheritance</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">An Eternal Inheritance</p>
<p class="box-first">Jesus Christ’s authority over heaven and earth results from his exalted status as the firstborn Son of the heavenly Father (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.29">Rom 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.17-19">Col 1:17-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.1.2-6">Heb 1:2-6</a>). As the “second Adam,” Christ is the firstborn from the dead by virtue of the resurrection (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.4">Rom 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.20-28,42-50">1 Cor 15:20-28, 42-50</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.22">Eph 1:22</a>). He has received the kingdom from his Father and rules as Lord of Lords (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.36">Acts 2:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.9-11">Phil 2:9-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.5.12-13">Rv 5:12-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.16">19:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Dan.7.13-14,26-27">Dn 7:13-14, 26-27</a>). Believers also share in this kingdom and inheritance and look forward to the consummation, when by virtue of union with Christ they shall receive their inheritance in full (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.13">Rom 4:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.29">Gal 3:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.18">Eph 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.16">Heb 11:16</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AngelOfTheLord">
  <title>Angel of the Lord</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Angel of the Lord</p>
<p class="box-first">Angelic being mentioned in the Bible, more properly translated the “messenger” of the Lord. In the OT the angel of the Lord, as God’s personal emissary, performed special functions at particular times in the history of Israel.</p>
<p>The OT references portray a variety of services rendered but a basic unity of purpose: the gracious intervention of the Lord toward his people, sometimes to an individual, sometimes on a national scale. The angelic figure served Israel positively as guide and protector (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.19">Ex 14:19</a>) and companion in the wilderness wanderings (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.20">Ex 23:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.33.2">33:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.20.16">Nm 20:16</a>) or negatively as assassin or destroyer (<a href="?bref=2Sam.24.16">2 Sm 24:16</a>), yet always acted to preserve the sanctity of Israel’s covenant with God. Certain individuals such as Hagar (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.7">Gn 16:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.21.17">21:17</a>), Balaam (<a href="?bref=Num.22.21-22">Nm 22:21-22</a>), and Abraham’s servant (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.7,40">Gn 24:7, 40</a>) were also confronted by the divinely commissioned messenger (cf. further references <a href="?bref=1Sam.29.9">1 Sm 29:9</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.14.20">2 Sm 14:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.19.27">19:27</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.7">1 Kgs 19:7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.35">2 Kgs 19:35</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.21.15">1 Chr 21:15</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.32.21">2 Chr 32:21</a>).</p>
<p>In certain texts, it seems impossible to distinguish between the angel of the Lord and the Lord himself (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.7-13">Gn 16:7-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.21.17">21:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.22.11-18">22:11-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.24.7,40">24:7, 40</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.31.11-13">31:11-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.48.16">48:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.3.2-10">Ex 3:2-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.6.12-14">Jgs 6:12-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.13.21-22">13:21-22</a>). Sometimes the angel is depicted acting for the Lord and yet is addressed as the Lord. God says, “You may not look directly at my face, for no one may see me and live” (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.20">Ex 33:20</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). And yet Hagar (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.13">Gn 16:13</a>), Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.32.30">Gn 32:30</a>), and Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.11">Ex 33:11</a>) are said to have seen God “face-to-face” in view of their confrontation with this angel. God promises that his very presence will be among the Israelites, and yet it is the angel who goes with them (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.23">Ex 23:23</a>). The commander of the army of God is given reverence equal to God’s (<a href="?bref=Josh.5.13-6.2">Jos 5:13–6:2</a>). The angel seems to possess the full authority and character of God. The presence of the messenger of the Lord, in whom God’s “name” resides (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.20">Ex 23:20</a>) assures the hearer-reader that it is one God who directs the course of history (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.7">Gn 16:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.31.11">31:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.3.2">Ex 3:2</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AngelsOfTheSevenChurches">
  <title>Angels of the Seven Churches</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Angels of the Seven Churches</p>
<p class="box-first">This term is used in <a href="?bref=Rev.1.20">Revelation 1:20</a> and repeated in its singular form in <a href="?bref=Rev.2.1,8,12,18">2:1, 8, 12, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.3.1,7,14">3:1, 7, 14</a>. The word “angel” is translated from the Greek word <span class="greek">angelos</span> (one who delivers a message). Hence, some versions render this word as “messenger” in these chapters. The word could also be translated “guardian” or “representative” in this context. There is no consensus as to the significance of this term in the first three chapters of Revelation. In fact, although the seven churches addressed here were actual places where churches existed, some have suggested that they are symbolic of the various conditions of the church throughout her history. With this view, the angel of each church could be considered a human messenger, minister, or representative of the local church. However, some say that an angel here is simply the personification of the prevailing spirit of each church. A third opinion holds that consistent usage of the word elsewhere in the book provides a persuasive argument that the epistles of Revelation were addressed to a true spiritual guardian angel of each church.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AntilegomenaTheBooksThatDidntMakeIt">
  <title>Antilegomena: The Books that Didn’t Make It</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Antilegomena: The Books that Didn’t Make It</p>
<p class="box-first">In <span class="era">AD</span> 303, the Roman emperor Diocletian began to direct severe persecution against the church. Orders were given to seek out and burn all Christian literature. In an effort to preserve their most sacred writings, the church leaders (or “fathers”) were forced to decide which books were of such importance that they had to be protected at all costs. Other books, of lesser spiritual value, could then be surrendered. In order to make such a distinction, two criteria were generally agreed upon for evaluating the worth of a writing: its association with the early apostolic community and its spiritual value, determined by the degree to which it was used in the church. Despite agreement on those criteria, the fathers were unable to agree on the worth of several books. In 325 Eusebius of Caesarea in his <span class="ital">Ecclesiastical History</span> summarized the situation by distinguishing three classes of NT writings: the <span class="greek">homologoumena</span><span class="ital">,</span> writings accepted by all; the <span class="greek">antilegomena</span><span class="ital">,</span> disputed books; and the <span class="greek">notha</span><span class="ital">,</span> writings that were completely absurd and unholy.</p>
<p>Eusebius subdivided the <span class="greek">antilegomena</span> into two groups. The first he called “the generally recognized books,” writings of good quality and reputation. In that category Eusebius included James, 2 Peter, 2 and 3 John, and Jude. Those books later came to be completely accepted and along with the <span class="greek">homologoumena</span><span class="ital">,</span> now comprise the NT canon. The second group of <span class="greek">antilegomena</span> was called the “spurious” writings generally doubted by the fathers. Included among them were the Acts of Paul, Apocalypse of Peter, Shepherd of Hermas, Barnabas, Didache, the Gospel of Hebrews, and the Apocalypse of John (the NT book of Revelation). The fact that John’s Apocalypse was numbered among both the <span class="greek">homologoumena</span> and the spurious <span class="greek">antilegomena</span><span class="ital">,</span> indicates the controversial nature of that work in the early church.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AnyOtherMediators">
  <title>Any Other Mediators?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Any Other Mediators?</p>
<p class="box-first">Despite the sufficiency and finality of Christ’s continuing mediation, the desire for additional mediators has lingered in the church, where people have prayed to martyrs, angels, departed saints, celibates, and the Virgin Mary. Biblical grounds for this kind of extended mediation were sought in the oneness of the church on earth and in heaven; in saints in either realm interceding for each other; in allusions to departed souls still praying for others (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.27-28">Lk 16:27-28</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.6.9-11">Rv 6:9-11</a>); and especially in the vision of Judas Maccabeus, in which Jeremiah and the high priest Onias, both deceased, invoked blessing on the Jews (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Macc.15.12">2 Macc 15:12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.15.1">Jer 15:1</a>).</p>
<p>At the same time, <a href="?bref=John.20.23">John 20:23</a> was held to show Jesus conferring mediatorial powers of absolution and excommunication upon the apostles and their successors. To these were soon added exclusive powers through the sacraments. This extended mediation was held to complement, not to supplant, that of Christ.</p>
<p>Most Protestants, however, deny the mediation of Mary, angels, departed saints, or the clergy, asserting instead the priesthood of all believers (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.5,9">1 Pt 2:5, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.1.6">Rv 1:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.5.10">5:10</a>). This was understood to mean for all Christians the privilege of individual direct access to God (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.2">Rom 5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.2.18">Eph 2:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.19-22">Heb 10:19-22</a>) and the duty of intercession for others (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.30">Rom 15:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.6.18">Eph 6:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.5.16">Jas 5:16</a>). <a href="?bref=John.20.23">John 20:23</a> is held to emphasize the responsibility of all Christians to bring Christ’s forgiveness to others by witnessing to the gospel. Protestants insist upon the sufficient and final mediation of Christ, who came to show us the Father, died to bring us to God, and ever lives to make intercession for us.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ArchaeologicalEvidenceShedsLightOnJeremiahsWritings">
  <title>Archaeological Evidence Sheds Light on Jeremiah’s Writings</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Archaeological Evidence Sheds Light on Jeremiah’s Writings</p>
<p class="box-first">A dramatic correspondence illustrating <a href="?bref=Jer.34.7">Jeremiah 34:7</a> came to light with the discovery of 21 inscribed potsherds at Lachish by the Wellcome Expedition between 1932 and 1938. Some of these letters refer to “the prophet” (Letter 16 includes the last letters of the name, -<span class="ital">iah</span>). The letters were written by Hoshaiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.42.1">Jer 42:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.43.2">43:2</a>). The latest letters indicate that fire signals had ceased from Azekah (note the reference to such signals in <a href="?bref=Jer.6.1">Jer 6:1</a>). The expected support from Egypt was not available to save either Lachish or Jerusalem.</p>
<p>At Tell Beit Mirsim two jar handles from Jeremiah’s time were inscribed with “Eliakim, steward of Jehoiachin.” A similar jar handle was discovered at Beth-shemesh. Evidently Jehoiachin was considered as the true king even after he was carried to Babylon, and he maintained his royal holding by the steward in charge of his estate.</p>
<p>The seal of Gedaliah found at Lachish in 1935 evidently gives a direct contact with the governor of Judah appointed by Nebuchadnezzar after the fall of Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.5-12">Jer 40:5-12</a>). The seal of Jaazaniah discovered at Tell en-Nasbeh dates to the time of Jeremiah, and probably belonged to the person named in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.23">2 Kings 25:23</a>, though a man of the same name and time is mentioned in <a href="?bref=Jer.35.3">Jeremiah 35:3</a>. The Shallum seal found at Lachish may refer to the youngest son of Josiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.22.11">22:11</a>), to the Shallum mentioned in the Lachish letters, or to a person mentioned in <a href="?bref=Jer.32.7">Jeremiah 32:7</a> or <a href="?bref=Jer.35.4">35:4</a>. The phrase “son of Mas” on the seal probably does not denote family relationship. The Hilkiah seal also reads “son of Mas.” Since the date of origin for this seal also fits Jeremiah’s time, the owner of the seal may have been the father of Jeremiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.1">1:1</a>) or the high priest or some other person.</p>
<p>One positive identification comes from the excavation near the Ishtar Gate of Nebuchadnezzar’s Babylon, where a cuneiform tablet dating about 585 <span class="era">BC</span> lists “Yaukin [Jehoiachin], king of the land of Yahud [Judah]” as one of the resident captives. The Babylonian record even mentions the five sons (cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.3.17-18">1 Chr 3:17-18</a>) who were under the care of a certain Kenaiah. Another identification comes from the recent discovery of Baruch’s seal—Baruch was Jeremiah’s secretary.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ArchaeologicalFindsAtSalamis">
  <title>Archaeological Finds at Salamis</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Archaeological Finds at Salamis</p>
<p class="box-first">Excavation of the site of Salamis reveals Roman baths, a Roman villa, a granite forum, the basilica, the agora, and the temple of Zeus. Portions of the city wall and ancient harbor have also been identified. The most impressive remains are at the north end and are called the Marble Forum. This vast complex includes remains of the gymnasium of the Greco-Roman period, the great hall, and baths from the early Byzantine period. The main forum, or market, measured 750 by 180 feet (228.6 by 54.9 meters), surrounded by large Corinthian columns. The basilica, or church building, is the largest known on the island. It was apparently built after Constantius II had renamed the city Constantia. The large Christian community that once flourished here bears witness to the pioneering work of Barnabas and Saul.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ArchaeologyAtJericho">
  <title>Archaeology at Jericho</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Archaeology at Jericho</p>
<p class="box-first">Jericho was excavated first by Charles Warren in 1868, then by Ernst Sellin and Carl Watzinger in 1907–11, and then by John Garstang in 1930–36. Garstang thought he had found the wall that fell before the Israelites, but the more thorough, scientific, and widely accepted results of the investigations by Kathleen Kenyon in 1952–56 showed that the topmost level of ruins was already too early to tell anything of the city of Joshua’s day. To her goes the credit for uncovering and interpreting the many layers of civilizations that date back to 8000 <span class="era">BC</span> at Jericho.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="AReveredSiteTheMountOfOlives">
  <title>A Revered Site: The Mount of Olives</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">A Revered Site: The Mount of Olives</p>
<p class="box-first">The Mt of Olives quickly became a center of Christian devotion. In the Byzantine era the mountain had 24 churches with vast numbers of monks and nuns. Constantine’s church dominated the summit, celebrating Christ’s ascension. In the fourth century it had even become the customary burial site for Jerusalem’s bishops.</p>
<p>Jews and Muslims likewise revere the site because it will be the place of judgment. According to the Talmud, the righteous will be resurrected between Jerusalem and the Mt of Olives. This explains the vast Muslim and Jewish cemeteries, especially on the western slope of the Mt of Olives. Christian, Jew, and Muslim alike view the Mt of Olives as the focal point for the final Day of the Lord.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BabelOrBabble">
  <title>Babel or Babble</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Babel or Babble</p>
<p class="box-first">The Genesis narrative about the construction of the tower recounts how God intervened and confused the builders so that they could no longer communicate with each other. The word translated “confuse” is <span class="hebrew">balal</span>; it means also “to babble.” A preposition combined with a form of this root, <span class="hebrew">ba-bal</span>, meaning “in confusion” or “in babbling,” became the name for the location of the tower-building project. A popular etymology replaced the original meaning of the name.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BabylonASymbolOfTheEnemyOfGodsPeople">
  <title>Babylon: A Symbol of the Enemy of God’s People</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Babylon: A Symbol of the Enemy of God’s People</p>
<p class="box-first">Several times in the NT, reference is made to the capital city of Nebuchadnezzar to which the Jews had been deported in 586 <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.11-12,17">Mt 1:11-12, 17</a>); in <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.13">1 Peter 5:13</a> and the book of Revelation, Babylon is used symbolically. “She who is at Babylon” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>) was the apostle Peter’s way of referring to the church in Rome, a city that had become as immoral and idolatrous as ancient Babylon. Just as that ancient cultural center had oppressed the Judean exiles, so Rome was now persecuting the Christians living there.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Rev.14.8">Revelation 14:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.16.19">16:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.5">17:5</a>; and <a href="?bref=Rev.18.2,10,21">18:2, 10, 21</a>, Babylon was again used as a symbol for first-century <span class="era">AD</span> Rome. It was pictured as the notorious prostitute, who sits upon the many waters. She was gorgeously arrayed like a queen, sitting on a scarlet beast with 7 heads and 10 horns. She was “drunk with the blood of the saints,” and on her forehead was written: “Babylon the Great, Mother of all Prostitutes and Obscenities in the World” (<a href="?bref=Rev.17.5">17:5</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>An angel helped to interpret the apocalyptic symbolism for John (<a href="?bref=Rev.17.1-18">Rv 17</a>). The “many waters” symbolize nations and peoples. The “seven heads” are seven mountains, which most commentators view as representing the seven hills of Rome. Seven times Babylon is called “the great city” and is described as a dreadfully immoral center of wealth and commerce, ruling over the kings of the earth and especially persecuting the saints of God. The wickedness personified in Babylon clearly symbolizes the historic manifestation of iniquity in first-century Rome.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Rev.18.1-24">Revelation 18</a> completes the picture. “Babylon is fallen—that great city is fallen!” (v <a href="?bref=Rev.18.2">2</a>). God’s final judgment upon her will be severe, repaying her a double penalty (v <a href="?bref=Rev.18.6">6</a>). The main reason for her destruction is her immorality and persecution of the saints (<a href="?bref=Rev.19.2">19:2</a>). The kings and merchants of the earth will mourn her demise (<a href="?bref=Rev.18.9-19">18:9-19</a>), but the pronouncement is made in order that the saints might rejoice and worship God.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BlasphemyAgainstTheHolySpirit">
  <title>Blasphemy against the Holy Spirit</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Blasphemy against the Holy Spirit</p>
<p class="box-first">This is a sin mentioned only in <a href="?bref=Mark.3.28-29">Mark 3:28-29</a> and its parallels, <a href="?bref=Luke.12.10">Luke 12:10</a> and <a href="?bref=Matt.12.31">Matthew 12:31</a>. The context in Mark portrays unbelievers reacting to Jesus’ sudden popularity and startling power in two ways: (1) his family considered him insane and tried to take him home; and (2) the religious leaders, who had already proclaimed him a blasphemer (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.1-12">Mk 2:1-12</a>), attributed his success to demon-possession. Matthew adds that the religious leaders were Pharisees upset by a particular healing. (Luke includes the saying in a totally different context, one of confessing Christ.) Jesus, pointing out that the charge of demon-possession was illogical, also stated strongly that blasphemy against the Holy Spirit can never be forgiven. Jesus was saying that to slander the Holy Spirit is worse even than insulting or blaspheming the Son of Man or God himself (a crime punishable by death in the OT; see <a href="?bref=Lev.24.16">Lv 24:16</a>). Yet Jesus said that those sins are forgivable. Many Jews believed that death forgave all sins, so when Jesus called blasphemy against the Holy Spirit “an eternal sin,” he was making it serious indeed.</p>
<p>The religious leaders to whom Jesus spoke had seen clear, public, and compelling evidence of the good hand of God. By calling that power evil or demonic, they were wickedly and consciously rejecting God, his power, and his saving grace. That was willful and high-handed sin by those who had seen the truth but rejected it and slandered it to others. Thus, the “unforgivable sin” is not some serious moral failure nor persistence in a particular sin nor even insulting or rejecting Jesus in blindness or a fit of rebellion. It is conscious rejection of the “good power of God.” It represents a perversion of the mind in which God and Satan are willfully confused, a free choice of evil rather than good.</p>
<p>How can this sin be unforgivable if God is always willing to forgive? Because it has gone beyond the possibility of recovery on the sinner’s part and because God respects the freedom of persons. It is unrepentable because the person, having refused so stubbornly to repent, finally becomes unable to repent; evidence is in, and such a one will still reject the truth while knowing it to be true.</p>
<p>From the definition it is clear that anyone who believes he or she has committed “the unforgivable sin” could not have done so; a troubled conscience and that kind of sin could never coexist. The fact that a person feels remorse proves that blasphemy against the Holy Spirit has not yet been committed. On the other hand, Jesus’ teaching about it warns all who know the truth of God not to reject that truth or to abandon their faith.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BlindBalaamRebukedByADonkey">
  <title>Blind Balaam Rebuked by a Donkey</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Blind Balaam Rebuked by a Donkey</p>
<p class="box-first">The purpose of this story is to show how spiritually blind Balaam was—no doubt because he had his mind set on the reward he would have if only the Lord would let him curse Israel. In other places in the Bible, Balaam is characterized as a man who “loved to earn money by doing wrong. But Balaam was stopped from his mad course when his donkey rebuked him with a human voice” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.2.15-16">2 Pt 2:15-16</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Jude said of certain persons that “like Balaam, they will do anything for money” (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.11">Jude 1:11</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="BrothersStepbrothersOrCousins">
  <title>Brothers, Stepbrothers, or Cousins?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Brothers, Stepbrothers, or Cousins?</p>
<p class="box-first">Whether the “brothers of Jesus” were half brothers (children of Mary by Joseph), stepbrothers (children of Joseph by a former marriage), or cousins (children of Mary’s sister) is a matter of controversy. The Protestant position maintains that the brothers were actual half brothers of Jesus. The Roman Catholic position asserts that the four were cousins of Jesus. The Greek Orthodox position agrees with the Roman Catholic stance that Mary and Joseph had no other children, but assumes that the brothers and sisters were Joseph’s by a former wife.</p>
<p>Protestants contend that not only the four brothers but at least two sisters were the children of Mary and Joseph. The plain sense of several passages is in favor of the usual meaning of the word “brother,” since no instance of a wider use of that word for actual kinship appears in the NT. Consistent with that understanding of “brother,” wherever brothers and sisters of Jesus are mentioned (except <a href="?bref=John.7.1-53">Jn 7</a> and <a href="?bref=1Cor.9.1-27">1 Cor 9</a>), is their appearance in close connection with Jesus and his mother, evidently one family under Mary’s care. That closeness could possibly fit their being Mary’s stepchildren, but it makes it less likely that they were only cousins of Jesus.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CallingJesusBeelzebul">
  <title>Calling Jesus “Beelzebul”</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Calling Jesus “Beelzebul”</p>
<p class="box-first">By NT times, the name had changed to Beelzebul (<span class="sc">kjv</span> Beelzebub), from the Syriac language meaning “lord of dung.” It was a common practice to apply the names of the gods of enemy nations to the devils of one’s own religion. Thus, the title was applied by the Jews to the devil, or Satan, the prince of demons (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.24,27">Mt 12:24, 27</a>). In their blasphemous criticism, the Pharisees called Jesus by this title to explain his ability to cast out demons (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.22">Mk 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.15">Lk 11:15</a>). In <a href="?bref=Matt.10.25">Matthew 10:25</a> Jesus tells the disciples, “If they have called the master of the house Beelzebul, how much more will they malign those of his household” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). Here Jesus seems to make his point by relying on another possible meaning of the words from rabbinic usage, “lord of the house”—“house” having reference to the temple, the house of the Lord. Thus, in response to the Jewish leaders, a play on words involving contrast may have been employed. They call Jesus “Beelzebul, lord of the dung heap,” and Jesus calls himself “Beelzebul, lord of the house.” By this, Jesus claims lordship over the house of God.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CanGodRepent">
  <title>Can God Repent?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Can God Repent?</p>
<p class="box-first">Occasionally, in some translations of the OT, God is said to ”repent.“ A classic example is found in his treatment of Nineveh during Jonah’s prophetic ministry there (<a href="?bref=Jon.3.10">Jon 3:10</a>). God told Jonah to proclaim judgment to Nineveh, yet once the Ninevites repented, God relented (<span class="sc">kjv</span> “repented”)—no judgment came. Such an attitude is not to be understood as denoting either personal sorrow on God’s part or a change in his eternal purpose, but rather a change in, or an updating of, his announced purpose and in his relations with people as they themselves change. Such a way of describing God’s relation to his creatures is one of many in which, as Calvin and others have stressed, God “accommodates himself” to humans.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ChaldeansAsAstrologers">
  <title>Chaldeans as Astrologers</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Chaldeans as Astrologers</p>
<p class="box-first">Long after the Chaldean Empire had ceased to exist, the name “Chaldeans” lingered in Hellenistic Egypt, Greece, and Rome as a term for magicians, astrologers, and diviners. The same usage of the term appears in the book of Daniel, where Chaldeans were linked with soothsayers, conjurers, and sorcerers (<a href="?bref=Dan.2.2,10">Dn 2:2, 10</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.4.7">4:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.5.7">5:7</a>).</p>
<p>Babylonians had long been renowned for their advanced knowledge of astronomy and for their dependence on the stars to help them predict the future. One Babylonian text from about 700 <span class="era">BC</span> described the zodiacal belt and named 15 constellations. Several of the names are still used by astrologers today: the Bull, the Twins (Gemini), the Scorpion, and Capricorn. In <a href="?bref=Dan.2.2">Daniel 2:2</a> and <a href="?bref=Dan.4.7">4:7</a> one of the terms linked with the Chaldeans is related to a Babylonian word referring to a class of priests who made use of incantations. Just how important they were for society has been shown in excavated tablets that describe the priests’ training. The most outstanding youths of Judah, including Daniel, were selected for a similar educational program (<a href="?bref=Dan.1.4">Dn 1:4</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CommunityOfTheSpirit">
  <title>Community of the Spirit</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Community of the Spirit</p>
<p class="box-first">The two-volume work of Luke the Evangelist, Luke–Acts, presents the church as that community of people in which, and through which, the Spirit of God is working. Insofar as the church is that, it is an extension of a reality already begun by Jesus of Nazareth. In Luke’s Gospel, John the Baptist announces the coming of one who would baptize with the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.16">Lk 3:16</a>). In Acts, this promise is seen fulfilled in the outpouring of the Spirit (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.5">Acts 1:5</a>). As Jesus was empowered for his mission by the Spirit (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.21-22">Lk 3:21-22</a>), so the early Christian community was empowered for its witness in the world (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.8">Acts 1:8</a>). As Jesus, the man of the Spirit, was confronted at the outset of his ministry with great obstacles (the temptation, <a href="?bref=Luke.4.1-13">Lk 4:1-13</a>), so the church, as the community of the Spirit, faced the temptation to yield to pressures that would compromise its mission (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.12-13">Acts 2:12-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.1-22">4:1-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.27-42">5:27-42</a>). As Jesus, empowered by the Spirit, proclaimed the Good News and touched the lives of people with reconciliation, release, and restoration (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.18-19">Lk 4:18-19</a>), so the church was empowered by the Spirit to become a caring and sharing community (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.43-47">Acts 2:43-47</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.33-37">4:33-37</a>). As Jesus, the man of the Spirit, reached out to the weak, poor, and rejects of the Palestinian society (this is a special emphasis throughout Luke’s Gospel), so the community of the Spirit was concerned with taking care of people’s needs (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.34">Acts 4:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.1-6">5:1-6</a>). These parallels illustrate Luke’s understanding of the oneness of Jesus’ ministry with that of the church—all because the Spirit of Jesus was, and is, in his church.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ContemporaryUnderstandingOfTheFall">
  <title>Contemporary Understanding of the Fall</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Contemporary Understanding of the Fall</p>
<p class="box-first">Within contemporary theology of all confessional varieties, there is widespread denial of the historicity of the biblical account of the fall. It may be granted that the Genesis account is told as history continuous with subsequent history and that within the worldview of the writers of the Bible the account is alluded to as history. But it is argued that moderns can receive the story of the fall only as myth. This view has its source in the development of an evolutionary view of human origins coupled with a negatively critical evaluation of the literary history of the Genesis account.</p>
<p>Although the historicity of Adam is often abandoned, there is usually an attempt to appreciate the “truth” conveyed by the myth. For example, it is said that every person is Adam, and that everyone living is a sinner as far back as he or she can remember. Others see in the myth not a fall but an ascent to conscious and independent responsibility. Sin is thought of as necessary to religious maturity in the same way that exposure to competition from opponents strengthens the prowess of an athlete.</p>
<p>Because of the way the Bible parallels Adam and Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.12-19">Rom 5:12-19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.22">1 Cor 15:22</a>), a mythological understanding of Adam leads to a mythological understanding of Christ. As Adam becomes a symbol for the universality of sin and death, so Christ becomes simply a symbol for the inherent righteousness and redemption of all men.</p>
<p>The modern isolation of the message from the history of <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-3.24">Genesis 1–3</a> violates the integrity of the account without offering a valid explanation for the universality of sin and death. Christian doctrine holds that sin entered the world through a specific man, Adam, and was overcome by Jesus Christ, another man, by his death and resurrection.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DavidAManOfGod">
  <title>David, A Man of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">David, A Man of God</p>
<p class="box-first">David, one of the most gifted and versatile individuals in the OT, is second only to Moses in Israel’s history. He was keenly conscious that God had enabled him to establish a kingdom (<a href="?bref=Ps.18.1-50">Ps 18</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Sam.22.1-51">2 Sm 22</a>); it was in that context that he was given the messianic promise of an eternal kingdom.</p>
<p>From David’s own suffering, persecution, and nearness to death came prophetic psalms that portrayed the suffering and death of the Messiah (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.2.1-12">Pss 2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.22.1-31">22</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.110.1-7">110</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.118.1-29">118</a>). Even the hope of the resurrection is expressed in <a href="?bref=Ps.16.1-11">Psalm 16</a>, as the apostle Peter noted on the day of Pentecost (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.25-28">Acts 2:25-28</a>).</p>
<p>Awareness of a vital personal relationship with God is expressed more consistently by David than by any of the faithful men and women who preceded him. He knew that it was not legalistic observance of rules or rituals that made him acceptable to God. Offering and sacrifice could not atone for sin if one had no accompanying contrition and humility. Many of David’s prayers are as appropriate for Christians as they were for God-fearing people in the OT. David’s writings show that “knowing God” was as real in OT times as it was for the apostle Paul, even though the full revelation of God in Jesus Christ was still in the future.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DeuteroIsaiahASecondAuthorOfTheBookOfIsaiah">
  <title>Deutero-Isaiah: A Second Author of the Book of Isaiah?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Deutero-Isaiah: A Second Author of the Book of Isaiah?</p>
<p class="box-first">Since the 18th century, certain Bible critics have questioned the unity of the book of Isaiah. Late in the 19th century a theory emerged that ascribed chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-66.24">40–66</a> to an unknown prophet—a deutero (“second”) Isaiah presumably living among the exiles in Babylon. Some scholars have even posited the existence of a third author (trito-Isaiah), limiting the extent of deutero-Isaiah to chapters <a href="?bref=Isa.40.1-54.17">40–54</a>.</p>
<p>The theory was first prompted not by problems of stylistic unity but by the issue of whether OT prophets could really foretell future events, especially with Isaiah’s amazing accuracy. Rationalist critics doubted that Isaiah could have possibly foretold the fall of Jerusalem, the later restoration of Palestine, and especially the name of the Persian king (Cyrus; see <a href="?bref=Isa.45.1">Is 45:1</a>) who would permit the Jews to return to their homeland from exile—events that did not occur until well over 100 years after the prophet had died.</p>
<p>Most conservative biblical scholars, however, affirm the unity of the book, its single authorship, and the supernatural origin of its prophetic passages.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DidJephthahOfferHisDaughterAsAHumanSacrifice">
  <title>Did Jephthah Offer His Daughter as a Human Sacrifice?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Did Jephthah Offer His Daughter as a Human Sacrifice?</p>
<p class="box-first">We know that human sacrifice was practiced at that time, though it was abhorred by the Hebrews and prohibited in the Mosaic law (<a href="?bref=Lev.18.21">Lv 18:21</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.13.13">Ex 13:13</a>). Did Jephthah, however, have his daughter killed? The text points to this sad reality. Indeed, the father’s cry seems conclusive proof that her life was to be forfeited as a sacrifice, and the language and tone of the Hebrew text bears this out. The theory that she was spared to become the founder of a sisterhood of perpetual virgins is of very late, medieval origin. The daughter exhibited extraordinary self-denial in her understanding of and respect for her father’s commitment. Such a sacrifice was by no means infrequent in Israel, and common in other cultures, however repugnant it seems to us today. For other evidences of its practice, see <a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.3">2 Kings 16:3</a>, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.17">17:17</a>, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.6">21:6</a>, <a href="?bref=Jer.7.31">Jeremiah 7:31,</a> and <a href="?bref=Mic.6.7">Micah 6:7</a>. That this took place illustrates how deeply ingrained Canaanite religious practice was in Israel during this dark age.</p>
<p>We should not think that God was pleased with this sacrifice. In fact, God had provided a way out for anyone who had made a rash vow. Those who made rash vows were commanded to confess their sins and then make an offering for sin, whether it be a sheep, a bird, or even fine flour (see <a href="?bref=Lev.5.4-13">Lv 5:4-13</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DidJesusSideWithHillelOrShammai">
  <title>Did Jesus Side with Hillel or Shammai?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Did Jesus Side with Hillel or Shammai?</p>
<p class="box-first">According to <a href="?bref=Matt.19.3">Matthew 19:3</a>, it is said that some Pharisees approached Jesus and tested him by asking, “Is it lawful to divorce one’s wife for any and every reason?” They wanted to see whether he would side with the school of Shammai or the school of Hillel. The Shammai school would allow divorce only for immorality, while the school of Hillel allowed a husband to divorce his wife for a variety of lesser reasons. Jesus’ response indicated that he did not affirm any kind of divorce, unless one partner had commited adultery (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.4-9">Mt 19:4-9</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DifficultiesInPrayer">
  <title>Difficulties in Prayer</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Difficulties in Prayer</p>
<p class="box-first">Why does God answer some prayers and not others? </p>
<p>In attempting to answer this question it is necessary to bear in mind that prayer is not to be thought of in mechanical terms. Prayer involves a personal relationship with God. So the reason why God answers one prayer and not another has nothing to do with the volume or length of the prayers themselves. Because prayer involves a personal relationship with God, sincerity and unaffectedness in that relationship are of paramount importance. There must be no hypocrisy or mere formalism in prayer. Length of prayer may be an indication of strength of desire, or it may not. Scripture contains examples of both long and short prayers.</p>
<p>Assuming sincerity, the most fundamental factor is the relationship between the one who prays and the express will of God. The only warrant for praying at all is that God commands it and desires it, and the only warrant for praying for some particular thing rather than for some other thing is that God wills it or may will it. A knowledge of the will of God as it is revealed in Scripture is basic to a proper understanding of petitionary prayer and to proper conduct in prayer.</p>
<p>It is necessary to distinguish between those matters that God has declared he will unfailingly grant upon true prayer being made and those matters that he may grant upon true prayer being made. The guide for prayer is not the petitioner’s own needs, either real or imaginary, nor his feelings or state of mind when he prays, nor his or others’ speculations about the future. The guide is Scripture alone. And the Scriptures distinguish between (1) those things a person may pray for that are desirable or good in themselves, and yet that are not for every believer’s highest good, and (2) those things that concern redemption. For instance, health or wealth, or a particular career, though each is desirable and lawful, may nevertheless not be best, in the wisdom of God, for a particular individual at a particular time. Paul’s “thorn in the flesh” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.12.7-9">2 Cor 12:7-9</a>) and the death of the child of David and Bathsheba (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.15-23">2 Sm 12:15-23</a>) are examples of unanswered prayer. So although health or wealth may be sincerely and warrantably prayed for, God in his wisdom and sovereignty may decline to grant these things—because these things may not be included in that particular array of things that are working together for the good of the believer concerned (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.28">Rom 8:28</a>).</p>
<p>By contrast, the blessings of redemption—such as forgiveness of sins, sanctification, and strength and wisdom for the fulfilling of duties—are always given to those who truly pray for them (<a href="?bref=Ps.84.11">Ps 84:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.13">Lk 11:13</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.37">Jn 6:37</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.3">1 Thes 4:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.1.5">Jas 1:5</a>). Even such unqualified or unconditional blessings may come after apparent delay, or from an unexpected source, and allowance for factors such as these must be made when judging whether or not prayer has been answered. An important part of petitioning God is the discipline of conforming one’s desires to the revealed will and the ongoing providence of God. In this sense prayer is educative for the believer. “Not my will but thine be done” is the concern of the sincere petitioner. The exercise of faith in prayer to God is seen in submission to the express will of God. Otherwise, faith becomes presumption, and humility becomes arrogance.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DisciplineIsGoodForUs">
  <title>Discipline Is Good for Us</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Discipline Is Good for Us</p>
<p class="box-first">Over the centuries the church has realized the value of certain “spiritual disciplines” encouraged in the NT. In the Roman Catholic tradition, they formed the basis for the way of life of “the religious” (priests, nuns, monks, etc.). Prayer (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.6.12">Lk 6:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.6.4">Acts 6:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.12.12">Rom 12:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.4.7">1 Pt 4:7</a>), fasting (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.16-18">Mt 6:16-18</a>), study of Scripture (<a href="?bref=Acts.17.11">Acts 17:11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.15">2 Tm 2:15</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.3.16-17">3:16-17</a>), and charity, or almsgiving (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.1-4">Mt 6:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.29-30">Acts 11:29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.9.1-15">2 Cor 9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.6.17-19">1 Tm 6:17-19</a>) have always been included among the spiritual disciplines. Protestants have been less inclined to establish religious orders or communities based on the spiritual disciplines, more often trusting the Holy Spirit to produce self-discipline in individual lives and seeking fellowship and exhortation in the context of the church. Among evangelicals there seems to be a new appreciation of the need for spiritual discipline. A well-ordered, wholesome, liberated life that releases the Christian for service is almost always a self-disciplined life.</p>
<p>Such ideals and the lifestyle they engender run counter to much of the prevalent permissiveness in Western culture. Young people are surrounded by superficial commitments, short-term relationships, instant gratification, the quest for freedom without responsibility, and obsession with self-centered indulgence. Christian parents need to help their children develop the self-discipline to stand against such pressures. Adult self-discipline often has its roots in a biblical pattern of discipline and an appreciation for the desirability of such discipline inculcated in childhood.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DoTheEblaTabletsProveTheBible">
  <title>Do the Ebla Tablets Prove the Bible?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Do the Ebla Tablets Prove the Bible?</p>
<p class="box-first">The discoveries at Tell Mardikh, astounding as they are, do not “prove” the Bible, for it does not need the proof of archaeology or of any other human skill. The Bible is God’s Word. Any attempt to “prove” it only exhibits our doubts. As other archaeological discoveries have done, the discoveries at Ebla will help us to see what kind of men and women God was dealing with, what kind of world they were living in, and how much he must have loved them to want to deliver them from the ways of the world to walk in his way. We still have much to learn, and Ebla will supply some of the background for that learning process.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EmperorWorship">
  <title>Emperor Worship</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Emperor Worship</p>
<p class="box-first">Emperor worship had its origins in the Near Eastern practice of considering the king divine. The Egyptian pharaoh was considered a descendant of the sun god Ra (Re), and Mesopotamian legends speak of kingship “descending from heaven.” Alexander the Great and other Greek heroes were worshiped after their deaths. The idea of a ruler’s divinity was encouraged by the central place of the king in pagan cults. Israel was directly affected by such worship during the Babylonian exile (see <a href="?bref=Dan.3.1-30">Dn 3</a>).</p>
<p>Such a background set the pattern for the Seleucid king Antiochus IV Epiphanes, who believed himself to be an incarnation of the Greek god Zeus. He desecrated the temple in Jerusalem by setting up an altar to Zeus in it (167 <span class="era">BC</span>). That event, which the Jews never forgot, triggered the Maccabean war for the liberation of Palestine.</p>
<p>Roman generals and emperors likewise assumed godhood as soon as they penetrated Asia Minor, especially after Augustus Caesar came to full power (27 <span class="era">BC</span>). Augustus saw his reign as the inauguration of a new age of peace for Rome and the world. Although the Romans acclaimed him as “savior,” he claimed for himself only the high priesthood. In the eastern provinces coins were minted with a double temple for Rome and Augustus. In Antioch coins depicted Augustus as the incarnate Zeus or “worship-worthy Son of God,” and altars were erected in his honor. Augustus encouraged the cult as a unifying element in his diverse empire and as a type of patriotism. After his death, temples were built in his honor and the symbols of divinity were transferred to succeeding emperors. For decades all new temples were for the imperial cult. (In <a href="?bref=Mark.12.13-17">Mk 12:13-17</a> and parallel passages about paying taxes, the coin was probably inscribed “Tiberius Caesar . . . Son of the Divine Augustus.”)</p>
<p>Gaius Caesar, nicknamed Caligula (<span class="era">AD</span> 37–41), was the first emperor to be worshiped in Rome during his own lifetime. On hearing of a dispute between Jews and Gentiles over worshiping him in Jamnia, he ordered a statue of himself to be placed in the temple in Jerusalem. His plan, which would surely have caused a general revolt, was averted only by the intercession of Herod Agrippa I. Under the succeeding emperors, Claudius (<span class="era">AD</span> 41–54) and Nero (<span class="era">AD</span> 54–68), the cult reached ridiculous extremes. Later emperors varied in how seriously they took the imperial cult, but it remained a test of loyalty to the empire, similar to loyalty oaths or pledging allegiance to the flag. For the sake of the empire’s unity, other religions had to accommodate emperor worship one way or another.</p>
<p>Emperor worship naturally caused problems for Christians, since the titles given to the emperor (“lord,” “prince of peace,” “son of god,” “savior”) were the same as those used for Christ. The confession “Jesus is Lord” (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.9">Rom 10:9</a>) was bound to conflict with the claim “Caesar is lord.” Christians who would not sacrifice to the emperor were charged with treason. The conflict between emperor worship and Christianity remained a focal point for the persecution of the church until the time of Constantine (<span class="era">AD</span> 306–37).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EnglishTranslationsAncientAndModernJohn115">
  <title>English Translations: Ancient and Modern/John 1:1-5</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">English Translations: Ancient and Modern/<a href="?bref=John.1.1-5">John 1:1-5</a></p>
<p class="box-h2">Tyndale’s Translation</p>
<p class="box-first">In the beginnynge was the worde, and the worde was with God: and the worde was God. The same was in the beginnynge with God. All things were made by it, and with out it, was made nothinge, that was made. In it was lyfe, and the lyfe was the lyghte of men, and the lyghte shyneth in the darckness, but the darckness comprehended it not.</p>
<p class="box-h2">King James Version</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">1</span>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. <span class="vn">2</span>The same was in the beginning with God. <span class="vn">3</span>All things were made by him; and without him was not any thing made that was made. <span class="vn">4</span>In him was life; and the life was the light of men. <span class="vn">5</span>And the light shineth in darkness; and the darkness comprehended it not.</p>
<p class="box-h2">American Standard Version</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">1</span>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. <span class="vn">2</span>The same was in the beginning with God. <span class="vn">3</span>All things were made through him; and without him was not anything made that hath been made. <span class="vn">4</span>In him was life; and the life was the light of men. <span class="vn">5</span>And the light shineth in darkness; and the darkness apprehended it not.</p>
<p class="box-h2">Revised Standard Version</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">1</span>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. <span class="vn">2</span>He was in the beginning with God; <span class="vn">3</span>all things were made through him; and without him was not anything made that was made. <span class="vn">4</span>In him was life, and the life was the light of men. <span class="vn">5</span>The light shines in the darkness; and the darkness has not overcome it.</p>
<p class="box-h2"><span class="ital">New American Standard Bible</span></p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">1</span>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">2</span>He was in the beginning with God.</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">3</span>All things came into being by Him, and apart from Him nothing came into being that has come into being.</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">4</span>In Him was life, and the life was the light of men.</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">5</span>And the light shines in the darkness, and the darkness did not comprehended it.</p>
<p class="box-h2">New International Version</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">1</span>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. <span class="vn">2</span>He was with God in the beginning.</p>
<p><span class="vn">3</span>Through him all things were made; without him nothing was made that has been made. <span class="vn">4</span>In him was life, and that life was the light of men. <span class="vn">5</span>The light shines in the darkness, but the darkness has not understood it.</p>
<p class="box-h2">Today’s English Version</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">1</span>Before the world was created, the Word already existed; he was with God, and he was the same as God. <span class="vn">2</span>From the very beginning the Word was with God. <span class="vn">3</span>Through him God made all things; not one thing in all creation was made without him. <span class="vn">4</span>The Word was the source of life, and this life brought light to mankind. <span class="vn">5</span>The light shines in the darkness, and the darkness has never put it out.</p>
<p class="box-h2"><span class="ital">The Living Bible</span></p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">1-2</span>Before anything else existed, there was Christ, with God. He has always been alive and is himself God. <span class="vn">3</span>He created everything there is—nothing exists that he didn’t make. <span class="vn">4</span>Eternal life is in him, and this life gives light to all mankind. <span class="vn">5</span>His life is the light that shines through the darkness—and the darkness can never extinguish it.</p>
<p class="box-h2"><span class="ital">New English Bible</span></p>
<p class="box-first">When all things began, the Word already was. The Word dwelt with God, and what God was, the Word was. The Word, then, was with God at the beginning, and through him all things came to be; no single thing was created without him. All that came to be was alive with his life, and that lifew was the light of men. The light shines on in the dark, and the darkness has never mastered it.</p>
<p class="box-h2">New Living Translation</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">1</span>In the beginning the Word already existed.</p>
<p class="poetry-2">The Word was with God,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and the Word was God.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">2</span>He existed in the beginning with God.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">3</span>God created everything through him,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and nothing was created except through him.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">4</span>The Word gave life to everything that was created,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and his life brought light to everyone.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">5</span>The light shines in the darkness,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and the darkness can never extinguish it.</p>
<p class="box-h2"><span class="ital">The New Jerusalem Bible</span></p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">1</span>In the beginning was the Word:</p>
<p class="poetry-1">the Word was with God,</p>
<p class="poetry-1">and the Word was God.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">2</span>He was with God in the beginning.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">3</span>Through him all things came into being,</p>
<p class="poetry-1">not one thing came into being except through him.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">4</span>What has come into being in him was life,</p>
<p class="poetry-1">life that was the light of men;</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">5</span>And light shines in darkness,</p>
<p class="poetry-1">and darkness could not overpower it.</p>
<p class="box-h2"><span class="ital">The New American Bible</span></p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">1</span>In the beginning was the Word,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and the Word was with God,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and the Word was God.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">2</span>He was in the beginning with God.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">3</span>All things came to be through him,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and without him nothing came to be.</p>
<p class="poetry-1">What came to be <span class="vn">4</span>through him was life,</p>
<p class="poetry-1">and this life was the light of the human race;</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">5</span>the light shines in the darkness,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and the darkness has not overcome it.</p>
<p class="box-h2">New Revised Standard Version</p>
<p class="box-first"><span class="vn">1</span>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. <span class="vn">2</span>He was in the beginning with God. <span class="vn">3</span>All things came into being through him, and without him  not one thing came into being. What has come into being <span class="vn">4</span>in him was life, and the life was the light of all people. <span class="vn">5</span>The light shines in the darkness, and the darkness did not overcome it.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ExplorationsAndExcavations">
  <title>Explorations and Excavations</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Explorations and Excavations</p>
<p class="box-first">Edward Robinson inaugurated the first important exploratory work. This American scholar made a series of topographical surveys of profound significance even today, and his activities mark the beginning of a flood of literature. Robinson’s chief contribution lay in his method. He dared to challenge the axiom that ecclesiastical traditions provide the primary source for reconstructing a city’s history. Instead, he sought to reconstruct Jerusalem’s history on the basis of the “unsuspected evidence of the stones,” thereby signaling for the holy city the advent of the archaeological method.</p>
<p>A second creative venture commenced in 1864 when, through the philanthropic contribution of Lady Burdett-Coutts of London, who wished to improve the sanitary conditions and water supply of the city, the Palestine Exploration Fund launched its first archaeological enterprise, under the direction of Charles Wilson. This nascent venture was enlarged between 1867 and 1870 as Charles Warren carried out extensive excavations around the temple area, on the southeastern hill, and in the Tyropean Valley, employing a system of underground shafts and tunnels. Of special interest is his unearthing of a section of the ancient city wall located near the southeastern sector of the temple. This find led him to postulate that the southeastern hill was the site of original occupation.</p>
<p>In the wake of the much-publicized discoveries of Wilson and Warren came the quests of Conder, Maudsley, and Clermont-Ganneau. In 1881 Guthe conducted additional excavations on the southeastern hill and at the pool of Siloam, while Schick reported the discovery of the now-famous Siloam Inscription. Schick also excavated a number of tombs just off the Nablus Road. At the same time Bliss and Dickie undertook elaborate excavations of the southern wall.</p>
<p>With the work of Raymond Weill, one enters a third creative period. While the territory on the southeastern hill actually excavated by Weill was proportionately small, it was he who first employed the stratigraphic excavation method at Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Following World War I, the southeastern hill was the object of a second campaign by Weill, of a team under the direction of Macalister and Duncan, and of an expedition led by Crowfoot and Fitzgerald. From 1925 to 1927, Sukenik, Mayer, and Fisher explored north of the city, discovering sections of the third (northern) wall (i.e., Herod Agrippa’s wall).</p>
<p>An important new period in archaeological research began with the protracted expedition under the leadership of Kathleen Kenyon. From 1961 to 1967, the British School of Archaeology project explored several regions of Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Since 1968 the Hebrew University Museum, under the direction of Amiran and Eitan, has intermittently conducted archaeological research in and near the city. The Israel Department of Antiquities and Museums engaged in isolated excavations of what was known prior to the 1967 war as the Jewish Quarter.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="FigurativeUseOfCistern">
  <title>Figurative Use of “Cistern”</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Figurative Use of “Cistern”</p>
<p class="box-first">The word “cistern” is also used figuratively in the Bible. Through the prophet Jeremiah, God rebuked Israel for rejecting him, the “fountain of living waters.” Instead, they had “dug for themselves cracked cisterns that can hold no water at all” (<a href="?bref=Jer.2.13">Jer 2:13</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). <a href="?bref=Eccl.12.6">Ecclesiastes 12:6</a> refers to a broken wheel at a cistern as a figurative description of old age.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="FollowersOfTheWay">
  <title>Followers of the Way</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Followers of the Way</p>
<p class="box-first">Early Christianity was far from being an abstract belief; it was a whole way of life. The new way of living was obvious to those around Christians and to the Christians themselves, for they were following Jesus’ lifestyle, the way he had lived and taught. Soon the term “this Way” or “the Way” meant Christian. Thus Saul (the pre-Christian name of Paul) was sent to Damascus to arrest anyone belonging to “the Way” (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.2">Acts 9:2</a>). Christians may also have used the term to describe themselves; Luke referred to the Christian movement as “the Way” (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.9,23">Acts 19:9, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.24.22">24:22</a>). It may be the only name Christians and non-Christians both  used for the new movement.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GodAndWar">
  <title>God and War</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">God and War</p>
<p class="box-first">Modern readers of the Bible often have difficulty with the military emphasis of the OT, asking, “How could God be a God of love and yet lead his chosen people into bloody wars?” The fact is that the Israelites were no more belligerent than the people who came before them or after them. God wanted to introduce new concepts of love and justice into the world through his people, but it was necessary for them to survive in order to do that. He did not take them out of their world—a world where resources were scarce and life precarious—but helped them fight for survival among far more brutal and acquisitive powers. Yet through the prophet Isaiah, God gave to his people the vision of a day when the art of warfare would be forgotten (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.2-5">Is 2:2-5</a>).</p>
<p>The centuries that followed were characterized by a series of crises precipitated by intrigue and war. Persia, Macedonia, Parthia, and Rome successively established a military presence in the land. No display of military prowess, however, could dim the prophetic vision. No experience of an imposed peace could satisfy its terms. Indeed, Christians believe that at a time when Israel was under total military domination by Rome, God brought forth a Ruler, his Messiah, the “Prince of Peace,” to establish a peace that will never end (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.6-7">Is 9:6-7</a>). The promise that nations will one day beat their swords into plowshares and their spears into pruning hooks accounts for the rebirth of hope in the hearts of God’s people—even when war or the threat of warfare looms imminent, or when a nation’s leadership directs its attention to arms and warfare. The accomplishment of Isaiah’s prophecy ultimately depends not on the ingenuity or intention of human beings but on the will of the sovereign God.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GodsJudgmentOnBaasha">
  <title>God’s Judgment on Baasha</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">God’s Judgment on Baasha</p>
<p class="box-first">The Bible’s evaluation of Baasha’s reign is not favorable. Baasha “did what was evil in the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>’s sight and followed the example of Jeroboam, continuing the sins of idolatry that Jeroboam had led Israel to commit” (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.34">1 Kgs 15:34</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). He received God’s indictment and judgment through the prophet Jehu: since Baasha had led Israel into sin and had angered God, dogs would eat the members of his family who died in the field (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.1-4">16:1-4</a>). Baasha died and was succeeded by his son Elah. Within two years Elah was assassinated, and all the rest of Baasha’s heirs were put to death by another usurper, Zimri (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.8-13">8-13</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GodsSovereigntyAndOurAssurance">
  <title>God’s Sovereignty and Our Assurance</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">God’s Sovereignty and Our Assurance</p>
<p class="box-first">A proper understanding of God’s sovereignty should encourage repentant sinners and faltering believers to call upon God for salvation and to walk secure in his love. Jesus said, “All that the Father gives me will come to me; and him who comes to me I will not cast out” (<a href="?bref=John.6.37">Jn 6:37</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Because God has planned and purposed our salvation, we may have assurance that he will accept and forgive those who trust him (<a href="?bref=John.3.16">Jn 3:16</a>). Christ’s sheep hear his voice and follow him; they will never perish or be snatched out of his hand (<a href="?bref=John.10.29">Jn 10:29</a>).</p>
<p>Such an attitude of trust in God removes the presumptive pride of the person who trusts his own good works for salvation (<a href="?bref=Matt.7.21-23">Mt 7:21-23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.12">1 Cor 10:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.3.12">Heb 3:12</a>), or the agonizing doubt of the believer who is sensitive to his own sinfulness. Because salvation is by grace (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.8">Eph 2:8</a>), the doubting believer may claim the finished and sufficient work of Christ and thus rest secure that God will finish his work in each believer (<a href="?bref=Phil.1.6">Phil 1:6</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GuidelinesForInterpretingParables">
  <title>Guidelines for Interpreting Parables</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Guidelines for Interpreting Parables</p>
<p class="box-first">Interpreting the parables is not easy, but certain guidelines can be presented that will avoid past errors and make sane interpretation possible.</p>
<p class="list">1. Analyze the parable thoroughly. Note the characters and movement of the story, its climax, and the repetition of key words or ideas. If it appears in more than one Gospel, do a comparative analysis of the various accounts to note both similarities and differences.</p>
<p class="list">2. Listen to the parable without any preconceptions as to its form or its meaning. Attempt to hear the parable as if sitting at the feet of Jesus without knowing the parable, its meaning, and Christian theology. While it is impossible for a modern reader to become a first-century Jewish hearer, it is imperative that a parable be interpreted in its original context and in the ways its author originally intended it to be understood.</p>
<p class="list">3. Look for help in the surrounding context, but realize that the original context for many of the parables has not been preserved. Often the parables appear where they do in the Gospels because of the arrangement of the Gospel writers.</p>
<p class="list">4. Notice features in the parable that reflect the life and thinking of the first-century world. An understanding of cultural and religious factors, and an awareness of the OT ideas reflected in a parable, will greatly assist in its interpretation.</p>
<p class="list">5. Note how the parable fits into the purpose and plan of the entire book. If the parable is present in the other Gospels, note its location and how it has been shaped to fit into the purpose of each Gospel writer.</p>
<p class="list">6. Determine as explicitly as possible the message of the parable in the teaching of Jesus. There may be several points that need to be made in a given parable, as was indicated above for the parable of the lost son. There may be legitimate secondary features in the parable, but be careful not to push the story too far. One should exercise caution since it is easy to violate a parable’s intention. No one would want to suggest that God has tormentors on the basis of the parable of the unforgiving servant (see <a href="?bref=Matt.18.34">Mt 18:34</a>); rather, this verse points out the seriousness of the sin and its judgment. However, some people wrongly overemphasize minor features of other parables. If one will interpret the parable as a whole—in keeping with its original intention—such errors will be minimized.</p>
<p class="list">7. Note where the teaching of the parable conforms to the teaching of Jesus elsewhere. Jesus’ nonparabolic teaching may provide the key for, or strengthen, the interpretation of a parable.</p>
<p class="list">8. Give due emphasis to the “rule of end stress.” Usually the climax and the most important part of a parable comes at its conclusion. Consequently, the focus of the interpretation should be there as well. Often, the end of the parable will include the theme of reversal. As elsewhere in the teaching of Jesus, his statement on a given topic is often the exact reverse of what others say or expect. Note <a href="?bref=Matt.10.39">Matthew 10:39</a>: “If you cling to your life, you will lose it; but if you give it up for me, you will find it” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). The parable of the workers in the vineyard tells of those who receive less than they expected and closes with a classic reversal statement: “the last shall be first and the first last” (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.16">Mt 20:16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.19.30">19:30</a>). Note the reversal in <a href="?bref=Matt.21.31">Matthew 21:31</a> at the end of the parable of the two sons (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.28-30">21:28-30</a>). After the religious authorities had made a judgment on the basis of the parable, the reversal is accomplished as they are told that the tax collectors and prostitutes were going into the kingdom of God before them (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.21.31-32">31-32</a>).</p>
<p class="list">9. Determine what principles are present in the parable that reveal the nature of God, his kingdom, the way he deals with humanity, or what he expects of humanity.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HadesAsHellAProblemInTranslation">
  <title>Hades as Hell: A Problem in Translation</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Hades as Hell: A Problem in Translation</p>
<p class="box-first">The <span class="sc">kjv</span> translators caused much confusion by translating two different Greek words (<span class="greek">hades</span> and <span class="greek">Gehenna</span>) with the same English word, “hell.” Hades almost always denotes the grave or the place of the dead. Gehenna, a much rarer expression in the NT, denotes the eternal fires. Thus, hell, as most people think about it, is really Gehenna, not hades. Unfortunately, this was not distinguished in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>. Modern translators have tried to correct the problem, but the popular misconception persists.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HowDoWeInterpretArmageddon">
  <title>How Do We Interpret Armageddon?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">How Do We Interpret Armageddon?</p>
<p class="box-first">Like most of Revelation the passage about Armageddon is difficult to interpret. A literal interpretation sees real armies gathered at an exact geographical location in the Near East. A more figurative interpretation sees John symbolically portraying a final worldwide conflict between wicked mankind and the Christ of God. Regardless of how literally or figuratively the passage is interpreted, it clearly describes a final battle in which Christ is victorious. That battle is known as the battle of Armageddon. The term has also passed into the secular vocabulary; for example, people now speak of the cataclismic end of the world as being “Armageddon.”</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HowDoWeKnowAboutThePhilistines">
  <title>How Do We Know about the Philistines?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">How Do We Know about the Philistines?</p>
<p class="box-first">Most of the knowledge of the Philistines comes from the Bible, the monuments and records of Egypt, and the archaeological excavations of Philistine cities. The biblical information centers in the historical books, but there are references to the Philistines in the Prophets and Psalms as well.</p>
<p>The historical records of Egyptian kings tell of their contacts with the Philistines. Other Egyptian written sources include the Amarna letters, “The Story of the Capture of Joppa,” “The Tale of a Mohar,” the Harris Papyrus I, and “The Adventures of Wenamon.” Paintings and reliefs of Philistines are found in the Theban necropolis and particularly in the temple of Ramses III at Medinet Habu.</p>
<p>Most of the information concerning the material culture of the Philistines comes from excavated pottery, which was distinctive and homogeneous. The earliest Philistine pottery at Ashdod had fish designs and other decorative motifs that resemble Cypriot ware. Decorations included several bands of designs, with carvings of geometric pattern. Paintings of birds were common, particularly the preening bird, with one wing raised and the head turned back. Interesting pottery forms included kraters (large, wide-mouthed bowls with two handles) and single-handled beer jugs with strainer spouts.</p>
<p>The excavation of the University Museum of the University of Pennsylvania at Tell el-Husn (Beth-shan, Beth-shean) unearthed two temples from the 11th century. Possibly the southern temple is that of Dagon (<a href="?bref=1Chr.10.10">1 Chr 10:10</a>) and the northern temple the House of Ashtaroth (<a href="?bref=1Sam.31.10">1 Sm 31:10</a>). Ashtaroth was not a Philistine deity but one borrowed from the Canaanites. Ekron had a god named Baal-zebub (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.1.2-3">2 Kgs 1:2-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.12.24">Mt 12:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.22">Mk 3:22</a>), who is equated with Beelzebul.</p>
<p>At Tell Qasile there was a Philistine temple with two pillars in the holy place, suggestive of the Gaza temple. This temple contained many objects associated with the cult, including a bird-shaped vessel and an incense altar. In houses and small shrines in Ashdod there were numerous clay figurines, both male and female, regarded as a pair of deities. There was also a strange ritual object of clay called an “Ashdoda,” best described as a four-legged chair, whose back becomes the stylized upper part of a nude goddess. Another pottery form of religious use was the kernos, which is a hollow ring vase with attached miniature vessels and figurines of heads of animals and birds.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HowShouldChristiansReadTheBookOfNahum">
  <title>How Should Christians Read the Book of Nahum?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">How Should Christians Read the Book of Nahum?</p>
<p class="box-first">The book of Nahum could be a problem for Christians. They could wonder how a prophet could rejoice in the carnage of battle, or how he could take delight in describing the death and destruction of the collapse of the Assyrian Empire. What the prophet was rejoicing over was the fact that God had proved himself active in history and victorious over his foes. Christians will also rejoice when the Great Babylon—the enemy of God—is destroyed (see <a href="?bref=Rev.18.1-19.21">Rv 18–19</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HowToUnderstandTheUseOfTheOldTestamentInTheNewTestament">
  <title>How to Understand the Use of the Old Testament in the New Testament</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">How to Understand the Use of the Old Testament in the New Testament</p>
<p class="box-first">The description of the use of the OT in the NT has pointed to the frequency of use, the difficulties encountered, and the variety of methods and purposes employed. A concluding list of suggestions for understanding the use of the OT follows: (1) Identify, if possible, which OT text is being employed. (2) Compare the wording of the NT and the OT passages. If there are significant differences, assistance may be required from scholarly studies before drawing conclusions. (3) Determine the original intention of the OT text in its context. (4) Determine how the NT used the OT text. Identify both the method by which the OT text is appropriated and the purpose for which it is employed. (5) Identify the teaching of both the OT and the NT texts for Christian understanding.</p>
<p>While the use of the OT in the NT is complex, no subject is more important or rewarding for a faith that speaks of itself and its founder as the fulfillment and climax of God’s word in the OT.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="InscriptionOnTheGreatSphinx">
  <title>Inscription on the Great Sphinx</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Inscription on the Great Sphinx</p>
<p class="box-first">An interesting inscription has been found on a granite column between the paws of the great Sphinx of Giza. The god Horus is said to have promised the throne of Egypt to Thutmose IV (1424–1417), Amenhotep II’s successor. Thus, Thutmose IV was possibly not the rightful heir to the throne. If so, then the biblical account that the pharaoh’s eldest son died in the tenth and final plague is verified (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.29">Ex 12:29</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="InterpretationsOnBindingAndLoosing">
  <title>Interpretations on Binding and Loosing</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Interpretations on Binding and Loosing</p>
<p class="box-first">The nature of Peter’s task and of his authority has been understood in various ways. Within the Roman Catholic tradition, the power of the keys has been taken to mean admission to, or exclusion from, the church. The authority to bind and loose is understood as apostolic authority to forgive sins or to refuse forgiveness. Further, it is understood as the authority to deliver decisions with regard to Christian faith and practice that are binding. Within the Roman Catholic tradition, it is also maintained that such authority belongs exclusively to the apostles and their successors, and most supremely to Peter and his successors, the bishops of Rome. Since those church authorities are seen as Christ’s representatives, their decisions on Christian faith and practice are believed to have received divine confirmation: “shall be bound ... [or] loosed in heaven” (that is, by God).</p>
<p>Within the Reformation tradition, the Roman Catholic interpretation of apostolic authority to bind and loose is rejected on the basis of several considerations. First, Jesus said nothing about successors to Peter and the other disciples. The concept of “apostolic succession” is therefore not grounded in the NT but was the result of historical development. Second, the position and authority of the original apostles was unique and unrepeatable. Jesus, the Christ, who lived on earth at a specific time and place, had a specific group of eyewitnesses who passed on his unique word, and on whose own witness the community of God’s people was built.</p>
<p>Thus, the authority to bind and to loose is not a scribal-type authority that forbids or permits certain things; nor is it the authority to refuse or to permit entrance into the kingdom of heaven, the sphere of God’s rule. Jesus’ disciples were called to be messengers of good news (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.7">Mt 10:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.14">24:14</a>); it is response to that Good News (the gospel) that binds or looses, which leads to forgiveness or to continuing bondage to sin, which sets persons free or judges them (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.14">Mt 10:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.10.14-17">Rom 10:14-17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.18">1 Cor 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.2.15-16">2 Cor 2:15-16</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="IsShilohAMessianicName">
  <title>Is Shiloh a Messianic Name?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Is Shiloh a Messianic Name?</p>
<p class="box-first">The transliteration of a Hebrew word in <a href="?bref=Gen.49.10">Genesis 49:10</a> was taken as a messianic name by the translators of the <span class="sc">kjv</span>: “The sceptre shall not depart from Judah, nor a lawgiver from between his feet, until Shiloh come; and unto him shall the gathering of the people be.”</p>
<p>A nonmessianic interpretation of the verse understands the term “Shiloh” to be nothing more than a reference to the city of that name, a city that was prominent during the period of the judges. Given this view, the last clause of the verse is translated “until he comes to Shiloh.” The basic objection to this approach is historical: Judah does not come into prominence until the time of the monarchy, at which time Shiloh was no longer an important center.</p>
<p>Many Christians since the time of Reformation have understood the word as a messianic proper name, as reflected in the translation of the clause in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>. Luther and Calvin viewed the word as derived from a Hebrew word they translated as “son.” This interpretation is forced: the word in question is not the same as the word <span class="ital">shiloh,</span> and its more precise meaning is “embryo.” Others associate the word with a Hebrew term meaning “be at ease, at rest” and translate the word as “rest-bringer.” The basic objection here is also the fact that this title is not further developed in the messianic expectation of the Bible.</p>
<p>Some commentators and translations divide the word in two, and translate it “as long as tribute comes to him” or “until tribute comes to him.” This approach is followed in the <span class="sc">tev</span>, the <span class="sc">neb</span>, and the <span class="sc">nasb</span>. Others identify the word <span class="ital">shiloh</span> as a Hebrew equivalent to a term in cognate languages meaning “ruler, prince.” The translation would read “until his ruler comes.”</p>
<p>The ancient translations (Septuagint, Peshitta, and Targums) understood the word <span class="ital">shiloh</span> as meaning “he to whom they belong.” This translation also has the support of <a href="?bref=Ezek.21.27">Ezekiel 21:27</a>; Ezekiel appears to be alluding to <a href="?bref=Gen.49.10">Genesis 49:10</a> and paraphrases the last clause “until he comes to whom it rightfully belongs.” Commentators and translations following this interpretation usually also understand the word translated “lawgiver” as “lawgiver’s staff,” so that the entire verse would read as follows: “The scepter will not depart from Judah, nor the ruler’s staff from his descendants, until the coming of the one to whom it belongs” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>There are difficulties with these and other approaches taken to the word <span class="ital">shiloh</span> in <a href="?bref=Gen.49.10">Genesis 49:10</a>. While a degree of uncertainty remains about the precise force of the term, the immediate context is brought into association with the Messiah in the NT (<a href="?bref=Rev.5.5">Rv 5:5</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="IsthmianGamesAtCorinthAndPaulsAthleticImagery">
  <title>Isthmian Games at Corinth and Paul’s Athletic Imagery</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Isthmian Games at Corinth and Paul’s Athletic Imagery</p>
<p class="box-first">Corinth was prominent because of the Isthmian Games, which occurred in the first and third years of the Olympiad (the four-year period between Olympic Games). They were supposedly originated by the mythical king Sisyphus and date from 523 <span class="era">BC</span>. Competition centered on three kinds of events: equestrian, gymnastics, and music. By the NT period, the games were influenced by Roman civilization, so chariot racing and other spectacles were probably added to the Hellenistic competitions. In an allusion to athletic contests, Paul mentioned both running and boxing (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.24-26">1 Cor 9:24-26</a>). The prize for winning the games was a wreath made of myrtle, olive, or pine branches, plus the additional benefits of a stipend from the state, remission of taxes, and special benefits for the champion’s children. Winners were national heroes.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JesusViewOnAlmsgiving">
  <title>Jesus’ View on Almsgiving</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Jesus’ View on Almsgiving</p>
<p class="box-first">Jesus criticized the way in which many of his contemporaries gave alms (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.2-4">Mt 6:2-4</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.3.2">Acts 3:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.36">9:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.2,4,31">10:2, 4, 31</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.24.17">24:17</a>). Jesus condemned the giving of alms when done in order to be praised by others. Those who gave for this reason, he said, would receive the reward of public recognition—but that was all. In contrast, God’s blessing rested on those who contributed to the poor without drawing attention to themselves.</p>
<p>Several NT passages testify to the early church’s continued concern. The needs of the poor in the Jerusalem church were supplied from a common pooling of resources (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.45">Acts 2:45</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.32-35">4:32-35</a>). The apostle Paul recognized the problems of the poor and was active in collecting contributions for them (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.13">Rom 12:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.25-27">15:25-27</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.1-4">1 Cor 16:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.8.1-9,15">2 Cor 8:1-9, 15</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.10">Gal 2:10</a>). James suggested that to demonstrate concern for widows and orphans was an example of pure religion (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.27">Jas 1:27</a>). The apostle John warned that anyone who has the world’s goods but refuses to share with another in need could hardly be considered a Christian (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.17">1 Jn 3:17</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JosephussWordsAboutJesus">
  <title>Josephus’s Words about Jesus</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Josephus’s Words about Jesus</p>
<p class="box-first">In his volume <span class="ital">Antiquities of the Jews</span> (18.2), Josephus said this about Jesus:</p>
<p class="box-extract">Now, there was about this time Jesus, a wise man, if it be lawful to call him a man, for he was a doer of wonderful works—a teacher of such men as receive the truth with pleasure. He drew over to him both many of the Jews and many of the Gentiles. He was Christ; and when Pilate, at the suggestion of the principal men among us, had condemned him to the cross, those that loved him at the first did not forsake him, for he appeared to them alive again the third day, as the divine prophets had foretold these and ten thousand other wonderful things concerning him; and the tribe of Christians, so named from him, are not extinct at this day.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="LetYourConscienceBeYourGuide">
  <title>“Let Your Conscience Be Your Guide”</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">“Let Your Conscience Be Your Guide”</p>
<p class="box-first">Since knowledge of what is good has been distorted by sin, can conscience be a valid moral guide? Many ethicists hold that all moral intuitions are developed entirely through social training; others take a less extreme view. Certainly children’s consciences are influenced by reinforcement of approved conduct and by discipline of misbehavior within the framework of family life. From a Christian point of view, although one’s conscience is an inner witness to spiritual and moral truth, it cannot be regarded invariably as the voice of God. No one has such a grasp on moral truth that his or her sinful nature may not overwhelm the conscience and render it unreliable.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, the existence of conscience argues strongly for God’s existence and reveals something about his nature—namely, that God always does what is right and that he punishes the transgression of his laws. Even unbelievers, simply from recognition of their moral nature, sense that they are ultimately responsible to God (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.19-20,32">Rom 1:19-20, 32</a>). The 18th-century philosopher Immanuel Kant, for example, posited belief in God, freedom, and immortality on the basis of conscience. The Christian knows that behind conscience is a God who is personal, ethical, self-revealing, and the Creator, Sustainer, and moral Governor of the universe.</p>
<p>In essentially every culture certain kinds of conduct are approved or disapproved. Such evidence suggests that conscience cannot be explained merely on the basis of social convention or the preferences of individuals. Within the Christian community, where considerable diversity also exists, the standard of morality is not provided primarily by a narrow social structure but by a broad allegiance to biblical truth. Maturity comes as Christians recognize themselves as part of a larger body, under the lordship of Christ, fellowship is maintained and a good conscience preserved by walking in the light (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.7">1 Jn 1:7</a>). A bad conscience is cleansed by confession of sin and the acceptance of God’s forgiveness (v <a href="?bref=1Jn.1.9">9</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="LeviticusAndTheChristian">
  <title>Leviticus and the Christian</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Leviticus and the Christian</p>
<p class="box-first">The laws in Leviticus were given many years before Christ and seem very remote from Christian living at the onset of the 21st century. However, though our circumstances are very different, the basic religious message of Leviticus still is vital and valid today. It is in terms of the sacrifices mentioned in Leviticus that the NT understands the death of Christ. Jesus was the true burnt offering, the Lamb of God, who takes away the sin of the world (<a href="?bref=John.1.29">Jn 1:29</a>). Jesus was the perfect sin offering whose blood cleanses us from all sin (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.7">1 Jn 1:7</a>). His death has, of course, made animal sacrifices obsolete, but these old Levitical sacrifices show us what Jesus achieved for us.</p>
<p>In other ways the theology of Leviticus still applies to the Christian. Christians are still called to be holy because God is holy (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.16">1 Pt 1:16</a>). As those who ate sacrifices while they were unclean were warned in Leviticus that they would be cut off, so Paul warned the Corinthians that those who partook of the Lord’s Supper unworthily would face judgment (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.27-32">1 Cor 11:27-32</a>). Leviticus insists that the priests must be examples of perfect holiness in their behavior; so Christian ministers are expected to be models of Christian virtue (<a href="?bref=1Tim.3.1-13">1 Tm 3:1-13</a>).</p>
<p>The practical exhortations to care for the poor, the blind, and the deaf; to be fair and honest; and to be faithful in marriage are just as applicable now as they were 3,000 years ago. Our Lord summed up the whole Law and the Prophets with a quotation from <a href="?bref=Deut.6.5">Deuteronomy 6:5</a>, “You must love the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God with all your heart,” and another from <a href="?bref=Lev.19.18">Leviticus 19:18</a>, “Love your neighbor as yourself” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.22.37-40">Mt 22:37-40</a>). By studying and meditating on Leviticus, the modern Christian can learn much about the character of God and his will for holy living.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="LocustPlagues">
  <title>Locust Plagues</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Locust Plagues</p>
<p class="box-first">Much in this chapter and the next seems descriptive of the kind of locust plagues that are still common in lands of the Middle East and North and Central Africa. Millions of locusts may cover hundreds of square miles of land. In flight they are like a cloud above the ground, and the sound they make has been described as “less like the whirring of wings than the rattle of hail or the crackling of bush on fire.” Nothing can resist their progress as they devastate field after field, stripping everything that is green, even branches of trees. It is thought that some passages in <a href="?bref=Joel.1.1-20">Joel 1</a> may speak of drought as well as the plague of locusts, but the devastation described may simply be due to the locusts.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ModernViewsOnTheIncarnation">
  <title>Modern Views on the Incarnation</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Modern Views on the Incarnation</p>
<p class="box-first">Recent incarnational theology has sometimes had difficulty balancing its understanding of Christ’s humanity and deity. Some theologians have given too much emphasis to his manhood, with the result that his atoning work is neglected. He then becomes an example of God’s gracious dealing with humanity. Such theological imbalance appears in those who have reacted too strongly to the “demythologizing” movement, stressing the Jesus of history to the extent that he has become little more than an object of rational thought.</p>
<p>On the other hand, some modern theology focuses only on Christ’s divinity. The Bultmannian (after Rudolf Bultmann) school has separated the “Christ of faith” from the “Jesus of history,” making him a hero in the Greek style. Some evangelicals make a similar error by removing Jesus’ teachings from the real world of history and placing them in a subjective realm of religious experience. Jesus thus becomes a vague object of religious devotion having no contact with the real world.</p>
<p>Another group has interpreted the biblical image of the church as the “body of Christ” to mean that the church somehow continues the Incarnation on earth. The NT does not teach that idea explicitly. Moreover, such an application of the theme can mislead the church to assume more divine authority for itself than it actually possesses.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="NewButNotNew">
  <title>New but Not New</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">New but Not New</p>
<p class="box-first">Why does <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.7-8">1 John 2:7-8</a> stress that the new commandment is not new but old? The phrase “from the beginning” (also found in <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.24">1 Jn 2:24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.11">3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Jn.1.6">2 Jn 1:6</a>) no doubt refers to the beginning of the readers’ Christian experience, that is, when they first heard the word of the gospel. Thus John meant that he was not teaching anything beyond the original message. His command was the same old “new commandment” that they heard when they first believed. He probably stressed its “oldness” because of false prophets in the churches (<a href="?bref=1Jn.4.1">1 Jn 4:1</a>) who were leading people into heresy by new and different teaching (<a href="?bref=2Jn.1.9">2 Jn 1:9</a>). The best protection against that deception was to obey what Jesus taught “of old,” including the new commandment (vv <a href="?bref=2Jn.1.6-7">6-7</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="OtherNamesForTheAntichrist">
  <title>Other Names for the Antichrist</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Other Names for the Antichrist</p>
<p class="box-first">The concept of antichrist undoubtedly comes from the teaching of Jesus in the Gospels. A lengthy passage (<a href="?bref=Mark.13.1-37">Mk 13</a>, paralleled in <a href="?bref=Matt.24.1-25.46">Mt 24–25,</a> and <a href="?bref=Luke.21.1-38">Lk 21</a>) records the instruction Jesus gave his disciples about the tragic events and persecution that they could expect before his return as the glorious Son of Man. His coming would be preceded by the appearance of many “deceivers” and “false Christs.” The term “false Christs” is used only twice (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.24">Mt 24:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.22">Mk 13:22</a>). Although it has obvious similarities to John’s “antichrist,” the Gospel passages do not refer to “a deceiver” or “false Christ” in the singular as do John’s and Paul’s writings.</p>
<p>In the book of Revelation, John’s symbol for the Antichrist is probably “the beast” (<a href="?bref=Rev.13.1-18">Rv 13:1-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.3,7-17">17:3, 7-17</a>). The Beast is described, not only as an opposer of Christ, but more specifically as a satanically inspired Christ-counterfeit. Although the Beast (Antichrist) is clearly distinguishable from the Lamb (Christ), he receives worship from everyone except God’s elect.</p>
<p>Another probable reference to the Antichrist is “the man of lawlessness” (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.3">2 Thes 2:3</a>). The passage is difficult to interpret, but the person described seems to be the same person later designated by John as the Beast. Both the apostles Paul and John saw present events as leading up to the events of the future. Instructing the church at Thessalonica about the second coming of Christ (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.1-12">2 Thes 2:1-12</a>), Paul stressed that the appearance and rebellion of the man of lawlessness must occur beforehand. That man would oppose the worship of any gods or God and even proclaim himself to be God (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.4">2 Thes 2:4</a>). He would subsequently be destroyed by Christ at his return (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.8">2 Thes 2:8</a>)—an indication that those events are set in the final days of history.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PaganParallelsToTheVirginBirth">
  <title>Pagan Parallels to the Virgin Birth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Pagan Parallels to the Virgin Birth</p>
<p class="box-first">Some critics of the virgin birth argue that the early church first propounded the belief that Jesus was the Son of God and then proved it by using Hellenistic parallels. In Greek mythology Zeus, as well as the other gods, bore many children by human mothers, including Perseus and Hercules. These offspring were also men of heroic proportion. In addition, there were tales of the miraculous births of great historical figures, such as Plato (whose father was Apollo) or Alexander the Great (whose father, Philip of Macedon, was kept from consummating his marriage until the child, conceived of Zeus, was born). Interestingly, the church fathers often used these stories in their polemic against their Greek opponents to show that the idea of the virgin birth was not really so incredible to the Greek mind. However, the differences between the pagan and Christian forms are too great. For one thing, the lustful promiscuity of the gods starkly contrasts with the sexual restraint commanded by the NT. Also, in the pagan stories the concept of “virgin” hardly has any stress. In all cases, it is simply a physical union between a god and a human, not a spiritual conception, as in the case of Jesus.</p>
<p>The same is true of the birth of Buddha, for the oldest records state that the entrance of the “white elephant” (representing the spirit of childbirth) into Gautama’s mother took place in a dream, and the story of an actual virgin birth is post-Christian. As for the Persian myths of the birth of Zoroaster or the birth of Mithras from a rock, there is no concept of a virgin birth. Babylonian tales do involve the goddess-mother Ishtar, but again virginity has no emphasis and is actually doubtful.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PamphyliaAndTheCritics">
  <title>Pamphylia and the Critics</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Pamphylia and the Critics</p>
<p class="box-first">Some critics have doubted the accuracy of Luke’s designation of Pamphylia as a separate province from Lycia (<a href="?bref=Acts.27.5">Acts 27:5</a>) because of an apparent contradiction by the early Roman historian Dio Cassius  who stated that Claudius combined Pamphylia and Lycia into one imperial province in <span class="era">AD</span> 43. However, an inscription from Pamphylia establishes that it remained an independent province for a while longer, was eventually connected with Galatia to the north, and finally was united to Lycia about <span class="era">AD</span> 74 by the Roman emperor Vespasian. Therefore, when Paul traveled through the region on his first missionary journey (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.13">Acts 13:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.14.24">14:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.15.38">15:38</a>), it is correctly referred to by Luke as Pamphylia.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PaulAndJamesOnJustification">
  <title>Paul and James on Justification</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Paul and James on Justification</p>
<p class="box-first">The Letter of James is often seen to be in conflict with Paul’s teaching on justification by faith apart from works of the law. In fact, James quotes the same text (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.6">Gn 15:6</a>) concerning Abraham and concludes, “You see that a man is justified by works and not by faith alone” (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.24">Jas 2:24</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Martin Luther even repudiated this letter because it seemed at variance with Paul. But two factors should be observed:</p>
<p>(1) Paul and James are faced with two completely opposite crises. Paul is compelled to oppose a legalism that made the law the basis for righteousness and enabled one to stand justified before God. The legalists were trying to maintain the law of Moses (in particular the obligation of circumcision) for those who would be justified. For these, the law was front and center. James, on the other hand, seeks to cope with an antinomianism that shows no concern for the law of God and says that faith is enough. For these persons the law is of no consequence. Paul’s opponents would put the law at the heart of justification, so Paul’s response is expressed largely in negative terms: “No one will be justified by works of the law” (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.20">Rom 3:20</a>). The opponents of James remove the law altogether and negate the significance or meaning of works in the name of faith. As a result James speaks positively of the law in relation to faith.</p>
<p>(2) When Paul and James speak of “works,” they speak of different concepts. Paul is speaking of works of the law, that is, works as an expression of the law, or what might be called “law-works” (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.20">Rom 3:20</a>). James, on the other hand, never speaks of works of the law but rather of works that give expression to faith, or what might be called “faith-works.” James regards faith without works as dead—that is, as no faith at all (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.17">Jas 2:17</a>). For him faith is expressed and perfected by works. Paul and James both affirm that one comes into, and continues in, living relationship to God through faith—apart from the law but not without the love and obedience that is born of faith.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PaulWritesHisOwnEpitaph">
  <title>Paul Writes His Own Epitaph</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Paul Writes His Own Epitaph</p>
<p class="box-first">Paul wrote his own epitaph in <a href="?bref=2Tim.4.6-8">2 Timothy 4:6-8</a>:</p>
<p class="box-extract">As for me, my life has already been poured out as an offering to God. The time of my death is near. I have fought a good fight, I have finished the race, and I have remained faithful. And now the prize awaits me—the crown of righteousness that the Lord, the righteous Judge, will give me on that great day of his return. And the prize is not just for me but for all who eagerly look forward to his glorious return. (<span class="sc">nlt</span>)</p>
<p class="box-first">This is a model for all true believers to emulate.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PentecostCelebrationsForJewsAndChristians">
  <title>Pentecost Celebrations for Jews and Christians</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Pentecost Celebrations for Jews and Christians</p>
<p class="box-first">Jews today celebrate the giving of the law at Sinai on Shavu‘oth, in addition to observing aspects of the Harvest Festival. After the destruction of the temple in <span class="era">AD</span> 70, this association became stronger and is now a central part of the festival. In addition to readings from the Pentateuch, the book of Ruth is read because of its harvest background. Much later in Judaism, this festival came to commemorate the anniversary of David’s death, so the Psalms are also read.</p>
<p>Christians annually celebrate Pentecost on a designated Sunday on the assumption that 50 days from Passover to the Feast of Weeks were counted until the day after the seventh Sabbath (our Sunday) as prescribed by <a href="?bref=Lev.23.15-16">Leviticus 23:15-16</a>. While the early church celebrated God’s gift of the Holy Spirit on Pentecost, in time it became a popular occasion for baptisms. The white dress of the candidates gave rise to the name Whitsunday (White Sunday) in Christian tradition.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="QuestioningTheAuthenticityOfTheChronicles">
  <title>Questioning the Authenticity of the Chronicles</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Questioning the Authenticity of the Chronicles</p>
<p class="box-first">The books of Chronicles, referred to as a single book in this article, have received considerable scholarly criticism about the nature of their content and about apparent discrepancies with material in Samuel and Kings. The differences can be classified as numerical, theological, and historical.</p>
<p>As an example of numerical differences, <a href="?bref=1Chr.11.11">1 Chronicles 11:11</a> says that one of David’s “mighty men” killed 300 men with his spear at one time, but the parallel account in <a href="?bref=2Sam.23.8">2 Samuel 23:8</a> says he killed 800 at one time. Again, <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.3-4">1 Chronicles 18:3-4</a> says that after defeating King Hadadezer of Zobah, David took from him 1,000 chariots, 7,000 horsemen, and 20,000 foot soldiers; a parallel account in <a href="?bref=2Sam.8.3-4">2 Samuel 8:3-4</a> says that David took 1,700 horsemen and 20,000 foot soldiers. Although <a href="?bref=2Chr.22.2">2 Chronicles 22:2</a> says that Ahaziah was 42 years old when he began to reign, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.8.26">2 Kings 8:26</a> says he was 22; and so on.</p>
<p>Many numbers in Chronicles seem exceptionally high. In <a href="?bref=1Chr.21.5">1 Chronicles 21:5</a>, Israel had just over a million men and Judah had 470,000. In another example of a remarkably high number, the temple’s vestibule is said to have been 120 cubits, or approximately 180 feet (54.8 meters), in height (<a href="?bref=2Chr.3.4">2 Chr 3:4</a>). In <a href="?bref=2Chr.13.3">2 Chronicles 13:3</a>, Judah’s army had 400,000 men and Israel’s army 800,000. Some 500,000 of Israel’s army were slain (<a href="?bref=2Chr.13.17">2 Chr 13:17</a>). In <a href="?bref=2Chr.14.9">2 Chronicles 14:9</a>, Zerah the Ethiopian had an army of a million men and 300 chariots.</p>
<p>How should such problems with numbers in Chronicles be understood? First, some of the problems in the text as it now stands may have come about from faulty copying. Also, some excessively high numbers may have been used figuratively to indicate a very large army, or perhaps as estimates. Though not all questions have been answered, scholars have found credible solutions to some of the problems. In the meantime, such matters are seen by evangelical scholars as verifying the human side of the Scriptures without necessarily detracting from their divine origin.</p>
<p>Chronicles also contains some different theological emphases from earlier materials. The best example can be seen by comparing <a href="?bref=1Chr.21.1">1 Chronicles 21:1</a> with <a href="?bref=2Sam.24.1">2 Samuel 24:1</a>. In the Samuel account the anger of the Lord was kindled against Israel, and he incited David to harm them by taking a national census. The Chronicler’s account is that “Satan stood up against Israel, and incited David to number Israel.” In one account God moved David to take the census; in the other Satan was the prime mover.</p>
<p>The authenticity of the Chronicler has also been questioned on historical grounds. Several incidents reported in Samuel-Kings are told in a different manner in Chronicles. In <a href="?bref=2Sam.8.13">2 Samuel 8:13</a> David is said to have slain 18,000 Edomites at the Valley of Salt, whereas the Chronicler reports that Abishai, David’s cousin, killed the Edomites (<a href="?bref=1Chr.18.12">1 Chr 18:12</a>). Again, according to <a href="?bref=2Sam.21.19">2 Samuel 21:19</a>, Elhanan slew Goliath the Gittite, whereas the Chronicler says that Elhanan slew Lahmi, the brother of Goliath the Gittite (<a href="?bref=1Chr.20.5">1 Chr 20:5</a>; most OT scholars today believe that Chronicles preserves the true reading of the original text). A more difficult historical problem is seen by comparing <a href="?bref=2Chr.20.35-37">2 Chronicles 20:35-37</a> with <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.48-49">1 Kings 22:48-49</a>. The Kings account says that the ships Jehoshaphat, king of Judah, built to bring gold from Ophir were wrecked at Ezion-geber, evidently before they ever left port. When Ahaziah, king of Israel, asked that his servants be allowed to go on the ships with Jehoshaphat’s servants, Jehoshaphat refused. The Chronicler’s version of what happened is different. There Jehoshaphat joined with the wicked Ahaziah in building ships at Ezion-geber to go to Tarshish, but a prophet prophesied that the Lord would destroy the ships because of the alliance with Ahaziah. Both accounts agree that Jehoshaphat built ships at Ezion-geber and that the ships were destroyed before they left port. On the basis of the present status of the texts, however, one cannot tell whether or not Jehoshaphat joined Ahaziah. Whatever happened, the ships were lost.</p>
<p>In a comparison of Chronicles with Kings, a serious problem arises over the war between Asa of Judah and Baasha of Israel. In <a href="?bref=2Chr.16.1">2 Chronicles 16:1</a> one reads that in Asa’s 36th year of reign, Baasha challenged Judah by building a fortress at Ramah. But according to the chronology of <a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.1-34">1 Kings 16</a>, Baasha was not even alive in the 36th year of Asa’s reign. <a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.6-8">First Kings 16:6-8</a> says that Baasha died and his son Elah succeeded him as king in the 26th year of Asa’s reign.</p>
<p>At one time scholars were quite skeptical about the authenticity of Chronicles. Now they tend to treat Chronicles with respect and appreciation. In some instances new archaeological evidence has tended to support the historicity of the Chronicler’s statement. In other instances reexamination of a discrepancy has shown it to be more apparent than real. If all the facts were known, other problems might also be cleared up to the satisfaction of impartial scholars.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="RabbisViewOfARainbow">
  <title>Rabbis’ View of a Rainbow</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Rabbis’ View of a Rainbow</p>
<p class="box-first">To the biblical account, the rabbis added the notion that the rainbow was created at evening on the sixth day of Creation, and that it did not appear during the lifetime of a saint whose good life was sufficient to preserve the world from destruction. To gaze directly at a rainbow risked injury, since the bow was a reflection of the glory of the Lord. A prescribed blessing was to be recited on seeing a rainbow: “Blessed are Thou O Lord our God, King of the universe, who remembers the covenant, is faithful to the covenant, and keeps His promise.”</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="RemarkableAstronomicalEventsInTheBible">
  <title>Remarkable Astronomical Events in the Bible</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Remarkable Astronomical Events in the Bible</p>
<p class="box-first">Several remarkable astronomical phenomena figure prominently in the Bible, including an apparent long day (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.12-14">Jos 10:12-14</a>), the retrogression of the shadow on a sundial, which was a sign for King Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.8-11">2 Kgs 20:8-11</a>), and the star that led the magi to Bethlehem.</p>
<p>Several explanations of Joshua’s long day have been suggested. The opinion is held by some that the rotation of the earth actually ceased. There is no theological difficulty involved in this event, for the Creator may perform miracles within the sphere of the universe by temporarily altering or suspending natural laws. There is a scientific difficulty in the fact that such an interruption of gravitational force probably would have caused great dislocation of everything on the earth’s surface. God could have acted within the limitations of natural law to prevent such an upheaval, however.</p>
<p>The long day may have been the result of other changes in the natural phenomena rather than the cessation of the earth’s rotation. Some have noted that the Hebrew word translated “stand still” may mean “to be quiet.” When applied to the sun, the word would imply a “quieting” of the sun’s activity, or a diminution of light. This would be an apt description of the eclipse of the sun. Such an occurrence would cause Israel’s enemies to flee in terror. Still others see the account as a highly poetic description of Joshua’s victory, not intended to be understood literally because it is a quotation from the book of Jashar. This book was probably a poetic work celebrating the exploits of Israel’s heroes.</p>
<p>Examination of the account of the shadow’s movement on Ahaz’s sundial (as a sign to Hezekiah) shows that the event was purely local, since envoys came from Babylon to learn about it (<a href="?bref=2Chr.32.31">2 Chr 32:31</a>). It is possible that both the long day and retrogression of the shadow were local phenomena, perhaps caused by abnormal refraction of light. Atmospheric disturbances could have occurred at the time; the account of Joshua’s battle specifically mentions hailstones (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.11">Jos 10:11</a>).</p>
<p>The star of Bethlehem (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.1-11">Mt 2:1-11</a>) has been identified with various astronomical phenomena such as the conjunction of Mars, Saturn, and Venus in 12 <span class="era">BC</span>. In 2 <span class="era">BC</span> Venus and Jupiter came into close proximity as well. That type of phenomenon does not seem to fit the description of the star, however. The star reportedly went before the magi and hovered over the site of the birth of the Christ child. Of course, the writer may have been using phenomenological language—that is, describing the event as it appeared to the observers. Some think the description points to a nova or supernova, a sudden increase in a star’s brightness; supernovas occur in a stellar system about once every 600 years. Although some natural event may serve to explain in whole or in part the star of Bethlehem, many Christians regard it as a miraculous supernatural phenomenon that God used to herald the event of the Incarnation.</p>
<p>These unusual phenomena and others like them accompanied important events in the history of God’s dealing with humanity. Not only do they witness to the importance of those events in God’s redemptive plan, but they demonstrate God’s power as well.</p>
<p>The attempts of some biblical scholars to explain these miracles in terms of natural phenomena is not an attempt to deny the validity of miracles. They only attempt to explain the phenomena within the sphere of observable natural order and the scope of biblical texts. Other scholars understand miracles to be the result of a supernatural alteration of physical laws, believing that the God who created the natural order continues to control that order and may perform miracles by altering the processes of nature to effect his will. In either case the power of God is central to the event, and the Bible faithfully records what took place.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="RembrandtsSamsonAndDelilah">
  <title>Rembrandt’s Samson and Delilah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Rembrandt’s Samson and Delilah</p>
<p class="box-first">Probably no painting more brutally depicts the theme of betrayal than that of the 17th-century Dutch artist Rembrandt. Delilah is hurrying out of her room, scissors and her lover’s streaming hair in hand, while Samson’s captors gouge out his eyes. The Bible makes no further mention of Delilah after the betrayal.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ReportsOfAncientEarthquakes">
  <title>Reports of Ancient Earthquakes</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Reports of Ancient Earthquakes</p>
<p class="box-first">The Jewish historian Josephus described a quake that occurred during the battle of Actium in which many animals and more than 30,000 people were killed. The earthquake in <span class="era">AD</span> 79 at Vesuvius was reported throughout the Roman world. Among many others, Agrippa was killed in this earthquake. Eusebius recorded the destruction of Caesarea and Emmaus by an earthquake during the reign of Hadrian. In spite of much ancient and modern earthquake activity in Palestine, Jerusalem has remained relatively undamaged.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ScientificEvidenceForTheFlood">
  <title>Scientific Evidence for the Flood?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Scientific Evidence for the Flood?</p>
<p class="box-first">With the beginning of modern archaeology in Mesopotamia, it became popular to associate evidence of flood destruction in sites such as Kish, Ur, and Shuruppak with the biblical Flood. Those places, however, were destroyed by different floods at different times. Their floods were also much too limited in scope to suit any interpretation of the Genesis account. More recently a “catastrophism” movement has developed within conservative circles, interpreting the world’s great geologic upheavals as chaotic remnants of the destruction caused by Noah’s Flood. That view suggests, among other things, that such geological formations may have taken shape in a short time (during the Flood) and in a relatively recent era (the time of Noah). Though that theory satisfies many, its opponents point out that some means of dating show the formations to be much earlier than the time of Noah.</p>
<p>Geologists exploring the Mt Ararat region have discovered on the mountain what is called “pillow lava,” volcanic rock formed under water. Such lava structures have been located up to the mountain’s ice cap at 13,500 feet (4,114.6 meters), so water evidently reached that height at one period. That phenomenon has been taken by some as a confirmation of worldwide scope for the Genesis Flood, but it does not prove that the lava was formed on Mt Ararat in the time of Noah. All it really indicates is that the structures originated under water, just as all land masses did.</p>
<p>The presence of “conglomerates” on Mt Ararat is cited as yet another proof of a universal deluge. Such rocks, varying in size from pebbles to boulders, resulted from a process of fusion in which eruptions of lava interacted with a violent disturbance of water. But again, the presence of such material at the 13,000-foot (3,962.2 meter) level merely indicates that Mt Ararat was born in precisely the same manner as modern islands and that the highest levels involved an eruption of volcanic rock in the ocean. Nor can such geological structures be used to imply that Mt Ararat was in the process of growth even while the Flood occurred. The Genesis account says nothing about the mountain erupting during Noah’s deluge. In any event, the material deposit would have been silt, not lava.</p>
<p>Interest in the nature of the Genesis Flood has been stimulated periodically since 1856, for some 200 persons have claimed to have seen Noah’s ark on Mt Ararat in 23 separate sightings. At least one report was a hoax, but many of them agree on the general nature of the object that has been sighted. Despite such apparent evidence, all concerned must admit that no conclusive proof exists that Noah’s ark is located on Mt Ararat. From a crevasse near the top of the mountain, Fernand Navarra in 1955 recovered a five-foot (1.5 meter) piece of wood, which was hand-tooled and originated at some distance from the mountain. Carbon-14 dating techniques, however, produced widely differing dates for the artifact. It has so far been impossible to locate what many have thought to be remains of the ark, despite the use of sophisticated photographic techniques.</p>
<p>The nature of the Genesis Flood will continue to be a matter of debate among interested parties, but it seems unlikely that the issue will be resolved unless some new archaeological or compelling scientific evidence is forthcoming. That there was a flood of enormous proportions is hardly to be doubted in the light of the Genesis account and other ancient traditions. However, the precise nature and extent of the biblical deluge must remain a matter of interpretation and speculation until incontrovertible evidence settles the issue.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ShishakAndArchaeology">
  <title>Shishak and Archaeology</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Shishak and Archaeology</p>
<p class="box-first">The discovery of a triumphal inscription prepared by Shishak for the temple at Karnak (ancient Thebes) is of great significance for biblical history. This inscription contains the names of many towns Shishak claims to have captured on his raids into the Asian region. Some of these names, in Egyptian orthography, correspond to names in the Hebrew language. Two dozen can be identified with certainty, affording valuable outside confirmation of biblical geography and history. Additional evidence of Shishak’s raid into Palestine was found at Megiddo (north-central area of Palestine), where a fragment of a triumphal stele erected by the pharaoh has been located.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ShouldTranslatorsUseTheExpressionOnlyBegotten">
  <title>Should Translators Use the Expression “Only Begotten”?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Should Translators Use the Expression “Only Begotten”?</p>
<p class="box-first">The phrase “only begotten” is not an accurate translation and should not be used in any of the nine passages noted above. This phrase is derived from the Latin Vulgate (a translation of the Bible from about the fifth century that has been quite influential on other translations) and reflects certain theological debates about the person of Christ. While the language of the Word being born of God is present in the second century, the most notable occurrence of this language is the creed from the Council of Nicaea in <span class="era">AD</span> 325. This creed speaks of the Son of God as begotten of the Father, unique—that is, from the substance of the Father—God from God, light from light, true God from true God, begotten and not made, of one substance with the Father. This creed was the result of the rejection of the heresy that the Son of God was the first created being. Ultimately, the phrase “begotten, not made” leads to what theologians call the doctrine of the eternal generation of the Son. It is an attempt to say that the Son is derived from the Father but that he is eternal with the Father. However, this discussion is an attempt to explain the mystery of the Trinity and goes far beyond the biblical text.</p>
<p>Whether there is any biblical passage that speaks of the Son being born from the Father is doubtful at best. The use of <a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Psalm 2:7</a> in <a href="?bref=Acts.13.33">Acts 13:33</a>, <a href="?bref=Heb.1.5">Hebrews 1:5</a>, and <a href="?bref=Heb.5.5">5:5</a> (“You are my son, today I have begotten you”) refers to the resurrection and exaltation of Christ. The use of “firstborn” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.29">Rom 8:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.15,18">Col 1:15, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.1.6">Heb 1:6</a>) stresses sovereignty rather than birth. The only text that possibly points to the idea of the Son’s being born from the Father is <a href="?bref=1Jn.5.18">1 John 5:18</a>, but the meaning of the words “the one having been born from God” is debated both because of a textual variant and because of the grammar. The words may refer to Christians instead of the Son.</p>
<p>In the end it must be said that “only begotten” is an incorrect translation. The idea being stressed is the uniqueness of Jesus’ relation to the Father, not any kind of birth per se.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SlaveANameAdoptedByChristianServants">
  <title>Slave: A Name Adopted by Christian Servants</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Slave: A Name Adopted by Christian Servants</p>
<p class="box-first">Five NT authors called themselves “a slave [or servant] of Jesus Christ”: Paul (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.1">Rom 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.10">Gal 1:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.1.1">Phil 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.4.12">Col 4:12</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.24">2 Tm 2:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.1">Ti 1:1</a>), James (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.1">Jas 1:1</a>), Peter (<a href="?bref=2Pet.1.1">2 Pt 1:1</a>), Jude (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.1">Jude 1:1</a>), and John (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.1">Rv 1:1</a>). In many cases, the term is a synonym for “Christian.” Why would such a term become a name for Christians? In the OT, God was viewed as a great king; the subjects of kings were their slaves. The people of Israel saw themselves in the same relationship to God: they were his slaves.</p>
<p>Often the title “slave of the king” meant that the person was an officer in the king’s service; it was a title of honor. In Jewish literature Moses and others were called slaves of God (<a href="?bref=Num.12.7-8">Nm 12:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.15.3">Rv 15:3</a>). The term “slave” was thus a title both of honor and of subjugation; in the NT it is hard to know which sense is intended. Certainly subjection was often meant (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.22">1 Cor 7:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.7">Phil 2:7</a>), but when applied to the apostolic writers, the term probably suggested their honored position in God’s household. At the same time, it indicated their obedience to Christ; he commanded and they obeyed. Since obedience was characteristic of all Christians, “slave of Christ” became a title for members of the young church.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SpiritualBlindness">
  <title>Spiritual Blindness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Spiritual Blindness</p>
<p class="box-first">Spiritual blindness is a figurative way of defining the lost and hopeless condition of sinful humanity. Such blindness includes willful rejection of God’s revelation in his creation and in Scripture, and an inability to see the truth of the gospel. Moses spoke of Israel’s apostasy as “blindness” (<a href="?bref=Deut.29.4">Dt 29:4</a>); Isaiah called it “dim” eyes (see <a href="?bref=Isa.6.10">Is 6:10</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>). Jesus charged the Pharisees with unbelief that made them “blind guides of the blind” (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.14">Mt 15:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.16">23:16</a>). Spiritual blindness is related to “hardness of heart” (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.17-18">Mk 8:17-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.17-18">Eph 4:17-18</a>) and is understood as the judgment of God both upon unbelievers (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.20-21">Rom 1:20-21</a>) and upon Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.29.10">Is 29:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.11.7-8">Rom 11:7-8</a>). According to Paul, it is also the work of Satan, who “has blinded the minds of those who don’t believe” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.4">2 Cor 4:4</a>). Healing from spiritual blindness is a special gift of God’s grace through the “new birth” (<a href="?bref=John.3.3">Jn 3:3</a>) and by seeing “the glorious light of the Good News” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.4">2 Cor 4:4</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="SymbolicUsesOfColors">
  <title>Symbolic Uses of Colors</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Symbolic Uses of Colors</p>
<p class="box-first">It is difficult to determine what the different colors symbolized in the ancient world. Some interpreters find no significance at all in the colors found in the Bible, whereas others do. According to Philo, a Greek-speaking Jewish writer who lived at the time of Christ, white represented the earth; purple, the sea; blue, the air; and scarlet, fire—reminiscent of the four basic elements of earthly matter in Aristotle’s philosophy. Ancient rabbis thought they could identify nations with the colors of Zechariah’s horses (e.g., red stood for Babylon because that empire had shed much blood). The Scofield Reference Bible (1909) interprets the colors in the tabernacle symbolically: gold represented death; silver, redemption; bronze, judgment; blue, heaven; purple, royalty; and scarlet, sacrifice.</p>
<p>It is probably unwise to insist that each color in the tabernacle hangings symbolized something. Only a few colors are given explicit significance in the Bible; further, no rule says that a color given symbolic meaning in one usage will always retain that meaning. The following colors frequently have symbolic meaning in the Bible: red, war and bloodshed (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.22">2 Kgs 3:22</a>); black, gloom or mourning (<a href="?bref=Isa.50.3">Is 50:3</a>); white, purity or righteousness (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.18">Is 1:18</a>); green, prosperity and health (<a href="?bref=Ps.92.14">Ps 92:14</a>); purple, royalty or honor (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.17">Mk 15:17</a>). Those colors have maintained similar symbolic associations to the present day.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheBeatitudesMatthew5112Nlt">
  <title>The Beatitudes, Matthew 5:1-12, NLT</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Beatitudes, <a href="?bref=Matt.5.1-12">Matthew 5:1-12</a>, NLT</p>
<p class="box-first">One day as he saw the crowds gathering, Jesus went up on the mountainside and sat down. His disciples gathered around him, <span class="vn">2</span>and he began to teach them.</p>
<p class="poetry-1-sp"><span class="vn">3</span>“God blesses those who are poor and realize their need for him,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">for the Kingdom of Heaven is theirs.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">4</span>God blesses those who mourn,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">for they will be comforted.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">5</span>God blesses those who are humble,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">for they will inherit the whole earth.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">6</span>God blesses those who hunger and thirst for justice,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">for they will be satisfied.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">7</span>God blesses those who are merciful,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">for they will be shown mercy.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">8</span>God blesses those whose hearts are pure,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">for they will see God.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">9</span>God blesses those who work for peace,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">for they will be called the children of God.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">10</span>God blesses those who are persecuted for doing right,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">for the Kingdom of Heaven is theirs.</p>
<p class="sp"><span class="vn">11</span>“God blesses you when people mock you and persecute you and lie about you and say all sorts of evil things against you because you are my followers. <span class="vn">12</span>Be happy about it! Be very glad! For a great reward awaits you in heaven. And remember, the ancient prophets were persecuted in the same way.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheBloodySweatPassage">
  <title>The Bloody-Sweat Passage</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Bloody-Sweat Passage</p>
<p class="box-first">This is the name for <a href="?bref=Luke.22.43-44">Luke 22:43-44</a>, which speaks of Jesus sweating, as it were, drops of blood. But the genuiness of this passage is doubted—at least, as to Lucan authorship. Several important manuscripts do not include the passage: P69, P75, Codex Sinaiticus, Codex Vaticanus, Codex Borgianus, and Codex Washingtonianus—manuscripts dating from the second to the fifth century. Other signs of its doubtfulness appear in manuscripts marking the passage with obeli (symbols), including 0171 (dated around 300) or crossing out the passage (as was done by the first corrector of Codex Sinaiticus). Writing in the fourth century, Epiphanius (Ancoratus 31.4-5) indicated that the verses were found in some “uncorrected copies” ofLuke. But other early church fathers (Justin, Irenaeus, Hippolytus, Dionysius, Eusebius) acknowledged this portion as part of Luke’s Gospel.</p>
<p>The debate about the genuiness of this passage has focused on what view one takes concerning whether or not Jesus needed to have been strengthened by angels during his trial in the Garden of Gethsemane. Some have said that the passage was excised because certain Christians thought that the account of Jesus overwhelmed with human weakness was incompatible with his deity. But it is more likely that the passage was an early (second century) interpolation, added from an oral tradition concerning the life of Jesus. Its transposition to <a href="?bref=Matt.26.1-75">Matthew 26</a> in some manuscripts and lectionaries indicates that it was a free-floating passage that could be interjected into any of the Passion narratives.</p>
<p>Despite the textual evidence against the passage, most English versions have kept it in the text for the sake of tradition. Therefore, many Christians consider this detail about Jesus’ Passion to be authentic. However, it is often interpreted incorrectly to say that Jesus was in such agony that he was sweating blood (technically called hemohydrosis or hematidrosis); that is why the passage is often called “the bloody-sweat” text. But the text says that he was sweating so profusely that it looked like blood dripping from a wound, not that his sweat became dripping blood.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheBranchASymbolForTheMessiah">
  <title>The Branch: A Symbol for the Messiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Branch: A Symbol for the Messiah</p>
<p class="box-first">In the following key passages, the “branch” is used as a symbol for the Messiah:</p>
<p class="list">1. <a href="?bref=Isa.4.2-6">Isaiah 4:2-6</a> is the first occurrence of “branch” as a title: “In that day the branch of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> shall be beautiful and glorious, and the fruit of the land shall be the pride and glory of the survivors of Israel” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). Many scholars interpret “branch” here to mean the Messiah for several reasons: (a) The whole tenor of the chapter makes it likely that it refers to the Messiah, who provides the harvest, establishes holiness, executes judgment, and creates “glory” in the land. (b) <a href="?bref=Isa.28.5">Isaiah 28:5</a> describes the Lord in similar terms, making a messianic interpretation of <a href="?bref=Isa.4.2">Isaiah 4:2</a> more probable. (c) <a href="?bref=Jer.23.5">Jeremiah 23:5</a> and <a href="?bref=Jer.33.15">33:15</a>, which seem to be commentaries on <a href="?bref=Isa.4.2">Isaiah 4:2</a>, interpret it to refer to the Messiah. Mention of a righteous remnant illustrates a concept developing along with the “branch” imagery and amplifying its meaning. The branch will become the “beauty and glory” of the remnant of Israel and will wreak destruction on apostate Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.4.4">Is 4:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1">Isaiah 11:1</a> adds a Davidic element to <a href="?bref=Isa.4.2">Isaiah 4:2</a>, since Jesse was David’s father. The “shoot” grew out of the “stump of Jesse,” that is, the royal line of David. The Davidic line is pictured as a fallen dynasty, a tree cut down (the passage probably mentions Jesse rather than David to stress a lowly origin). The stump remains, however, and there is still life within it. That stump is insignificant in contrast to the mighty forest of Assyria, but the Lord will level that forest (<a href="?bref=Isa.10.15-19,33-34">Is 10:15-19, 33-34</a>) and bring forth from Jesse’s stump a fruitful shoot who will recover the Israelite remnant (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.4,11-12">Is 11:4, 11-12</a>), destroy their adversaries, and reign in wisdom through the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
<p class="list">3. <a href="?bref=Jer.23.5">Jeremiah 23:5</a> and <a href="?bref=Jer.33.15">33:15</a> contrast the righteous reign of the Branch with the evil leadership of King Zedekiah. In both passages a remnant is pictured under the metaphor of a flock gathered back to their fold under caring shepherds (<a href="?bref=Jer.23.3-4">Jer 23:3-4</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.33.12-13">33:12-13</a>). The shepherds are ruled by the Branch, who is given the title “The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is our righteousness” (<a href="?bref=Jer.33.16">33:16</a>). That phrase in Hebrew is a deliberate wordplay on the name “Zedekiah” (meaning “the Lord is my vindication”). Zedekiah was righteous in name but not in reign. The Branch of the Lord, in contrast, will rule justly.</p>
<p class="list">4. <a href="?bref=Zech.3.8">Zechariah 3:8</a> and <a href="?bref=Zech.6.12">6:12</a> apply the branch metaphor in a different context—that of the postexilic task of rebuilding the temple. Zechariah described Joshua the high priest as a symbol of the future “servant- Branch” to be sent from the Lord. The Branch is seen as performing a priestly function in restoring righteous worship to the land. The royal line would be reinstated and the glories of the priestly line would also be reconstituted in the Branch. The servant of the Branch is probably taken from Isaiah’s servant songs, where similar language is used (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.2">Is 53:2</a>). Zechariah specifically related the priestly activity to rebuilding the temple. Zerubbabel had earlier been given the task of completing the literal building (<a href="?bref=Zech.4.7-9">Zec 4:7-9</a>), so the allusion must go beyond that to the “spiritual temple” to come. (Since Zerubbabel’s name means “shoot of Babylon,” the connection seems deliberate). Finally, Zechariah combines the two messianic aspects of the Branch: “He will build the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>’s Temple, and he will receive royal honor and will rule as king from his throne. He will also serve as priest from his throne, and there will be perfect harmony between the two” (<a href="?bref=Zech.6.13">6:13</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p class="sp">“Branch” is never used as a title in the NT. Yet there are hints of that concept’s influence, as in the familiar “vine and branches” metaphor (<a href="?bref=John.15.1-8">Jn 15:1-8</a>), in the use of palm branches at Jesus’ triumphal entry into Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=John.12.13">12:13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.11.8">Mk 11:8</a> and parallels), and possibly in the origin of the titles “Righteous One” (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.14">Acts 3:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.52">7:52</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jas.5.6">Jas 5:6</a>) and “Just One” (<a href="?bref=Acts.22.14">Acts 22:14</a>). Some have also taken an enigmatic reference to Christ, “He shall be called a Nazarene” as an allusion to the “branch” because in <a href="?bref=Isa.11.1">Isaiah 11:1</a> and other references <span class="hebrew">netzer</span> is similar to “Nazarene.”</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheChristianExperienceOfForgiveness">
  <title>The Christian Experience of Forgiveness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Christian Experience of Forgiveness</p>
<p class="box-first">The Christian understanding of forgiveness has broad implications:</p>
<p class="list">1. It reflects the character of God as one who pardons and enters into a meaningful relationship with his creature, producing a change in human relationship with him. This has been done in the costly anguish of the cross of Christ.</p>
<p class="list">2. It expresses the efficacy of divine atonement in the reconciliation of man with God. Those who truly realize their condition as sinners know that God can remove sin and redeem sinners. This must be experienced, not just comprehended intellectually. In Christ’s death, sin is condemned and absolutely judged, and yet Christ bears the penalty on our behalf by his sacrifice.</p>
<p class="list">3. For the apostle Paul, the bare concept of forgiveness does not convey deeply enough the full consequences. Instead, he speaks of being justified. To be “treated as righteous” is a rich consequence of forgiveness (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.5">Rom 4:5</a>), a gift of God’s grace (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.24">3:24</a>), a present experience (<a href="?bref=1Cor.4.4">1 Cor 4:4</a>) for those who have a faith relationship with Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.26">Rom 3:26</a>). Thus, justification is the positive relationship that forgiveness provides.</p>
<p class="list">4. Forgiveness implies that God has reconciled man to himself (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.14-17">Eph 2:14-17</a>). The outcome is peace with God (<a href="?bref=Phil.4.7">Phil 4:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.15">Col 3:15</a>), a reconciliation accomplished by the cross (<a href="?bref=Col.1.20">Col 1:20</a>). This is the implication of all the references in <a href="?bref=Rom.5.1-21">Romans 5</a> to being justified, reconciled, and trusting.</p>
<p class="list">5. Forgiveness includes the theme of fellowship with God the Father (<a href="?bref=1Thes.1.3">1 Thes 1:3</a>), Son (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.9">1 Cor 1:9</a>), and Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=2Cor.13.14">2 Cor 13:14</a>). It is expressed in the Pauline phrase “in Christ” or “in the Lord” (used some 164 times), indicating a profound relationship of communion and union with God. Forgiveness as reconciliation and restoration to fellowship with God comprehends, in effect, the whole nature of the Christian life. Sanctification is its fruit, and glorification is its objective. In forgiveness, God ultimately remains God, and the erring sinner is brought home to the Father who has eternally loved him.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheChurchDisplaysGodsManifoldWisdom">
  <title>The Church Displays God’s Manifold Wisdom</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Church Displays God’s Manifold Wisdom</p>
<p class="box-first">The Epistle to the Ephesians is Paul’s treatise on the universal church, the body of Christ. As such, it is not encumbered with local problems. It soars high above any mundane affairs and takes us into heaven, where we are presented with a heavenly view of the church as it fits into God’s eternal plan. In this epistle Paul paints the church with multifarious splendor. He depicts her as God’s inheritance (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.11">1:11</a>); Christ’s body, his fullness (vv <a href="?bref=Eph.1.22-23">22-23</a>), God’s masterpiece (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.10">2:10</a>); the one new person (v <a href="?bref=Eph.2.15">15</a>); the household of God (v <a href="?bref=Eph.2.19">19</a>); the habitation of God (vv <a href="?bref=Eph.2.21-22">21-22</a>); the joint body comprised of Jewish and Gentile believers (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.6">3:6</a>); the vessel for God to display his manifold wisdom (v <a href="?bref=Eph.3.10">10</a>); the body equaling Christ’s full stature (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.12-13">4:12-13</a>); the full-grown, perfect person (v <a href="?bref=Eph.4.13">13</a>); the body growing into a building (v <a href="?bref=Eph.4.16">16</a>); the bride of Christ (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.23-32">5:23-32</a>); the object of Christ’s love (v <a href="?bref=Eph.5.25">25</a>); the very members of Christ’s body (v <a href="?bref=Eph.5.30">30</a>); and God’s warrior against Satan (<a href="?bref=Eph.6.11-18">6:11-18</a>).</p>
<p>Paul’s presentation of the church reached its pinnacle in this epistle. The church he pictured with words was the church in ideal perfection, the church as seen from heaven but not yet manifested on earth in fullness. There have been real expressions of this church throughout history, but most would agree that the church has not yet reached the measure of the stature of the fullness of Christ. Nor is it yet the glorious church without spot or blemish. But there is the expectation that the church will grow and grow until its manifestation matches the ideal image.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheChurchsViewOfSpiritualGifts">
  <title>The Church’s View of Spiritual Gifts</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Church’s View of Spiritual Gifts</p>
<p class="box-first">The spiritual gifts of prophecy, glossolalia, and healing seem to have disappeared from the mainstream of the church’s life by the middle of the third century. The longer ending to Mark (<a href="?bref=Mark.16.17">Mk 16:17</a>), Justin Martyr, Irenaeus, and Tertullian all testify to the continuing experience of such gifts before then, but in the fourth century Chrysostom and Augustine of Hippo thought of them as belonging to the past. This was in large part due to the increasing institutionalization of the church, in the course of which <span class="ital">chrismation</span> (anointing with oil) progressively replaced <span class="ital">charismata</span> as the sign of the Spirit. The body of Christ came to be conceived of as a hierarchical structure, and the phrase “gifts of the Spirit” was referred more frequently to <a href="?bref=Isa.11.2">Isaiah 11:2</a>. Over the centuries there were successive claims that one or more of the more striking gifts had been restored—most notably by the early Montanists (second century), Joachim of Fiore (1132?–1202), many of the Anabaptists, and the early Quakers—but such claimants were usually either pushed to the fringes of Christianity or persecuted outright.</p>
<p>More recently, events have taken a different turn. Renewed interests in spiritual gifts, particularly healing and glossolalia, at the end of the 19th century heralded the emergence of Pentecostalism in the 20th century. With the acceptance of Pentecostalism as a third or fourth main stream of Christianity (beside Orthodoxy, Catholicism, and Protestantism), and charismatic renewal within the older denominations, the charismatic dimension of Christian life and worship has steadily gained recognition, not least among the Catholics.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheConceptOfBackslidingInTheNewTestament">
  <title>The Concept of Backsliding in the New Testament</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Concept of Backsliding in the New Testament</p>
<p class="box-first">In the NT, the term “backsliding” does not appear, but the concept is present in a number of ways. It is usually viewed from an individual more than from a group perspective. In a conversation on the Mt of Olives, Jesus observed that toward the end of the age, evil would abound and most people’s love would grow cold (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.12">Mt 24:12</a>). Steadfastness and perseverance were the only reliable antidotes to backsliding. Paul likewise warned believers of the dangers of falling away. Israel’s idolatry in the wilderness and God’s judgment upon their waywardness should serve as a stern warning (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.1-11">1 Cor 10:1-11</a>). Paul instructed his converts in Galatia against forsaking their freedom in Christ and an enslaving religion of works. He marveled that the new believers had so quickly been deceived (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.1">Gal 3:1</a>) and were abandoning the gospel of Christ (<a href="?bref=Gal.1.6">1:6</a>). The new Christians who had begun so well were failing to obey the truth (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.7">5:7</a>). In correspondence with Timothy, Paul was grieved to learn that some believers had already turned aside after Satan (<a href="?bref=1Tim.5.15">1 Tm 5:15</a>). Love of money and philosophical speculation had precipitated their downfall (<a href="?bref=1Tim.6.10,20-21">6:10, 20-21</a>). A Christian by the name of Demas turned back from serving God because he loved the world more than Christ (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.10">2 Tm 4:10</a>). Finally, in Revelation, the risen Christ reproached the churches for the spiritual indifference and coldness of their backsliding (<a href="?bref=Rev.2.4">Rv 2:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.3.16">3:16</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheDayOfAtonementAndTheNewTestament">
  <title>The Day of Atonement and the New Testament</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Day of Atonement and the New Testament</p>
<p class="box-first">In the NT the crucifixion account, many references in Paul’s epistles, and the whole book of Hebrews are inseparably connected to the Day of Atonement. The ritual of the day is explained as a “type” of the atonement made by Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.1-10.39">Heb 9–10</a>). Christ, the High Priest, shed his blood on Calvary and then, having atoned for the world’s sins, appeared in heaven before the Father (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.11-12">Heb 9:11-12</a>). Unlike the annual repetitions of the day in Israel, Christ’s atonement is seen in the NT as securing eternal redemption (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.12">Heb 9:12</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">Rom 3:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.9-10">5:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.7">1 Cor 5:7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.18-21">2 Cor 5:18-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.13-14">Gal 3:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.14">Col 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.2.14">Ti 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.18-19">1 Pt 1:18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.2">1 Jn 2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.10">4:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.5.9">Rv 5:9</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheDocumentaryFormOfTheCovenant">
  <title>The Documentary Form of the Covenant</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Documentary Form of the Covenant</p>
<p class="box-first">Modern biblical scholarship has established that the Sinai covenant and its renewals were formally patterned after a particular type of human covenant, namely the suzerainty treaty of the ancient world (an agreement between a great power and a lesser power). Archaeological discoveries in the 20th century brought to light a number of such international political documents, the most interesting coming from the ancient Hittite Empire and dating from approximately the 14th century <span class="era">BC</span>. Study of those treaty documents has revealed a fairly consistent pattern. Comparison with biblical passages describing the Sinai covenant shows a remarkable parallel.</p>
<p>In Deuteronomy, the Hebrews seem to have adapted the form of international suzerainty treaties to express their own covenant relationship with God. Why did they choose that particular form? Perhaps the Hebrews had been bound to their Egyptian masters by that kind of treaty, so they wanted to dramatize their liberation by making a new treaty, this time with their God at Sinai. Also, the Sinai covenant formed the constitution of a new but small Near Eastern nation. Whereas other small nations commonly depended for their existence on the generosity of a suzerain power (e.g., Egypt), Israel was to be a free nation, owing allegiance only to God. Israel’s “treaty” with God meant that it could acknowledge no other master. Its freedom and strength lay in its wholehearted commitment to God alone.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheEssenesAndChristianity">
  <title>The Essenes and Christianity</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Essenes and Christianity</p>
<p class="box-first">Some scholars have compared certain sayings of Jesus in the Gospels, certain passages in Acts, and certain statements in Paul’s epistles, and constructed a fantasy Christianity that is ascetic, communal, and legalistic. In short, they have painted early Christianity to be an Essene community. Point by point we could demonstrate parallels with Essene beliefs and practices, but such techniques are a denial of true scholarship. Taken as a whole, the teachings of Jesus exalt marriage and the family, and place the rights and proper use of property in the conscience of the owner, while legalism is strongly rejected. The same can certainly be said for the early church as portrayed in Acts and for the teaching of Paul in his epistles. By no proper use of the materials can Christianity be equated with Essenism, or for that matter, with Qumranism.</p>
<p>This is not to deny, however, that there are elements of Essenism that can be compared with elements of Christianity. We should not object to the theory that some Essenes may have heard the gospel and become Christians. Nor is there any sufficient reason to reject the notion that certain Essene ideas could have been influential in the early church. A careful study of the NT will show that there were many currents and crosscurrents in the early church. The differences between Peter and Paul provide only one example out of many. If the ultimate redemptive purpose of God is to remove the divisions that man has erected and to unify those who have been divided (cf. <a href="?bref=Eph.2.14">Eph 2:14</a>), then we may properly conclude that the church on earth must be the mixing bowl where all kinds of ingredients are brought together, to be sifted, blended, and purified by God’s Spirit.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheExcavationOfNebuchadnezzarsBabylon">
  <title>The Excavation of Nebuchadnezzar’s Babylon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Excavation of Nebuchadnezzar’s Babylon</p>
<p class="box-first">Much of Nebuchadnezzar’s Babylon was excavated by Robert Koldewey for the German Oriental Society in a series of campaigns beginning in 1899. Koldewey discovered that Nebuchadnezzar’s Babylon was the largest city in antiquity, with an area of about 2,500 acres (1,013 hectares). The older part of the city was completely enclosed by two walls made of unbaked mud bricks. The inner and higher wall, which was more than 21 feet (6.4 meters) thick, was separated from the outer wall by a military road 23 feet (7 meters) wide. The outer wall, though thinner, was still more than 12 feet (3.7meters) thick. Both walls were buttressed by massive fortified towers at intervals of about 65 feet (19.8 meters). Outside the wall was a moat that reached a width of more than 200 feet (61 meters) in places.</p>
<p>One of the most magnificent finds was the Ishtar Gate, a double gateway 40 feet (12.2 meters) high covered with enameled brick reliefs of 575 bulls and dragons in vivid colors. (Ishtar was a goddess of love and fertility.) Through that gate ran the Procession Way, a road covered with limestone slabs 3 feet (.9 meter) square. An inscription credited the road to Nebuchadnezzar. The walls along the Procession Way were overlaid with enameled bricks decorated with 120 lions representing Ishtar. The road led to the temple of Marduk and its adjacent ziggurat.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheGreeksViewOfResurrection">
  <title>The Greeks’ View of Resurrection</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Greeks’ View of Resurrection</p>
<p class="box-first">Greek dualism, the separation of body from soul, was not conducive to the acceptance of resurrection, with the exception of some miracle-story resuscitations.</p>
<p>Instead of a doctrine of resurrection, the Greeks developed a doctrine of the immortality of the soul. The body was thought to be a disposable physical outer garment, whereas the soul was related to the immortal forms and sustained from age to age. The Greek cyclical view of time lent itself to the development of a sophisticated view of the transmigration of the soul from body to body.</p>
<p>Whether the Athenians misunderstood Paul or not, their reaction to Paul’s preaching of Jesus and the resurrection (<a href="?bref=Acts.17.16-32">Acts 17:16-32</a>) is quite compatible with Greek thought. The idea of a genuine resurrection from the dead to an immortal state, whether for persons in general or for a specific person like Jesus, was foreign to Greek philosophy.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheKingdomWillCome">
  <title>The Kingdom Will Come</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Kingdom Will Come</p>
<p class="box-first">Earthly kingdoms dominate Daniel’s visions, but Jesus established the kingdom of God. That kingdom, however, has only partially come; it will reach its fullness in Christ’s second advent. The message of Daniel speaks within that tension of a kingdom already come and yet still to come in its fullness. The modern world reveals not the universal kingdom of God but the clamorous kingdoms of humanity. They are powerful and often appear to hold the world’s future firmly in their hands. Daniel’s message is that they do not: God is sovereign, and his kingdom will finally come in its full power.</p>
<p>To say more than that with respect to Daniel’s visions is a delicate business. Trying to identify the nations of Daniel’s dreams with modern nations misses the intention of the book. If Daniel, even with the help of angelic interpreters, found it difficult to understand his own visions, caution is appropriate for the modern reader. Yet Daniel ended his mysterious book with a note of hope: “As for you, go your way until the end. You will rest, and then at the end of the days, you will rise again to receive the inheritance set aside for you” (<a href="?bref=Dan.12.13">12:13</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheMysteriousMagi">
  <title>The Mysterious Magi</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Mysterious Magi</p>
<p class="box-first">Matthew did not tell how many magi came to honor the infant Jesus. The Eastern church believed there were 12 travelers, although this may simply derive from the biblical penchant for that number (12 tribes of Israel, 12 disciples). The Western church settled on three magi or wise men, based presumably on the three gifts brought in homage. The exact number is not known.</p>
<p>A similar silence exists in Matthew regarding the names of the wise men. The names Gaspar, Melchior (Melkon), and Balthasar are legendary; they do not come from Matthew’s text. Similarly, the later tradition that Gaspar was a king of India, Melchior a king of Persia, and Balthasar a king of Arabia has no basis in fact.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheMysteryOfElection">
  <title>The Mystery of Election</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Mystery of Election</p>
<p class="box-first">In the teaching of Augustine and Calvin, the doctrine of election is of fundamental importance. They taught that God had chosen before the creation of the world to save a number of specific individuals from sin and judgment and to give them eternal life. Those whom he chose did nothing to deserve it; their merits are no better than the rest of humankind who will be judged for their sins. But in his mercy God decided to save some; therefore, he chose them and sent Jesus to be their Savior. The Holy Spirit regenerates and brings to faith through an “effectual calling” those whom God has elected. God’s Spirit effectively persuades each of them to submit to the gospel, so they are guaranteed recipients of eternal life.</p>
<p>This choice by God to save some selectively may seem unjust. But God is not obliged to show mercy to anybody; he is free to show mercy as he pleases. People cannot protest that because they were not the elect, they never had a chance of being saved. They never deserved that chance anyway. But anybody who hears the gospel and responds to it with faith can know that he is one of the elect. Whoever rejects the gospel has only his own sinfulness to blame.</p>
<p>Many Christians reject that explanation of God’s election. They maintain that, although it appears to be logically consistent with Scripture, it makes God the prisoner of his own plan. His predestination of certain individuals to salvation commits him personally to a detailed, predetermined, unilateral course of action that reduces human action to a charade and renders it insignificant. God ceases to be a person dealing with persons.</p>
<p>The Augustinian and Calvinist view of election, according to its critics, also makes God out to be arbitrary in his choice of the elect. In effect, chance becomes the arbiter of human destiny rather than a holy and loving God. Those difficulties arise because, they say, the teaching of Scripture has been pressed into an artificial logical system that distorts it.</p>
<p>Some Christians avoid the difficulties by saying that God elects “those whom he foreknew” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.29">Rom 8:29</a>), that is, those whom he knew beforehand would respond to the gospel in faith. Augustine briefly held that view but eventually rejected it. Many believe that the “solution” produces even greater logical problems and undermines the sovereignty of God.</p>
<p>Karl Barth proposed an alternative solution. Instead of teaching that God has chosen to save some of humankind and has passed by the others or chosen to reject them, Barth has noted how Jesus is spoken of in Scripture as “the Elect One.” Jesus is the object both of God’s rejection and of his election. In him the human race was rejected and endured judgment for its sins, Barth argued, but in him also the race is chosen and appointed to salvation. It is thus in Jesus Christ that we are chosen by God (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.4">Eph 1:4</a>). Barth’s interpretation could conceivably lead to universalism (that is, the view that all humanity will be saved), but Barth explicitly rejected that as a necessary conclusion. He insisted that a person may reject his or her calling and election. Nevertheless, difficulties remain. It has been argued that Barth’s view places too much weight on one text and also that it confuses God’s election of Jesus for service with his election to salvation of the whole human race.</p>
<p>The teaching of Scripture should not be overly systematized. In the words of the Westminster Confession, election is a “high mystery . . . to be handled with special prudence and care, that men attending the will of God revealed in his word, and yielding obedience thereunto, may, from the certainty of their effectual vocation, be assured of their eternal salvation” (3:8).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheMysteryOfTheKingdom">
  <title>The Mystery of the Kingdom</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Mystery of the Kingdom</p>
<p class="fl">A “mystery” is a divine truth hidden in the heart of God but in due time revealed to people (see <a href="?bref=Rom.16.25-26">Rom 16:25-26</a>). The mystery of the kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.11">Mt 13:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.11">Mk 4:11</a>) is precisely this: that prior to its eschatological consummation, the kingdom has come in an unexpected form in the historical mission of Jesus. This mystery is illustrated in Jesus’ parables (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.1-58">Mt 13</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.1-41">Mk 4</a>). Modern scholarship recognizes two critical norms in interpreting the parables. First, a parable is not an allegory but a story taken from daily life, teaching essentially a single truth. Second, the parables must be interpreted in the life setting of Jesus’ mission.</p>
<p>The parable in <a href="?bref=Mark.4.26-29">Mark 4:26-29</a> is not a parable of stages of growth but an illustration that “the earth produces of itself” (v <a href="?bref=Mark.4.28">28</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The kingdom is God’s reign—a supernatural thing, not a human work.</p>
<p>The parable of the four soils (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.3-9,18-23">Mt 13:3-9, 18-23</a>) does not intend to teach that there are precisely four kinds of hearers of the word of the kingdom. The central truth is that the word of the kingdom must be <span class="ital">received;</span> otherwise it does not bear fruit. In other words, the kingdom as Jesus proclaimed and embodied it requires a human response to be effective.</p>
<p>The parable of the wheat and weeds (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.24-30">Mt 13:24-30</a>) teaches that the kingdom of God has actually come into history without effecting the eschatological judgment that will separate the good from the bad. Both are to grow together in the world (v <a href="?bref=Matt.13.38">38</a>) until the Day of Judgment, when the eschatological separation will take place.</p>
<p>The parables of the mustard seed and leaven (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.31-33">Mt 13:31-33</a>) are parables of contrast between present insignificance and future magnificence. The emphasis is not upon how the kingdom progresses from small beginnings. Jesus never spoke of the growth of the reign of God. What is now like a tiny seed—a Galilean prophet and a handful of followers—will one day be like a great tree.</p>
<p>The parables of the treasure and pearl (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.44-46">Mt 13:44-46</a>) teach that this apparently insignificant appearance of the kingdom in Jesus nevertheless merits every effort to attain it.</p>
<p>The parable of the net (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.47-50">Mt 13:47-50</a>) teaches that the movement set up by the presence of the kingdom in Jesus brings together a mixed people. (Jesus’ disciples even harbored a traitor.) There will nevertheless be an eschatological separation.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheNazarethDecree">
  <title>The Nazareth Decree</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Nazareth Decree</p>
<p class="box-first">A fascinating document comprising some 20 lines of rather poor Greek inscribed on a simple slab of white marble was discovered in Nazareth in the latter part of the nineteenth century. This document reads:</p>
<p>“Ordinance of Caesar. It is my pleasure that graves and tombs remain undisturbed in perpetuity for those who have made them for the cult of their ancestors, or children, or members of their house. If, however, any man gives information that another has either demolished them, or has in any other way extracted the buried, or has maliciously transferred them to other places in order to wrong them, or has displaced the sealing or other stones, against such a one I order that a trial be instituted, as in respect of the gods, so in regard to the cult of mortals. For it shall be much more obligatory to honor the buried. Let it be absolutely forbidden for anyone to disturb them. In the case of contravention I desire that the offender be sentenced to capital punishment on charge of violation of sepulture.”</p>
<p>In order to understand the full significance of this text we need to be able to make a very close approximation to the date by means of the style of writing. According to this text, the inscription is to be dated to about <span class="era">AD</span> 50. The most likely emperor under whom such a decree was issued was Claudius (<span class="era">AD</span> 41–54). He is known to have taken an interest in the regulation of Jewish affairs in other lands.</p>
<p>The secular historian Suetonius, in his biography of Claudius, made reference to riots that broke out within the Jewish community “at the instigation of Chrestus,” that is Christ, as the name appears misspelled in the text (<span class="ital">Life of Claudius</span> 25.4). We may conjecture that Christian Jews in Rome who preached Jesus to their fellows provoked riots in that city. Claudius seems to have expelled all the Jews from Rome (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.2">Acts 18:2</a>). Another copy of a letter of Claudius was found among papyri in Egypt in 1920, dating to <span class="era">AD</span> 41. It forbade the Alexandrian Jews “to bring or invite other Jews to come by sea from Syria. If they do not abstain from this conduct, I shall proceed against them for fomenting a malady common to the world.”</p>
<p>Against this background we may propose an explanation of the Nazareth Decree. The early Christians were proclaiming that Jesus Christ had risen from the dead. The rabbis of the time claimed that “his disciples came and stole away the body” (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.13">Mt 28:13</a>). Whatever the truth of the matter from the viewpoint of Claudius, he did not wish to encourage theories about the disappearance of bodies from tombs. The Nazareth Decree thus becomes a strong pointer to the resurrection of Christ, which was at that time upsetting the Roman world. So Claudius took steps to curb the spread of these disturbing ideas.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheOssuaryOfTheStCatherineMonastery">
  <title>The Ossuary of the St. Catherine Monastery</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Ossuary of the St. Catherine Monastery</p>
<p class="box-first">The famous ossuary of the St Catherine Monastery in Sinai is situated in the corner of a garden. For the bone remains of the monks, there is a house, where the bones are piled up in regular order, arranged according to their kind, as skulls, legs, and arms. In an uncovered porch before the bone house, there are vaults and pits in which the corpses of the monks are usually interred without coffins until the flesh is changed into dust, and then the bones are collected into the common ossuary.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheRelationshipBetweenEphesiansAndColossians">
  <title>The Relationship between Ephesians and Colossians</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Relationship between Ephesians and Colossians</p>
<p class="box-first">Written at approximately the same time as Colossians, Ephesians displays both striking similarities and significant differences in comparison with that letter. By studying these, some knowledge can be gained about the composition of Ephesians.</p>
<p>Many words and phrases appear in almost identical form in the two letters. This is often more obvious in the Greek text than in modern translations. One example is found in <a href="?bref=Eph.1.4">Ephesians 1:4</a> and <a href="?bref=Col.1.22">Colossians 1:22</a>, where at the end of each verse Paul states that God will not charge the believer with any fault. There are also longer passages that are parallel to one another. These include teachings on adopting a new way of life (e.g., <a href="?bref=Eph.4.22-24">Eph 4:22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.8-10">Col 3:8-10</a>), singing praise (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.19-20">Eph 5:19-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.16-17">Col 3:16-17</a>), and living together in harmony (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.22-6.9">Eph 5:22–6:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.18-4.1">Col 3:18–4:1</a>).</p>
<p>These similarities are not absolute, however. In the passages just cited on human relationships, Ephesians has a detailed section on husbands and wives that is lacking in Colossians. Also, in Ephesians some unique sections are interspersed that are thought to have a liturgical character (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.3">Eph 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.3.20-21">3:20-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.5-6">4:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.14">5:14</a>). Others sound as though they were intended for public exhortation, some think at a baptism or for renewal of dedication (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.17-5.2">4:17–5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.3-21">5:3-21</a>).</p>
<p>Further, some verses in Ephesians seem to be conflations of verses from various parts of Colossians. For example, <a href="?bref=Eph.1.7">Ephesians 1:7</a> seems to combine thoughts found in <a href="?bref=Col.1.14">Colossians 1:14</a> and <a href="?bref=Col.1.20">20</a>. The ideas of <a href="?bref=Col.1.3-4">Colossians 1:3-4</a> and <a href="?bref=Col.1.9">9</a> seem to be brought together in <a href="?bref=Eph.1.15-16">Ephesians 1:15-16</a>. A similar instance is <a href="?bref=Eph.2.1-5">Ephesians 2:1-5</a>, which combines two widely separated verses, <a href="?bref=Col.2.13">Colossians 2:13</a> and <a href="?bref=Col.3.6">3:6</a>.</p>
<p>Theories abound to account for such similarities and differences. A few have proposed that Ephesians was written first; most, however, grant priority to Colossians. Some think that a preliminary version of one was used in the other, and was then expanded into its present form. According to one popular theory, which assumes that Paul is not the author, Ephesians was written by a later Christian who prepared it as an introduction to a collection of Paul’s genuine writings, drawing material from Colossians and other Pauline letters.</p>
<p>The most satisfying reconstruction is that Paul wrote Colossians to meet the specific needs of the church at Colosse, planning to ask his friend Tychicus to take the letter there (<a href="?bref=Col.4.7">Col 4:7</a>). Meanwhile, Paul was reflecting on several of the themes touched on in Colossians. He thought also about the ultimate goals of his missionary endeavors. God had revealed to Paul his comprehensive plan for the church and the universal headship of Christ. Paul wrote Ephesians by drawing on some of the phrases and sentences that were fresh in his mind from Colossians.</p>
<p>This reconstruction also explains why some of the terms are used in a somewhat different way than they are in Colossians. Paul’s purposes were different. Colossians is polemical, dealing with the problem of false teachers and teaching. Ephesians is reflective, dealing with the general subject of the church. There are other topics that are distinct in Ephesians but barely touched on in Colossians.</p>
<p>It is then clear why the term “mystery” is applied differently (see article). In Colossians, where the issue revolves largely around the person of Christ, the “mystery” is applied to the Lord himself. In Ephesians, with its emphasis on the church, the term is applied to the unity of Jews and Gentiles in the church. Neither usage exhausts the comprehensive meaning of the term.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheSevenLastSayingsInTheChurch">
  <title>The Seven Last Sayings in the Church</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Seven Last Sayings in the Church</p>
<p class="box-first">The seven last words have a deep pastoral content that has captured the imagination of the church. Many forms for Christian meditation focus on these words. They have been celebrated in liturgy (especially Good Friday liturgies). They have been put to music (e.g., Heinrich Schutz in the 1700s). They have been an example of Christian behavior and a basis for Passion theology (particularly the fourth). Thus, they form an invaluable part of church tradition.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheSignificanceOfAtonementInTheNewTestament">
  <title>The Significance of Atonement in the New Testament</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Significance of Atonement in the New Testament</p>
<p class="box-first">Many terms are employed to express the atoning significance of Christ’s death. His death is the “sacrifice to God” (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.2">Eph 5:2</a>) and a “single sacrifice for sins” (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.12">Heb 10:12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.9.26">9:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.27">7:27</a>). Paul wrote that God set Christ forth to be a “propitiation” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) or “expiation” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). The <span class="sc">niv</span> helps to clarify the concept by using the term “atoning sacrifice,” an expression that includes the ideas of both propitiation and expiation. The death of Christ is seen as the fulfillment of all that was prefigured by the OT sacrificial system.</p>
<p>The sacrificial nature of Christ’s death is clearly expressed. He was referred to by Paul as “our paschal lamb” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.5.7">1 Cor 5:7</a>). The apostle Peter stated that believers are rescued “not with perishable things such as silver or gold, but with the precious blood of Christ, like that of a lamb without blemish or spot” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.18-19">1 Pt 1:18-19</a>). So also the references in <a href="?bref=John.1.29,36">John 1:29, 36</a> to Jesus as the “Lamb of God” probably had in mind the idea of sacrifice.</p>
<p>If Christ is viewed as our sacrifice, he is also viewed as our representative. That is, he represented us in his death. One of the most difficult phrases to interpret precisely is the common biblical expression “for us” (“for me,” etc.). It may mean generally “for my sake” or something more specific. Does Christ represent us? More specifically, is he a substitute for us? Some texts clearly speak of him as our representative. Thus Paul said, “We are convinced that one has died for all; therefore all have died” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.14">2 Cor 5:14</a>). If “substitution” were meant, the last clause would conclude that we will not, or do not, die. Hebrews speaks of Christ as our High Priest before the Father, which is probably what John had in mind when he referred to Christ as our “advocate with the Father” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.2">1 Jn 2:2</a>).</p>
<p>The expression “for us” at times seems to mean much more than representation; it often carries the sense of substitution, an idea prevalent in the OT. So, “For our sake he made him to be sin who knew no sin, so that in him we might become the righteousness of God” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.21">2 Cor 5:21</a>). Two “ransom sayings” also portray substitution: “The Son of man came not to be ministered unto, but to minister, and to give his life a ransom for many” (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.45">Mk 10:45</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). He “gave himself as a ransom for all” (<a href="?bref=1Tim.2.6">1 Tm 2:6</a>). He became a “curse for us” (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.13">Gal 3:13</a>). The unintended prophecy of Caiaphas the high priest pointed to the same reality: “It is expedient for you that one man should die for the people, and that the whole nation should not perish” (<a href="?bref=John.11.50">Jn 11:50</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheSignificanceOfBitterHerbs">
  <title>The Significance of Bitter Herbs</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Significance of Bitter Herbs</p>
<p class="box-first">The significance of the bitter herbs is not explained in the Exodus narrative. In the traditional interpretation, the herbs symbolize the bitterness of the Hebrews’ experience of Egyptian bondage. The two other references to bitter herbs (<a href="?bref=Num.9.11">Nm 9:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.3.15">Lam 3:15</a>) shed no direct light upon the kind of plant or its significance. The Numbers passage specifies how the Passover commemoration was to be celebrated by persons unable to participate at the normally appointed time (<a href="?bref=Num.9.6-12">Nm 9:6-12</a>). The Lamentations passage describes the prophet Jeremiah’s personal affliction. He pictures himself as suffering at the hands of the Lord who has filled him with bitterness. If the prophet’s experience could be symbolized by reference to bitter herbs, it is reasonable that Israel’s experience of slavery in Egypt might also have been symbolized in that way. After that night of the Hebrews’ deliverance from bondage, the herbs were used annually in a commemorative observance of the Passover.</p>
<p>Today the Samaritans use the leaves of the wild lettuce plant as bitter herbs for their Passover observance. Jews of European origin customarily use red horseradish.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheSignificanceOfTheDeadSeaScrolls">
  <title>The Significance of the Dead Sea Scrolls</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Significance of the Dead Sea Scrolls</p>
<p class="box-first">Before the Qumran discoveries, the oldest existing Hebrew manuscripts of the OT dated from about <span class="era">AD</span> 900—with the exception of the Nash Papyrus fragments (see below). The oldest complete manuscript was the Firkowitsch Codex from <span class="era">AD</span> 1010. The greatest importance of the Dead Sea Scrolls, therefore, lies in the discovery of biblical manuscripts dating back to only about 300 years after the close of the OT canon. That makes them 1,000 years earlier than the oldest manuscripts previously known to biblical scholars. The most frequently represented OT books are Genesis, Exodus, Deuteronomy, Psalms, and Isaiah. The oldest text is a fragment of Exodus dating from about 250 <span class="era">BC</span>. The Isaiah Scroll from Cave One dates from about 100 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The Dead Sea Scrolls show that the OT text has been handed down along three main lines of transmission. The first is the Masoretic Text, which was preserved in the oldest Hebrew manuscripts known before the Qumran discoveries. The Masoretes, whose scholarly school flourished between <span class="era">AD</span> 500 and 1000 at the city of Tiberias, standardized the traditional consonantal text by adding vowels and marginal notes (the ancient Hebrew alphabet had no vowels). Some scholars dated the origin of the consonantal Masoretic Text to the editorial activities of Rabbi Akiba and his colleagues in the second century <span class="era">AD</span>. The discoveries at Qumran, however, proved them wrong, by showing that the Masoretic Text went back several more centuries into antiquity and had been accurately copied and transmitted. Although there are some differences in spelling and grammar between the Dead Sea Scrolls and Masoretic Text, the differences have not warranted any major changes in the substance of the OT. Yet they have helped biblical scholars gain a clearer understanding of the text.</p>
<p>A second line of transmission of the OT text has been the Greek translation of the Hebrew OT known as the Septuagint. The majority of OT quotations in the NT are from the Septuagint. That translation was made about 250 <span class="era">BC</span> and ranks second in importance to the Masoretic Text for reconstructing an authentic OT text. Some scholars used to attribute differences between the Septuagint and the Masoretic Text to imprecision, subjectivity, or laxity on the part of the Septuagint’s translators. Now it seems that many of those differences resulted from the fact that the translators were following a slightly different Hebrew text. Some Hebrew texts from Qumran correspond to the Septuagint and have proved helpful in solving textual problems. Septuagint manuscripts have also been found among the Dead Sea Scrolls.</p>
<p>A third line of OT transmission has been in the Samaritan preservation of the Hebrew text of the Pentateuch dating from the second century <span class="era">BC</span>. The copies of the Samaritan Pentateuch were written in the same script used in some of the Qumran documents. Some of the Hebrew biblical texts found at Qumran have closer affinities with the Samaritan version than with the one handed down by the Masoretic scholars. All of the manuscripts have shed new light on grammatical forms, spelling, and punctuation.</p>
<p>Whatever differences may have existed between the community at Qumran and the mainstream of Jews from which they separated, it is certain that both used common biblical texts. The discovery of the Dead Sea Scrolls is thus a witness to the antiquity and accurate transmission of the biblical text.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheSongOfSongsChapter4Niv">
  <title>The Song of Songs, Chapter 4 (NIV)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Song of Songs, Chapter 4 (NIV)</p>
<p class="box-h2-poetic">Lover</p>
<p class="poetry-1">How beautiful you are, my darling!</p>
<p class="poetry-2">Oh, how beautiful!</p>
<p class="poetry-2">Your eyes behind your veil are doves.</p>
<p class="poetry-1">Your hair is like a flock of goats</p>
<p class="poetry-2">descending from Mount Gilead.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">2</span> Your teeth are like a flock of sheep just shorn,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">coming up from the washing.</p>
<p class="poetry-1">Each has its twin;</p>
<p class="poetry-2">not one of them is alone.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">3</span> Your lips are like a scarlet ribbon;</p>
<p class="poetry-2">your mouth is lovely.</p>
<p class="poetry-1">Your temples behind your veil</p>
<p class="poetry-2">are like the halves of a pomegranate.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">4</span> Your neck is like the tower of David,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">built with elegance;</p>
<p class="poetry-1">on it hang a thousand shields,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">all of them shields of warriors.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">5</span> Your two breasts are like two fawns,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">like twin fawns of a gazelle</p>
<p class="poetry-2">that browse among the lilies.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">6</span> Until the day breaks</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and the shadows flee,</p>
<p class="poetry-1">I will go to the mountain of myrrh</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and to the hill of incense.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">7</span> All beautiful you are, my darling;</p>
<p class="poetry-2">there is no flaw in you.</p>
<p class="poetry-1-sp"><span class="vn">8</span> Come with me from Lebanon, my bride,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">come with me from Lebanon.</p>
<p class="poetry-1">Descend from the crest of Amana,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">from the top of Senir, the summit of Hermon,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">from the lions' dens</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and the mountain haunts of the leopards.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">9</span> You have stolen my heart, my sister, my bride;</p>
<p class="poetry-2">you have stolen my heart</p>
<p class="poetry-1">with one glance of your eyes,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">with one jewel of your necklace.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">10</span> How delightful is your love, my sister, my bride!</p>
<p class="poetry-2">How much more pleasing is your love than wine,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and the fragrance of your perfume than any spice!</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">11</span> Your lips drop sweetness as the honeycomb, my bride;</p>
<p class="poetry-2">milk and honey are under your tongue.</p>
<p class="poetry-2">The fragrance of your garments is like that of Lebanon.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">12</span> You are a garden locked up, my sister, my bride;</p>
<p class="poetry-2">you are a spring enclosed, a sealed fountain.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">13</span> Your plants are an orchard of pomegranates</p>
<p class="poetry-2">with choice fruits,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">with henna and nard,</p>
<p class="poetry-2"><span class="vn">14</span> nard and saffron,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">calamus and cinnamon,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">with every kind of incense tree,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">with myrrh and aloes</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and all the finest spices.</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">15</span> You are [b] a garden fountain,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">a well of flowing water</p>
<p class="poetry-2">streaming down from Lebanon.</p>
<p class="box-h2-poetic">Beloved</p>
<p class="poetry-1"><span class="vn">16</span> Awake, north wind,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and come, south wind!</p>
<p class="poetry-1">Blow on my garden,</p>
<p class="poetry-2">that its fragrance may spread abroad.</p>
<p class="poetry-1">Let my lover come into his garden</p>
<p class="poetry-2">and taste its choice fruits.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TheSpiritualSignificanceOfCircumcision">
  <title>The Spiritual Significance of Circumcision</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">The Spiritual Significance of Circumcision</p>
<p class="box-first">The hygienic act of circumcision symbolized the need for cleansing if the holy God was to enter into relationship with an unholy people. At first it was God’s intention to let the ritual teach its own lesson. In <a href="?bref=Gen.17.9-27">Genesis 17:9-27</a> the observance merely serves as the covenant seal; Abraham is given little explanation of the significance of the rite itself. Later Moses used the expression “uncircumcised lips” to describe his unskilled speech (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.12,30">Ex 6:12, 30</a>). When Israel entered the Promised Land, the yield of its fruit trees was to be considered “uncircumcised” for the first three years; after that it would be holy to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.23-24">Lv 19:23-24</a>).</p>
<p>By the time of the exodus, it became evident that circumcision had to do with ethical as well as physical considerations. In <a href="?bref=Deut.10.16">Deuteronomy 10:16</a> Moses exhorted the people to circumcise the foreskins of their hearts, and in <a href="?bref=Deut.30.6">Deuteronomy 30:6</a> this command assumes the form of a promise: “The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God will circumcise your heart and theheart of your offspring, so that you will love the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God with all your heart and with all your soul” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Sin in the lives of the chosen people made their circumcision meaningless before God. Thus Moses told the Israelites to humble their uncircumcised hearts (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.41">Lv 26:41</a>). The prophets further develop this teaching. Jeremiah urged the citizens of Judah to remove the foreskins of their hearts to avoid God’s wrath because of their evil ways (<a href="?bref=Jer.4.4">Jer 4:4</a>), warning that the “uncircumcised ears” of Israel were not sensitive to the word of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Jer.6.10">Jer 6:10</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span> mg). Judgment will come upon Egypt, Edom, Ammon, Moab, and Judah, declares God, for “I am going to punish all who are circumcised only in flesh . . . for all these nations, and the whole House of Israel too, are uncircumcised at heart” (<a href="?bref=Jer.9.24-25">Jer 9:24-25</a>, JB). Through Ezekiel the Lord complains that the temple has been profaned by the admission of aliens uncircumcised in heart and flesh (<a href="?bref=Ezek.44.7,9">Ez 44:7, 9</a>). Isaiah looks forward to the day when there will be a new Jerusalem into which the uncircumcised and unclean will no longer come.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ThreeAnointedOnesForeshadowTheMessiah">
  <title>Three Anointed Ones Foreshadow the Messiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Three Anointed Ones Foreshadow the Messiah</p>
<p class="box-first">Jesus’ office and function were foreshadowed by the three groups of OT anointed officials: prophets, priests, and kings. Elisha’s anointing by Elijah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.16">1 Kgs 19:16</a>) shows anointing of prophets was practiced, although not required by OT law. Moses was the first OT prophet (<a href="?bref=Deut.18.18">Dt 18:18</a>) whose ministry prompted the messianic hope for the coming of the Prophet (<a href="?bref=John.6.14">Jn 6:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.1.1">Heb 1:1</a>). All priests, from Aaron on, were ordained by anointing with oil in required consecration rites (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.41">Ex 28:41</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.29.7-9">29:7-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.30.30">30:30</a>). The kings of Israel, beginning with Saul and David, were anointed as a sign of divine choice and approval (<a href="?bref=1Sam.9.15-17">1 Sm 9:15-17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.10.1">10:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.16.13">16:13</a>). Essential to the external ceremony was the pouring of perfumed olive oil upon the person’s head (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.22-33">Ex 30:22-33</a>). The internal reality was the gift of the Spirit to the recipient: “from that day on the Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> came upon David in power” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.16.13">1 Sm 16:13</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). The anointed person was not a free agent. As prophet, priest, or king, he spoke, served, or ruled in the name of the Lord and as his representative to the people of God.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ToWhomWasTheRansomPaid">
  <title>To Whom Was the Ransom Paid?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">To Whom Was the Ransom Paid?</p>
<p class="box-first">This question has perplexed scholars for hundreds of years. Origen (c. 185–254), a theologian of Alexandria, maintained that the ransom was paid to the devil. Origen’s form of the theory was that Christ cheated the devil by escaping through his resurrection.</p>
<p>Although Jesus Christ defeated Satan and liberates believers from Satan’s bondage, Scripture does not indicate that the ransom was paid to him. God was wronged by human sin, yet he showed his great love in providing redemption (<a href="?bref=John.3.16">Jn 3:16</a>). God declared humans guilty for their sin and imposed the death penalty for human transgression. Thus Scripture indicated that the ransom was really directed by Christ to the Father. The biblical references to Jesus’ life as a ransom are echoed in the satisfaction views of the atonement.</p>
<p>Anselm of Canterbury in 1098 developed the satisfaction view of the atonement, emphasizing that the honor of God required satisfaction for sin. Later views emphasized the justice of God in requiring payment (ransom) for the just demands of the law and for the removal of the curse of the law, which is death (see <a href="?bref=Eph.1.7,14">Eph 1:7, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.14">Col 1:14</a>). Paul emphasized the justice of God, which was met so that he would be just in justifying sinners who believe (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.23-26">Rom 3:23-26</a>).</p>
<p>Reformed theology emphasizes the ransom as being paid by Christ’s death to meet the satisfaction of God’s justice in Christ’s atonement. Without using the term “ransom,” the same implications are carried in such condensed expressions as “Christ died for our sins” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.3">1 Cor 15:3</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="UnityWithChristMeansCommunityWithChristians">
  <title>Unity with Christ Means Community with Christians</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Unity with Christ Means Community with Christians</p>
<p class="box-first">The equation of Christ and the church in this image of “body” leads to a very particular understanding of the nature of Christian existence. Paul speaks of the life of faith as life “in Christ.” To be “in Christ” is to be a “new creation” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.17">2 Cor 5:17</a>). But for Paul, this is not just an individual experience, a kind of mystical union between the believer and Christ. For in a real sense, to be “in Christ” is at the same time to be in the church. To be “baptized into Christ” (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.27">Gal 3:27</a>) is to become one with a community where the traditional barriers of human society are overcome—“for you are all one in Christ Jesus” (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.28">3:28</a>). Again, to be “in Christ” is to be “baptized into one body” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.12-13">1 Cor 12:12-13</a>), for “you are the body of Christ and individually members of it” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.27">12:27</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). For Paul, then, there is no such thing as a Christian in isolation, nurturing an individual relationship with Christ. To be a Christian is to be incorporated into a community of persons that is growing toward expressing, in its “body life,” the reality of Christ, fleshing out this reality in its common life and work.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WarningsAgainstApostasy">
  <title>Warnings against Apostasy</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Warnings against Apostasy</p>
<p class="box-first">Many NT passages, using different words, convey warnings against apostasy. In the last days, tribulation and persecution will cause many to “fall away” (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.9-10">Mt 24:9-10</a>); false prophets will arise and “lead many astray” (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.11">Mt 24:11</a>). Other causes of apostasy include temptation (<a href="?bref=Luke.8.13">Lk 8:13</a>) and unbelief (<a href="?bref=Heb.3.12">Heb 3:12</a>). Paul cited Hymenaeus and Alexander as examples of those who had rejected the faith (<a href="?bref=1Tim.1.20">1 Tm 1:20</a>). The writer of Hebrews referred to those who had believed and then departed from the faith as being in a hopeless state—with no possibility of further repentance (<a href="?bref=Heb.6.1-6">Heb 6:1-6</a>). The consequences of willful sinning after receiving Christ are terrifying (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.26-31">Heb 10:26-31</a>). The apostle Peter said that, for believers in Christ who knowingly turned away, “they are worse off than before” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.2.20-22">2 Pt 2:20-22</a>). The apostle John addresses this same problem (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.18-19">1 Jn 2:18-19</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WatchOut">
  <title>Watch Out</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Watch Out</p>
<p class="box-first">Sometimes eschatology has been a divisive force within Christian circles because believers have quarreled over minor points. In some cases denominations in which there was agreement on the major doctrines of eschatology have split over a minor point, such as the tribulational views. Another danger to be avoided is date setting. While we are to be alert to the “signs of the times,” we must remember that God has not revealed the exact time of our Lord’s return to any human being, or even to the angels (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.36">Mt 24:36</a>). Some have believed that they could determine the exact time of the Lord’s return. When their calculations proved incorrect, these believers had their faith jeopardized as a result.</p>
<p>Properly understood and applied, eschatology has a powerful positive significance for Christians. It is to be a source of comfort (<a href="?bref=1Thes.4.18">1 Thes 4:18</a>) and encouragement (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.58">1 Cor 15:58</a>); it challenges Christians to watchfulness and faithful service (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.14-30">Mt 25:14-30</a>). Because the time is limited, Christians are to use faithfully the opportunities that are theirs. Because of the certainty of our Lord’s return, we are to be filled with hope and courage.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WhatHappenedToTheArk">
  <title>What Happened to the Ark?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">What Happened to the Ark?</p>
<p class="box-first">Little is known about the ark’s history after the time of Solomon. What happened to it when Judah was exiled to Babylon is a mystery. It may have been destroyed when Nebuchadnezzar destroyed the temple and the whole city of Jerusalem in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. The new temple built after return from the exile had no ark. There is a legend in the Apocrypha that Jeremiah hid the ark in a cave on Mt Nebo until a time when God would again restore his people (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Macc.2.4-8">2 Macc 2:4-8</a>).</p>
<p>The disappearance of the ark at the exile, however, was providential. For not only had the presence of God disappeared from above the mercy seat, but God had long since rejected worship as it was offered at the temple (<a href="?bref=Lam.2.6,7">Lam 2:6, 7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.11-14">Is 1:11-14</a>). Moreover, the very purpose and significance of the ark was ultimately to be fulfilled in the person and work of Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>With the coming of Jesus Christ, the yearly sprinkling of the mercy seat with the blood of bulls and goats was no longer necessary. Christ, with the shedding of his own blood, secured an eternal redemption (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.11-14">Heb 9:11-14</a>). Consequently, those who trust in him are encouraged to come with boldness before the God of grace enthroned above the mercy seat (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.14-16">Heb 4:14-16</a>). Whereas before, the veil hung as a barrier between men and the ark, Christ through his death tore the veil in two and passed through it (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.51">Mt 27:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.20">Heb 10:20</a>), opening the way for all worshipers to see the ark of God’s covenant (<a href="?bref=Rev.11.19">Rv 11:19</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WhereAreTheseCities">
  <title>Where Are These Cities?</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Where Are These Cities?</p>
<p class="box-first">The question of the location of the cities of the plain has been an intriguing one in biblical study. Today scholars generally conclude that these cities stood at the south end of the Dead Sea. Scripture itself connects them with the valley of Siddim. Either they stood in the valley or else the valley lay adjacent to the plain where they were located. Between the days of Abraham and Moses, the water level of the Dead Sea evidently had risen enough to cover at least part of the valley of Siddim; <a href="?bref=Gen.14.3">Genesis 14:3</a> declares that the valley of Siddim was “the Salt Sea” (in Moses’ time). The southern part of the Dead Sea is now only 12 to 15 feet (3.7 to 4.6 meters) deep, whereas the northern part reaches a depth of 1,300 feet (396 meters). Josephus, a first-century <span class="era">AD</span> historian, declared that ruins of the five cities were still to be seen at the south end of the Dead Sea. No trace of these ruins has been discovered in modern times.</p>
<p>Though much of the region south of the Dead Sea is now burned out and sterile, the area to its southeast is still fertile. Three streams pour down from the mountains of Moab into this area and furnish water for irrigation. W. F. Albright, a 20th-century archaeologist, noted that five streams flow into the south end of the Dead Sea. Atown could have stood on each of them.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WipingOutTheCanaanites">
  <title>Wiping Out the Canaanites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">Wiping Out the Canaanites</p>
<p class="box-first">Many have expressed objection to the apparent cruelty of the Israelites in wiping out the Canaanite people, sometimes calling it barbarism. It should be noted, however, that total annihilation was not practiced everywhere but only in Jericho and Ai and the later punishment of the Amalekites under Saul (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.1-35">1 Sm 15</a>). As in the earlier conquest of the Midianites (<a href="?bref=Num.31.17-18">Nm 31:17-18</a>), not all the population was killed. In <a href="?bref=Deut.20.10-18">Deuteronomy 20:10-18</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.21.10-14">21:10-14</a>, a distinction is drawn between the treatment of Canaanites (actually a heterogeneous group, see <a href="?bref=Deut.20.17">Dt 20:17</a>) and other captive peoples. With the Canaanites, the command to “save alive nothing that breathes” (v <a href="?bref=Deut.20.16">16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) was given “that they may not teach you to do according to all their abominable practices which they have done in the service of their gods, and so to sin against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God” (v <a href="?bref=Deut.20.18">18</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>In Abraham’s time the wickedness of the Amorites was not yet “complete” (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.16">Gn 15:16</a>), but by Joshua’s time it was. Archaeology has documented the sexual perversions, child sacrifices, idolatry, and cruelty of the Canaanites. The Land of Promise was intended to be swept clean of such abominations so that Israel could live an unhampered life, ordered by the covenant law of their God.</p>
</body>
</item>
<item typename="Textbox" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="YouMustBeBornAgain">
  <title>You Must Be Born Again</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">You Must Be Born Again</p>
<p class="box-first">The Bible insists that regeneration is absolutely necessary. Apart from it, all persons are dead in trespasses and sin (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.1">Eph 2:1</a>). A shocking description of this condition is given in <a href="?bref=Eph.2.2-3">Ephesians 2:2-3</a>. An unregenerated person is unable to understand the things of God, and no amount of good works can change it (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.14">1 Cor 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.5">Ti 3:5</a>). This is why Jesus insisted, in his dialogue with Nicodemus, “You must be born again” (<a href="?bref=John.3.7">Jn 3:7</a>).</p>
</body>
</item>
</items>