<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Glory">
  <title>Glory</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GLORY</p>
<p class="fl">The singular splendor of God and the consequences for humanity.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGloryofGod">The Glory of God</p>
<p class="fl">The glory of God can be described in two senses: (1) as a general category or attribute, and (2) as a specific category referring to particular historical manifestations of his presence.</p>
<p class="h3">As an Attribute</p>
<p class="fl">God’s glory refers primarily to his majestic beauty and splendor; it also refers to the expression of God’s character (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.23">Rom 3:23</a>). The Scriptures record praise to his glorious name (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.5">Neh 9:5</a>), describe him as the glorious Father (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.17">Eph 1:17</a>) and the King of glory (<a href="?bref=Ps.24.1-10">Ps 24</a>); he is exalted above the heavens, and his glory is over all the earth (<a href="?bref=Ps.57.5,11">Pss 57:5, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.108.5">108:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.113.4">113:4</a>). He is the God of glory who appeared to the patriarchs of the OT (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.2">Acts 7:2</a>). He is jealous to maintain his glory and unwilling that it be given to another (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.8">Is 42:8</a>); he acts to bring glory to himself (<a href="?bref=Ps.79.9">Ps 79:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.48.11">Is 48:11</a>).</p>
<p>The glory of God is proclaimed by the Creation (<a href="?bref=Ps.19.1">Pss 19:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.97.6">97:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.20">Rom 1:20</a>). It is revealed by his mighty acts of salvation and deliverance (<a href="?bref=1Chr.16.24">1 Chr 16:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.72.18-19">Pss 72:18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.96.3">96:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.145.10-12">145:10-12</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.4,40">Jn 11:4, 40</a>). His glory is the theme of the praise (<a href="?bref=1Chr.16.24-29">1 Chr 16:24-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.29.1-2,9">Pss 29:1-2, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.66.1-2">66:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.96.7-8">96:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.115.1">115:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.42.12">Is 42:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.4.20">Rom 4:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.9-11">Phil 2:9-11</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">As His Presence</p>
<p class="fl">References to the glory of the Lord are often to particular historical manifestations of his presence; images of light and fire are prominently associated with these occurrences. The foremost example is what is known in rabbinical literature as <span class="translatorCheckTargetLanguage">the shekinah glory, a phrase meaning the “dwelling glory.”</span> It refers primarily to the presence of God in the pillar of cloud and fire in the OT.</p>
<p>The first explicit reference to the glory cloud is found in <a href="?bref=Exod.13.21-22">Exodus 13:21-22</a>. At the time of the exodus, the glory of God appeared in the pillar of cloud and fire to lead the people through the sea and wilderness (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.11-12,19">Neh 9:11-12, 19</a>). At Sinai, with Israel encamped around the mountain, the glory of God comes in the cloud and fire to speak with Moses in the sight of the people (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.9,16-18">Ex 19:9, 16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.24.15-18">24:15-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.5,22-24">Dt 5:5, 22-24</a>). When Moses is given a glimpse of that glory unconcealed by the cloud and fire, his own face becomes radiant and must be veiled because of the people’s fear (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.18-23">Ex 33:18-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.29-35">34:29-35</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.7-18">2 Cor 3:7-18</a>).</p>
<p>The picture of Israel encamped around the glory of God on Sinai portrays God dwelling in the midst of his people. When the tabernacle is completed and the people set out on their march, the glory cloud of God’s presence dwells above them throughout their journey (<a href="?bref=Exod.40.34-38">Ex 40:34-38</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.10.11-12">Nm 10:11-12</a>). When they encamp, the tribes encircle the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Num.1.50-2.2">Nm 1:50–2:2</a>), and the cloud reminds them of his presence in their midst. Later, the same glory filled the new temple that Solomon builds (<a href="?bref=2Chr.5.13-6.1">2 Chr 5:13–6:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.7.1-3">7:1-3</a>). The psalmists celebrated Jerusalem and the temple as the place where his glory dwelt (<a href="?bref=Ps.26.8">Pss 26:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.63.2">63:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.85.9">85:9</a>); God was in their midst.</p>
<p>Later in Israel’s history they denied God’s glorious presence (<a href="?bref=Isa.3.8">Is 3:8</a>) and exchanged the glory of the Lord for idols made by human hands (<a href="?bref=Ps.106.20">Ps 106:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.10-11">Jer 2:10-11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.1.23">Rom 1:23</a>). Because of their disobedience, judgment came against Jerusalem; the penalties of covenant violation were enforced. God would no longer be the God of a disobedient people (<a href="?bref=Hos.1.9">Hos 1:9</a>). God’s presence in the glory cloud left the temple (<a href="?bref=Ezek.10.4,18-19">Ez 10:4, 18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.11.22">11:22</a>), and Israel went into exile (<a href="?bref=Ezek.12.1-15">12:1-15</a>).</p>
<p>Yet out of this judgment God determined to bring a remnant to rebuild the city and the temple. In his visions Ezekiel saw the glory of the Lord return to dwell in the temple again (<a href="?bref=Ezek.43.2-9">Ez 43:2-9</a>), a time when the glory would return to a purified people and dwell among them forever. When the exile was over and the second temple was under construction, Haggai and Zechariah urged the people on with the promise of the return of the glory of God to fill the temple as it had done in the first temple and to “be glory in their midst” (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.3-9">Hg 2:3-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.2.5,10-11">Zec 2:5, 10-11</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGloryofGodinJesusChrist">The Glory of God in Jesus Christ</p>
<p class="fl">We are not told if the shekinah glory returned to the second temple. But we are told that God’s glory was seen again on earth in the person of Jesus Christ. <a href="?bref=John.1.14">John 1:14</a> says, “The Word became flesh and <span class="ital">dwelt</span> among us, and we beheld his <span class="ital">glory, glory</span> as of the only Son” (italics added). As such, Jesus was the new tabernacle for God’s abiding glory. In Jesus, God dwelt among people. Since Christ was (and is) the very image of God, to see the light of his face was to know the glory of God (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.4-6">2 Cor 4:4-6</a>). To see Jesus was to see a “light to the Gentiles and the glory of Israel” (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.30-32">Lk 2:30-32</a>). The disciples who witnessed the Transfiguration (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.1-8">Mt 17:1-8</a>) saw his glory in a marvelous way (<a href="?bref=2Pet.1.16-17">2 Pt 1:16-17</a>), for it was a glory that burst out of his human body. This outburst of glory prefigured the glorification Christ experienced in resurrection and ascension (see <a href="?bref=John.17.5">Jn 17:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.5-11">Phil 2:5-11</a>).</p>
<p>Because Jesus humbled himself and was obedient to the point of death, God highly exalted him (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.8-9">Phil 2:8-9</a>). After he suffered death on the cross, he entered into his glory (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.26">Lk 24:26</a>) with a new and glorious body (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.39-43">1 Cor 15:39-43</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.3.21">Phil 3:21</a>). The glorified Christ appeared to his servants. Stephen saw his glory (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.55">Acts 7:55</a>), and Saul was blinded by his splendor (<a href="?bref=Acts.9.3">9:3</a>). That same Christ is predicted to return in glory. He will sit on his throne in judgment (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.31">Mt 25:31</a>); evil will be punished (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.27">16:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.30">24:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.26">Mk 13:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.21.27">Lk 21:27</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.9-10">2 Thes 2:9-10</a>). Those who have professed him before men need not fear his glorious appearing (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.38">Mk 8:38</a>).</p>
<p>At the consummation, the whole earth will be filled with his glory (<a href="?bref=Ps.72.19">Ps 72:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.6.3">Is 6:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.2.14">Hb 2:14</a>). No longer will a glory cloud rest above a temple to mark the Holy Place, for there will be a new heaven and a new earth (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.1">Rv 21:1</a>). The Holy City will have the radiance of the glory of God (vv <a href="?bref=Rev.21.10-11">10-11</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="GloryandthePeopleofGod">Glory and the People of God</p>
<p class="fl">The people of God have experienced the glory of the presence of God. The glory cloud of the OT was <span class="ital">their</span> glory (<a href="?bref=Ps.106.20">Ps 106:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.11">Jer 2:11</a>). Christ came as the embodiment of the glory of God; God was in the midst of his people. When Christ ascended, he sent his Spirit to the believers (<a href="?bref=John.16.7-14">Jn 16:7-14</a>) so that God could live in the midst of his people. The Spirit of glory rests on those who suffer for the name of Christ (<a href="?bref=1Pet.4.14">1 Pt 4:14</a>); that Spirit is the guarantee of the glorious inheritance of the saints (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.16-17">Rom 8:16-17</a>).</p>
<p>God has given to his people the hope of glory (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.2">Rom 5:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.3.21">Phil 3:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.27">Col 1:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Jude.1.24-25">Jude 1:24-25</a>). Those whom he has chosen he will also glorify (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.30">Rom 8:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.9.23">9:23</a>); they will share in the glory of Christ (<a href="?bref=Col.3.4">Col 3:4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.14">2 Thes 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.10">2 Tm 2:10</a>). The sufferings of this age do not compare with the glory that will be revealed (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.18">Rom 8:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.4.17">2 Cor 4:17</a>). The whole of creation longs to see the glorious freedom of the children of God (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.21">Rom 8:21</a>). This hope of glory is so certain that Peter can speak of participating in it even now (<a href="?bref=1Pet.5.1">1 Pt 5:1</a>) while looking forward to that eternal glory (v <a href="?bref=Rom.5.10">10</a>). As partakers in the glory of Christ, the church is called to glorify God. Because of the hope that is in them, they purify themselves (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.3">1 Jn 3:3</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Boast_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Boast</a>; <a href="?item=GodBeingandAttributesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Being and Attributes of</a>; <a href="?item=PillarofFireandCloud_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Pillar of Fire and Cloud</a>; <a href="?item=Shekinah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shekinah</a>; <a href="?item=Theophany_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Theophany</a>; <a href="?item=Wealth_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wealth</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>