<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gospel">
  <title>Gospel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GOSPEL</p>
<p class="fl">Term used for various ways of describing the good news that God offers salvation through Jesus Christ.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#TheGospelMessageofIsaiah">The Gospel Message of Isaiah</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheGospelintheNewTestament">The Gospel in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheGoodNewsofChristsComing">The Good News of Christ’s Coming</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheGospelaccordingtoJesus">The Gospel according to Jesus</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheGospelafterJesusResurrection">The Gospel after Jesus’ Resurrection</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGospelMessageofIsaiah">The Gospel Message of Isaiah</p>
<p class="fl">Of all the passages cited, those of Isaiah provide the most important background for the gospel in the NT. According to Isaiah’s gospel, it is God alone who saves, and there is no explanation for his saving action except in his own nature. Israel’s deliverance is undeserved; she is no more worthy of the divine love now than when she went into captivity. In whatever measure she has paid the just due for her past sins (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.2">Is 40:2</a>), she remains a sinful people (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.25">42:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.46.12-13">46:12-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.48.1">48:1</a>). It is only by God’s grace that she is saved (<a href="?bref=Isa.55.1-7">55:1-7</a>). By God’s design, Israel’s salvation depends not upon her own righteousness but upon his (<a href="?bref=Isa.41.10">41:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.45.24">45:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.46.13">46:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.51.5-6">51:5-6</a>). There being no righteousness to reward, the Lord acts to <span class="ital">create</span> righteousness in Israel (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.8">45:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.61.3,10-11">61:3, 10-11</a>). Yet as these references indicate, salvation is not accomplished at the expense of justice. The penalty for Israel’s sins is to be paid in full. God’s mercy is not hereby called into question. On the contrary, it is precisely here that his mercy is most poignantly expressed, for the penalty is exacted not from his people but from the Servant appointed to stand in their place (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.4-12">53:4-12</a>). Through the Servant’s work, many shall be justified (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.11">53:11</a>). The Evangelist—the preacher of the good news—will come, as predicted in <a href="?bref=Isa.61.1-11">Isaiah 61</a>. He is called the anointed One (v <a href="?bref=Isa.61.1">1</a>) who proclaims the year of the Lord’s favor (v <a href="?bref=Isa.61.2">2</a>). God will be glorified through his preaching (v <a href="?bref=Isa.61.3">3</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGospelintheNewTestament">The Gospel in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In only two places (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.8">Gal 3:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.2,6">Heb 4:2, 6</a>) does the NT speak of the proclamation of the gospel prior to the Christian era. This is quite remarkable, given (1) the unmistakable presence of the gospel in the OT, (2) the extent of gospel terminology in the NT (in the Greek the noun appears 76 times; and the verb, 54), and (3) the fact that the NT presents Christ as the fulfillment of the OT and draws heavily on the OT to interpret his person and work. Not only is it remarkable; it is very significant. It indicates that the NT usage depends not only upon the <span class="ital">character</span> of the message (truth about salvation) but also upon <span class="ital">historical events.</span> Almost without exception, the NT restricts its application of gospel terminology to proclamations made during the time of fulfillment—the age in which the salvation promised in the OT is actually accomplished. The NT is preoccupied, not with promises of salvation, but with news of salvation. According to <a href="?bref=Mark.1.1-4">Mark 1:1-4</a>, the gospel “begins” not in the OT but with John the Baptist, in whose work OT prophecy is fulfilled. In <a href="?bref=Rom.1.1-5">Romans 1:1-5</a> the gospel is represented as a blessing promised in the OT but not actually given until Jesus comes (see also <a href="?bref=Acts.13.32-33">Acts 13:32-33</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGoodNewsofChristsComing">The Good News of Christ’s Coming</p>
<p class="fl">The promised birth of John the Baptist is good news (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.19">Lk 1:19</a>), not only for his parents (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.1.7,24-25">7, 24-25</a>) but for all the people: John is sent to prepare them for Messiah’s coming (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.1.14-17,67-79">14-17, 67-79</a>). John’s own preaching is gospel (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.18">3:18</a>) for the same reason. The Messiah would be coming to execute judgment, a process that involves both condemnation and salvation (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.3.3-17">3-17</a>). John’s message is gospel for sinners in that they are warned of impending doom and urged to repent before the ax falls (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.3.7-9">7-9</a>); it is gospel for the repentant in that they are promised forgiveness (v <a href="?bref=Luke.3.3">3</a>) and membership in Messiah’s community (v <a href="?bref=Luke.3.17">17</a>). The birth of the Savior himself is announced as good news bringing great joy (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.10-11">2:10-11</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGospelaccordingtoJesus">The Gospel according to Jesus</p>
<p class="h3">The Coming of the Kingdom of God</p>
<p class="fl">Jesus was authorized by God and anointed by the Spirit to proclaim the gospel (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.14">Mk 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.18">Lk 4:18</a>). At the heart of his preaching stands the announcement “The time is fulfilled, and the kingdom of God is at hand; repent, and believe in the gospel” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.15">Mk 1:15</a>). (For further references to this gospel, see <a href="?bref=Matt.4.23">Mt 4:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.9.35">9:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.14">24:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.26.13">26:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.35">Mk 8:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.29">10:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.10">13:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.9">14:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.43">Lk 4:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.1">8:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.16.16">16:16</a>.) The message is good news for several reasons: (1) The kingdom is coming. The God whom Jesus proclaims is sovereign over all he has made. Yet paradoxically his rule is incomplete: his will is not done on earth as it is in heaven; wrong, not right, prevails. But these conditions are not final, according to Jesus. When the kingdom comes, God’s rule will be completed; wrong will be judged, righteousness established, and his people blessed. (2) The kingdom is <span class="ital">now</span> being inaugurated. “The time is fulfilled,” declares Jesus (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.15">Mk 1:15a</a>). The time appointed for the fulfillment of the OT promises has arrived. (3) The consummation of the kingdom is therefore no longer a distant prospect; the full realization of God’s rule is “at hand” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.15">Mk 1:15b</a>). (4) God is establishing his rule for a saving purpose. This is implied in Jesus’ call to repentance (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.15c">Mk 1:15c</a>). It is especially clear in the passages to which we now turn.</p>
<p class="h3">The Salvation of the Poor</p>
<p class="fl">Invited to read the Scripture in the synagogue at Nazareth, Jesus turns to <a href="?bref=Isa.61.1-11">Isaiah 61</a>: “The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, because he has anointed me to preach good news to the poor. He has sent me to proclaim release to the captives and recovering of sight to the blind, to set at liberty those who are oppressed, to proclaim the acceptable year of the Lord” (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.18-19">Lk 4:18-19</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Having read the prophecy, Jesus announces its fulfillment in his own ministry (v <a href="?bref=Luke.4.21">21</a>). Included among those whom Jesus has come to free are the physically infirm, such as the blind (v <a href="?bref=Luke.4.18">18</a>) and the leprous (v <a href="?bref=Luke.4.27">27</a>) (cf. the references to healing miracles in vv <a href="?bref=Luke.4.23,33-41">23, 33-41</a>; the close connection between evangelizing and healing in <a href="?bref=Matt.4.23">Mt 4:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.9.35">9:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.11.5">11:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.21-22">Lk 7:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.6">9:6</a>; and the description in <a href="?bref=Matt.12.22-29">Mt 12:22-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.11-16">Lk 13:11-16</a>, of the physically afflicted as captives of Satan now liberated by Jesus). Also included are the materially poor—people like the widow helped by Elijah during the famine (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.25-26">Lk 4:25-26</a>). It is the literally poor and hungry whom Jesus pronounces “blessed” in <a href="?bref=Luke.6.20-21">Luke 6:20-21</a>. Yet it is primarily “spiritual” poverty that is in view. Still applying <a href="?bref=Isa.61.1-11">Isaiah 61</a>, Jesus speaks in <a href="?bref=Matt.5.3">Matthew 5:3</a> of the “poor in spirit.” These are people broken and grieved by misery and poverty, oppression and injustice, suffering and death, national apostasy and personal sin—people who in their extremity turn to God and longingly wait for him to bring forth justice, bestow his mercy, and establish his kingdom. It is to just such people that Jesus brings good news (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.3-10">Mt 5:3-10</a>). God sent him to usher in the kingdom, to rescue the lost, to liberate the enslaved, to cure the afflicted, to bind up hearts that are broken, and to forgive the guilty (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.5,10,17">Mk 2:5, 10, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.45">10:45</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.18-21">Lk 4:18-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.48-49">7:48-49</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.15.1-32">15:1-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.19.10">19:10</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Gift of Grace</p>
<p class="fl">The kingdom's arrival is not the effect or the reward of human effort but God’s answer to the human predicament—the gift of his favor (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.32">Lk 12:32</a>). Correspondingly, the explanation for the salvation of the poor lies nowhere but in God’s own character. As the prodigal himself recognized, he hardly deserved to be his father’s servant, much less his son. Nothing he did, not even his repentance, accounted for the father’s love (<a href="?bref=Luke.15.11-32">15:11-32</a>). In the parable of <a href="?bref=Matt.20.1-16">Matthew 20:1-16</a>, it is owing entirely to the goodness of the employer that the last workers to be hired receive a full day’s wages. The first debtor in the story of <a href="?bref=Matt.18.23-35">Matthew 18:23-35</a> earned nothing but the right to be sold into slavery; instead, the king canceled his enormous debt. The publican, who had nothing to offer God but a confession of sin and plea for mercy, went home justified (<a href="?bref=Luke.18.13-14">Lk 18:13-14</a>). The same holds true for the more virtuous among the poor, such as the persons described in <a href="?bref=Matt.5.7-10">Matthew 5:7-10</a>. Their virtue is real, not imagined. Yet in keeping God’s commands, they do not put him in their debt; they are simply doing their duty (<a href="?bref=Luke.17.7-10">Lk 17:7-10</a>). Furthermore, even the most merciful need divine mercy (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.7">Mt 5:7</a>). For even those most eager to obey God’s law are unable to fulfill all its requirements (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.11.28-30">11:28-30</a>). The first servant in <a href="?bref=Matt.18.23-35">Matthew 18:23-35</a> owes far more money than someone in such a situation could possibly pay—which serves to magnify the generosity of the king. Grace depends for its exercise upon the inability of its objects (<a href="?bref=Luke.14.12-14">Lk 14:12-14</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Call to Salvation</p>
<p class="fl">The Israelites are without exception a sinful people, all of them needing the salvation that Jesus brings (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">Mt 1:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.77">Lk 1:77</a>). In demonstration of God’s grace, Jesus proclaimed his gospel to the entire nation (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.23">Mt 4:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.9.35">9:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.15.24">15:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.43">Lk 4:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.6">9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.1">20:1</a>). From the most respectable to the least, all are summoned to submit to God’s rule, all are invited to come and partake freely of the banquet he has spread (<a href="?bref=Luke.14.16-24">Lk 14:16-24</a>). But the gift of salvation must be received if it is to be experienced (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.15">Mk 10:15</a>). And while it is indeed a gift that costs nothing, it is also a priceless treasure for which a wise person will freely sacrifice everything else (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.44-46">Mt 13:44-46</a>), a sacrifice exceeded only by the cost of rejecting the gospel (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.20-24">Mt 11:20-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.34-39">Mk 8:34-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.14.24,33">Lk 14:24, 33</a>). “Repent and believe in the gospel,” Jesus commands (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.15">Mk 1:15</a>). The self-righteous and the self-sufficient must be jolted out of their false sense of security and humbly recognize their need for God (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.24-26">Lk 6:24-26</a>). Only then will Jesus’ message to the poor be seen as gospel. An announcement of liberation (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.18-19">4:18-19</a>) is good news only to people who are enslaved and know they are. The command applies also to the destitute and the afflicted. Those among them who bemoan their lot must repent of their sins. But something further is needed for the response to be complete: a person cannot believe Jesus’ gospel without a commitment to the <span class="ital">Person</span> of Christ (<a href="?bref=John.3.16">Jn 3:16</a>). Even those who are already “poor in spirit,” in the sense defined earlier, are not really “blessed” until they acknowledge the truth of Jesus’ claims (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.6">Mt 11:6</a>) and commit themselves to a life of obedience on his terms (<a href="?bref=Matt.7.21-27">7:21-27</a>). This prepares us for the next point.</p>
<p class="h3">Summary</p>
<p class="fl">Throughout Jesus’ earthly ministry, the theme of his gospel remains the progressive advent of God’s kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.23">Mt 4:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.14">24:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.43">Lk 4:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.16.16">16:16</a>), a message that is preached almost exclusively to Jews (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.5-6">Mt 10:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.15.24">15:24</a>). Yet Jesus also provides glimpses into what the gospel was to become once his work on earth was accomplished: (1) In <a href="?bref=Mark.8.35">Mark 8:35</a> and <a href="?bref=Mark.10.29">10:29</a> Jesus speaks of individuals who needed to make great sacrifices “for my sake and for the gospel.” While distinguished from each other, the person of Jesus and the gospel are here associated in the closest possible way. The time was approaching when the Proclaimer of the gospel would become the Proclaimed. (2) In <a href="?bref=Mark.13.10">Mark 13:10</a> and <a href="?bref=Matt.24.14">Matthew 24:14</a> (and the textually doubtful <a href="?bref=Mark.16.15">Mk 16:15</a>) Jesus predicts that the gospel of the kingdom will be preached to the gentile nations. (3) In <a href="?bref=Mark.14.1-72">Mark 14</a>, having interpreted a woman’s action (v <a href="?bref=Mark.14.3">3</a>) as an anointing of his body beforehand for burial (v <a href="?bref=Mark.14.8">8</a>), Jesus declares, “And truly, I say to you, wherever the gospel is preached in the whole world, what she has done will be told in memory of her” (v <a href="?bref=Mark.14.9">9</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.26.13">Mt 26:13</a>). This statement strongly implies that both the person of Jesus and the event of his death will figure prominently in the message that is to be proclaimed; otherwise, it is strange that the gospel and this particular act should be so solemnly bound together. In this text, there already is an indication of how crucial Jesus’ death is for salvation, as announced in his gospel (cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.14.22-24">Mk 14:22-24</a>), and for the launch of the evangelistic mission to the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.28">Mt 20:28</a> is vital for explaining the shift from <a href="?bref=Matt.15.24">Mt 15:24</a> to <a href="?bref=Matt.28.18-20">28:18-20</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheGospelafterJesusResurrection">The Gospel after Jesus’ Resurrection</p>
<p class="fl">After the resurrection of Jesus, the gospel was proclaimed by his eyewitnesses. The contents of this gospel are recorded in the book of Acts and in Paul’s letters. Of the 43 instances of <span class="greek">euangelizomai</span> (“evangelize”) beyond the Gospels, 15 occur in Acts and 21 in Paul’s writings; of the 64 instances of <span class="greek">euangelion</span> (“gospel”), 2 occur in Acts and no fewer than 60 in Paul.</p>
<p class="h3">The Gospel of Christ</p>
<p class="fl">Having risen from the dead, Jesus Christ again evangelizes (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.16-17">Eph 2:16-17</a>), doing so now through his appointed representatives (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.16-18">Rom 15:16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.17">1 Cor 1:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.9.12-18">9:12-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.4.13-14">Gal 4:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.4.11">Eph 4:11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.1.9-11">2 Tm 1:9-11</a>). More than that, Christ has become the central theme of the gospel; the Proclaimer is now the Proclaimed. This is repeatedly affirmed in Acts (<a href="?bref=Acts.5.42">5:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.8.4-5,35">8:4-5, 35</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.20">11:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.18">17:18</a>) and in Paul’s writings (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.1-4">Rom 1:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.10.8-17">10:8-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.19-20">15:19-20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.4.4-6">2 Cor 4:4-6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.4">11:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.16">Gal 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.3.8">Eph 3:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.1.15-18">Phil 1:15-18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.8">2 Tm 2:8</a>). The NT always speaks of <span class="ital">the gospel</span>—never the gospels—of Christ. A second gospel is as inconceivable and as unnecessary as a second Christ. This is the one gospel that God authorizes (e.g., <a href="?bref=Rom.1.1-17">Rom 1:1-17</a>) and proclaims (e.g., <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.13-14">2 Thes 2:13-14</a>). <a href="?bref=Gal.2.7-9">Galatians 2:7-9</a> speaks not of two gospels but of two mission fields. Paul (the apostle to the uncircumcised) and Peter (the apostle to the circumcised) are both entrusted with “the gospel of Christ” (<a href="?bref=Gal.1.7">Gal 1:7</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-11">1 Cor 15:1-11</a>), the message that God has ordained for the salvation of Jews and Gentiles alike (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">Rom 1:16</a>). The “different gospel” that Paul denounces in <a href="?bref=Gal.1.6-9">Galatians 1:6-9</a> and <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.4">2 Corinthians 11:4</a> is not another gospel about Jesus but a message about “another Jesus”—not the real one, but one who exists only in the minds and the messages of those who proclaim him. To preach the true Christ is to preach the true gospel, however questionable one’s motives (<a href="?bref=Phil.1.15-18,27">Phil 1:15-18, 27</a>), and to respond rightly to the gospel is to turn to Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.20-21">Acts 11:20-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.10.8-17">Rom 10:8-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.14-16">Gal 2:14-16</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Gospel as a Witness to Saving Events</p>
<p class="fl">The gospel bears witness to every aspect of Christ’s saving work, from his birth (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.3">Rom 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.8">2 Tm 2:8</a>) and public ministry (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.1">Mk 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.36-38">Acts 10:36-38</a>) to his second coming (<a href="?bref=Col.1.5,23">Col 1:5, 23</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Col.3.1-4">3:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.5-10">1 Thes 1:5-10</a>) and the last judgment (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.16">Rom 2:16</a>). But it is the death and the resurrection of Christ that are most crucial for the accomplishment of salvation, and that are therefore most prominent in the gospel’s witness. These are the events with which Mark’s proclamation climaxes (chs <a href="?bref=Mark.15.1-16.20">15–16</a>), and for which everything else prepares (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.31">8:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.31">9:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.33-34">10:33-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.6-8">12:6-8</a>); special stress is placed upon Jesus’ death as the means of salvation from sin (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.45">10:45</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.3-9,22-24">14:3-9, 22-24</a>). In Paul’s gospel, too, the death and resurrection of Jesus are central (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.25">Rom 4:25</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-4">1 Cor 15:1-4</a>), with the cross occupying the very center (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.17-2.5">1 Cor 1:17–2:5</a>). Had Christ not risen from the dead, Paul argues, preaching about the cross would be a waste of time (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.14,17">1 Cor 15:14, 17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.6.3-11">Rom 6:3-11</a>). However, now that Christ has risen, his death deserves special emphasis as the place where God provides atonement for sins (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.21-26">Rom 3:21-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.6-11">5:6-11</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.14-21">2 Cor 5:14-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.7">Eph 1:7</a>). The gospel according to Acts proclaims Jesus’ death (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.25">Acts 8:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.20.24,28">20:24, 28</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.10.36-43">10:36-43</a>) and preeminently his resurrection, the event by which he conquered death and was exalted as Lord and coming Judge (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.36-43">10:36-43</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.32-33">13:32-33</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.18,31">17:18, 31</a>). According to 1 Peter, the bearers of the gospel (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.12">1 Pt 1:12</a>) concentrated, as had the OT prophets, on “the sufferings of Christ and the subsequent glory” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.11">1:11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.18-19">1:18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.21-24">2:21-24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.18-22">3:18-22</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Gospel as a Power for Salvation</p>
<p class="fl">The gospel is much more than a report of past events and an exposition of doctrine. Paul declares in <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.17-18">1 Corinthians 1:17-18</a> and again in <a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">Romans 1:16</a> that the gospel is “the power of God”—not merely a witness to his power but an <span class="ital">expression</span> of his power. Thus, it cannot be fettered (<a href="?bref=2Tim.2.8-9">2 Tm 2:8-9</a>). “Our gospel came to you not only in word, but also in power,” Paul writes in <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.5">1 Thessalonians 1:5</a>. His point is not that the gospel was accompanied by mighty works (though this happened; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.15.18-19">Rom 15:18-19</a>), but that the gospel itself is a mighty work. God makes it so through his Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.18-19">Rom 15:18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.1-5">1 Cor 2:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.6">1 Thes 1:6</a>). Furthermore, God’s singular purpose in exercising his power is to change people’s lives, to liberate them from sin and death, and to reconcile them to himself—in short, to save them. The gospel has power to effect the salvation it announces and to impart the life it promises (e.g., <a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">Rom 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.10.8-17">10:8-17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.17-18">1 Cor 1:17-18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-2">15:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.13">Eph 1:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.13-14">2 Thes 2:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.1.8-11">2 Tm 1:8-11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.23-25">1 Pt 1:23-25</a>). If people are to experience salvation, they must hear and believe the gospel. It is precisely in and through this message that the saving power manifested in the person and work of Christ (especially in his death and resurrection) is conveyed to men and made effective in their lives. Similarly it is in association with the gospel, or as a direct result of the reception of the gospel, that the Holy Spirit is imparted to believers (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.36-44">Acts 10:36-44</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.15.7-8">15:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.4">2 Cor 11:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.1-2">Gal 3:1-2</a>). In short, the gospel is the decisive place of encounter between the sinner and God the Savior.</p>
<p class="h3">The Gospel of Grace</p>
<p class="fl">According to Peter’s testimony at the Jerusalem Council (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.7-11">Acts 15:7-11</a>), an essential part of the gospel—for Gentiles and Jews alike—is salvation “through the grace of the Lord Jesus.” Toward the close of his missionary career, Paul states that his basic concern has been “to testify to the gospel of the grace of God” (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.24">Acts 20:24</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). This statement can be understood only in relation to Paul’s concept of the righteousness of God, particularly as set forth in Romans. Paul is here not merely expounding a divine attribute. Rather, he is dramatizing a divine activity—the manifestation of God’s righteousness now, “in the present time” (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.26">Rom 3:26</a>), in the new age inaugurated by Jesus' arrival. The manifestation is twofold. Viewing the two aspects together, and doing so in the light of the gospel declared by Isaiah and by Jesus (both of whom strongly influenced Paul), respectively, will help us to understand why Paul speaks of “the gospel of the grace of God.”</p>
<p>First, the gospel is a <span class="ital">witness</span> to God’s grace. In offering his Son as a sacrifice for sins (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">Rom 3:25a</a>), God demonstrates his righteousness (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.3.25-26">25b-26</a>). That is, in the death of Jesus sins formerly “passed over” (v <a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">25</a>c) become the object of God’s wrath (cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.1.18">1:18</a>) and judgment. Yet in the very place where God deals justly and decisively with sins, he shows his grace to sinners. For the judgment against sin is focused not upon the sinners themselves but upon the One appointed to act on their behalf and to stand in their place (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.25">Rom 4:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.6,11">5:6, 11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.21">2 Cor 5:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.13">Gal 3:13</a>). On this basis, sinners are freely pardoned (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.24">Rom 3:24</a>). “The grace of the Lord Jesus” (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.11">Acts 15:11</a>) toward the sinful is also in evidence, for he willingly bears their iniquities and suffers the consequences of their wrongdoing (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.20">Gal 2:20</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.8.9">2 Cor 8:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.6-8">Phil 2:6-8</a>).</p>
<p>Second, the gospel is a <span class="ital">channel</span> of God’s grace. “The righteousness of God is revealed” in the gospel, says Paul (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.17">Rom 1:17</a>). By this he means, not that the gospel talks about the righteousness of God (though it does), but that God’s righteousness is actively at work in the gospel. This activity in turn explains how the gospel becomes “the power of God for salvation” (v <a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">16</a>). And just how does God demonstrate his righteousness at this stage? In short, by bestowing it as a free gift on sinful human beings. It remains the righteousness of God, but by God’s grace, it is a righteousness in which humans may share. Furthermore, partaking of God’s righteousness depends on being personally united with Jesus Christ. In Paul’s view the saved person is one who has been acquitted, justified, “declared righteous” by God the judge. The basis for the verdict is not that I in myself am righteous (God justifies the ungodly, <a href="?bref=Rom.4.5">Rom 4:5</a>). Nor does God treat me as though I were righteous. According to Paul I am declared righteous because I really <span class="ital">am</span> righteous—not in myself but in Christ (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.30">1 Cor 1:30</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.21">2 Cor 5:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.3.9">Phil 3:9</a>). This union is established through the revelation—and the free offer—of God’s righteousness in the gospel (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.16-17">Rom 1:16-17</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Responding to the Gospel</p>
<p class="fl">The gospel calls for a threefold response:</p>
<p>1. <span class="ital">Believing.</span> The gospel, says Paul, is “the power of God for salvation to every one who has faith” (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">Rom 1:16</a>). For Paul, faith is the abandonment of all reliance upon “works of law” for justification (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.28">3:28</a>) and utter dependence upon the grace of God as demonstrated in the work of Christ, especially his death (v <a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">25</a>). Accordingly, the “different gospel” of <a href="?bref=Gal.1.6">Galatians 1:6</a> and <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.4">2 Corinthians 11:4</a> is deceitful, for it preaches salvation by personal merit rather than (or together with) the work of Christ (cf. <a href="?bref=Gal.2.16">Gal 2:16</a>). Ultimately faith rests upon God (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.24">Rom 4:24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.8-9">1 Thes 1:8-9</a>) and upon Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.22,26">Rom 3:22, 26</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.16,20">Gal 2:16, 20</a>). Yet it is imperative that one believe the gospel also (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.12">Acts 8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.11.20-21">11:20-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.15.7">15:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">Rom 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.10.8-17">10:8-17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.17-24">1 Cor 1:17-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.1.27">Phil 1:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.2">Heb 4:2</a>), for it is just by this means that God’s salvation is made known and mediated. Moreover, believing the gospel entails repentance (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.15">Acts 14:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.20.21,24">20:21, 24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.1.5-10">1 Thes 1:5-10</a>) and obedience (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.5">Rom 1:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.16-18">15:16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.6">Heb 4:6</a>). Those who refuse to obey the gospel are endangering their lives (<a href="?bref=2Thes.1.5-10">2 Thes 1:5-10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.4.17">1 Pt 4:17</a>).</p>
<p>2. <span class="ital">Growing.</span> The Gospel is more than a message to be received—it is also a place in which to stand (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-2">1 Cor 15:1-2</a>). It is sustainer of life as well as giver of life. One grows as a Christian not by turning from the gospel to other things (to turn away from the gospel is to abandon God and Christ, <a href="?bref=Gal.1.6">Gal 1:6</a>), but by going ever more deeply into the gospel. In <a href="?bref=Rom.1.15">Romans 1:15</a> Paul expresses his eagerness to proclaim the gospel to the Christians in Rome. In the following chapters, anticipating his visit, he offers one of his most profound expositions of the gospel—one whose truth has never been fathomed and whose power has never been exhausted.</p>
<p>3. <span class="ital">Hoping.</span> “The hope of the gospel” (<a href="?bref=Col.1.23">Col 1:23</a>) includes not only the return of Christ and the glory of heaven (<a href="?bref=Col.1.5">Col 1:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.1-4">3:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.14-16">2 Thes 2:14-16</a>) but the final judgment as well. For those who embrace the gospel, the last judgment holds no terrors, because the Judge is the very one who rescues them from the wrath to come (<a href="?bref=1Thes.1.10">1 Thes 1:10</a>). Those who are united to him need not dread condemnation now or at the end (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.1">Rom 8:1</a>). Instead, the last judgment will mark their final vindication (<a href="?bref=1Cor.4.5">1 Cor 4:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.5">Gal 5:5</a>). Accordingly, this theme is not just a corollary but an integral part of the Good News (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.16">Rom 2:16</a>). Those who have died since believing the gospel (<a href="?bref=1Pet.4.6">1 Pt 4:6</a>) may seem to have suffered a fate common to all people, or even the condemnation reserved for the lawless. In fact, their response to the gospel assures them of approval by the coming Lord (<a href="?bref=1Pet.4.5-6">4:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.4">5:4</a>) and of a share in the imperishable inheritance of heaven (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.4">1:4</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>