<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Grace">
  <title>Grace</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GRACE</p>
<p class="fl">The gift of God as expressed in his actions of extending mercy, loving-kindness, and salvation to people.</p>
<p>Grace is the dimension of divine activity that enables God to confront human indifference and rebellion with an inexhaustible capacity to forgive and to bless. God is gracious in action. The doctrine of divine grace underlies the thought of both the OT and NT. However, the OT merely anticipates and prepares for the full expression of grace that becomes manifest in the NT.</p>
<p class="h2" id="GraceintheOldTestament">Grace in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Early in the narrative of the OT, God reveals himself as a “God merciful and gracious, slow to anger, and abounding in steadfast love and faithfulness” (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6">Ex 34:6</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). As a result, it becomes possible for undeserving humans to approach him with the prayer, “If now I have found favor [or grace] in thy sight, O Lord, . . .” (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.9">Ex 34:9</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Through divine initiative, human separation from God is transformed into a state of unmerited acceptance that opens the way for reconciliation and redemptive usefulness.</p>
<p>Divine grace was already shown in the Garden of Eden when, instead of abandoning or punishing humanity after the fall, God responded with the promise of redemption (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Gn 3:15</a>) and solicitous care. The call to Abraham was an extension of grace, not only to him as an individual, but through him as a means of universal outreach. God’s promise to bless Abraham and his descendants indicated that these blessings would play a major role to bring a universal blessing to “all the families of the earth” (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.2-3">Gn 12:2-3</a>). Consequently, both the election of Abraham and the promise of universal blessing find expression in a God-given covenant, the object of which is to extend God’s grace to the whole human race. In a solemn confirmation of the promise to Abraham, God affirmed, “My covenant is with you, and you shall be the father of a multitude of nations. . . . And I will establish my covenant between me and you and your descendants after you throughout their generations for an everlasting covenant” (<a href="?bref=Gen.17.4,7">Gn 17:4, 7</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). This promise was to be understood as finding fulfillment on the basis of grace, not of race, so that it would become applicable to all Abraham’s offspring—not only to Jewish believers, his racial descendants, but also to his spiritual descendants, believers from all nations who profess a faith like Abraham’s (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.16">Rom 4:16</a>). Thus, from the perspective of divine grace, the election of Abraham and of national Israel was not an end in itself. It was God’s plan for extending his redemptive designs to all believers, from all nations. In extending his grace to Abraham, God was establishing the beginnings of the church, the community of grace.</p>
<p>The divine and particular way through which God chose Abraham to become the recipient of His grace serves as a model for how He selected all the individuals throughout the history of redemption. Individuals like Abraham, David, the prophets, and later the apostles received the benefits of grace through their calling. Their contributions played a significant role in fulfilling the covenant of God on behalf of the community of those who share the faith of Abraham—the church. In the gracious dealings of God with Israel, with its patriarchs and its leaders, God was laying the basis for his outreach of grace to the church universal. God’s gracious interventions in the old covenant were intended to manifest the ultimacy of the church in his redemptive purposes. In the exercise of their ministries, the prophets of the old covenant knew that they were serving not themselves but the church (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.10-12">1 Pt 1:10-12</a>).</p>
<p>As a transitional, mediatory expression of divine grace, the institutions of the old covenant possessed only a temporary validity that has been superseded by the ultimate manifestations of God’s grace in the new covenant (<a href="?bref=Heb.8.6-7">Heb 8:6-7</a>). Consequently, the old covenant was to become obsolete and replaced by a new covenant that would display the full manifestation of God’s grace. The proverbial tension between law and grace becomes intelligible in this perspective. Like the election of racial Israel, the law (as one of the most visible institutions of the old covenant) was a temporary measure of divine grace accorded to anticipate and prepare the covenant of justification through grace by faith in Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.23-29">Gal 3:23-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.1">Heb 10:1</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="GraceintheNewTestament">Grace in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The concept of grace defined as God’s active involvement on behalf of his people receives a sharper focus in the NT. Divine grace is personified in Jesus Christ, who visibly demonstrates the dynamic nature of God’s grace. Through his ministry of redemption, Jesus fulfills the old covenant promises relative to God’s gracious interactions with humanity (<a href="?bref=John.1.14,17">Jn 1:14, 17</a>).</p>
<p>God’s grace manifested in Jesus Christ makes it possible for God to forgive sinners and to gather them in the church, the new covenant community. During his ministry, Jesus repeatedly pronounced the words of forgiveness on a great number of sinners and ministered God’s benevolent aid to a variety of desperate human needs. Through teachings such as the prodigal son and the lost sheep, Jesus made it clear that he had come to seek and save those who were lost. But ultimately it was his redemptive death on the cross that opened wide the gate of salvation for repentant sinners to find access to God’s forgiving and restorative grace. This simple truth is formulated in the doctrine of justification by faith through grace (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.23">Rom 3:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.7">Ti 3:7</a>). According to this teaching, God’s gracious provision of the substitutionary death of Christ enables him to pronounce a verdict of “just” or “not guilty” on repentant sinners and to include them in his eternal purposes. As a result, they enter into the realm of God’s gracious activity, which enables them to implement the process of individual sanctification in cooperation with the Holy Spirit.</p>
<p>God’s grace manifested in Jesus Christ also makes it possible for God to bestow on believers undeserved benefits that enrich their lives and unite them together in the church, the body of Christ. Their acceptance on the basis of grace endows them with a new status as children of God, members of the household of God, so that they relate to him as to their heavenly Father (<a href="?bref=Gal.4.4-6">Gal 4:4-6</a>). Consequently, they become members of a community where race, class, and sex distinctions are irrelevant, since they all became equal inheritors of God’s age-long promise to Abraham of universal blessing (<a href="?bref=Gal.3.28-29">3:28-29</a>). In order to enrich their individual lives and to assure the usefulness of their participation in the life of the new community, the Holy Spirit graciously energizes believers with a variety of gifts for the performance of ministries designed to benefit the church (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.6-8">Rom 12:6-8</a>). Foremost among those ministries is that of apostle, itself closely linked to God’s gracious provision (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.5">1:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.15-16">15:15-16</a>) since it combines with the ministry of the prophets of old to provide the foundational structure of the church (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.20">Eph 2:20</a>). Because the riches of divine grace are freely lavished upon believers in their community life upon earth (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.7-8">1:7-8</a>), the church translated into eternity will demonstrate, by its very existence, the immeasurable riches of God’s grace in Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.6">2:6</a>).</p>
<p>Finally, God’s grace manifested in Jesus Christ makes it possible for God to cause believers to reflect his grace in their character and relationships. The irreducible condition for receiving God’s grace is humility (<a href="?bref=Jas.4.6">Jas 4:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.5">1 Pt 5:5</a>). Such humility in relation to God enables believers to practice humility in regard to other people. From a position of grace, they can set aside selfishness and conceit in order to treat others with deference (<a href="?bref=Phil.2.3-4">Phil 2:3-4</a>) in an attitude of mutual servanthood (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.21">Eph 5:21</a>), and in a spirit of mutual forgiveness (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.23-35">Mt 18:23-35</a>) so that even their communication can exhibit divine grace (<a href="?bref=Col.4.6">Col 4:6</a>). Since the grace of Jesus Christ constitutes the existential context of the lives and relationships of believers, they are exhorted not to pervert the grace of God into ungodly practice (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.4">Jude 1:4</a>) but instead to grow in the grace of the Lord (<a href="?bref=2Pet.3.18">2 Pt 3:18</a>).</p>
<p>The essential meaning of grace in the Bible refers to God’s disposition to exercise goodwill toward his creatures. This favorable disposition of God finds its supreme expression in Jesus Christ. By its very definition, this grace is rendered fully accessible to all humans with no other precondition than a repentant desire to receive it (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.11-12">Ti 2:11-12</a>). As a result, the human condition of alienation from God and from his purposes becomes replaced with access to the otherwise unapproachable majesty of God represented by a throne, so that his grace may become available to meet human need (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.16">Heb 4:16</a>). The tragic alternative to receiving God’s grace is to remain in hopeless alienation or to pursue sterile attempts to merit God’s favor through human efforts doomed to futility (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.21">Rom 1:21</a>). God unconditionally accepts sinners, and the only condition that may affect this acceptance is if they themselves reject it.</p>
<p>Because Christ represents the fulfillment, the embodiment, and the dispenser of divine grace, the early Christians freely referred to God’s grace as “the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ.” They considered this grace to be basic and pervasive to their individual lives and to the existence of their communities of faith, so they naturally coupled the traditional greeting of <span class="hebrew">shalom</span> (“peace”) with a reference to the grace of Jesus Christ. This is why almost every book of the NT uses a variation of the same basic greeting formula, “The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all” (<a href="?bref=2Thes.3.18">2 Thes 3:18</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=GodBeingandAttributesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Being and Attributes of</a>; <a href="?item=Love_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Love</a>; <a href="?item=Mercy_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mercy</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>