<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GadTribeof">
  <title>Gad, Tribe of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GAD, Tribe of</p>
<p class="fl">Descendants of Jacob’s seventh son Gad (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.11">Gn 30:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.1.24-25">Nm 1:24-25</a>), and eighth largest of the 12 tribes that came out of Egypt with Moses (according to the number of warriors in <a href="?bref=Num.1.1-3,24-25">Nm 1:1-3, 24-25</a>). They raised livestock and had a reputation for being fierce in battle (<a href="?bref=Num.32.1">Nm 32:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.33.20">Dt 33:20</a>).</p>
<p>During the wilderness period, they were led by Eliasaph’s son Deuel (<a href="?bref=Num.1.14">Nm 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.2.14">2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.7.42">7:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.10.20">10:20</a>). When Israel encamped, Gad was located south of the tabernacle behind the tribes of Reuben and Simeon (<a href="?bref=Num.2.14-15">2:14-15</a>). They are mentioned at the tribal offering to the tabernacle, and after the plague, which God brought upon Israel (<a href="?bref=Num.7.42-47">7:42-47</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.15,18">26:15, 18</a>). Maki’s son Geuel represented the tribe as one of the 12 spies sent by Moses into Canaan (<a href="?bref=Num.13.15">13:15</a>).</p>
<p>At the close of the wilderness period, Gad, Reuben, and half of Manasseh’s tribe requested permission to settle east of the Jordan, for it had good pastureland (<a href="?bref=Num.32.1-2">Nm 32:1-2</a>). This was permitted on the condition that they would help in the conquest of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Num.32.20-22">Nm 32:20-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.1.12-18">Jos 1:12-18</a>).</p>
<p>During the Conquest under Joshua, Gad is mentioned only at the battle of Jericho (<a href="?bref=Josh.4.12">Jos 4:12</a>). After the end of the conflict, Gad, Reuben, and half of Manasseh settled their land east of the Jordan (cf. <a href="?bref=Num.34.13-14">Nm 34:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.6">Jos 12:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.13.8">13:8</a>).</p>
<p>Gad’s inheritance was between Manasseh’s tribe to the north and Reuben’s to the south. The Arabian Desert formed its eastern border and the Jordan River its western. There seem to have been no fixed borders between the two and a half tribes, and the whole area was often referred to as Gilead and Bashan (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.33">2 Kgs 10:33</a>). Its land ran north to the Sea of Chinnereth (Galilee), but among the mountains it seems to have run eastward only as far as the Jabbok River. To the south, the cities of Aroer and Heshbon mark their southern limits (<a href="?bref=Deut.3.12-13">Dt 3:12-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.1-6">Jos 12:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.13.24-28">13:24-28</a>).</p>
<p>The history of Gad from its settlement to the Captivity was closely tied with the two neighboring Hebrew tribes. Shortly after returning to their lands, these two and a half tribes almost started a civil war by erecting a large altar (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.10-34">Jos 22:10-34</a>). During the time of the judges, Gilead (including Gad) was threatened, if not occupied, by the Ammonites until they were defeated by Jephthah (Jgs 11). Some Gadites joined David at Ziklag during his exile (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.14,37">1 Chr 12:14, 37</a>). In the 14th year of David’s reign the two and a half tribes were formally brought together under an overseer named Jerijah (and his brothers, <a href="?bref=1Chr.26.30-32">26:30-32</a>).</p>
<p>During the time of the divided kingdom, the tribes east of the Jordan were constantly under attack. During Jehu’s reign (841–814 <span class="era">BC</span>), Hazael annexed all the land east of the Jordan, and they were later carried off into captivity by Tiglath-pileser, king of Assyria (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.29">2 Kgs 15:29</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.5.26-27">1 Chr 5:26-27</a>). Subsequently, the Ammonites occupied Gad’s land (<a href="?bref=Jer.49.1">Jer 49:1</a>).</p>
<p>In the postexilic period Gad is mentioned only once—in Ezekiel’s vision of the restoration of Israel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.48.1,27-28,34">Ez 48:1, 27-28, 34</a>). In the NT, Gad is mentioned only in the book of Revelation, in the list of the tribes sealed by God (<a href="?bref=Rev.7.5">Rv 7:5</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=GadPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Gad (Person) #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>