<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gath">
  <title>Gath</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GATH</p>
<p class="fl">Walled city (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.6">2 Chr 26:6</a>) and one of the five chief cities of the Philistines, which also included Gaza, Ashdod, Ashkelon, and Ekron (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.3">Jos 13:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.6.17">1 Sm 6:17</a>), all situated on or near the southern coast of Palestine. Although frequently involved in conflict with the Israelites, the city was apparently not subdued until David’s time (<a href="?bref=1Chr.18.1">1 Chr 18:1</a>). It was a Canaanite city, the home of the giant Goliath (<a href="?bref=1Sam.17.4">1 Sm 17:4</a>) and other men of great height (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.18-22">2 Sm 21:18-22</a>). A remnant of the Anakim was left, even after the extensive campaigns of Joshua (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.36-39">Jos 10:36-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.11.21-22">11:21-22</a>).</p>
<p>When the Philistines captured the ark of God, they carried it from Ebenezer to Ashdod, from there to Gath (<a href="?bref=1Sam.5.8">1 Sm 5:8</a>), and then to Ekron. After many of the Philistines died or were stricken with tumors, the ark was returned to Israel, first to Beth-shemesh and then to Kiriath-jearim (<a href="?bref=1Sam.6.14">6:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.7.1">7:1</a>). When David fled from Saul, he came to Gath and feigned madness before Achish, the king of the city (<a href="?bref=1Sam.21.10-15">21:10-15</a>). During the rebellion of Absalom, 600 Gittites served among David’s mercenaries (<a href="?bref=2Sam.15.18">2 Sm 15:18</a>). According to <a href="?bref=2Chr.11.8">2 Chronicles 11:8</a>, Rehoboam fortified the city of Gath, and <a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.17">2 Kings 12:17</a> relates that it was taken by Hazael, king of Syria, in the ninth century. But it was apparently again in Philistine control when Uzziah broke down its walls (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.6">2 Chr 26:6</a>). The city disappeared after being besieged and conquered by Sargon II in the eighth century <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=Amos.6.2">Am 6:2</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PhilistiaPhilistines_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Philistia, Philistines</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>