<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gedaliah">
  <title>Gedaliah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GEDALIAH</p>
<p class="list">1. Ahikam’s son, and grandson of Shaphan (King Josiah’s royal scribe). In 586 <span class="era">BC</span> Nebuchadnezzar, the Babylonian king, appointed Gedaliah as governor over the Jews remaining in Israel to work the fields, vineyards, and orchards (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.12,22">2 Kgs 25:12, 22</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Gedaliah established his headquarters at Mizpah, where he was joined by the prophet Jeremiah and the Jewish commanders and their guerrilla forces who had escaped capture during the fall of Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.6-8">Jer 40:6-8</a>). Gedaliah assured them that if they would settle down and live in peaceful subjection to Babylon, all would be well (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.23-24">2 Kgs 25:23-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.40.9-10">Jer 40:9-10</a>). On the basis of that assurance, many of the Jews who were dispersed in the Transjordan and other countries returned to Israel to work the land into great productivity (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.11-12">Jer 40:11-12</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Though warned about a plot against him by Ishmael, Gedaliah entertained the schemer at a meal and was killed (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.25">2 Kgs 25:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.40.11-12">Jer 40:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.41.1-3">41:1-3</a>). Along with some pilgrims visiting the temple, Ishmael fled with hostages to Ammon, escaping the vengeance of Johanan (<a href="?bref=Jer.41.10-15">Jer 41:10-15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Temple musician in the time of King David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.25.3,9">1 Chr 25:3, 9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Jeshua’s son and one called to divorce his foreign wife during Ezra’s reforms (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.18">Ezr 10:18</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Pashhur’s son and one of the Jerusalem officials who urged King Zedekiah to put the prophet Jeremiah to death for his pro-Babylonian prophetic pronouncements (<a href="?bref=Jer.38.1">Jer 38:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Amariah’s son, grandson of King Hezekiah, and grandfather of the prophet Zephaniah (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.1">Zep 1:1</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>