<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GenesisBookof">
  <title>Genesis, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GENESIS, Book of</p>
<p class="fl">First book of the Bible.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Name">Name</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Date">Date</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Purpose">Purpose</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Structure">Structure</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Name">Name</p>
<p class="fl">The name Genesis comes into English as a transliteration of the Greek word meaning “origin” or “beginning.” This name was given to the book in the Greek translation of the Hebrew Scriptures, known as the Septuagint. Genesis reflects both the content of the book and the Hebrew name for it, which is taken from its first word, <span class="hebrew">bere’shith</span><span class="ital">,</span> “in the beginning.”</p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">The authorship of Genesis is closely related to the authorship of the entire Pentateuch (lit. “five-volumed,” the first five books of the Bible, which in Hebrew are called the Torah). It is clear that the Bible regards the human author of these books as Moses. On several occasions the Lord commanded Moses to write down various things: “in a book” (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.14">Ex 17:14</a>) “write these words” (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.27">34:27</a>). The Pentateuch reports that “Moses wrote all the words of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (<a href="?bref=Exod.24.4">24:4</a>); he wrote the itinerary of the exodus wanderings (<a href="?bref=Num.33.2">Nm 33:2</a>); “Moses wrote this law” (<a href="?bref=Deut.31.9">Dt 31:9</a>). (Here it is not certain that all five books are meant, but it must refer to at least the greater part of Deuteronomy.) In <a href="?bref=Exod.24.7">Exodus 24:7</a> it is said that Moses read the Book of the Covenant, which he must have just completed.</p>
<p>The rest of the OT bears witness to the writing of the Pentateuch by Moses. David referred to “the law of Moses” (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.3">1 Kgs 2:3</a>). In the time of Josiah, there was found in the temple the “Book of the Law of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> . . . given through Moses” (<a href="?bref=2Chr.34.14">2 Chr 34:14</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Day by day Ezra read from “the Book of the Law of God” (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.18">Neh 8:18</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>In the NT, Jesus refers to “the book of Moses” (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.26">Mk 12:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.37">Lk 20:37</a>) and otherwise mentions the commands or statements of Moses (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.4">Mt 8:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.19.8">19:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.7.10">Mk 7:10</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.16.31">Lk 16:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.24.44">24:44</a>). The Jews also quoted from the Torah as coming from Moses, and Jesus did not contradict them.</p>
<p>Of Genesis in particular, it may be said that Moses had the opportunity and ability to write the book. He could have written it during his years in Egypt or while exiled with the Kenites. As the recognized leader of the Israelites, he would have had access to, or perhaps even custody of, the records that Jacob brought from Canaan. He was “instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians” (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.22">Acts 7:22</a>) and probably could have written in several languages and in several scripts (hieroglyphic, cuneiform, Old Hebrew). Although Moses was admirably fitted for the task of writing, one must remember that he was not putting together a human composition but was writing under the inspiration of God (<a href="?bref=2Pet.1.21">2 Pt 1:21</a>). We may with confidence conclude that Moses was the human author of Genesis.</p>
<p>The liberal view of the authorship of Genesis is that the book is an editorial composite—a view first put forward by a French physician, Jean Astruc, who suggested that the different names for God indicated different documents or sources for the writing of the book. The German higher critics expanded the view of the use of documents in the writing of Genesis and developed it into the Graf-Wellhausen-Kuenen, or Documentary, Hypothesis, which may also be called the JEDP theory of the authorship of the book. This view holds that there were four basic documents: (1) J, which uses the name YHWH (Jehovah or Yahweh) for God, dates from about the ninth century <span class="era">BC</span> and comes from Judah; (2) E uses the name Elohim, dates from the eighth century, and comes from the northern kingdom; (3) D is Deuteronomy and is supposed to come from the time of Josiah, about 621 <span class="era">BC</span>; and (4) P is the priestly element, which deals with matters of the priesthood and ritual, dating to the fifth century <span class="era">BC</span> or later. Some may date portions of Genesis as late as the Hellenistic period. According to this theory, the various documents were blended together by editors, so that there was a JE, JED, and so on.</p>
<p>The science of archaeology discredited many of the extreme postulations of these critics, and the work of W. F. Albright and his followers did much to restore confidence in the historicity of Genesis. Within the last several decades, the patriarchal narratives and the account of Joseph have again come under strong attack, but these views are extreme, and much of the evidence adduced by Albright and earlier scholars like R. D. Wilson, W. H. Green, and others still has validity.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Date">Date</p>
<p class="fl">The date of the book is also a matter of debate. Even among those who accept Mosaic authorship there is debate as to when Moses lived. Based on the biblical data, Moses should have lived in the 15th century <span class="era">BC</span> (cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.11.26">Jgs 11:26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.1">1 Kgs 6:1</a>), but many scholars incline toward a 13th-century date. As outlined above, the liberal view of the date of Genesis would be from the ninth to the fifth centuries <span class="era">BC</span>, with the final editing coming around the fifth century or perhaps even later.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Purpose">Purpose</p>
<p class="fl">Genesis sketches the origin of many things: the universe, the earth, plants, animals, and mankind. It gives the beginnings of human institutions, professions, and crafts. It describes the origin of sin and death, and illustrates the insidious working of Satan in human life. Above all, Genesis relates the beginning of the history of redemption with the announcement of a Redeemer who was to come (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Gn 3:15</a>). It names the early progenitors in the lineage of the Messiah and the beginning of the Hebrew people through whom the Bible and the Savior came. Genesis also gives a selective history of people and events as viewed from the perspective of the purposes of God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Structure">Structure</p>
<p class="fl">The book is divided into 11 parts of uneven length, each set off by the expression “these are the generations [descendants, history] of” (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.4">2:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.5.1">5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.6.9">6:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.10.1">10:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.11.10,27">11:10, 27</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.25.12,19">25:12, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.36.1">36:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.37.2">37:2</a>). Only three times does the formula coincide with the first verse of a chapter. Usually called a heading or superscription, the expression serves as a kind of link between what precedes and what follows.</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="KeyPlacesinGenesis"/>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">The Creation (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-2.25">1:1–2:25</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">These two chapters have been a scientific-theological battleground for many years, as researchers and students have tried to probe the origins of the universe and of life. Much of the evidence is not subject to scientific scrutiny, for science by definition requires that the evidence must be reproducible by experiment.</p>
<p>The statement of <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1">Genesis 1:1</a> remains the grandest, most precise, and most accurate statement of origins: “In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth.” He did this <span class="ital">ex nihilo</span> (“out of nothing”) by his word (<a href="?bref=Heb.11.3">Heb 11:3</a>); he spoke the word of command and it was done (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.3,6,9,11,14,20">Gn 1:3, 6, 9, 11, 14, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.33.6,9">Ps 33:6, 9</a>).</p>
<p>The date of the beginning is unknown. Uniformitarian cosmogonists (students of the origins of the universe who believe that natural events have always followed a uniform pattern; cf. <a href="?bref=2Pet.3.3-7">2 Pt 3:3-7</a>) have speculated that the beginning of the universe was billions of years ago. But some creationists posit a world thousands of years old.</p>
<p>To accommodate geological ages and the existence of extinct animals, some interpreters have proposed a gap between <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1">Genesis 1:1</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.1.2">1:2</a>, with <a href="?bref=Gen.1.2-2.3">Genesis 1:2–2:3</a> representing a second or new creation. But this is conjecture. So is the idea that each day represents a geological age.</p>
<p>As the text stands, there is a correlation between the first three days and the second three days. Day one saw the creation of light; day four, the light bearers. Day two was the time of the creation of the firmament (better, “expanse”), which divided the waters; day five, birds and swarming water creatures. On day three, God made the dry land and plants; on day six he created the land animals and man. He made man in the image of God (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.26">Gn 1:26</a>), “a little less than God” (<a href="?bref=Ps.8.5">Ps 8:5</a>), and gave him dominion over the earth. He made everything “according to their kinds,” so that each kind is distinct and unique. The perfection of his work is affirmed in that “God saw that it was good” (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.4,10,12,18,21">Gn 1:4, 10, 12, 18, 21</a>; “very good,” v <a href="?bref=Gen.1.31">31</a>). The seventh day was a time of cessation from the activity of creating and served as a type for mankind’s day of rest (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.1-3">2:1-3</a>).</p>
<p>Critical scholarship eyes <a href="?bref=Gen.2.4-25">2:4-25</a> as a doublet in conflict with <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-2.3">Genesis 1:1–2:3</a>. To conservative scholars, the second chapter is the same account from a different perspective. Chapter <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">1</a> gives the Creation from the standpoint of sequence; chapter <a href="?bref=Gen.2.1-25">2</a> shows it in view of the centrality of mankind in God’s creative work.</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Gen.2.1-25">2</a> gives details of the creation of man of “dust from the ground” (v <a href="?bref=Gen.2.7">7</a>) and woman from a rib of the man (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.2.21-22">21-22</a>). She was created to be “a companion who will help him” (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.2.18-20">18-20</a>). They were created as mature adults, with the gift of speech and with great intelligence. Adam had imagination and vocabulary sufficient for naming all of the animal species (v <a href="?bref=Gen.2.19">19</a>).</p>
<p>The location of the Garden of Eden is given (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.2.10-14">10-14</a>). Two of the four rivers, the Tigris and the Euphrates, can be identified with certainty. So man lived in this beautiful garden in the bliss of innocence.</p>
<p class="h3">The History of Humankind from Eden to Babel (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.1-11.26">3:1–11:26</a>)</p>
<p class="h4">The Fall</p>
<p class="fl">The loss of Eden and the break in fellowship with God is the saddest chapter in human history. The serpent, the devil, approached Eve with the same philosophy he always uses: doubt of God’s word (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.1">Gn 3:1</a>), denial of death (v <a href="?bref=Gen.3.4">4</a>), and the suggestion of equality with God (v <a href="?bref=Gen.3.5">5</a>). He gained access to her will by deceiving her with the promise that the fruit would make her as wise as God is (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.5">Gn 3:5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.16">1 Jn 2:16</a>). Eve was deceived, but when she offered the fruit to Adam, he took it willingly, knowing what he was doing (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.6">Gn 3:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Tim.2.14">1 Tm 2:14</a>). Later, he tried to blame God for giving him the wife who gave him the fruit (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.12">Gn 3:12</a>). Fellowship with God was broken (v <a href="?bref=Gen.3.8">8</a>), yet God came seeking Adam and found him.</p>
<p>With sin came judgment, and the Lord pronounced righteous judgment on the serpent, the woman, and the man. The earth was also “subjected to frustration” and now groans as it awaits renewal (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.21-22">Rom 8:21-22</a>). God gave hope to man and a promise of a Redeemer (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.15">Gn 3:15</a>), who was to bruise the serpent’s head. Adam and Eve were forced out of the Garden, and it was made inaccessible to them.</p>
<p>The impatience of humankind is shown in Eve’s expectation that her son Cain was the promised Deliverer. Instead, he developed a wrong-hearted attitude toward God and became so jealous of his younger brother that he murdered him. Apprehended by God and confronted with his crime, Cain showed only self-pity and went east from Eden, where he built a city (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.1-16">4:1-16</a>). Chapter <a href="?bref=Gen.4.1-26">4</a> closes with another contrast: the brazen Lamech, who called for vengeance, while others began to call upon the name of the Lord.</p>
<p class="h4">The Generations of Adam</p>
<p class="fl">This genealogical table (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.1-32">5:1-32</a>) brings humankind to the time of Noah and the Flood. The longevity of the antediluvian patriarchs seems very striking to us, but one must remember that the earth had not yet been subjected to pollution and that the effects of sin on the human race were still nominal. The refrain “and he died” reminds us of man’s mortality. For Enoch, however, there was something better: “He enjoyed a close relationship with God throughout his life. Then, suddenly, he disappeared because God took him” (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.24">5:24</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p class="h4">The Flood</p>
<p class="fl">With increased population came an eruption of sin (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.1-5">6:1-5</a>). As men multiplied, so did their corruption. The universal condemnation of verse <a href="?bref=Gen.6.5">5</a> shows a world ripe for judgment. Noah, however, “found favor with the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,” for he was a righteous and blameless man who walked with God (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.8-9">6:8-9</a>).</p>
<p>The Lord planned to annihilate the human race, but he determined to save Noah and his family. Intending to flood the earth, God instructed Noah to build an ark. Noah was directed to take animals aboard the ark, two by two, male and female, for the preservation of each species. When all was in readiness, the Flood came: “the underground waters burst forth on the earth, and the rain fell in mighty torrents from the sky” (<a href="?bref=Gen.7.11">7:11</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). It rained for 40 days and 40 nights. The highest mountains were covered, and life outside the ark perished. “But God remembered Noah” and sent a wind to evaporate the waters (<a href="?bref=Gen.8.1">8:1</a>). Eventually the ark came to rest on the mountains of Ararat (v <a href="?bref=Gen.8.4">4</a>). Noah made a sacrifice to the Lord, and the Lord determined that he would never again bring such destruction upon the earth.</p>
<p>The Flood is another of God’s acts that has been much debated. Many have argued for a local flood, which affected only part of Mesopotamia. Archaeologists have pointed to various flood strata in the excavation of Mesopotamian city-mounds as evidence for the account of the flood and have cited the various flood stories from that area as the source of the Genesis record. The epic of Gilgamesh gives an interesting tale of this hero, who went on a mission to visit Utnapishtim, the cuneiform Noah, in quest of eternal life. The flood story told by Utnapishtim has many parallels to Genesis, but there are greater contrasts, which demonstrate that the Bible preserves the true account.</p>
<p>Both the Genesis account and the references to it in the NT (cf. <a href="?bref=2Pet.3.6">2 Pt 3:6</a>) favor the view that the deluge was not a minor episode in the Tigris-Euphrates area but was an unprecedented worldwide catastrophe. Christian geologists affirm that the Flood had far-reaching effects on the earth itself. Flood stories are almost universally known, lending support to the conclusion that the Flood covered the whole earth. Following the Flood, God blessed Noah and his sons, Ham, Shem, and Japheth. God made a covenant with Noah, promising that he would never again send a worldwide flood. As a sign of this, he established the rainbow.</p>
<p>Noah was the first tiller of the soil, and he planted a vineyard (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.20">9:20</a>). Noah became drunk from wine he made and lay uncovered in his tent. Ham saw him and reported this to his brothers, who discreetly covered him. Ham and his son Canaan were cursed; Shem and Japheth were blessed.</p>
<p class="h4">The History of the Nations</p>
<p class="fl">“This is the history of the families of Shem, Ham, and Japheth, the three sons of Noah. Many children were born to them after the Flood” (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.1">10:1</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). This chapter lists the descendants of Noah’s three sons, in the order of Japheth (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.10.2-5">2-5</a>), Ham (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.10.6-20">6-20</a>), and Shem (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.10.21-31">21-31</a>). Many of the names of their descendants are preserved in tribes and nations of the world.</p>
<p class="h4">The Tower of Babel</p>
<p class="fl">The building of the Tower of Babel (“Gate of God”) illustrates man’s perversity and his tendency to want independence from God. The desire of man to displace God follows the fateful example of Lucifer and is a basic tenet of many cults. God thwarted the designs of the builders of Babel by confusing their languages, so that the project came to a halt (<a href="?bref=Gen.11.1-9">11:1-9</a>). The site of this tower is not known with certainty. Some associate it with Birs Nimrud, not far from the ruins of the city of Babylon. <a href="?bref=Gen.11.10-25">Genesis 11:10-25</a> picks up the line of Shem and carries it down to Terah, the father of Abram.</p>
<p class="h3">The History of Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.11.27-25.10">11:27–25:10</a>) and Isaac (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.1-28.5">21:1–28:5</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Abram came from Ur of the Chaldees, a prosperous city. The city had an imposing ziggurat (temple-tower), with many temples, storehouses, and residences. Abram and Sarai, his half sister and wife, went with his father to Haran in Syria, which like Ur was a center of the worship of the moon god, Sin (or Annar).</p>
<p class="h4">Abram’s Call</p>
<p class="fl">The call of God came to Abram directing him to leave his relatives and move to a land that the Lord would show him (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.1">12:1</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.7.2-3">Acts 7:2-3</a>). Abram obeyed. At the age of 75, he, Sarai, and his nephew Lot left Haran and went to Shechem, where the Lord appeared to him and promised that land to his descendants.</p>
<p>Famine drove Abram down to Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.10-20">Gn 12:10-20</a>). Because of Sarai’s beauty, he feared that someone might kill him to get her, so he passed her off as his sister. She was taken into the pharaoh’s harem. When the Lord plagued Pharaoh because of this, Abram’s lie was discovered and Sarai was returned to him.</p>
<p class="h4">Abram and Lot</p>
<p class="fl">Abram and Lot returned to Canaan, where strife broke out between Abram’s herdsmen and those of Lot. Abram suggested that they should separate, and he gave Lot the choice of territory. Lot chose the well-watered Jordan Valley and the cities of the plain, Sodom and Gomorrah (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.13.1-18">13</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">The Invasion of the Four Kings from the East</p>
<p class="fl">The four kings who invaded along the King’s Highway in Transjordan cannot be identified with certainty. Those kings were successful in their attack against the five cities of the plain, and they moved off with much booty and many captives, including Lot. Abram took 318 retainers, born in his household, and set off after them. By surprise attack, Abram recovered both Lot and the loot. On his return he was met by Melchizedek, king of Jerusalem, to whom Abram paid tithes (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.14.1-24">14</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">The Covenant</p>
<p class="fl">The Lord promised Abram a son as heir, and in an impressive nighttime ceremony, God made a covenant with Abram and promised him the land from the River of Egypt (Wadi el Arish) to the Euphrates (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.15.1-21">15</a>). Because of her own barrenness, Sarai gave her Egyptian maid, Hagar, to Abram. Hagar gave birth to Ishmael, the progenitor of the Arab peoples. When trouble arose between the women, Sarai sent Hagar away, which was her right according to Near Eastern customs (as illustrated by the Nuzi tablets). God showed mercy to Hagar and promised that she would have a great posterity (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.16.1-16">16</a>).</p>
<p>God repeated his promise to Abram concerning his descendants and changed the names of Abram (“exalted father”) and Sarai to Abraham (“father of many”) and Sarah (“princess”). A covenant sign of circumcision was given to Abraham (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.17.1-27">17</a>). This operation had already been practiced among the Egyptians for several centuries.</p>
<p class="h4">The Destruction of the Cities of the Plain</p>
<p class="fl">The Lord and two angels appeared to Abraham and announced the birth of the promised heir within a year, as well as proclaimed the impending destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah, concerning which Abraham bargained with God (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.22-33">18:22-33</a>). Lot and his immediate family were rescued from Sodom, and the cities were destroyed by God with brimstone and fire (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.24-25">19:24-25</a>). Lot’s two daughters, wishing to preserve their family line, got their father drunk and had sexual relations with him. Moab and Ammon, enemies of Israel in later times, were the result.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Gen.20.1-18">Genesis 20:1-18</a>, Abraham again represented Sarah as his sister and got into trouble with Abimelech, king of Gerar.</p>
<p class="h4">Isaac</p>
<p class="fl">When Isaac was born (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.1-3">21:1-3</a>), trouble again broke out between Sarah and Hagar. Hagar was driven out a second time, and once more was befriended by the Lord.</p>
<p>A disagreement arose between Abraham and Abimelech concerning a well, but they made a covenant of peace at Beersheba (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.25-34">21:25-34</a>).</p>
<p>God tested Abraham’s faith by asking him to sacrifice Isaac on Mt Moriah, which probably is the same site David later bought from Araunah the Jebusite (<a href="?bref=2Sam.24.16-25">2 Sm 24:16-25</a>), the place where the temple was to stand. As Abraham was about to use the knife, God called to him and showed him a ram caught in a thicket. Isaac was freed and the animal was sacrificed in his stead.</p>
<p>Sarah died at Hebron, and Abraham purchased the cave of Machpelah as a burial place from Ephron the Hittite (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.23.1-20">23</a>), in a transaction typical of Near Eastern business dealings. To find a wife for Isaac, Abraham sent his servant Eliezer back to the area of Haran, and the Lord directed Eliezer to Rebekah (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.24.1-67">24</a>).</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Gen.25.1-34">25</a> records the marriage of Abraham to Keturah, who bore him a number of children. Abraham died at the age of 175 years and was buried in the cave of Machpelah by his two sons, Isaac and Ishmael.</p>
<p class="h3">The History of Jacob and Esau (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.19-37.1">25:19–37:1</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Rebekah gave birth to twin sons, Esau and Jacob. When the boys were grown, Esau sold his birthright to Jacob for a meal of red pottage (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.27-34">25:27-34</a>).</p>
<p>When famine came to the land, Isaac went to Gerar, as his father had done (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.20.1-18">20</a>), and repeated his father’s lie by calling his wife his sister (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.1-11">26:1-11</a>). Trouble arose with the Philistines over wells, but Isaac was a peaceable man and preferred digging new wells rather than fighting over old ones (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.26.17-33">17-33</a>).</p>
<p>In Isaac’s old age, when his sight had failed, Rebekah connived with Jacob to trick Isaac into giving to Jacob the blessing of the firstborn, which was rightfully Esau’s. This oral blessing had legal validity and was irrevocable, according to the ancient Nuzi tablets. Fearing for Jacob’s life at the hands of Esau, Rebekah arranged to send Jacob to Haran to find a wife from among her own people. At Bethel, God appeared to Jacob in a dream of a ladder leading up to heaven; God renewed with Jacob the promise made to Abraham and Isaac (<a href="?bref=Gen.28.10-22">28:10-22</a>).</p>
<p>Jacob reached Haran, found his uncle Laban, and was employed by him (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.29.1-35">29</a>). His wages for seven years of labor were to be Laban’s younger daughter, Rachel, as his wife. But Laban substituted Leah, so that Jacob had to work another seven years for Rachel. The Lord prospered Jacob, but he continually had difficulties with Laban. The Lord directed Jacob back to Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.31.3">31:3</a>), so he left secretly with his wives, children, and property. Laban pursued them because his household gods were missing (possession of these “gods” made the holder heir to the owner’s estate, according to Nuzi custom). Rachel had taken them but successfully concealed them from her father, and Laban went back to Haran.</p>
<p>Fearing a meeting with Esau as they passed through Edom, Jacob sent gifts to his brother and divided his own party into two camps for security. On this return journey, Jacob had an unexpected wrestling bout with the Angel of the Lord, and he was left with a limp and a new name, Israel (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.32.1-32">32</a>).</p>
<p>The meeting with Esau was friendly, and Jacob went on to Shechem (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.33.1-20">33</a>), where his sons killed the male Shechemites because of the rape of their sister Dinah (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.34.1-31">34</a>). God told Jacob to go to Bethel and build an altar to the Lord. All idols of foreign gods were buried (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.1-4">35:1-4</a>). At Bethel, God reaffirmed his promise of a posterity and the land (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.35.9-15">9-15</a>). Rachel died on the way to Bethlehem, while giving birth to Benjamin, Jacob’s 12th and last son. Isaac died at Hebron at age 180 and was buried in the cave of Machpelah by Esau and Jacob.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Gen.36.1-43">Genesis 36</a> records “the generations of Esau” (v <a href="?bref=Gen.36.1">1</a>). Here Esau is also named Edom (“Red”; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.25.30">25:30</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The History of Joseph (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.2-50.26">37:2–50:26</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Joseph was Jacob’s favorite son and thus incurred the jealousy of his brothers. This was heightened by Joseph’s dreams of lordship over them. Their resentment of Joseph came to a climax when Jacob gave Joseph a beautiful coat. The brothers determined to kill Joseph, but they compromised by selling him to a caravan of merchants, who took him to Egypt and sold him as a slave to Potiphar, an Egyptian captain of the guard (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.36">37:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.39.1">39:1</a>).</p>
<p>Chapter <a href="?bref=Gen.38.1-30">38</a> relates a historic case of levirate marriage. Judah failed to give his widowed daughter-in-law to his third son. She deceived him into fathering twin sons and forced him to acknowledge his faults. The elder son, Perez, is named in Luke’s genealogy of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.33">Lk 3:33</a>).</p>
<p>The Lord blessed Joseph, who soon was put in charge of Potiphar’s household (<a href="?bref=Gen.39.1-23">Gn 39</a>). The young man attracted the attention of Potiphar’s wife, who, after many attempts to seduce him, at last accused him of attempted rape. Sentenced on this charge, Joseph met with favor in prison, where he had opportunity to interpret dreams for two of the pharaoh’s servants (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.40.1-23">40</a>). When the king had dreams that his magicians and wise men could not interpret, Joseph was summoned from jail. Joseph told Pharaoh that the dreams meant seven years of plenty, followed by seven years of famine. Joseph was then exalted to the office of vizier, or prime minister, second only to the king, and put in charge of the administration of the land (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.37-44">41:37-44</a>).</p>
<p>When the famine came to Palestine, Jacob sent his sons to Egypt to purchase grain. Joseph recognized his brothers but did not reveal his identity to them. Joseph put them to the test by accusing them of being spies (<a href="?bref=Gen.42.9">42:9</a>), by keeping one of the brothers (Simeon) hostage (v <a href="?bref=Gen.42.19">19</a>), and by demanding that if they came to Egypt again, they must bring their youngest brother with them (<a href="?bref=Gen.42.20">42:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.43.3">43:3</a>). The famine became so severe in Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.43.1">43:1</a>) that Jacob at last allowed Benjamin to go with his brothers to Egypt. The brothers were again set up by Joseph, who had his silver cup put into Benjamin’s grain sack and then had him apprehended as a thief (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.44.1-34">44</a>).</p>
<p>At this point Joseph revealed his identity to his brothers (<a href="?bref=Gen.45.4-15">45:4-15</a>) and there was much rejoicing. Joseph pointed out that it was God who had sent him to Egypt (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.45.7-8">7-8</a>), in order to preserve the lives of all the family. Jacob was then sent for (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.1">46:1</a>), and Joseph met him in the land of Goshen (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.28-29">46:28-29</a>). The Israelites were assigned land in the region of Goshen, where they prospered (<a href="?bref=Gen.47.27">47:27</a>).</p>
<p>In Jacob’s final illness, Joseph brought his two sons, Manasseh and Ephraim, to his father for his blessing. Jacob gave the primary blessing to the second-born, Ephraim (<a href="?bref=Gen.48.13-20">48:13-20</a>). Jacob blessed each of his own sons and then died at the age of at least 130 years. Joseph arranged for Jacob’s body to be prepared for burial according to Egyptian custom (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.2-3">50:2-3</a>). After the burial of their father in the cave of Machpelah at Hebron, Joseph’s brothers worried about vengeance, but Joseph declared, “As far as I am concerned, God turned into good what you meant for evil. He brought me to the high position I have today so I could save the lives of many people” (v <a href="?bref=Gen.50.20">20</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Joseph died at age 110 with the prophetic request that when the Israelites went up from Egypt they would take his bones with them (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.25">50:25</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.13.19">Ex 13:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.32">Jos 24:32</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Abraham_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Abraham</a>; <a href="?item=AdamPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Adam (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=Covenant_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Covenant</a>; <a href="?item=Creation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Creation</a>; <a href="?item=Eve_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eve</a>; <a href="?item=FallofMan_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Fall of Man</a>; <a href="?item=Floodthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Flood, The</a>; <a href="?item=Isaac_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Isaac</a>; <a href="?item=Jacob_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jacob #1</a>; <a href="?item=Joseph_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Joseph #1</a>; <a href="?item=Nations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Nations</a>; <a href="?item=Noah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Noah #1</a>; <a href="?item=PatriarchsPeriodofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Patriarchs, Period of the</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>