<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gennesaret">
  <title>Gennesaret</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GENNESARET</p>
<p class="fl">Area on the northwest shore of the Sea of Galilee between Capernaum and Magdala, where many of Jesus’ healing miracles took place (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.34">Mt 14:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.53">Mk 6:53</a>).</p>
<p>The plain of Gennesaret, as the region was called, curves along a distance of about four miles (6.5 kilometers) with an average width from sea to mountains of approximately one mile (1.6 kilometers). The topography is generally level, with the land rising slowly as it nears the bordering mountains. The unusually fertile soil is laced with flowing streams and rivers and noted for its productivity. Temperatures ranging from hot to mild allow for a long growing season and abundant crops. The fruits of Gennesaret were so exceptional that the rabbis did not allow them in Jerusalem during feast observances, fearing many would attend only to enjoy their succulence. Rabbis termed this area the Garden of God. During Jesus’ lifetime, the area was considered the garden spot of Palestine. Trees such as the walnut, palm, olive, and fig, which require a wide diversity of growing conditions, all flourished here. Rich harvests of grapes, walnuts, rice, wheat, vegetables, and melons, as well as wild trees and flowers, were common. Later, centuries of neglect caused the plain to be largely overgrown with thornbushes, although in more recent years, certain areas have been cleared and productivity restored.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Luke.5.1">Luke 5:1</a>, the Sea of Galilee is referred to as the Lake of Gennesaret. The alternate name undoubtedly derived its origin from the bordering plain.</p>
<p>Gennesaret (more accurately termed Gennesar) was also the later name of the town Chinneroth (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.2">Jos 11:2</a>), an ancient city that had long since fallen into ruin by Jesus’ day.</p>
  </body>
</item>