<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gezer">
  <title>Gezer</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GEZER</p>
<p class="fl">Modern Tell Jezer (also known as Tell Abu Shusha), and an important ancient city in a strategic position in the north Shephelah hills. The city of the third millennium <span class="era">BC</span> was protected by a brick wall, which was replaced by a 13-foot- (4-meter-) thick stone wall. The Canaanite city reached its zenith during the 20th to 14th centuries <span class="era">BC</span>. The so-called outer wall was 14 feet (4.3 meters) thick and enclosed an area of 27 acres. There was a Canaanite high place (c. 1600 <span class="era">BC</span>) with 10 pillars or standing stones (up to 10 feet, or 3 meters, high) and a stone altar or basin. A 216-foot (65.8-meter) tunnel with steps led down to a spring in a cave, so that there was safe and ready access to water in time of siege, as at Gibeon and other Palestinian sites. Objects found indicate cultural and commercial contacts with Egypt. The Gezer Calendar, a stone tablet with a Hebrew inscription that gives the months of the year in terms of agricultural activities, has been dated to the 10th century <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>Horam, the king of Gezer, was defeated by the Israelites under Joshua (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.33">Jos 10:33</a>). Gezer was a Levitical city in the tribal territory of Ephraim (<a href="?bref=Josh.16.3">16:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.21">21:21</a>), but Ephraim was unable to drive out the Canaanites (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.29">Jgs 1:29</a>). Merneptah (c. 1225–1215 <span class="era">BC</span>) of Egyptian dynasty 19 lists Gezer, along with Ashkelon and Yanoam, on the Israel Stele, which gives an account of his conquests.</p>
<p>During the reign of David, the Philistines invaded the plain of Rephaim, but the Lord instructed David in a successful ambush and David struck down the Philistines “from Geba to Gezer” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.25">2 Sm 5:25</a>).</p>
<p>After Solomon’s marriage to the daughter of the king of Egypt, the pharaoh, whose identity is uncertain, captured and burned Gezer and gave it as a dowry to his daughter (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.16">1 Kgs 9:16</a>). Solomon rebuilt Gezer, along with a number of other cities that served as store-cities or chariot-cities (cf. vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.15-19">15-19</a>). He fortified Gezer and made a strong gate with four sets of piers, like those at Hazor and Megiddo.</p>
<p>In the fifth year of Rehoboam’s reign, Shishak (Sheshonk), king of Egypt, invaded Israel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.25">1 Kgs 14:25</a>). Gezer is included in the list of captured cities inscribed on the wall of the temple of Karnak.</p>
<p>The capture of Gezer by the Assyrian king Tiglath-pileser III (745–727 <span class="era">BC</span>) was shown in reliefs on the walls of his palace at Nimrud (biblical Calah). The Assyrians brought to Gezer conquered people from other areas, as they did at Samaria (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.24">2 Kgs 17:24</a>). Cuneiform tablets of contracts testify to their presence.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=LeviticalCities_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Levitical Cities</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>