<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Gilgal">
  <title>Gilgal</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GILGAL</p>
<p class="list">1. Town near Jericho. Gilgal was assigned to Benjamin’s tribe when Canaan was divided among the tribes of Israel. For many years it was a center of religious, political, and military importance, especially during the periods of the conquest of Canaan and the early monarchy under Saul.</p>
<p class="list-text">Gilgal was the first place where Israel encamped in Palestine after the miraculous crossing of the Jordan River (<a href="?bref=Josh.4.19">Jos 4:19</a>). No doubt the tabernacle was set up here, since Israel occupied Gilgal for some time and used it as the center of the commonwealth. Several significant religious events occurred at Gilgal: the circumcision of all Hebrew males born in the wilderness during the 40 years of wandering (<a href="?bref=Josh.5.2-9">5:2-9</a>), the celebration of the Passover (v <a href="?bref=Josh.5.10">10</a>), the cessation of the manna (v <a href="?bref=Josh.5.12">12</a>), and a divine manifestation to Joshua by the “commander of the army of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (vv <a href="?bref=Josh.5.13-15">13-15</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Militarily, Gilgal was Israel’s first foothold in Canaan and the base of operations for the Conquest. From here Joshua led Israel to the conquest of Jericho (<a href="?bref=Josh.6.1-27">Jos 6</a>) and Ai (<a href="?bref=Josh.8.3">8:3</a>), formed a treaty with the Gibeonites (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.3-15">9:3-15</a>), attacked the five Amorite kings (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.6-43">10:6-43</a>), and launched his northern campaign (ch <a href="?bref=Josh.11.1-23">11</a>). At Gilgal, Judah, Manasseh, and Ephraim were assigned their portions of Palestine (chs <a href="?bref=Josh.15.1-17.18">15–17</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">After the relocation of the tabernacle at Shiloh, Gilgal retained its importance to Israel. It was one of the towns visited regularly by Samuel in his annual circuit as judge (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.16">1 Sm 7:16</a>) and was one of the primary places for offering sacrifices (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.8">10:8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.13.9-10">13:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.15.21">15:21</a>). At Gilgal, Saul, a Benjamite, was crowned king (<a href="?bref=1Sam.11.14-15">11:14-15</a>), and later rejected (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.4-15">13:4-15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.15.17-31">15:17-31</a>). Here the men of Judah met David returning to Palestine after Absalom’s rebellion (<a href="?bref=2Sam.19.15">2 Sm 19:15</a>). That Gilgal was still a religious center of some importance as late as the eighth century <span class="era">BC</span> is indicated in the denunciation by Hosea and Amos of the sanctuary and sacrificial cult located there (<a href="?bref=Hos.4.15">Hos 4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.9.15">9:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.12.11">12:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.4.4">Am 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.5">5:5</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The exact location of Gilgal is disputed among archaeologists. Some locate it at Khirbet en-Nitleh about two miles (3.2 kilometers) east of modern Jericho. Others prefer Khirbet Mefjir, a mound about one mile (1.6 kilometers) from ancient Jericho (Tell es-Sultan). <a href="?bref=Josh.4.19">Joshua 4:19</a> places it on the eastern border of Jericho, and Josephus gives the distance from the Jordan fording place to Gilgal as 50 stadia (5.8 miles, or 9.3 kilometers), with Gilgal being about 10 stadia from Jericho (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 5.6.4). These distances fit best with Khirbet Mefjir.</p>
<p class="list">2. Place perhaps near Jericho (<a href="?bref=Deut.11.30">Dt 11:30</a>); however, the language of the passage implies that it is located in the neighborhood of Mt Ebal and Mt Gerizim.</p>
<p class="list">3. KJV rendering of “Goiim in Galilee” in <a href="?bref=Josh.12.23">Joshua 12:23</a>. Although its location is uncertain, the context places it in northern Palestine in the area of Galilee. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Goiim_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Goiim #2</a>.</p>
<p class="list">4. Place describing the northern border of Judah (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.7">Jos 15:7</a>). It was near Adummim and was perhaps identifiable with Geliloth in <a href="?bref=Josh.18.17">Joshua 18:17</a>.</p>
<p class="list">5. Place mentioned in connection with Elijah and Elisha (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.1">2 Kgs 2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.38">4:38</a>). It was apparently a town farther from the Jordan River than #1 above. In the story of Elijah’s translation into heaven, he and Elisha were going from Gilgal to Bethel to Jericho. Since the account places Bethel between Gilgal and Jericho, it could not have been the first Gilgal. It may refer to the modern Jiljiliah, a town on top of a hill in central Palestine, about seven miles (11.3 kilometers) north of Bethel.</p>
  </body>
</item>