<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Glorification">
  <title>Glorification</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GLORIFICATION</p>
<p class="fl">The expression of God’s glory and splendor. The Hebrew word for “glory” originally meant “weighty, heavy, or important.” From there it moved to the idea of an influential, rich, or prominent person. In ancient cultures the wealthy and the powerful were marked by the finery of their dress and jewels. Hence, a person’s glory meant the ostentatious signs of wealth and power. Glory also suggested beauty, since fine clothes and jewels were items of beauty. The concept was then extended to God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="GloryofGod">Glory of God</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT the glory of God means something obvious about God. The book of Exodus is rich with references to God’s glory. There was the fiery pillar and the glory that entered into the Holy of Holies in the tabernacle (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.40.34-38">40:34-38</a>).</p>
<p>In the making of the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.1-27.21">Ex 25–27</a>), the concepts of glory and beauty are joined. There is evidence that the “goodness” of the Lord that Moses saw (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.19">Ex 33:19</a>) could also be translated as “beauty.” Hence, God’s glory is his beauty.</p>
<p>The NT continues the thought of the OT that God is a God of glory (cf. the vision of God in his glory in <a href="?bref=Rev.4.1-11">Rv 4</a>). But the primary message in the NT centers on the glory of Christ. The transfiguration of Christ was a breaking out into the open of his glory (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.1-8">Mt 17:1-8</a>). The apostle Paul called Jesus the Lord of glory (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.8">1 Cor 2:8</a>) and wrote that the glory of God radiated from his face (<a href="?bref=2Cor.3.18">2 Cor 3:18</a>). John’s Gospel is uniquely the Gospel of glory. In the Incarnation, the Son of God showed the glory that was his as the only begotten of the Father (<a href="?bref=John.1.14">Jn 1:14</a>). The raising of Lazarus was a manifestation of the glory of God in Christ (<a href="?bref=John.11.40">11:40</a>). Jesus’ prayer in <a href="?bref=John.17.1-26">John 17</a> is filled with comments on the glory of Christ, including the affirmation that the disciples of the Lord would share in that glory.</p>
<p class="h2" id="GlorificationoftheBeliever">Glorification of the Believer</p>
<p class="fl">In <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.18">2 Corinthians 3:18</a> spiritual transformation is described as a changing from glory to glory. Glorification is implied as the last event in the change from glory to glory. In the process of salvation Paul lists glorification as the last and final event (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.28-30">Rom 8:28-30</a>). The verb used in verse <a href="?bref=Rom.8.30">30</a> is in the past tense, which some have taken to mean the certainty and finality of glorification. Glorification is the completion, the consummation, the perfection, the full realization of salvation.</p>
<p>Glorification is the perfection of sanctification as it pertains to one’s inner character. No one passage treats this theme extensively, but <a href="?bref=Eph.5.27">Ephesians 5:27</a> may be taken for all. In that passage Paul wrote of presenting the church to Christ, but what he says of the church is true of each Christian. Jesus will present the church to himself in “splendor, without spot or wrinkle or any such thing, that she [the church] might be holy and without blemish.” Or in the language of <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.10">2 Timothy 2:10</a>, “Therefore I endure everything for the sake of the elect, that they also may obtain salvation in Christ Jesus with its eternal glory” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Just as the inner person undergoes glorification, so does the believer’s body. Paul calls the resurrection of the body the redemption of the body (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.23">Rom 8:23</a>). In <a href="?bref=Phil.3.21">Philippians 3:21</a> Paul speaks of the transformation of bodies of humiliation (i.e., humiliated by sin and mortality) into bodies of glory identical to that of Christ. The power that shall do this is the power of God by which he subjects all things to his reign.</p>
<p>The most extensive treatment on the glorification of the body is found in <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-58">1 Corinthians 15</a>, with some additional details in <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.1-21">2 Corinthians 5</a>. Paul’s theme in <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-58">1 Corinthians 15</a> is that as Christians have borne the image of the mortal clay of Adam, they shall bear the image of the immortal Son of God. Paul contrasts the two bodies. The present body is perishable; the resurrection body will be imperishable. This body is one of dishonor; the resurrection body will be one of glory. This body is one of weakness; the resurrection body is one of power. This body is of the current physical order; the resurrection body will be of the future, spiritual, eternal order.</p>
<p>Salvation involves justification, regeneration, and sanctification in this life. In the life to come it means the glorification of the inner person and the resurrection of the body in glory. But such a glorified person must live in a glorified environment. Hence, Scripture must logically end the course of salvation with a glorious new heaven, new earth, and a new Jerusalem.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Glory_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Glory</a>; <a href="?item=Resurrection_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Resurrection</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>