<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="GodFearer">
  <title>God-Fearer</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GOD-FEARER</p>
<p class="fl">One who fears God. This can be a term of reverence, an emotional reaction of terror, or a dread of God’s vengeance.</p>
<p>Phrases describing the God-fearer in the OT are frequently coupled with such terms as “stood in awe” and “held in awe” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.16.25">1 Chr 16:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.22.23">Ps 22:23</a>). Reverence for the Lord is used less frequently, but it is used with this meaning when Obadiah hid the prophets in a cave to save them from being assassinated by Jezebel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.3-4,12">1 Kgs 18:3-4, 12</a>). A man could expect to receive justice from a God-fearing ruler (<a href="?bref=2Sam.23.3">2 Sm 23:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.19.7">2 Chr 19:7</a>), and long life was a reward for those who feared the Lord (<a href="?bref=Pr.10.27">Prv 10:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.14.27">14:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.19.23">19:23</a>). A God-fearing family would rely on the Lord for practical help in time of trouble (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.1">2 Kgs 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.14.26">Prv 14:26</a>). The fear of the Lord was effective in driving away sin and was itself the beginning of wisdom (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.10.13">Wisd of Sol 10:13</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT fear of God is frequently used in conjunction with admonitions to love and serve the Lord (<a href="?bref=Col.3.22">Col 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.17">1 Pt 2:17</a>). In the Magnificat, Mary’s statement “His mercy is on those who fear him” is used in the sense of revere and obey (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.50">Lk 1:50</a>). In Acts, the term “God-fearer” is given a specific interpretation, being used with reference to Gentiles who attended the synagogue. Paul mentions them separately when introducing his address: “Men of Israel, and you that fear God” (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.16">Acts 13:16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Cornelius was an honest, generous, and God-fearing Roman centurion who, although not a Jew, was recognized as leading a life acceptable to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Acts.10.2,35">10:2, 35</a>).</p>
<p>The fear of God was also used in both the OT and the NT to denote dread or terror of the mighty power and judgment of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.10">Gn 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.9.19">Dt 9:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.6.4">Jb 6:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.9.28-29">9:28-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.76.8">Ps 76:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.17.7">Mt 17:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.28.10">28:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.10">Lk 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.5">12:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.5,11">Acts 5:5, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.5.20">1 Tm 5:20</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Fear_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Fear</a>; <a href="?item=Proselyte_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Proselyte</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>