<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Grief">
  <title>Grief</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">GRIEF</p>
<p class="fl">Emotional suffering brought on by bereavement, mishap, or disaster. To grieve is either to cause or feel sorrow or distress. The concept is found in the Scriptures under a variety of circumstances. Isaac and Rebekah experienced grief when their son Esau married a Hittite woman (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.35">Gn 26:35</a>). God mourned the misery of Israel brought upon them by disobedience (<a href="?bref=Judg.10.16">Jgs 10:16</a>). Because she had no son, Hannah was sad—so much so that she appeared to be drunk while praying (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.16">1 Sm 1:16</a>). Similarly, Samuel, distraught at King Saul’s disobedience, prayed all night. Job was exceedingly sorrowful over his personal loss (<a href="?bref=Job.2.13">Jb 2:13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Job.6.2">6:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.16.6">16:6</a>), and the psalmist poetically demonstrated distress and sorrow (<a href="?bref=Ps.6.7">Pss 6:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.31.9-10">31:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.69.26">69:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.73.21">73:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.95.10">95:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.112.10">112:10</a>). The book of Lamentations is devoted to the expression of grief, and the prophets in general speak of judgment because Israel had grieved a holy God.</p>
<p>Jesus experienced sorrow and distress (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.5">Mk 3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.33">Jn 11:33</a>), including crying over the death of a friend (<a href="?bref=John.11.35">Jn 11:35</a>). The Jews are said to have been grieved as the apostles taught about Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.2">Acts 4:2</a>). The apostle Paul instructed believers not to grieve one another (<a href="?bref=Rom.14.15">Rom 14:15</a>) and did not want to cause any sorrow himself (<a href="?bref=2Cor.2.1-5">2 Cor 2:1-5</a>). Most of all, the believer is not to grieve the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.30">Eph 4:30</a>). A believer may, of course, experience grief and suffering in an alien world (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.19">1 Pt 2:19</a>). In Bible times grief was given particular expression at a time of death by means of shrieks, wails, and laments (<a href="?bref=Jer.9.17-18">Jer 9:17-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.16">Am 5:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.5.38">Mk 5:38</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Mourning_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mourning</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>