<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Caiaphas">
  <title>Caiaphas</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CAIAPHAS</p>
<p class="fl">High priest during the life and ministry of Jesus. As official head of the Jewish state, Caiaphas presided over the council, or Sanhedrin—its highest court. Next to the Roman governor, he was the most powerful man in Judea and was responsible to the Romans for the conduct of the nation. Caiaphas was, therefore, especially concerned about the popular enthusiasm and political unrest centering on the ministry of Jesus and about its implications for the revolutionary sentiment of the time. The activities of the Zealots were increasing and were destined to break out soon into open revolt.</p>
<p>A huge stir among the people, caused by the raising of Lazarus (<a href="?bref=John.11.1-57">Jn 11</a>), brought matters to a head. Alarmed lest the activities of those seeking a political messiah should lead the Romans to intervene with armed force, Caiaphas advised that Jesus should be put to death (<a href="?bref=John.11.48-50">Jn 11:48-50</a>). The Gospel writer John pointed out that, in so doing, Caiaphas unwittingly prophesied concerning the atoning nature of Jesus’ death (<a href="?bref=John.11.51-52">Jn 11:51-52</a>).</p>
<p>Caiaphas played a chief role in Jesus’ arrest and trial. The leaders laid their plans in his palace (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.3-5">Mt 26:3-5</a>); it was there also that part of Jesus’ preliminary trial took place with Caiaphas presiding (vv <a href="?bref=Matt.26.57-68">57-68</a>). That was after Jesus had first been taken before Annas, Caiaphas’s father-in-law (<a href="?bref=John.18.13">Jn 18:13</a>). Matthew, Mark, and Luke omit the visit to Annas, and Mark and Luke do not refer to Caiaphas by name. Upon Jesus’ admission that he was “the Christ, the Son of God,” Caiaphas tore his robes and charged him with blasphemy (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.63-66">Mt 26:63-66</a>). After Pentecost, he, along with other Jewish leaders, presided over the trial of Peter and John when the council attempted to stop the preaching of the apostles (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.5-6">Acts 4:5-6</a>).</p>
<p>Annas, who had held the office of high priest before Caiaphas, remained influential in the affairs of the nation. That explains why Luke, in his Gospel, set the ministry of John the Baptist “in the high-priesthood of Annas and Caiaphas” (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.2">Lk 3:2</a>), and in Acts called Annas the high priest (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.6">Acts 4:6</a>). John’s account of Jesus’ visit to Annas makes plain that Annas was still popularly referred to as “high priest” (<a href="?bref=John.18.22">Jn 18:22</a>).</p>
<p>The historian Josephus records that Caiaphas was appointed to his office about <span class="era">AD</span> 18 and ruled until he was deposed about <span class="era">AD</span> 36. The high priest held office at the whim of the Romans, so Caiaphas’s unusually long term indicates that he was a man of considerable political skill. Caiaphas was removed from his position by the proconsul Vitellus, and nothing more is known of him.</p>
  </body>
</item>