<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Caleb">
  <title>Caleb</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CALEB</p>
<p class="list">1. Son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite (<a href="?bref=Num.32.12">Nm 32:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.14.6">Jos 14:6</a>) and older brother of Kenaz (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.13">Jgs 1:13</a>). Caleb was one of the 12 spies sent to scout out the land of Canaan. Although he and Joshua, another spy, recommended an immediate attack, their suggestion was rejected by the Israelite tribes because of other reports of heavily defended fortresses. Consequently, entrance into Canaan, the Promised Land, was delayed for some years as a divine judgment (<a href="?bref=Num.14.21-23,34-35">Nm 14:21-23, 34-35</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">When Israel under Joshua’s leadership finally occupied Canaan, Caleb, at age 85 (<a href="?bref=Josh.14.6-7,10">Jos 14:6-7, 10</a>), was assigned Hebron, which he conquered by overcoming its Anakim inhabitants (vv <a href="?bref=Josh.14.13-14">13-14</a>). Caleb offered his daughter Achsah to whomever would overthrow nearby Debir (Kiriath-sepher). Othniel, Kenaz’s son and Achsah’s cousin, was able to claim her as his wife by conquering the town (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.16-17">15:16-17</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Hebron later became a Levitical city of refuge (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.13">Jos 21:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.55-57">1 Chr 6:55-57</a>). In some portion of Caleb’s territory David spent time as an outlaw and met his future wife Abigail, then the wife of Nabal, a Calebite (<a href="?bref=1Sam.25.3">1 Sm 25:3</a>). Here also his wives were captured by Amalekite marauders who had raided southern Judah and “the Negev of Caleb” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.30.14">1 Sm 30:14</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Hezron’s son and brother of Jerahmeel (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.18,42">1 Chr 2:18, 42</a>), also called Chelubai (v <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.9">9</a>). Many scholars, however, believe that this Caleb is the same as #1 above because (1) Achsah is mentioned as the daughter of both (v <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.49">49</a>); and (2) the prominent place of an otherwise unknown Caleb in the genealogy would be hard to account for. According to these scholars, Caleb was listed as a son of Hezron (the grandson of Judah) in order to establish his position and inheritance in Judah’s tribe. In reality, however, Caleb was a foreigner, son of Jephunneh, a Kenizzite, who had joined himself and his clan to Judah’s tribe. Some support this view by arguing that Caleb is a Horite rather than Israelite name.</p>
<p class="list">3. Hur’s son, according to the <span class="sc">kjv</span> (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.50">1 Chr 2:50</a>). Most likely, however, the <span class="sc">kjv</span> joins what should be two separate phrases. The <span class="sc">nlt</span> correctly renders it, “These were all descendants of Caleb. The sons of Hur . . .”</p>
  </body>
</item>