<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CalfGolden">
  <title>Calf, Golden</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CALF, Golden</p>
<p class="fl">Calf-shaped idol fashioned at the Israelites’ request from their own gold jewelry (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.1-4">Ex 32:1-4</a>). Under Aaron’s supervision, the idol was created while Moses was receiving the Ten Commandments on Mt Sinai. Upon seeing the golden calf and the immoral carousing in which the people were engaged, Moses smashed the tablets containing the commandments. He then ground the calf to powder, scattered it on the water, and made the people drink it (vv <a href="?bref=Exod.32.15-20">15-20</a>). Some of the transgressors were slaughtered (vv <a href="?bref=Exod.32.25-29">25-29</a>), while others were punished by God himself with a plague (vv <a href="?bref=Exod.32.33-35">33-35</a>).</p>
<p>Aaron’s golden calf was probably modeled after Apis, an Egyptian bull god. Apis was connected with another Egyptian god, Osiris. Magnificent bulls worshiped in life as Apis were buried at death as Osiris-Apis, a name that became Serapis during the intertestamental period. The notoriety of Aaron’s golden calf is underscored by several biblical references to it in historical summaries (<a href="?bref=Deut.9.16,21">Dt 9:16, 21</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.18">Neh 9:18</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.106.19-20">Ps 106:19-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.39-41">Acts 7:39-41</a>).</p>
<p>Jeroboam I (930–909 <span class="era">BC</span>), the first king of Israel after the division of the monarchy, set up shrines at Dan in the far north and at Bethel in the south, installing a gold calf in each (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.26-33">1 Kgs 12:26-33</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.11.13-15">2 Chr 11:13-15</a>). Israel’s prophets knew that such calves were not the one true God (<a href="?bref=Hos.8.5-6">Hos 8:5-6</a>). Hosea called the calf at Bethel (“house of God”) the calf of “Beth-aven” (“house of wickedness,” <a href="?bref=Hos.10.5-6">Hos 10:5-6</a>). Within two centuries after Jeroboam’s time, people had stooped to kissing calves (<a href="?bref=Hos.13.2">13:2</a>), and Jeroboam’s sinful act was listed as one of the main factors leading to the destruction of Samaria, Israel’s capital city, and the northern kingdom’s exile in 722 <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.16">2 Kgs 17:16</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>