<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CanaanCanaanite">
  <title>Canaan, Canaanite</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CANAAN, CANAANITE</p>
<p class="fl">Palestinian territory (the Promised Land) west of the Jordan River, settled by the Israelites at the time of Joshua’s leadership. Portions of southern Syria were also frequently considered part of Canaanite territory, the northern borders of which were never clearly defined. The pre-Israelite peoples of western Palestine, excluding northern Syria and such places as Ugarit (Ras Shamra) on the Mediterranean coast of Syria, carried the broad designation of Canaanites.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#LandandPeople">Land and People</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Language">Language</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Literature">Literature</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#History">History</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Religion">Religion</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#InfluenceonIsrael">Influence on Israel</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="LandandPeople">Land and People</p>
<p class="fl">In the “table of nations” (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.15-19">Gn 10:15-19</a>), Noah’s grandson Canaan was progenitor of 11 groups that lived in the area of Syria and Palestine. The first six evidently occupied territory at or south of Sidon, whereas the others lived farther north. The northerners mostly settled on the edge of the coastal plain; in the south, settlement spread eastward to the upland areas. OT references specifically placed the Canaanites in western Palestine’s valleys and coastal areas; the upland country was occupied by Amorites and other peoples (<a href="?bref=Num.13.29">Nm 13:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.5.1">Jos 5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.7.9">7:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.1.27-36">Jgs 1:27-36</a>).</p>
<p>One of the earliest known references to the people of Canaan is in a tablet from Mari (15th century <span class="era">BC</span>), in which a military officer reported his surveillance of “thieves and Canaanites.” The Canaanites were listed as a group on the Memphis Stele (inscribed column) of the Egyptian pharaoh Amenophis II (c. 1440 <span class="era">BC</span>). The land of Canaan was mentioned in a 15th-century inscription of Idrimi, king of Aleppo (west of Ugarit), who fled to the Canaanite seaport of Ammiya and then became ruler of Alalakh (north of Ugarit). During the Amarna Age (15th–14th centuries <span class="era">BC</span>), Palestine was politically dominated by Egypt, according to the Egyptian Amarna tablets.</p>
<p>Just as “Canaan” designated the whole western Palestinian area, so “Canaanite” described its pre-Israelite inhabitants without specifying race. Among the peoples who lived in Palestine, the Amorites first appeared in the second millennium <span class="era">BC</span> as immigrants from Mesopotamia.</p>
<p>Several OT references seem to equate Amorite territory and the land of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.5-6">Gn 12:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.15.18-21">15:18-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.48.22">48:22</a>), a tradition reflected in the 18th-century <span class="era">BC</span> Alalakh tablets, which depicted “Amurru” as part of Syria-Palestine. Tablets from Mari from about the same period speak of an Amorite ruler of Hazor in northern Palestine. The Tell el-Amarna texts (14th–13th centuries <span class="era">BC</span>) indicate that the Amurru kingdom of the Lebanon region was monopolizing coastal trade and commerce; therefore, references to the two peoples (Amorites and Canaanites) together in Moses’ time and throughout the late Bronze Age (c. 1550–1200 <span class="era">BC</span>) are not surprising.</p>
<p>At the end of that period, the “Sea Peoples” (largely Philistines) destroyed the Hittite Empire, and in the time of Ramses III (c. 1180 <span class="era">BC</span>) occupied western Palestine. The Israelite conquest of Palestine broke the power of many Canaanite and Amorite city-states, while the rise of a Philistine confederacy on the southern Palestinian coast restricted further the range of specifically Canaanite territory. From the beginning of the Iron Age the cultural heirs of the Canaanites were the Phoenicians, centered in the city-states of Tyre and Sidon, who themselves liked to be known as Canaanites (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.15.21-22">Mt 15:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.7.24-26">Mk 7:24-26</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Language">Language</p>
<p class="fl">The various groups that inhabited western Palestine in the pre-Israelite period probably spoke related dialects of the Northwest Semitic linguistic family. The large territory covered by those peoples and the possible influence of Amorite, Hurrian, and Ugaritic languages complicate modern theories about what is properly meant by “Canaanite” as a language.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Literature">Literature</p>
<p class="fl">As with language, it is difficult to be specific about Canaanite literature. One clear fact is that our own alphabet originated in middle Bronze Age Canaan. Before that time, writing was either pictographic (words or ideas represented by pictures), cuneiform (wedge-shaped impressions in soft clay representing syllables and whole words), or hieroglyphic (Egyptian pictorial writing). Alphabetical writing was passed on through the Hebrews and Phoenicians to the Greeks, who gave our present alphabet its classical form.</p>
<p>Until 1929 little Canaanite literature was known, but with the discoveries at Ugarit a large body of literary material came to light. The discoveries included portions of an epic poem about the god Baal and his consort Anath (possibly from c. 2000 <span class="era">BC</span>), a legend about a royal personage named Aqhat (from c. 1800 <span class="era">BC</span>), the legendary activities of King Keret (written c. 1500 <span class="era">BC</span>), and fragmentary religious, medical, and administrative material.</p>
<p class="h2" id="History">History</p>
<p class="fl">Archaeological evidence shows that western Palestine was occupied as far back as the Old Stone Age. Mesolithic, Neolithic, and Chalcolithic deposits have also been found at several sites. It is possible that Semitic-speaking peoples inhabited places such as Jericho, Megiddo, and Byblos around 3000 <span class="era">BC</span>. Discoveries at Tell Mardikh (Ebla) show that a vigorous Canaanite Empire existed in Syria about 2500 <span class="era">BC</span>, and there is no doubt that both Amorite and Canaanite peoples were firmly settled in Syria and Palestine by 2000 <span class="era">BC</span>. The best evidence for Canaanite occupation of western Palestine has come from the middle and late Bronze Age (c. 1950–1200 <span class="era">BC</span>), when the land was dotted with Canaanite and Amorite city-states.</p>
<p>The Egyptians made periodic forays into Palestine during their 5th and 6th dynasties; in the 13th dynasty (second millennium <span class="era">BC</span>) they controlled much of Syria-Palestine both politically and economically.</p>
<p>Canaanite contacts with Mesopotamia from about 2000 <span class="era">BC</span> are indicated in texts discovered at Mari and Ugarit. Evidently Amorites, Hurrians, early Assyrians, and other peoples periodically migrated to Canaan, bringing with them a diversity of political and social forms. By the late 16th century <span class="era">BC</span>, most of the small Canaanite kingdoms were firmly under Egyptian control. Within two centuries the most northerly ones were subject to Hittite political influence.</p>
<p>Canaanite history is further complicated by the activities of the Hyksos people between about 1800 and 1500 <span class="era">BC</span>. Of mixed Asiatic origin, the Hyksos owed much of their political influence to their military use of iron-fitted chariots and the compound Asiatic bow. From Canaanite locations like Hazor and Jericho, they invaded Egypt and established control there from about 1776 to about 1570 <span class="era">BC</span>. When they were expelled at the start of Egypt’s New Kingdom (1570–1100 <span class="era">BC</span>), they retreated to fortified sites in southern Canaan.</p>
<p>Egyptian control over western Palestine had disappeared by the time of the Israelite conquest of Canaan; Joshua met predominantly Canaanite and Amorite opposition. The Israelite occupation of Canaan was aided by the state of decay into which the small Palestinian kingdoms had fallen. With the destruction of Hittite culture by the Sea Peoples and their occupation of the northern and coastal regions, the traditional city-states collapsed. From about 1100 <span class="era">BC</span>, Canaanite culture was restricted to Tyre, Sidon, and a few other places.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Religion">Religion</p>
<p class="fl">Before the Ugaritic discoveries, little was known about Canaanite religion apart from OT references to it. From what is now known of Canaanite culture, the head of the Canaanite list of gods was a shadowy personage named El, who was worshiped as the “father of man.” His consorts were Athirat, known to the Israelites as Asherah, Astarte, and Baaltis. El had a son, Baal, a fertility god described in myths as the lord of rain and storm. Baal succeeded his father as head of the pantheon (list of gods) and supposedly resided in the distant northern heavens. A monument found at Ugarit represented him carrying a thunderbolt at his left side and a mace in his right hand.</p>
<p>Many small terra-cotta figurines with exaggerated secondary sexual characteristics, representing one or the other of the female deities, have been recovered from middle and late Bronze Age sites in western Palestine. A center devoted to the Anath cult, excavated at Byblos in Phoenicia, was evidently notorious for religious prostitution and sexual fertility rites; many naked female figures were found there. Other Canaanite cult objects included a sacred pillar of some sort <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">massebah</span><span class="ital">)</span> and a wooden image <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">asherah</span><span class="ital">),</span> probably of the goddess herself.</p>
<p>In the Amarna Age, Canaanite orgiastic religion was especially influential in the Near East; it infiltrated to some extent even the conservative religions of Egypt and Babylonia. Four principal festivals associated with agriculture seem to have been celebrated by the Canaanites, invariably occasions of revelry, drunkenness, and sexual excess. Canaanite religion was evidently the most sexually depraved of any in the ancient world.</p>
<p class="h2" id="InfluenceonIsrael">Influence on Israel</p>
<p class="fl">Israelite morality, as defined by the covenant laws of Mt Sinai, was very different from the cultic traditions of Canaanite life. Hebrew ethical monotheism was in many ways opposite to the depraved polytheistic nature worship of Canaanite religion. It was clear that the two systems could not coexist. Hence the law contained strict instructions that the Canaanites and their ways were to be eliminated from the Promised Land (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.24">Ex 23:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.13-16">34:13-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.7.1-5">Dt 7:1-5</a>) and that the Hebrews were to remain separate from Canaanite religion in loyalty to God’s covenant. That was far from easy, if only because both peoples spoke closely related dialects and therefore used similar expressions of speech. Further, the invading Israelites under Joshua found that the Canaanites were superior to them in building stone structures and in making metal tools, implements, and weapons. The Hebrews, at a disadvantage, must have faced the prospect of requiring technical help from the Canaanites. In the time of King Solomon, Canaanites from Phoenicia were enlisted to design and construct the temple of the Lord in Jerusalem. A superficial resemblance between some aspects of Canaanite and Hebrew religion, such as peace offerings and certain divine titles, also made it difficult to maintain Israel’s cultural distinctiveness.</p>
<p>Except for the “ban” imposed at Jericho, the Israelites were able to use Canaanite equipment captured in battle. Hence their determination to destroy all traces of the Canaanites, including their corrupt religion, was gradually weakened. By the time of King Ahab, when the worship of the Tyrian Baal was firmly entrenched in the northern kingdom of Israel, the Hebrews were in serious danger of losing their spiritual and theological distinctiveness. Their priests, who should have played a major part in maintaining the uniqueness of the covenant faith, often lapsed into Canaanite ways, emulating the immorality of their pagan neighbors and encouraging the Israelite people to do likewise (cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.2.22">1 Sm 2:22</a>).</p>
<p>As a result, Hebrew prophets proclaimed that their nation, which had almost completely succumbed to Canaanite blandishments, would have to be purified by exile before a renewed faith could become a possibility for Israel.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CanaaniteDeitiesandReligion_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Canaanite Deities and Religion</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=Palestine_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Palestine</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>