<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Capernaum">
  <title>Capernaum</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CAPERNAUM</p>
<p class="fl">City of Galilee, mentioned only in the Gospels, which was the headquarters of much of Jesus’ ministry. It lay on the northwest side of the Sea of Galilee (or Lake of Gennesaret). Its name means “village of Nahum,” but it is impossible to say who this Nahum was, whether the OT writer or someone else. Matthew gives us the following information: Capernaum was located near the Sea of Galilee, in the territory of Zebulun and Naphtali (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.13">Mt 4:13</a>). The west shore of the lake was settled by the tribe of Naphtali. Two of the characters described as being in Capernaum help to identify its location as being near the border of the Jordan and the political frontier. The story of the centurion (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.5">Mt 8:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.2">Lk 7:2</a>) points to the small garrison of about 100 men found at such a frontier town. The story of Levi’s call to leave the customs post controlling the taxation of the area reflects on the same border character of the town (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.9">Mt 9:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.2.14">Mk 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.27">Lk 5:27</a>).</p>
<p>Jewish evidence argued for Tell Hum as the site for ancient Capernaum. The Greek <span class="greek">Capharnaum</span> is rendered by the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">Kaphar nahum</span> in Midrash Kohelet 1.8 and 7.26 (c. <span class="era">AD</span> 110), proving that Capernaum still existed in the second century. There is no further mention until 1160, when Benjamin of Tudela refers to “Capharnaum which is Kaphar Nahum.” The Franciscans, who acquired the site, have found a considerable number of coins of that period at Tell Hum, and the ruins of the synagogue there may well date from the third century <span class="era">AD</span>. Recent excavations of Tell Hum have revealed that it is unquestionably the site for ancient Capernaum. During the excavations, a private house was uncovered beneath a fourth-century Jewish-Christian place of meeting. As early as the first half of the second century, it had served as an assembly hall for the early Christians. Inscriptions and the reports from early Christian travelers make it likely that it was the home of Peter.</p>
<p>Capernaum was an important settlement, with a Roman garrison, adopted by Jesus as his own city after his rejection by Nazareth (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.1">Mt 9:1</a>). Here he was at home (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.1">Mk 2:1</a>) and performed many miracles (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.34">Mk 1:34</a>): the healing of the centurion’s servant (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.5">Mt 8:5</a>); the healing of Peter’s mother-in-law (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.31">Mk 1:31</a>); and the exorcism of the unclean spirit (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.23">Mk 1:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.33">Lk 4:33</a>). Thus highly favored by the ministry of Jesus, there was also a heavy curse imposed on the city because of its unrepentance: “And you, Capernaum, will you be exalted to heaven? You shall be brought down to Hades” (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.23">Mt 11:23</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
  </body>
</item>