<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CaphtorCaphtorimCaphtorites">
  <title>Caphtor*, Caphtorim*, Caphtorites</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CAPHTOR*, CAPHTORIM*, CAPHTORITES</p>
<p class="fl">Place-name and the name of the people associated with the place. The Caphtorim among the Hamitic peoples in the “table of nations” are listed as the “sons” of Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.13-14">Gn 10:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.12">1 Chr 1:12</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span> “Caphthorim”). The text makes the Casluhim the parent people of the Philistines. However, prophets referred to the Philistines as colonists from Caphtor (<a href="?bref=Jer.47.4">Jer 47:4</a>; see <a href="?bref=Amos.9.7">Am 9:7</a>). This has been the basis for some translators to transpose the clause of <a href="?bref=Gen.10.14">Genesis 10:14</a> and to translate “Caphtorites, from whom the Philistines were descended” (<span class="sc">neb</span>). Others understand that although the Philistines may originally have been a Casluhian colony, they settled in regions that became known primarily as those of the Caphtorites.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfAncientSynagogueInCapernaum"/>
<p>Caphtor is referred to as <span class="ital">Kaptara</span> in Accadian, <span class="ital">kptr</span> in Ugaritic, and <span class="ital">Keftiu</span> in Egyptian. These references are to be dated from as early as 2200 <span class="era">BC</span> down to about 1200 <span class="era">BC</span>. The Egyptian sources are especially helpful in identifying Caphtor as Crete. On the other hand, there is a Jewish tradition that the Caphtorim were from Cappadocia; the Septuagint reads “Cappadocia” instead of “Caphtor.” This has led some to suggest that Caphtor is to be identified with a coastal region of Asia Minor or with the island of Carpathos. Perhaps by the 13th century <span class="era">BC</span>, “Caphtor” was used in a broad sense for the Aegean area from which the Philistines came.</p>
<p>The Caphtorim are mentioned also as a people who invaded the region around Gaza, dispossessed the Avvim, and settled there (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.23">Dt 2:23</a>). It appears that the Caphtorim were firmly settled around Gaza before Israel crossed the Jordan at the time of the Conquest. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=CasluhimCasluhites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Casluhim, Casluhites</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>