<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CherubCherubim">
  <title>Cherub*, Cherubim</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CHERUB*, CHERUBIM</p>
<p class="fl">Winged creatures mentioned occasionally in Scripture (“cherubim” is the plural form of the Hebrew “cherub”). They belong to a supernatural created order along with the seraphim and angels. Some scholars have argued that the term “cherub” had its origin in the <span class="ital">karibu</span> (“intercessor”) of Akkadian mythological texts, commonly represented in Mesopotamian art as a griffin (a creature half lion and half eagle) or as a winged human. The sphinx also appears to go back to this concept. The biblical evidence, however, does not seem to support that identification.</p>
<p>The prophet Ezekiel described four “living creatures,” each with four faces and four wings (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.5-24">Ez 1:5-24</a>); those creatures corresponded to cherubim (<a href="?bref=Ezek.10.2-22">10:2-22</a>). The splendor of Ezekiel’s vision was recaptured more modestly in his description of the king of Tyre, who in the midst of his own prosperity seemed to be playing the part of a towering or guardian cherub before being dispossessed (<a href="?bref=Ezek.28.13-16">28:13-16</a>). That passage has been interpreted by some as a description of Satan’s “fall from grace” after he had once been in the service of God as a ranking member of a high celestial order.</p>
<p>Despite Ezekiel’s elaborate visionary descriptions, it is difficult to be certain about the form in which cherubim appeared. Thus, in <a href="?bref=Ezek.41.18">Ezekiel 41:18</a> the cherubim that were to decorate Ezekiel’s ideal temple had only two faces, a man’s and a young lion’s, in contrast to the four-faced creatures of the earlier visions. The four faces of <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.10">Ezekiel 1:10</a> were those of a man, a lion, an ox, and an eagle, whereas in <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.14">Ezekiel 10:14</a> the cherub had its own face (“the face of the cherub”), along with the faces of a man, a lion, and an eagle. If the cherub’s face corresponded to that of an ox, that might account for the fact that cherubim in Near Eastern art were represented as four-footed creatures, though frequently different otherwise from biblical cherubim. In addition to their wings, the cherubim of Ezekiel’s vision had straight legs and feet with hooves like those of a calf (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.7">Ez 1:7</a>).</p>
<p>That complex description has led scholars to try to identify cherubim in the statues and carvings of non-Israelite peoples. The throne of Ahiram, king of Byblos, was flanked by sphinxes, which some have judged to be cherubim. The sphinx, however, seems to have been a popular decorative motif, as evidenced by an ivory box from Megiddo and ivories from Samaria, Nimrud, and elsewhere. Other decorative creatures have various combinations of human and animal bodies, with wings generally prominent. None of them adequately represents the OT descriptions of cherubim.</p>
<p>The four living creatures of the book of Revelation were similar to the cherubim of Ezekiel but lacked their whirling wheels (<a href="?bref=Rev.4.6-9">Rv 4:6-9</a>). Subsequent references to the creatures in Revelation (<a href="?bref=Rev.5.6-14">5:6-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.1-8">6:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.7.1-11">7:1-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.14.3">14:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.15.7">15:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.4">19:4</a>) add nothing to the initial description.</p>
<p>The cherubim of <a href="?bref=Gen.3.24">Genesis 3:24</a> acted as guardians or custodians. Supernatural guardians seem to have been common in Near Eastern thought. In <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.1-22">Ezekiel 10</a> the cherubim were also executors of divine judgment, spreading burning coals over a city (<a href="?bref=Ezek.10.2,7">Ez 10:2, 7</a>).</p>
<p>In early Israelite thought the cherubim stretched out their wings and provided God with a throne (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.4">1 Sm 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.6.2">2 Sm 6:2</a>; etc.). God spoke to Moses from such a throne on the cover of the ark of the covenant (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.22">Ex 25:22</a>). In Ezekiel’s vision (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.26">Ez 1:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.1">10:1</a>) God was seated in a four-wheeled chariot moved by the cherubim and borne aloft by their wings. In Hebrew poetry God was portrayed as employing clouds for his chariot (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.3">Ps 104:3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.19.1">Is 19:1</a>) or riding on a cherub in flight (<a href="?bref=2Sam.22.11">2 Sm 22:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.18.10">Ps 18:10</a>). The idea of cherubim furnishing a seat or platform for the invisible deity found expression in Near Eastern art, where the pagan gods stood on the backs of animals.</p>
<p>In Israel cherubim were carved on the covenantal ark (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.18-20">Ex 25:18-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.37.7-9">37:7-9</a>), and representations of them were also embroidered on the curtains of the tabernacle and the veil that screened the innermost sanctuary in which the ark rested.</p>
<p>The Most Holy Place of Solomon’s temple was adorned by two large representations of cherubim, made of olive wood and covered with gold leaf. When placed side by side with outstretched wings, they spanned the entire width of the inner sanctuary. Smaller cherubim and palms were carved on the temple’s wooden panels and some of the doors, and were also represented on the sides of the laver stands (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.29,36">1 Kgs 7:29, 36</a>). Cherubim alternating with palm trees formed part of the decor of Ezekiel’s visionary temple (<a href="?bref=Ezek.41.17-20">Ez 41:17-20</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Angel_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Angel</a>; <a href="?item=SeraphSeraphim_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Seraph, Seraphim</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>