<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Christ">
  <title>Christ</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CHRIST</p>
<p class="fl">Official title given to Jesus in the NT. It signifies his office as anointed Savior and alludes to his spiritual qualifications for the task of saving his people. The word derives from Greek <span class="greek">Christos</span><span class="ital">,</span> which translates Hebrew <span class="hebrew">Messiah</span> (<a href="?bref=John.1.41">Jn 1:41</a>). Both terms come from verbs meaning “to anoint with sacred oil”; hence, as titles they mean “the Anointed One.” Applied to Jesus, they express the conviction that he had divine appointment for his office and function.</p>
<p>In the NT the title is used in combination with the given name, as “Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.1">Mt 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.1">Mk 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.1.4">Rom 1:4</a>), “Christ Jesus” (<span class="sc">niv</span> <a href="?bref=Rom.1.1">Rom 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.1">1 Cor 1:1</a>), with the article “the” (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.4">Rom 7:4</a>), or with another title “Lord” (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.18">Rom 16:18</a>). It is also used alone as the one favored substitute name or title for Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.20.31">Jn 20:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.3">Rom 15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.3.6">Heb 3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.5.5">5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.11,19">1 Pt 1:11, 19</a>).</p>
<p>The Gospels portray Jesus as modestly accepting the title and role of the Messiah. His baptism should be understood as his anointing to the threefold office of prophet, priest, and king. At his baptism by John (the new Elijah, <a href="?bref=Matt.11.14">Mt 11:14</a>), Jesus received the outpouring of the Spirit and God’s mandate to begin his ministry (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.16-4.17">Mt 3:16–4:17</a>). John himself denied being the anointed one but tacitly identified Jesus as the Christ (<a href="?bref=John.1.20">Jn 1:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.14-17">Lk 3:14-17</a>). Jesus’ first disciples followed him because they knew he was the Messiah (<a href="?bref=John.1.41">Jn 1:41</a>). The demons recognized him as “the Holy One [anointed] of God” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.24">Mk 1:24</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.8.29">Mt 8:29</a>). The crowds followed him as the Prophet, the new Moses (<a href="?bref=John.6.14,32">Jn 6:14, 32</a>), but deserted him when they understood that his kingdom was a spiritual, not a political realm (v <a href="?bref=John.6.66">66</a>). The Twelve remained loyal, saying, “We believe . . . you are the Holy One of God” (<a href="?bref=John.6.69">Jn 6:69</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). The confession of the disciples voiced by Peter and approved by Jesus as a divine revelation is “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God” (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.16">Mt 16:16</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). At his trials the decisive factor in Jesus’ condemnation was his claim to be the Christ (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.63-64,68">Mt 26:63-64, 68</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.27.11,17,22,37">27:11, 17, 22, 37</a>).</p>
<p>An important feature in the earliest Christian preaching was the proclamation that Jesus is the Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.36">Acts 2:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.3.18-20">3:18-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.22">9:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.28.23,31">28:23, 31</a>). This remains the earliest (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.16">Mt 16:16</a>) and most basic article of Christian confession (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.23">1 Cor 1:23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.5.1">1 Jn 5:1</a>), affirming that Jesus perfectly fulfilled the role of anointed prophet, priest, and king as the servant of God for his people (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.16">Lk 7:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.25">1 Cor 15:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.22-28">Heb 7:22-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.16">Rv 19:16</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Life and Teachings of</a>; <a href="?item=Messiah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Messiah</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="ThreeAnointedOnesForeshadowTheMessiah"/>
  </body>
</item>