<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Christian">
  <title>Christian</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CHRISTIAN</p>
<p class="fl">Name first given to the followers of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.26">Acts 11:26</a>). When the Christian movement reached Antioch in Syria, the gospel was preached to Gentiles as well as Jews. Such evangelism marked the sect as more than a new type of Judaism; it was a new religion. The Gentiles in Antioch invented a name for the new group. Since members of the group constantly talked about Christ, they were called Christians, meaning the “household” or “partisans” of Christ. Some satire may have been intended in the name. For instance, since the “Augustinians” were an organized group who led the public praise of the emperor Nero Augustus, the citizens of Antioch may have made a comparable Latinized name out of Christ as a joke. Similar groups included Herod’s partisans, the Herodians. “Christ” was an unusual and meaningless name to Gentiles, but Chrestos (meaning “good” or “kind”) was a common name; some pagans called the new sect “Chrestians.” Thus, Suetonius wrote of the Jews being expelled from Rome in <span class="era">AD</span> 49 on account of “Chrestus.”</p>
<p>The Christians themselves apparently did not appreciate the name, but like many other nicknames, “Christian” stuck. It appears only three times in the Greek NT: <a href="?bref=Acts.11.26">Acts 11:26</a> describes its origin; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.28">Acts 26:28</a> records Herod Agrippa II saying satirically to Paul, “In a short time you think to make me a Christian!”; <a href="?bref=1Pet.4.16">1 Peter 4:16</a> instructs believers not to be ashamed if they suffer because the name has been applied to them. No further record of the name appears until the second century, when Ignatius of Antioch became the first Christian to call believers Christians. The Roman governor Pliny (from the area to which 1 Peter was addressed) wrote to the emperor Trajan about people accused in his court of being Christians. From that time on, the nickname became popular among Christians. What better name could there be than one declaring that they belonged to Christ?</p>
  </body>
</item>