<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Citizenship">
  <title>Citizenship</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CITIZENSHIP</p>
<p class="fl">In NT usage (1) designation of belonging to the city or city-state where one was born and reared, and (2) status of sharing in the privileges and responsibilities of the Roman Empire. Thus the apostle Paul claimed to be a citizen of both Tarsus (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.39">Acts 21:39</a>) and Rome (<a href="?bref=Acts.22.27-28">22:27-28</a>).</p>
<p>The right of Roman citizenship most commonly was acquired by birth, as was true of Paul. The status of a child whose parents were married was determined by the status of the father at the time of conception. The status of a child born out of wedlock was determined by that of the mother at the child’s birth. Slaves automatically became citizens when freed by their masters. Although known as “freedmen,” they were often denied the rights of regular freeborn citizens. Greedy magistrates frequently sold the right of citizenship for a high price. The tribune Claudius Lysias received his citizenship in that manner (<a href="?bref=Acts.22.28">Acts 22:28</a>). Citizen rights could also be granted by treaty or imperial declaration. Following the Social War (about 90–85 <span class="era">BC</span>), citizenship was granted to all the inhabitants of Italy. Julius Caesar extended the right to colonies in Gaul (France) and provinces in Asia Minor. According to the census of the emperor Augustus (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.1">Lk 2:1</a>), there were approximately 4,233,000 Roman citizens at the time of Christ’s birth. By the time of Paul’s ministry, the number had reached 6,000,000.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="WhereAreTheseCities"/>
<p>Roman citizens were often required to give proof of their citizenship. That was usually accomplished by reference to the census archives, where the name of every citizen was recorded. In addition, freeborn citizens possessed a small wooden birth certificate containing information about their status at birth. Military documents and taxation tables also carried the names of registered citizens. Further, every Roman citizen had three names, whereas noncitizens generally had only one.</p>
<p>The rights of Roman citizenship were extensive, including the right to vote; to hold office; to serve in the military; to purchase, possess, sell, and bequeath property; to enter into a legal contract; to have a fair trial; and to appeal to Caesar. Thus Paul, upon mention of his Roman citizenship, received an apology from magistrates at Philippi for having imprisoned him without a trial (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.38-39">Acts 16:38-39</a>). He also avoided a scourging in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Acts.22.24-29">22:24-29</a>) and was able to request a trial before Caesar (<a href="?bref=Acts.25.10-12">25:10-12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.26.32">26:32</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>