<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CitiesofthePlain">
  <title>Cities of the Plain</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CITIES OF THE PLAIN</p>
<p class="fl">Group of five cities in the plain or basin of the Jordan River which were also referred to as “cities of the valley.” Since the region in which these cities were located was particularly fruitful, it attracted Abraham’s nephew Lot when the growing size of the flocks and herds forced a division of these two patriarchal communities (<a href="?bref=Gen.13.10-12">Gn 13:10-12</a>). The cities are enumerated as Sodom, Gomorrah, Admah, Zeboiim, and Bela or Zoar. Evidently each was a city-state with its own king.</p>
<p>These cities entered the biblical narrative in four connections. (1) They provided a region where Lot could settle; he ultimately decided to make his home in Sodom. (2) The five kings of the cities of the plain fought with a superior force led by four kings of lands far to the east. In the struggle they were defeated and their cities ransacked. The plunder was great, as was the number of captives, especially women and children (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.1-24">Gn 14</a>). Since Lot was among those carried off, Abraham felt an obligation to launch a rescue operation. In this he was immensely successful, recovering not only Lot but also the other captives and the booty. (3) The wicked cities of the plain later came in for God’s judgment. Their evil was so great that Abraham’s intercession on their behalf was to no avail (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.22-33">Gn 18:22-33</a>). Their depravity is illustrated by the account of the homosexual mob at Lot’s door in Sodom (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.19.1-38">19</a>). Soon thereafter, Lot and his family were ordered to flee before the cities were wiped out. Brimstone and fire obliterated the cities, changing the composition of the whole area. (4) References to the destruction of these cities appear in numerous passages in both the OT and NT to serve as a warning of divine punishment for sin (<a href="?bref=Isa.3.9">Is 3:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.50.40">Jer 50:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.46-56">Ez 16:46-56</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.10.15">Mt 10:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.9.29">Rom 9:29</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>