<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CleannessandUncleannessRegulationsconcerning">
  <title>Cleanness and Uncleanness, Regulations concerning</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CLEANNESS AND UNCLEANNESS, Regulations Concerning</p>
<p class="fl">Aspect of Hebrew religion having physical, ceremonial, moral, and spiritual significance. Though these senses of clean and unclean can be distinguished with reference to their contexts, they also merge into and illustrate each other; the physical and ceremonial contexts point to a moral state of the worshiper and to a spiritual relationship between God and his people.</p>
<p>The OT vision of a people’s relationship with God is along moral and personal lines—God’s personal nature being expressed in his giving of the law to Moses. The personal and uniquely consistent character of Israel’s Lord made him morally a completely different being from the many gods of pagan cultures. Unlike the Lord, the Baals of the Canaanites were capricious and vicious; nobody expected them to be ethically consistent. Israel’s Lord, on the other hand, could be trusted to keep his word (a verbal communication through his chosen prophets). Nobody, not even the high priest or the king, was above the law, which expressed not only God’s character but also his sovereign will for the individual and the nation. His moral consistency carried over into his miraculous interventions into history to protect his people, to judge them and their enemies, and to redeem humanity itself.</p>
<p>Cleanness as defined in the book of Leviticus, therefore, was always conditioned by the presence of the personal God who gave the law. As the people sought to approach the Lord, they necessarily did so on his terms and therefore within the framework of the cultic ceremonies he had prescribed. Details of the Levitical ceremonies were designed to illustrate the moral implications of the sinner’s approach to God and God’s provision for his people to become morally clean in his sight.</p>
<p>The meaning of the Levitical system was stated clearly in the psalmist’s words: “Who shall ascend the hill of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>? And who shall stand in his holy place? He who has clean hands and a pure heart, who does not lift up his soul to what is false, and does not swear deceitfully” (<a href="?bref=Ps.24.3-4">Ps 24:3-4</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). One’s state of cleanness depends not only on external actions but also on an internal relationship with God. As a result, the sinner’s inability to satisfy the moral demands of a holy God leads to his or her complete dependence on God and on God’s provision for satisfying his own demands. That provision was detailed in the law.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#EarlyHistory">Early History</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LeviticalPrescriptions">Levitical Prescriptions</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurificationRites">Purification Rites</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#NewTestamentPerspective">New Testament Perspective</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="EarlyHistory">Early History</p>
<p class="h3">Gentile Religious Background</p>
<p class="fl">The gentile conscience was no doubt a strong influence on the development of ethnic notions of clean and unclean. The subjective sense of sin’s uncleanness is universally encountered in one form or another in the literature of every great religion, whatever explanation is given for it. Many religions have rites of purification based on water and washings. The Hebrews’ ritual avoidance of certain objects, some because of their holiness and others because of their unholiness, finds an analogy in the taboos of many primitive religions, including some of those with which the early Hebrews came into contact.</p>
<p>The similarities between the Hebrew and other ancient religions are easily established by superficial comparison. It would be surprising if there were none. Those differences that give biblical religion its distinctive character, however, must be accounted for.</p>
<p class="h2" id="LeviticalPrescriptions">Levitical Prescriptions</p>
<p class="h3">Ceremonial and Moral Law</p>
<p class="fl">The relationship between the external ceremonial details of the Mosaic law and the internally directed moral requirements of such parts of it as the Ten Commandments is one of the fundamental issues of OT theology. It is possible to demonstrate that, throughout the OT, uncleanness and sin are virtually synonymous. In many passages sin is described as uncleanness (e.g., <a href="?bref=Lev.16.16,30">Lv 16:16, 30</a>; the ordeal of the bitter water in <a href="?bref=Num.5.11-28">Nm 5:11-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.13.1">Zec 13:1</a>).</p>
<p>The relationship between ceremonial and moral cleanness can be illustrated from passages mentioning clean hands on the one hand (<a href="?bref=2Sam.22.21">2 Sm 22:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.17.9">Jb 17:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.22.30">22:30</a>) and a clean heart on the other (<a href="?bref=Ps.24.4">Pss 24:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.51.10">51:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.73.13">73:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.9">Prv 20:9</a>). The prophet Isaiah felt convicted of “unclean lips” when he was in God’s presence; a purifying coal, perhaps representing forgiveness and atonement, cleansed him (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.5-7">Is 6:5-7</a>). In many passages cleanness represents innocence before God (<a href="?bref=Job.11.4">Jb 11:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.33.9">33:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.51.7-10">Ps 51:7-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.9">Prv 20:9</a>), and uncleanness is said to come from sin (<a href="?bref=Ps.51.2">Ps 51:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.16">Is 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.64.6">64:6</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Causes of Uncleanness</p>
<p class="fl">From the Mosaic law a number of causes of uncleanness can be derived.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Some foods were not to be eaten. Various laws concerning animals make a “distinction between the unclean and the clean and between the living creature that may be eaten and the living creature that may not be eaten” (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.47">Lv 11:47</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Permitted food was what was acceptable to God (see also <a href="?bref=Deut.14.3-21">Dt 14:3-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.15.28-29">Acts 15:28-29</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Diseases, especially leprosy, produced an unclean state (<a href="?bref=Lev.13.1-14.57">Lv 13–14</a>). The story of Naaman refers to leprous defilement (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.5.1-14">2 Kgs 5:1-14</a>). The Gospels refer often to lepers (e.g., <a href="?bref=Matt.8.1-4">Mt 8:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.10.8">10:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.11.5">11:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.27">Lk 4:27</a>). Many swellings, sores, and rashes were included under that heading, including Hansen’s disease (modern leprosy). The defilement of disease included all things touched by a diseased person (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.33-57">Lv 14:33-57</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Bodily discharges were unclean, and contact with them defiled a person for various periods of time. Emission of semen produced uncleanness until the evening, whether in intercourse (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.16-18">Lv 15:16-18</a>) or inadvertently during the night (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.10">Dt 23:10</a>). An unnatural discharge, since it usually indicated disease, made a person unclean for seven days after it had ceased (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.1-15">Lv 15:1-15</a>). Menstruation also produced uncleanness lasting seven days after it ceased (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.19-24">Lv 15:19-24</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.11.4">2 Sm 11:4</a>). Sexual intercourse during that time made both partners unclean (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.19-24">Lv 15:19-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.20.18">20:18</a>). Contact with the spittle of an unclean person produced uncleanness for a day (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.8">15:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Dead bodies, or even parts of them such as bone, caused uncleanness (<a href="?bref=Num.19.16">Nm 19:16</a>). Persons who touched a dead body were unclean for a month, and only after that period could they celebrate their own Passover if they had missed it (<a href="?bref=Num.9.6-11">9:6-11</a>). The high priest could not even bury his own parents because of his special ritual responsibilities (<a href="?bref=Lev.21.10-11">Lv 21:10-11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Num.6.6-7">Nm 6:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.13">Hg 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.27">Mt 23:27</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Idolatry was the greatest source of spiritual defilement. The entire nation of Israel was defiled because of it (<a href="?bref=Ps.106.38">Ps 106:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.30.22">Is 30:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.36.25">Ez 36:25</a>), as were the Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Jer.43.12">Jer 43:12</a>). Consequently, contact with Gentiles was thought to produce defilement. The gospel’s universal appeal confronted that conviction (e.g., <a href="?bref=John.4.9">Jn 4:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.28">Acts 10:28</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Gal.2.11-14">Gal 2:11-14</a>). Closely related to the defilement of idolatry was the defilement caused by unclean spirits (<a href="?bref=Zech.13.2">Zec 13:2</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.10.1">Mt 10:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.23-27">Mk 1:23-27</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Laws about Objects</p>
<p class="fl">Certain laws illustrate the principle that uncleanness was transmitted much like a contagion. Dead bodies contaminated what they touched, as did dead insects and certain crawling things (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.29-38">Lv 11:29-38</a>). It is interesting that dry grain, running springwater, and water in a cistern were expressly excluded from that law of contamination; perhaps otherwise, starvation would have resulted, dead insects and mice being found in grain and water every day in an agricultural community. Unclean pottery had to be broken, but wooden vessels merely required washing (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.12">Lv 15:12</a>). Even uncovered pots in a house where a person had died became unclean (<a href="?bref=Num.19.15">Nm 19:15</a>); everyone who entered the house was unclean.</p>
<p>Because of their idolatrous associations, the possessions of pagans were unclean; therefore, booty taken in war had to be cleansed by fire or washing (<a href="?bref=Num.31.21-24">Nm 31:21-24</a>). Clothing of wool, linen, or leather could contract unclean “leprosy” from diseased persons and had to be tested. If the leprous spots (greenish or reddish patches) spread after a test period, the garments had to be burned (<a href="?bref=Lev.13.47-59">Lv 13:47-59</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.14.33-53">14:33-53</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Laws about Places</p>
<p class="fl">The land and people of Israel were holy; they could be defiled by the uncleanness of economic oppression or idolatry (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.17-19">Jos 22:17-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.13.27">Jer 13:27</a>). Jerusalem was a holy city, but it could be defiled by the sins of its people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.22.2-4">Ez 22:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.1.8">Lam 1:8</a>) or by the blood of its slaughtered inhabitants (<a href="?bref=Lam.4.15">Lam 4:15</a>).</p>
<p>The temple could be defiled by unclean persons. It was necessary for Hezekiah to cleanse the temple after Ahaz’s idolatrous worship (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.15-19">2 Chr 29:15-19</a>); Nehemiah had to cleanse the rooms in which Tobiah had been living (<a href="?bref=Neh.13.9">Neh 13:9</a>). One of the functions of the Day of Atonement was removal of impurities transferred to the temple by the sins of the Israelites during the past year (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.16-19">Lv 16:16-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.16.31-33">31-33</a>).</p>
<p>An unclean place received the pieces of a leprous house after its demolition (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.45">Lv 14:45</a>). The valley of Hinnom became Jerusalem’s garbage dump in later years, giving rise to the visions of “Gehenna” as a place of eternal punishment in NT eschatology. Since the Israelite camp was a holy place, care was taken to bury human excrement outside its boundaries (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.12-14">Dt 23:12-14</a>). The value of that simple expedient in preventing disease during military excursions can hardly be exaggerated, since plagues were a great scourge of ancient armies.</p>
<p class="h3">Laws about Food</p>
<p class="fl">Certain kinds of animals were unclean and thus could not be eaten (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.1-47">Lv 11</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.14.3-21">Dt 14:3-21</a>). Animals that died of old age, disease, or injury, or had been wounded by predators, were unclean. Animals that did not both chew the cud and have a cloven hoof were unclean, a definition that included pigs, camels, badgers, and rabbits among others. Israelites could eat only those fish that had both fins and scales. Birds of prey and scavengers were unclean. All winged insects were unclean except hopping insects (locusts, grasshoppers, and crickets). A large classification of “crawling things” was prohibited, including worms, lizards, snakes, weasels, and mice. In addition to all those was the ancient prohibition against eating blood (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.4">Gn 9:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.17.14-15">Lv 17:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.12.16-23">Dt 12:16-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.15.28-29">Acts 15:28-29</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="PurificationRites">Purification Rites</p>
<p class="h3">Purification by Lapse of Time</p>
<p class="fl">Secondary contamination could often be canceled simply by waiting until the evening (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.24">Lv 11:24</a>) or for 7, 14, 40, or 80 days. Dead bodies contaminated what they touched for 7 days (<a href="?bref=Num.19.11">Nm 19:11</a>), as did menstruation (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.19">Lv 15:19</a>). When a child was born, the mother’s unclean condition lasted 7 days for a boy and 14 days for a girl. An additional 33 days for a male child and 66 days for a female were required before the mother could touch any sacred thing.</p>
<p class="h3">Purification by Water</p>
<p class="fl">Contact with unclean things, such as bodily discharges, often required washing of hands and clothing, usually accompanied by the lapse of a day (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.5-11">Lv 15:5-11</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Purification by Ceremonial Substances</p>
<p class="fl">Ceremonial substances used in purification rites included the ashes of a red heifer mixed with water (<a href="?bref=Num.19.1-10">Nm 19:1-10</a>), and (in cases of leprosy) cedarwood, scarlet cloth, hyssop, and blood (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.2-9">Lv 14:2-9</a>). When the altar was used in a purification ceremony, only blood was suitable, since the altar was the place of sacrifice for sin (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.18-19">Lv 16:18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.43.20">Ez 43:20</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Purification by Sacrifice</p>
<p class="fl">Sacrifice was the ultimate source of both ritual and moral purification. All bodily discharges except sexual ones were purified by offerings of doves and pigeons (<a href="?bref=Lev.15.14-15,29-30">Lv 15:14-15, 29-30</a>). Childbirth required a lamb and a bird (<a href="?bref=Lev.12.6">12:6</a>). Poor people could offer birds in place of an animal (<a href="?bref=Lev.12.8">Lv 12:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.14.21-32">14:21-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.24">Lk 2:24</a>).</p>
<p>In sacrifice, blood was symbolic of a life given and therefore a death experienced; the uncleanness of disease or sin was thought of as being transferred to the victim, thus removing the uncleanness (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.7">Lv 14:7</a>). Sacrificial death, therefore, always had a substitutionary element. Only blood sacrifice could provide the moral cleansing necessary for sin itself; such sacrifice was therefore the basis of all cleansing, including that of disease.</p>
<p class="h3">Purification by Fire</p>
<p class="fl">Some contamination could be removed only by fire, such as contamination of metal pots (<a href="?bref=Num.31.22-23">Nm 31:22-23</a>). Incest was punishable not only by death but also by burning the bodies (<a href="?bref=Lev.20.14">Lv 20:14</a>). Idolatry had to be put away by total destruction of the objects and by burning (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.20">Ex 32:20</a>). Cities consecrated to pagan deities were to be burned.</p>
<p class="h2" id="NewTestamentPerspective">New Testament Perspective</p>
<p class="fl">The NT did not reject the OT concept of clean and unclean, but rather reinterpreted it in a new context. It stressed in particular the moral sense of the concept as well as the identification of uncleanness with sin.</p>
<p>The Gospels were written in the context of OT law and its Pharisaic and Sadducean accretions. Jesus obeyed the law but was often at odds with the practical casuistry (system) that had grown up around it. Jesus taught that true defilement came from the sinner’s heart and not from outside contamination (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.14-23">Mk 7:14-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.39-41">Lk 11:39-41</a>). A central element in his teaching was his attack on the ceremonial externalism of the Pharisees. Thus it has been said that Jesus “internalized” the law. It would be more correct to say that he forced attention to the law’s demands on people’s inner lives.</p>
<p>The intrinsic wickedness of demons is underscored by the use of the term “unclean spirit” throughout the Gospels. In fact, the word “unclean” itself always appears in the Gospels in the context of spirit, a detail that illustrates the NT shift of emphasis from ritual uncleanness to sin and its guilt.</p>
<p>An important episode in the life of the early church came in <a href="?bref=Acts.10.1-48">Acts 10</a>, when God taught the apostle Peter that Gentiles were not unclean in themselves and that Peter was obliged to receive them. The result was Cornelius’s conversion.</p>
<p>Jesus’ assertion that uncleanness originates in the heart bore fruit in the apostle Paul’s doctrine of Christian freedom. Paul, a Pharisee who could say of himself that he had never broken an external law, came to see that nothing is unclean in itself (<a href="?bref=Rom.14.14-20">Rom 14:14-20</a>). Throughout his epistles, cleanness is the result of obedience of the heart flowing from regeneration; it is based on the cleansing power of the Atonement (see <a href="?bref=Rom.6.19">Rom 6:19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.2.3-4">1 Thes 2:3-4</a>, where uncleanness is strictly moral).</p>
<p>Christ’s atonement was the final cleansing agent for sin and its moral results (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.14,22">Heb 9:14, 22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.1.7">1 Jn 1:7</a>), doing in reality what the blood of bulls and goats only typified. Thus those who are washed in the blood of the Lamb (<a href="?bref=Rev.7.14">Rv 7:14</a>) are seen as wearing clean white robes (<a href="?bref=Rev.15.6">15:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.8-14">19:8-14</a>). His blood, symbolizing the life given and the death died by the Son at the behest of the Father, satisfies the attributes of personal justice of the triune God. Because the personal character of a righteous Father was vindicated, the personal forgiveness of sinners is morally possible. God can be in history only what he is eternally: he is both just and the justifier of believers in Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.24-26">Rom 3:24-26</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Baptism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Baptism</a>; <a href="?item=Circumcision_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Circumcision</a>; <a href="?item=Uncircumcision_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Uncircumcision</a>; <a href="?item=OfferingsandSacrifices_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Offerings and Sacrifices</a>; <a href="?item=LawBiblicalConceptof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Law, Biblical Concept of</a>; <a href="?item=DietaryLaws_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dietary Laws</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>