<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Clothing">
  <title>Clothing</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CLOTHING</p>
<p class="fl">Clothing mentioned in the Bible is usually referred to in such general terms as “inner garment,” “outer garment,” or “tunic.” Few descriptions give specific details of costumes or clothing, and it is therefore necessary to rely on paintings, pottery, decorations, statues, and bas-reliefs to show the clothing styles of the period.</p>
<p>Many ancient Near Eastern peoples (including the Israelites) kept flocks of sheep before the discovery of spinning and weaving and used the leather of their hides for clothing. Later, wool plucked from the sheep and from branches on which the fleece had accumulated as the animals brushed past was made into a feltlike fabric. Wool remained one of the most important fabrics for clothing throughout the biblical period.</p>
<p>As the seminomadic Israelite tribes became more sedentary in nature, flax was cultivated. It was woven into linen, which became a commonly used fabric. At the beginning of the middle Bronze Age (c. 2000 <span class="era">BC</span>), fine silks began to be imported from China, and wild silk was produced in some areas of the Near East. Cotton was known in Egypt, but it does not appear to have been produced anywhere in Palestine in the biblical period.</p>
<p class="h2" id="MaleClothing">Male Clothing</p>
<p class="fl">Early in biblical times the loincloth formed an important item of male clothing that was worn by all levels of society. Prior to 2000 <span class="era">BC</span>, a type of loincloth was also the customary piece of clothing for all Egyptians, from the lowliest laborer to the pharaoh. At a later period, however, it appeared only as part of military dress (<a href="?bref=Ezek.23.15">Ez 23:15</a>). The inner garment (a tunic or shirt) was made of wool or linen. It had openings for the neck and arms, and appears to have had long sleeves, although some styles had half sleeves. It was worn next to the skin and fell either to the knees or, more often, to the ankles, frequently being belted at the waist. The Greek <span class="greek">chiton</span> (“coat”) and the Roman tunic would have been undergarments of a similar character. A man who was wearing nothing except this undergarment was considered “naked.” The young man who followed after Jesus at Gethsemane at his arrest was probably attired in this manner (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.51-52">Mk 14:51-52</a>).</p>
<p>Generally speaking, the outer garment, formed out of a square-shaped piece of cloth, was referred to as a cloak or mantle. It had openings for the arms and was draped over one or both shoulders.</p>
<p>A Hebrew man was considered improperly dressed without his cloak, and one was forbidden to demand another’s mantle as a loan or pledge. At night, when the other items of clothing were removed, the cloak, which was often made of animal skin or wool, was used as a blanket (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.26-27">Ex 22:26-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.13">Dt 24:13</a>). Cloaks made of goat’s hair or camel’s hair, such as John the Baptist wore (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.4">Mt 3:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.6">Mk 1:6</a>), would have been particularly warm at night.</p>
<p>The coat of many colors that Jacob gave to Joseph was probably a striped shirt or tunic made of leather or wool felt. The entire garment may have been bound with a woolen border (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.3">Gn 37:3</a>). The garment Hannah made each year for the young Samuel was probably a coat or mantle (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.19">1 Sm 2:19</a>).</p>
<p>Cloaks were usually made with a hem; it was this that the woman touched when she came to Jesus for healing (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.20">Mt 9:20</a>). The robe that Roman soldiers placed derisively upon Jesus to symbolize his kingship was probably a purple military cloak such as Roman officers commonly wore (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.28-31">Mt 27:28-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.15.17">Mk 15:17</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.2">Jn 19:2</a>).</p>
<p>The Greeks used the term <span class="greek">himation</span> for an outer garment, similar to the robe that was placed on the prodigal son (<a href="?bref=Luke.15.22">Lk 15:22</a>) when his father celebrated the son’s return with his best food, clothing, and jewelry. The cloak that Paul wore (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.13">2 Tm 4:13</a>) may well have been a circular style of cape that was popular in the first century <span class="era">AD</span>.</p>
<p>Garments were of different qualities and signified rank or office (<a href="?bref=Isa.3.6">Is 3:6</a>). The scribes and prophets wore special mantles symbolic of their professions. Elijah wore a prophet’s mantle (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.13,19">1 Kgs 19:13, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.2.8,13-14">2 Kgs 2:8, 13-14</a>). In NT times scribes wore special robes (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.38">Mk 12:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.46">Lk 20:46</a>).</p>
<p>Christ and his disciples probably wore tunics and sandals, and carried moneybags and staffs (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.9-10">Mt 10:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.8">Mk 6:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.3">Lk 9:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.4">10:4</a>). When Roman soldiers divided Jesus’ clothing after the Crucifixion (<a href="?bref=John.19.23-24">Jn 19:23-24</a>), they cast lots for the inner garment, one woven without any seams and probably made of wool. This was the most valuable of Jesus’ items of clothing.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Footwear">Footwear</p>
<p class="fl">In Bible times footwear consisted of shoes and sandals, which were an essential part of a person’s wardrobe (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.15">2 Chr 28:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.12.8">Acts 12:8</a>). Occasionally sandals had wooden soles, but usually they were leather. Sometimes they had an enclosed upper front and open back. The upper part was typically made of open strips of leather, and sometimes the sandal merely consisted of a sole with thongs laced around the leg or ankle. A woman’s sandals were considered an attractive and fashionable part of her wardrobe (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.10.4">Jdt 10:4</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Jdt.16.9">16:9</a>).</p>
<p>On a long journey through the country, one’s sandals might be carried and saved for arrival in the next town, so that they would not be worn out. (Being barefoot in a town or city was a sign of abject poverty.) Since sandals were so open in design, one can easily understand the necessity for the ritual foot washing of a guest.</p>
<p>Shoes were not worn in the temple or on any holy ground (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.5">Ex 3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.5.15">Jos 5:15</a>) and were also taken off when a person was in a house. It was customary to remove the sandals at a time of mourning. The shoes that the Israelites wore in their wilderness wanderings did not wear out (<a href="?bref=Deut.29.5">Dt 29:5</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ClothandClothManufacturing_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cloth and Cloth Manufacturing</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>