<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Color">
  <title>Color</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COLOR</p>
<p class="fl">The OT and NT have no exact word for “color,” although the word appears several times in our English Bibles. The words translated “color” have quite different meanings in the original languages.</p>
<p>The word most frequently translated “colour” in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> literally means “eye” and suggests “appearance” (<a href="?bref=Lev.13.55">Lv 13:55</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.11.7">Nm 11:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.23.31">Prv 23:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.1.4,7,16,22,27">Ez 1:4, 7, 16, 22, 27</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.8.2">8:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.10.9">10:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.10.6">Dn 10:6</a>). Only <a href="?bref=Lev.13.55">Leviticus 13:55</a> retains the translation “color” in the <span class="sc">rsv</span>. Other words translated as “color” in the <span class="sc">rsv</span> refer to facial appearance (<a href="?bref=Dan.5.6-10">Dn 5:6-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.7.28">7:28</a>), fabrics of variegated colors (<a href="?bref=Pr.7.16">Prv 7:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.17.3">Ez 17:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.24">27:24</a>), stones (<a href="?bref=1Chr.29.2">1 Chr 29:2</a>), and breastplates (<a href="?bref=Rev.9.17">Rv 9:17</a>). Joseph’s “coat of many colours” (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.3">Gn 37:3</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>) and Tamar’s “garment of divers colours” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.18-19">2 Sm 13:18-19</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>) were either long-sleeved robes or richly ornamented tunics that served as a mark of preferred status.</p>
<p>In the NT, a word that means “pretense” is used archaically in <a href="?bref=Acts.27.30">Acts 27:30</a> and was interpreted as “colour” by the <span class="sc">kjv</span> translators. They also added the word “colour” to <a href="?bref=Rev.17.4">Revelation 17:4</a>, evidently to clarify the meaning.</p>
<p>Though many colors are mentioned in the Bible, colors are not particularly singled out for emphasis. Natural colors are seldom mentioned in descriptions. Colors that appear frequently and that are most carefully differentiated are manufactured colors, especially dyes.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ColorsMentionedintheBible">Colors Mentioned in the Bible</p>
<p class="fl">Because the Hebrews perceived color differently than we do in Western culture, it is sometimes difficult to translate precisely the various Hebrew words denoting colors. Thus there is often a wide variation in translations of such words in English Bibles. To provide a base for comparison, this article will follow the <span class="sc">rsv</span> except as noted.</p>
<p>Colors mentioned most often in the OT and NT are the following:</p>
<p>“Black” is the translation of five words in the OT and one in the NT, expressing varying degrees of darkness. The words describe the color of lambs (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.32-33,35,40">Gn 30:32-33, 35, 40</a>), hair (<a href="?bref=Lev.13.31,37">Lv 13:31, 37</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.5.11">Sg 5:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.5.36">Mt 5:36</a>), skin (<a href="?bref=Job.30.30">Jb 30:30</a>), horses (<a href="?bref=Zech.6.2,6">Zec 6:2, 6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.5">Rv 6:5</a>), the sky (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.45">1 Kgs 18:45</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.50.3">Is 50:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.4.28">Jer 4:28</a>), the day (<a href="?bref=Job.3.5">Jb 3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.3.6">Mi 3:6</a>), the darkened sun (<a href="?bref=Rev.6.12">Rv 6:12</a>), and an invading army (<a href="?bref=Joel.2.2">Jl 2:2</a>). Job’s “blackness” (<a href="?bref=Job.30.28">Jb 30:28</a>) has been understood as disease or sadness.</p>
<p>“Blue” probably refers to a blue-purple dye obtained from Mediterranean mollusks. A popular color, it was considered less desirable in antiquity than “royal” purple. Both dyes were produced in Tyre, which at one time had a monopoly on the manufacture of blue and purple dye (<a href="?bref=2Chr.2.7,14">2 Chr 2:7, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.24">Ez 27:24</a>). Ships of Tyre had awnings of blue and purple (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.7">Ez 27:7</a>). Blue was used in the tabernacle fabrics (<a href="?bref=Exod.26.1">Ex 26:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.4.6-9">Nm 4:6-9</a>), the priests’ garments (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.5-6">Ex 28:5-6</a>), in Solomon’s temple (<a href="?bref=2Chr.2.7,14">2 Chr 2:7, 14</a>), and in the Persian court (<a href="?bref=Esth.1.6">Est 1:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.8.15">8:15</a>). Blue is not mentioned in the NT.</p>
<p>“Crimson” is the English translation of three different Hebrew words. This red color of varying shades was derived from certain insects. The word describes certain fabrics in Solomon’s temple (<a href="?bref=2Chr.2.7,14">2 Chr 2:7, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.3.14">3:14</a>) and was used figuratively to describe sin (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.18">Is 1:18</a>). The word translated “crimsoned” to describe garments from Bozrah (<a href="?bref=Isa.63.1">63:1</a>) probably means “vivid colors” rather than a specific hue.</p>
<p>“Gray,” a color found only in the OT, is used exclusively to describe old age—as in gray hair or gray-headed (<a href="?bref=Gen.42.38">Gn 42:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.44.29-31">44:29-31</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.32.25">Dt 32:25</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.12.2">1 Sm 12:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.6,9">1 Kgs 2:6, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.15.10">Jb 15:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.71.18">Ps 71:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.29">Prv 20:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.46.4">Is 46:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.7.9">Hos 7:9</a>). A different word used to describe dappled gray horses (<a href="?bref=Zech.6.3">Zec 6:3</a>) probably means “spotted” or “speckled.”</p>
<p>“Green” translates seven words in the OT and two in the NT. Most of the words refer to vegetation and are descriptive of the fresh or moist condition of plants rather than their color. The following are described as “green”: plants (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.30">Gn 1:30</a>), trees (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.23">1 Kgs 14:23</a>), branches (<a href="?bref=Job.15.32">Jb 15:32</a>), pastures (<a href="?bref=Ps.23.2">Ps 23:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.22">Jl 2:22</a>), herbs (<a href="?bref=Ps.37.2">Ps 37:2</a>), olive trees (<a href="?bref=Ps.52.8">Ps 52:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.11.16">Jer 11:16</a>), thorns (<a href="?bref=Ps.58.9">Ps 58:9</a>), leaves (<a href="?bref=Jer.17.8">Jer 17:8</a>), grass (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.39">Mk 6:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.8.7">Rv 8:7</a>), and wood (<a href="?bref=Luke.23.31">Lk 23:31</a>). In addition to various plants, a dove’s wing (<a href="?bref=Ps.68.13">Ps 68:13</a>), a couch (<a href="?bref=Song.1.16">Sg 1:16</a>), and a righteous person (<a href="?bref=Ps.92.14">Ps 92:14</a>) are also described as “green.” Idolatrous worship practices took place under “every green tree” (<a href="?bref=Deut.12.2">Dt 12:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.4">2 Kgs 16:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.57.5">Is 57:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.20">Jer 2:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.6.13">Ez 6:13</a>), although the word actually describes the luxurious growth of the leaves rather than their color.</p>
<p>Another word, “greenish,” is derived from one of the OT words for “green” and refers to disease (<a href="?bref=Lev.13.49">Lv 13:49</a>) and fungus that forms on the walls of houses (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.37">14:37</a>).</p>
<p>“Purple” was the most highly valued dye in the ancient world. Encompassing shades varying from actual purple to red, it was obtained from mollusks of the Gastropoda class. The first people to use the dye were perhaps the ancient Phoenicians, whose name may come from a Greek word meaning “bloodred.” At any rate, the Phoenicians monopolized the purple industry for many years. Some fabrics were described as being purple: those used in the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.4">Ex 25:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.26.1">26:1</a>), in the garments of the priests (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.5-8,15,33">28:5-8, 15, 33</a>), in Solomon’s temple (<a href="?bref=2Chr.2.7">2 Chr 2:7</a>), in the upholstery of Solomon’s chariot (<a href="?bref=Song.3.10">Sg 3:10</a>), and in decorations of the Persian court (<a href="?bref=Esth.1.6">Est 1:6</a>). Purple was customarily worn by wealthy people and royalty (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.26">Jgs 8:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.31.22">Prv 31:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.5.7">Dn 5:7</a>). Mordecai was rewarded with a garment of purple (<a href="?bref=Esth.8.15">Est 8:15</a>). Daniel was given a similar garment (<a href="?bref=Dan.5.29">Dn 5:29</a>). It was worn by Assyrian soldiers (<a href="?bref=Ezek.23.6">Ez 23:6</a>). Jeremiah described idols that were robed in blue and purple garments (<a href="?bref=Jer.10.9">Jer 10:9</a>). Ships of Tyre had awnings of blue and purple (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.7">Ez 27:7</a>), and purple dye was an item of trade between Tyre and the people of Aram (v <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.16">16</a>). It is used once to describe the color of hair (<a href="?bref=Song.7.5">Sg 7:5</a>).</p>
<p>References to purple in the NT are fewer than in the OT but affirm the continued economic importance of the dye. Purple clothing denoted wealth (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.19">Lk 16:19</a>). Jesus was robed in purple by Roman soldiers (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.17,20">Mk 15:17, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.2,5">Jn 19:2, 5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.27.28">Mt 27:28</a>, “scarlet”). The purple and scarlet garment of the harlot Babylon symbolized royal rank (<a href="?bref=Rev.17.4">Rv 17:4</a>). Lydia of Thyatira was a seller of purple fabrics (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.14">Acts 16:14</a>).</p>
<p>“Red” frequently refers to the natural color of certain objects mentioned in the Bible: skin (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.25">Gn 25:25</a>), pottage (v <a href="?bref=Gen.25.30">30</a>), the eye (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.12">49:12</a>, though the word used here may mean “sparkling” or “dark”), a sacrificial heifer (<a href="?bref=Num.19.2">Nm 19:2</a>), water (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.22">2 Kgs 3:22</a>), the face of a weeping person (<a href="?bref=Job.16.16">Jb 16:16</a>), wine (<a href="?bref=Pr.23.31">Prv 23:31</a>), the eyes of one drinking wine (v <a href="?bref=Pr.23.29">29</a>), clothing (<a href="?bref=Isa.63.2">Is 63:2</a>), a shield (<a href="?bref=Nah.2.3">Na 2:3</a>), and horses (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.8">Zec 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.2">6:2</a>). It is used figuratively to describe sin (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.18">Is 1:18</a>). A leprous disease (<a href="?bref=Lev.13.49">Lv 13:49</a>), a spot on the skin (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.13.19,24,42-43">19, 24, 42-43</a>), and fungus on the wall of a house (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.37">14:37</a>) were discolored with a reddish hue. The Red Sea is mentioned frequently in the OT (<a href="?bref=Exod.10.19">Ex 10:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.15.4">15:4</a>), but the Hebrew words thus translated actually mean “Sea of Reeds.” However, in the NT the Greek word is actually the word “red” (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.36">Acts 7:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.29">Heb 11:29</a>). In the NT, red is used to describe the color of the sky (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.2-3">Mt 16:2-3</a>), a horse (<a href="?bref=Rev.6.4">Rv 6:4</a>), and a dragon (<a href="?bref=Rev.12.3">12:3</a>).</p>
<p>“Scarlet,” a brilliant red hue derived from certain insects, was used for fabrics and yarns and was highly valued in the ancient world (<a href="?bref=Rev.18.12">Rv 18:12</a>). It is difficult to distinguish between “scarlet” and “crimson” in the Bible. A scarlet thread was bound to the hand of Zerah at birth (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.28,30">Gn 38:28, 30</a>). The word describes certain fabrics in the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.4">Ex 25:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.26.1,31,36">26:1, 31, 36</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.27.16">27:16</a>), the priests’ garments (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.5-8,15,33">28:5-8, 15, 33</a>), rope (<a href="?bref=Josh.2.18,21">Jos 2:18, 21</a>), clothing (<a href="?bref=2Sam.1.24">2 Sm 1:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.31.21">Prv 31:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.4.30">Jer 4:30</a>), lips (<a href="?bref=Song.4.3">Sg 4:3</a>), and soldiers’ uniforms (<a href="?bref=Nah.2.3">Na 2:3</a>). Some kind of scarlet material was used during the ratification of the covenant at Sinai (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.19">Heb 9:19</a>), for the cleansing of a leper (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.4-6">Lv 14:4-6</a>) and of a house (vv <a href="?bref=Lev.14.49-52">49-52</a>), for covering the articles on the table of the bread of the Presence (<a href="?bref=Num.4.8">Nm 4:8</a>), and for the ritual of the red heifer (<a href="?bref=Num.19.6">19:6</a>). Matthew described Jesus’ robe at his trial as scarlet (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.28">Mt 27:28</a>). The woman of <a href="?bref=Rev.17.3-4">Revelation 17:3-4</a> was dressed in purple and scarlet and seated upon a scarlet beast. The luxury associated with Rome is suggested by the description of clothing of purple and scarlet (<a href="?bref=Rev.18.16">Rv 18:16</a>). Scarlet, like crimson and red, is also used figuratively of sins (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.18">Is 1:18</a>).</p>
<p> “White” translates a number of words found in the Bible. It is generally the color of natural objects such as goats (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.35">Gn 30:35</a>), hair (<a href="?bref=Lev.13.10">Lv 13:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.5.36">Mt 5:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.1.14">Rv 1:14</a>), diseased skin (<a href="?bref=Exod.4.6">Ex 4:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.13.4,17">Lv 13:4, 17</a>), manna (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.31">Ex 16:31</a>), snow (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.5.27">2 Kgs 5:27</a>), milk and teeth (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.12">Gn 49:12</a>), horses (<a href="?bref=Zech.1.8">Zec 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.3">6:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.2">Rv 6:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.11">19:11</a>), a donkey (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.10">Jgs 5:10</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>; <span class="sc">rsv</span> “tawny”), wool (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.18">Ez 27:18</a>), special stones (<a href="?bref=Rev.2.17">Rv 2:17</a>), light (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.2">Mt 17:2</a>), clouds (<a href="?bref=Rev.14.14">Rv 14:14</a>), and fields ready for harvest (<a href="?bref=John.4.35">Jn 4:35</a>). It is used to describe the color of curtains (<a href="?bref=Esth.1.6">Est 1:6</a>), clothing (<a href="?bref=Esth.8.15">Est 8:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.9.8">Eccl 9:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.7.9">Dn 7:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.16.5">Mk 16:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.3.5,18">Rv 3:5, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.4.4">4:4</a>), the garments of angels (<a href="?bref=John.20.12">Jn 20:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.10">Acts 1:10</a>), and a throne (<a href="?bref=Rev.20.11">Rv 20:11</a>). It is used figuratively to describe cleansing from sin (<a href="?bref=Ps.51.7">Ps 51:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.18">Is 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.12.10">Dn 12:10</a>) and the appearance of princes (<a href="?bref=Lam.4.7">Lam 4:7</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ClothandClothManufacturing_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cloth and Cloth Manufacturing</a>; <a href="?item=DyeDyeingDyer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dye, Dyeing, Dyer</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="SymbolicUsesOfColors"/>
  </body>
</item>