<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ColossaeColosse">
  <title>Colossae*, Colosse</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COLOSSAE*, COLOSSE</p>
<p class="fl">Ancient city in Asia Minor, located in the southwestern part of present-day Turkey, and remembered primarily for the apostle Paul’s letter to the church there (<a href="?bref=Col.1.2">Col 1:2</a>). Colosse was near the Lycus River, a tributary of the Meander. The city flourished during the sixth century <span class="era">BC</span>. According to Herodotus, an ancient Greek historian, when the Persian king Xerxes came to Colosse, it was a city of great size. Another Greek historian, Xenophon, related that Cyrus the Great, founder of the Persian Empire, had passed Colosse still earlier on his way to Greece.</p>
<p>Colosse was situated in the region known as Phrygia and was a trading center at a crossroads on the main highway from Ephesus to the east. In Roman times relocation of the road leading north to Pergamum brought about both the growth of Laodicea, a city 10 miles (16 kilometers) away, and Colosse’s gradual decline. Colosse and Laodicea shared in the wool trade. Thus, the name Colosse was derived from a Latin name <span class="ital">collossinus,</span> meaning “purple wool.”</p>
<p>In the apostle Paul’s time Colosse was a small city with a mixed population of Phrygians, Greeks, and Jews. During his extended stay in Ephesus, Paul may have taught Jews and Greeks who lived in Colosse (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.10">Acts 19:10</a>). Epaphras, a Colossian, visited Paul in Rome and informed him about the condition of the church at Colosse (<a href="?bref=Col.1.7">Col 1:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.4.12">4:12</a>), then was later imprisoned with Paul (<a href="?bref=Phlm.1.23">Phlm 1:23</a>). Others from the Colossian church included Philemon, Apphia, Archippus, and Onesimus, a slave who became a Christian (<a href="?bref=Phlm.1.16">Phlm 1:16</a>). Subsequent history is silent on the church at Colosse. The city was weakened under Islamic rule and was eventually destroyed in the 12th century.</p>
  </body>
</item>