<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CommandmenttheNew">
  <title>Commandment, the New</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COMMANDMENT, The New</p>
<p class="fl">Christ’s commandment for Christians to love each other. The phrase “new commandment” occurs four times in the NT, all in the writings of John (<a href="?bref=John.13.34">Jn 13:34</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.7,8">1 Jn 2:7, 8</a>; <a href="?bref=2Jn.1.5">2 Jn 1:5</a>). Initially, it was a command given by Jesus to his disciples on the night of his arrest: “I am giving you a new commandment: Love each other. Just as I have loved you, you should love each other” (<a href="?bref=John.13.34">Jn 13:34</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The same command occurs elsewhere (<a href="?bref=John.15.12,17">Jn 15:12, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.13.8">Rom 13:8</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.22">1 Pt 1:22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.11,23">1 Jn 3:11, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.7,11-12">4:7, 11-12</a>) but is not called “new” in those passages.</p>
<p class="h2" id="LoveasaCommandment">Love as a Commandment</p>
<p class="fl">Jesus had already commanded his disciples to love their enemies (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.43-45">Mt 5:43-45</a>) and to love their neighbors as themselves (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.25-37">Lk 10:25-37</a>). The “new commandment” demanded that Christians love each other. In no sense did it overrule the other two love commands. Jesus’ command to love those within the church was intended to produce a compelling testimony to those outside the church. It would offer them demonstrable proof (1) that his followers were Christlike in their love toward one another; (2) that the basis for vital human community could be found “in Christ”; and (3) that, by extension, what Jesus said about himself and his work was really true (<a href="?bref=John.13.35">Jn 13:35</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.21-23">17:21-23</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus chose the word used to describe the OT law, giving similar authority to his new commandment. In fact, the law included commands to love (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.18,34">Lv 19:18, 34</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.10.19">Dt 10:19</a>). The apostle Paul thought of love as the “law of Christ” (<a href="?bref=Gal.6.2">Gal 6:2</a>), and James called the love command “the royal law” (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.8">Jas 2:8</a>) and “the perfect law of liberty” (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.25">1:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.12">2:12</a>).</p>
<p>The word “commandment” had another meaning as well. Many Jews in Jesus’ day wrongly supposed that the commandments were given in order that men, by obeying them, could show themselves worthy of God’s blessing (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.3">Rom 8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.3.2">Gal 3:2</a>). Jesus made it clear, however, that love was a natural result of God’s blessing, not a necessary condition for it. For Jesus, the commandment expressed how one who is already living in the joy of God’s blessing should act. Disciples were commanded to love in the same sense that branches were “commanded” to bear fruit: the branch by abiding in the vine, the Christian by abiding in Christ (<a href="?bref=John.15.4">Jn 15:4</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="WhatMadeItNew">What Made It New?</p>
<p class="fl">The character of the new commandment comes from the “new covenant” (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.31-34">Jer 31:31-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.22.20">Lk 22:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.25">1 Cor 11:25</a>), which Jesus inaugurated at the Last Supper. Under the new covenant, God “writes” his law on the hearts of believers (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.16">Heb 10:16</a>). That is, he actively works in them in the person of the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Ezek.36.27">Ez 36:27</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.3.3">2 Cor 3:3</a>), and gives them a new willingness to obey him (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.4">Rom 8:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.16">Gal 5:16</a>). The new commandment of love is the all-embracing, single requirement of the new covenant (<a href="?bref=Rom.13.8,10">Rom 13:8, 10</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.5.14">Gal 5:14</a>). Obedience, therefore, is a gift, because “love is from God; and every one who loves is born of God” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.4.7">1 Jn 4:7</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>). It is the fruit of faith (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.23">3:23</a>) and part of the gospel itself (v <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.11">11</a>).</p>
<p>The close relationship between the new covenant and the new commandment may explain partly why the command to love was called “new.” Christ’s incarnation inaugurated a new age. “The darkness is disappearing,” John wrote, “and the true light is already shining” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.8">1 Jn 2:8</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Anticipating his ascension into heaven (<a href="?bref=John.13.33-35">Jn 13:33-35</a>), Jesus left one inclusive commandment to preserve his disciples in the new age until its consummation at the Judgment Day (<a href="?bref=John.5.28-29">Jn 5:28-29</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.17">1 Jn 4:17</a>). Obedience to the new commandment was supposed to identify them as Jesus’ disciples during his absence (<a href="?bref=John.13.35">Jn 13:35</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.21-23">17:21-23</a>). The love command was thus new in the sense that it had a special function in the new age.</p>
<p>What made the age new was that Jesus Christ’s coming had revealed God the Father with an unprecedented and incomparable clarity (<a href="?bref=John.1.18">Jn 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=John.10.30">10:30</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.6-8">17:6-8</a>). No prophet had ever been able to say, “Anyone who has seen me has seen the Father” (<a href="?bref=John.14.9">14:9</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Therefore Jesus’ demand that the disciples love each other “as I have loved you” (<a href="?bref=John.13.34">13:34</a>) was, by every human standard, new and astonishing. No human had ever loved perfectly like Jesus (v <a href="?bref=John.13.1">1</a>). To follow his example of love, then, was a new commandment. The greatness of Jesus’ love moved him to “lay down his life for his friends” (<a href="?bref=John.15.13">15:13</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). Accordingly, John drew the conclusion that “we ought to lay down our lives for our brothers” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.16">1 Jn 3:16</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). It follows that love means never shutting one’s heart against another Christian in need (v <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.17">17</a>), but rather rejoicing to sacrifice one’s temporal good for another’s blessing.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CommandmentstheTen_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Commandments, The Ten</a>; <a href="?item=LawBiblicalConceptof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Law, Biblical Concept of</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="NewButNotNew"/>
  </body>
</item>