<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Compassion">
  <title>Compassion</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COMPASSION</p>
<p class="fl">Quality of showing kindness or favor, of being gracious, or of having pity or mercy. In the Bible, God is described as being like a compassionate father to those who revere him (<a href="?bref=Ps.103.13">Ps 103:13</a>). Jesus Christ exemplified God’s compassion in his preaching and healing (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.36">Mt 9:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.14.14">14:14</a>), in his concern for the lostness of humanity (<a href="?bref=Luke.19.41">Lk 19:41</a>), and finally in his sacrifice on the cross (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.8">Rom 5:8</a>). The church is to demonstrate compassion as one facet of the love Jesus commanded (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.4-7">Mt 5:4-7</a>; <a href="?bref=John.13.34">Jn 13:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.8-18">Jas 2:8-18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.18">1 Jn 3:18</a>). In scriptural usage compassion is always both a feeling and the appropriate action based on that feeling.</p>
<p>In the OT, compassion describes one aspect of God’s covenantal relationship with his people. One of the Hebrew words translated “compassion” is derived from a root word meaning “womb,” thus comparing God’s love with maternal love. God’s compassion, however, went beyond simply feeling the emotion; it was always demonstrated by definite acts that testified to his covenant with Israel. In spite of Israel’s rebellions, God still had compassion on his people (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.23">2 Kgs 13:23</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.36.15">2 Chr 36:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.38">Ps 78:38</a>), as well as on all his creation (<a href="?bref=Ps.145.9">Ps 145:9</a>). When Israel was chastised, the nation often feared that God had permanently withdrawn his favor (<a href="?bref=Ps.77.9">Ps 77:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.27.11">Is 27:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.63.15">63:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.13.14">Jer 13:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.21.7">21:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.13.14">Hos 13:14</a>). Yet God’s compassion would revive, and he would restore his people (<a href="?bref=Deut.30.3">Dt 30:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.135.14">Ps 135:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.14.1">Is 14:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.49.13">49:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.54.7-8">54:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.12.15">Jer 12:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.30.18">30:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.7.19">Mi 7:19</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT, Jesus Christ, the Son of God, exactly reflected the Father’s compassion in his dealings with a fallen humanity. Jesus healed diseases and infirmities, cast out spirits, empowered others, and sent them out to do likewise. He fed hungry people and, in response to a mother’s grief, raised her only son from the dead. Following Jesus’ example, Christians are to show compassion in dealing with others. Jesus set forth the example in the parables of the Good Samaritan, who had compassion on a wounded traveler (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.33">Lk 10:33</a>), and the Prodigal Son, whose father had compassion on him when he returned home (<a href="?bref=Luke.15.20">15:20</a>).</p>
<p>The apostle Paul listed a number of qualities that the Colossian church “as God’s chosen ones” was to incorporate; the first was compassion (<a href="?bref=Col.3.12">Col 3:12</a>). It was to be an integral part of the concept of Christian community. The Greek word means literally “to be moved in one’s bowels.” The term points to the very core of one’s inner feelings, much as the term “heart” does today. One’s intense inner feelings should always lead to outward compassionate acts of mercy and kindness.</p>
  </body>
</item>