<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ConcubinageConcubines">
  <title>Concubinage*, Concubines</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CONCUBINAGE*, CONCUBINES</p>
<p class="fl">Practice of a man cohabiting with a woman (concubine) who is regarded only as his sexual partner or as a secondary wife in his household, of lower station than his primary wife. Concubinage was practiced in many ancient cultures, especially in Mesopotamia, where the king maintained a harem and where a private citizen might have one or two concubines in addition to his primary wife. Both types of concubinage are referred to in the Bible. A concubine was often a slave or part of the booty of war (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.30">Jgs 5:30</a>).</p>
<p>A man might have a concubine simply as an economical form of marriage, since no dowry, or bride-price, was required. A concubine could add to a man’s prestige by giving him two wives and thus an increased capacity for children. Such offspring were normally delivered onto the knees of the legal wife, thus establishing their legitimacy as family members. The concubine was also another servant to add to the man’s work force.</p>
<p>In the patriarchal period, concubinage was customary (<a href="?bref=Gen.22.24">Gn 22:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.35.22">35:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.36.12">36:12</a>), especially when the primary wife was childless (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.1-3">Gn 16:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.25.5-6">25:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.32">1 Chr 1:32</a>). A concubine could exercise certain rights and secure recognition and inheritance for her offspring (note <a href="?bref=Gen.49.1-28">Gn 49:1-28</a>, where the sons of Bilhah and Zilpah were included along with the sons of Leah and Rachel; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.35.22-26">Gn 35:22-26</a>). The custom was not suppressed by the Mosaic law, which must have included concubines in its treatment of multiple wives (<a href="?bref=Deut.17.17">Dt 17:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.21.15-17">21:15-17</a>).</p>
<p>Concubinage continued through the period of the judges. Gideon had a concubine (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.31">Jgs 8:31</a>), as did an unnamed man of Levi’s tribe (<a href="?bref=Judg.19.1-30">Jgs 19</a>). Abuse of that man’s concubine by men from Benjamin’s tribe caused a bloody civil war (<a href="?bref=Judg.20.1-21.25">Jgs 20–21</a>). During the period of Israel’s monarchy, the luxury of concubines could be afforded only by kings such as Saul (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.7">2 Sm 3:7</a>), David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.13">5:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.15.16">15:16</a>), Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.3">1 Kgs 11:3</a>), and Rehoboam (<a href="?bref=2Chr.11.21">2 Chr 11:21</a>). Royal harems existed in many other cultures of that time, including Egypt, Persia (<a href="?bref=Esth.2.14">Est 2:14</a>), and Babylon (<a href="?bref=Dan.5.2-3,23">Dn 5:2-3, 23</a>).</p>
<p>Concubines were thus a legitimate part of many ancient cultures, even when a society acknowledged the superiority of monogamous marriage. Concubinage was fostered by a desire for prestige and a large family, but could at times degenerate into a license for sexual freedom (cf. <a href="?bref=Eccl.2.8">Eccl 2:8</a>). Concubinage was part of the contemporary Greek and Roman cultures, but it was not in keeping with the teachings of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.1-9">Mt 19:1-9</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CivilLawandJustice_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Civil Law and Justice</a>; <a href="?item=FamilyLifeandRelations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Family Life and Relations</a>; <a href="?item=MarriageMarriageCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Marriage, Marriage Customs</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>