<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Consecration">
  <title>Consecration*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CONSECRATION*</p>
<p class="fl">Separation of persons, utensils, buildings, or places from everyday secular uses for exclusive dedication to holy or sacred use. In the Bible consecration was demonstrated by an appropriate rite or vow. Hebrew expressions imply “separation” (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.2">Ex 13:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.8.10-12">Lv 8:10-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.15.19">Dt 15:19</a>), “dedication” (<a href="?bref=Lev.21.12">Lv 21:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.6.9">Nm 6:9</a>), or “ordination” (lit. “filling the hand,” <a href="?bref=Exod.28.41">Ex 28:41</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.13.33">1 Kgs 13:33</a>). NT references are fewer, but they frequently connote the idea of holiness (<a href="?bref=John.10.36">Jn 10:36</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.14">1 Cor 7:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.4.5">1 Tm 4:5</a>).</p>
<p>In church usage, especially among hierarchical denominations, the term describes solemn rites that establish a bishop. It is also used to describe dedication of shrines, reliquaries, cathedrals, elements of the Mass, or buildings set aside for ecclesiastical functions.</p>
<p>Protestant teaching stresses the priesthood of every believer. Thus all Christians are “saints” (from the same root word as “consecration”), that is, devoted to God for life. In Roman Catholic doctrine the church consecrates (canonizes) great Christians as saints after they have died.</p>
<p>Consecration is significant in relation both to God and to the world. The apostle Paul spells out the term’s meaning in <a href="?bref=Rom.12.1-2">Romans 12:1-2</a>, stressing that consecration involves a living sacrifice to God. Its importance in relation to people and things is a basic theme of the apostle Peter’s first letter. In everyday life each Christian is meant to live out a “holy” and “royal” priesthood for God’s glory (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Pt 2:9</a>). Christians consider the consecration of one’s own personality by the work of the Holy Spirit to be an important mark of spiritual maturity.</p>
  </body>
</item>