<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Conscience">
  <title>Conscience</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CONSCIENCE</p>
<p class="fl">Self-awareness that judges whether or not an act one has carried out or plans to carry out is in harmony with one’s moral standards. The conscience also functions to make a person aware of actions taken that were wrong.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="LetYourConscienceBeYourGuide"/>
<p>Both the English word “conscience” and the Greek word translated as “conscience” in the NT literally mean “to be with knowledge.” In the OT, Adam and Eve hid themselves from God in shame because their consciences passed moral judgment on their disobedience (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.8-10">Gn 3:8-10</a>). All human beings normally have the power of moral judgment: “The spirit of man is the lamp of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, searching all his innermost parts” (<a href="?bref=Pr.20.27">Prv 20:27</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Conscience, then, is a gift of God to provide light in matters of good and evil.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The word “conscience” is found 32 times in the NT (see <span class="sc">kjv</span>), especially in the writings of the apostle Paul. Conscience, in Paul’s writings, is regarded as passing judgment not only on conduct that has already taken place but also on what ought to be done in the future. The behavior of people who are without God’s law shows that the law’s requirement is “written on their hearts” (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.14-15">Rom 2:14-15</a>). Paul’s statement that every person should “be subject to the higher authorities” to avoid God’s judgment and “for the sake of conscience” presupposes that conscience can establish obedience as a moral requirement (<a href="?bref=Rom.13.5">13:5</a>).</p>
<p>To approve, or pronounce “not guilty,” is a function of conscience just as important as self-condemnation. Paul said, “I am not aware [using the same root word from which ‘conscience’ is derived] of anything against myself” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.4.4">1 Cor 4:4</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Yet conscience is neither a final court of appeal nor an all-sufficient guide: Paul went on to say, “I am not thereby acquitted. It is the Lord who judges me.” In another passage Paul called on his conscience to verify his truthfulness, linking the verdict of conscience with the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.1">Rom 9:1</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.12">2 Cor 1:12</a>) without developing the nature of that relationship.</p>
<p>Justifying his ministry to the Corinthians, Paul asked them to judge his conduct in the light of their own consciences (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.1-2">2 Cor 4:1-2</a>). Insisting that God knew the motivation behind his conduct (that is, the “fear of the Lord”), he hoped that the Corinthians’ conscience would also recognize it (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.11">5:11</a>). When Paul wrote to Timothy, he linked a good conscience with sincere faith (<a href="?bref=1Tim.1.5">1 Tm 1:5</a>); when people depart from the faith, their consciences can become “seared” or rendered insensitive by their persistence in evil (<a href="?bref=1Tim.4.2">4:2</a>).</p>
<p>Answering a question about meats offered to idols, Paul spoke of the conscience as exercising judgment on prospective as well as on past behavior (<a href="?bref=1Cor.8.1-10.33">1 Cor 8-10</a>). Some had a conscience that was “weak” due to ignorance (<a href="?bref=1Cor.8.7">1 Cor 8:7</a>); they failed to understand that everything is clean (<a href="?bref=Rom.14.20">Rom 14:20</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>