<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CorinthiansFirstLettertothe">
  <title>Corinthians, First Letter to the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CORINTHIANS, First Letter to the</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DateandOrigin">Date and Origin</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurposeandTeaching">Purpose and Teaching</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">There is no doubt about who wrote 1 Corinthians, for all scholars agree that the apostle Paul wrote it on his third missionary journey while he was living in Ephesus. By this time Paul was a mature, middle-aged (perhaps 55 years old) missionary, fully seasoned from planting churches around a quarter of the Mediterranean world.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DateandOrigin">Date and Origin</p>
<p class="fl">Paul worked in Corinth from about <span class="era">AD</span> 50 to 52. After a brief stay in Jerusalem, he returned to his missionary work, this time at Ephesus (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.1-41">Acts 19</a>), where he ministered for three years (<span class="era">AD</span> 53–55/56). During this period, he wrote at least three letters to Corinth and made a visit as well. His first letter, often called “the previous letter,” is referred to in <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.9-11">1 Corinthians 5:9-11</a>. We know from this reference that the letter was misunderstood, but we know little of its content, for it has been lost.</p>
<p>Sometime in <span class="era">AD</span> 55, after hearing reports from Chloe’s household (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.11">1 Cor 1:11</a>), who were probably members of Chloe’s house church, he dictated a second letter to Corinth, our 1 Corinthians. This was probably sent off in the hands of Stephanas, Fortunatus, and Achaicus (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.17">16:17</a>). Paul would later write a third letter to Corinth, called “the letter of tears” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.2.2-3">2 Cor 2:2-3</a>), and then finally 2 Corinthians.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">Corinth was a seaport city, destroyed by the Romans in 146 <span class="era">BC</span> and rebuilt in 46 <span class="era">BC</span> by Julius Caesar. After 27 <span class="era">BC</span>, it was the Roman capital of Achaia, where the proconsul had his residence (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.12">Acts 18:12</a>). The city itself was really three cities: the port of Cenchrea, about eight miles (13 kilometers) to the east, where ships from the Aegean would unload; the port of Lechaion, about a mile (1.6 kilometers) to the west on the Gulf of Corinth, where the ships would be reloaded, their goods having been transported in wagons over the isthmus and the ships on rollers; and the city itself on the high ground in between.</p>
<p>The acropolis of the city, on top of the steep, high Acrocorinth, contained the temple of Aphrodite, where 1,000 female slaves were dedicated to the service of this goddess of love. This distinctive cult of Corinth was dedicated to the veneration of Aphrodite, goddess of love, beauty, and fertility, who is identified with the Roman Venus. Associated with such religious practices was a general moral degradation. Corinthian morals were notoriously corrupt, even when compared with pagan Rome. Down in the city was the synagogue (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.4">Acts 18:4</a>); for while the city as a Roman colony was largely populated by Italians, it had attracted other peoples from the Mediterranean, among whom were the Jews.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeandTeaching">Purpose and Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">The main concern of Paul in 1 Corinthians was the unity of the church. There was a self-centeredness in Corinth that resulted in building cliques within the church, in flaunting knowledge and liberty in the face of others scandalized by it, and in selfish displays in the worship services.</p>
<p>Two other major concerns also surface in the book. First, along with other pagan practices, the lax sexual ethics of Corinth had influenced the church; Paul needed to erect some barriers. Second, there was a problem in accepting the resurrection of the body; Paul realized that this issue had implications for the core of the faith and vigorously affirmed the resurrection.</p>
<p>Both of these latter two areas, as well as aspects of the unity issue (particularly their concern with knowledge), have been identified by some scholars as Gnostic motifs, leading to the conclusion that Paul was opposing a Gnostic party in Corinth. Careful examination reveals, however, that while some of the elements floating in the Corinthian milieu would later contribute to the development of Gnosticism, it would be anachronistic to call them gnostic. While recognizing protognostic ideas in the Corinthian situation, it is important to keep interpretation within the first-century context.</p>
<p>Thus, the focus of Paul’s concern was the church, its unity and purity. Paul was fighting to keep this church from disintegrating into a number of competing and bickering factions divided over moral and doctrinal issues. Furthermore, he wanted to keep the focus of the church on Jesus, the exalted Lord.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Greeting, <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.1-9">1:1-9</a></p>
<p class="fl">Paul begins with a standard greeting, followed by his usual thanksgiving prayer. Two features stand out. First, the greeting associates Sosthenes with Paul. While we cannot be sure who Sosthenes was, he was surely well known to the Corinthians; probably he was the Sosthenes whom <a href="?bref=Acts.18.17">Acts 18:17</a> identifies as the ruler of the synagogue, following the conversion of Crispus.</p>
<p>Second, Paul stresses the Corinthians’ abilities in speech, knowledge, and spiritual gifts. They had all of these, and these were genuine, but it was precisely these good things that they were abusing. Paul’s solution is not to suppress these gifts (indeed, he thanks God for them), but to place them in a new context.</p>
<p class="h3">Report from Chloe’s People, <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.10-4.21">1:10–4:21</a></p>
<p class="fl">The Corinthians had made Paul, Cephas (Peter), Apollos, and even Christ into party leaders. We are not sure what each of these groups stood for, but one might guess that the Pauline group stressed Paul’s slogans of liberty; the Petrine group, the need to hold to Jewish practices; and the Apollos group, the value of philosophical understanding and oratory. Whatever they stood for, Paul is appalled that it breaks their unity. His first response is to argue that his behavior was not calculated to build a following but to point to Christ. That is, he did not insist on personally baptizing converts; who performed these acts did not matter, since they were all baptized into Christ.</p>
<p>Paul immediately moves to the underlying issue, that of various persons wanting to show themselves better or wiser than others who did not have the insights of their party in the church. Their seeking for wisdom contradicts Paul’s preaching of the gospel.</p>
<p>First, the message of a crucified Christ (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.18">1:18</a>) made no sense within the wisdom and values of either Jews or Greeks. It demanded a whole new way of looking on life—God’s way.</p>
<p>Second, God had not chosen them on the basis of their status in society; quite the contrary, he had made their only status the equal status they received from him (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.26-31">1:26-31</a>).</p>
<p>Third, their faith had not been based on Paul’s oratory but on the gifts of the Spirit that Paul had manifested (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.4">2:4</a>), which had convinced them that God was acting in Paul. Thus, it was not argument that led them to God, but God’s Spirit. Therefore it was the Spirit, not human reasoning, that would continue to reveal God to them. Unless they became fools with respect to the world’s ways of reasoning, they would never be able to rethink life from the perspective of the Spirit, who gives true wisdom.</p>
<p>Fourth, they were not acting on this spiritual level when they claimed Paul and others as party leaders; this activity demonstrates the evil impulse in human beings (“the flesh” or “fallen human nature”) at work since it elevates human servants rather than the God who works equally in each of them.</p>
<p>Fifth, these servants were working together to build one “temple” for God based on the one foundation in Jesus Christ, that is, the church. God alone will judge how each Christian contributes to the work of building the church. But woe to the person who divides the church, for “if anyone destroys God’s temple, God will destroy him” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.3.17">3:17</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). (Note that here the temple imagery is used collectively; the church is the temple. In chapter <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.1-20">6</a> it will be used individually; each Christian is the temple.)</p>
<p>Finally, he points to their overrealized eschatology, for with their spiritual gifts (which were genuine) and vaunted wisdom (which was worldly) they claimed they were reigning with Christ (<a href="?bref=1Cor.4.8-13">4:8-13</a>). Paul, with ironic sarcasm, points out how different this claim is from the lifestyle of the apostles. The apostles lived like Jesus—a life of suffering, expecting exaltation later. The Corinthians were trying to have their exaltation now without crucifixion.</p>
<p>Paul closes this section with an admonition. He softens his words toward some who would be responsive, urging them to copy his lifestyle. The teacher was the message (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.14-16">14-16</a>). Timothy will also faithfully live the truth before them. Then he threatens the “arrogant” (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.4.18">18</a>), pointing out that he will not challenge their words but their spiritual power if he comes.</p>
<p class="h3">The Report from the Corinthian Messengers, <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.1-6.20">5:1–6:20</a></p>
<p class="fl">Paul now turns to three issues raised by oral reports from the messengers bearing the Corinthians’ letter to him.</p>
<p>The first issue is that of church discipline (<a href="?bref=1Cor.5.12-13">5:12-13</a>). Paul cites a case of flagrant immorality—that of incest. This immorality was so clear (even pagans considered it immoral), that it was not a case of ignorance of Christian principles. Further, the church had taken no action but rather boasted in its tolerance, perhaps on the basis of a misunderstanding of Paul’s teaching on freedom from the law.</p>
<p>Paul presents three principles in this section: (1) the primary goal of church discipline is the repentance and restoration of the offender; (2) the secondary goal of church discipline is the protection of the church (<a href="?bref=1Cor.5.6-8">5:6-8</a>); and (3) the church is not to seek to judge or control the actions of evil persons in the world—they are God’s responsibility—but to discipline those within the church (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.9-13">9-13</a>). Paul will use these principles also in the following chapters (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.12-16">7:12-16</a>).</p>
<p>The second issue is that of lawsuits between Christians (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.1-11">6:1-11</a>). The Corinthian society was as prone to litigation as our own, and Christians did not see anything wrong in suing each other. Paul was troubled. If Christians are to judge the world, they certainly should not bring the world in to judge issues within the church. Rather than put their cases before “those who are least esteemed by the church” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.4">6:4</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>, i.e., pagan judges), they should decide the cases within the church.</p>
<p>Paul has an even better way than bypassing the pagan courts, and that is to simply suffer the wrong (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.7">1 Cor 6:7</a>). Applying the teaching of Jesus quite literally (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.38-42">Mt 5:38-42</a>), Paul argues that it would be best to allow themselves to be defrauded. Instead, the Corinthians are willing to step on their brothers in Christ to get what they feel are their rights. This raises the issue as to whether greed is not still in their hearts (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.9-11">1 Cor 6:9-11</a>). While Paul accepts people who formerly did all sorts of evil (for Jesus has cleansed them), he makes it very clear that anyone presently practicing greed or immorality is not part of the kingdom, whatever their doctrinal commitments may be.</p>
<p>The final issue in this section is that of casual sexual intercourse (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.12-20">6:12-20</a>). In a world where virginity was important if a woman wished to be married and where slaves in the temple of Aphrodite were available as prostitutes, prostitution was the major form of casual sex. The libertine party used two slogans: “All things are lawful for me,” a saying that may well have been derived from Paul’s teaching, and “Food is meant for the stomach and the stomach for food”—that is, since the body works this way, it must be the Creator’s purpose. Paul qualifies rather than contradicts their slogans. Freedom is subordinate to other goals (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.12,20">6:12, 20</a>). The body is not made to be used as we wish, but is to be dedicated to the Lord, as the doctrine of the resurrection demonstrates (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.13-14">13-14</a>).</p>
<p>Furthermore, sexual intercourse is an act of the whole person, unlike eating (Paul cites <a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Gn 2:24</a>; cf. Jesus in <a href="?bref=Matt.19.5">Mt 19:5</a>). Therefore, this act takes a member (i.e., the person) from the body of Christ and makes him a unity with a prostitute (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.15-17">1 Cor 6:15-17</a>). Thus immorality is unlike other sins that are external to the self, for it changes the self and thus defiles the body, the place where the Holy Spirit dwells. It disregards the fact that Christ has redeemed the body, and that the whole of the Christian belongs to God, not to the Christian.</p>
<p class="h3">Paul’s Answers to the Corinthians, <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.1-16.4">7:1–16:4</a></p>
<p class="fl">Now Paul turns to the Corinthians’ own issues, building on the answers he has already given to questions they did not ask.</p>
<p>The first issue is that of marriage (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.1-24">7:1-24</a>). The slogan of the ascetic party in Corinth (perhaps a reaction against the libertines of ch <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.1-20">6</a>) was “It is good for a man not to touch a woman” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.1">7:1</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). The Corinthians applied this slogan to both married and unmarried, arguing that married Christians should abstain from sexual relations. Paul clarified the matter with three points. First, he said that this was totally unrealistic, for total abstinence would lead to immorality (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.2,7-9">2, 7-9</a>). Second, when people get married they no longer own their own bodies; their bodies belong to each other for their mutual benefit (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.3-4">3-4</a>). Sexual refusal denies a spouse what rightly belongs to him or her. Third, abstinence is allowed for limited periods by mutual agreement as a type of fast to help focus on Christ (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.5">5</a>).</p>
<p>While Paul will address the issue of the unmarried more fully in <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.25-40">7:25-40</a>, in a side remark he indicates that he is himself content to be unmarried. But since some do not have this gift, full sexual expression in marriage is far better than fighting passion (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.7-9">7:7-9</a>). Once two Christians are married, divorce is unthinkable. A clear word of Christ proves this (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.31-32">Mt 5:31-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.11-12">Mk 10:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.16.18">Lk 16:18</a> and parallels), so there are no exceptions (Paul either does not know of the exception clause in <a href="?bref=Matt.19.9">Mt 19:9</a> or he understands it as referring to something like premarital unchastity discovered before the wedding, not to adultery after the wedding). Although in some cases a Christian couple must live separately, it is always with a view to reconciliation. The teaching of Jesus does not allow him to think of the marriage as ending (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.10-11">1 Cor 7:10-11</a>).</p>
<p>But what if the spouse is not a Christian? Paul applies his principles to a situation for which Jesus did not leave a clear word. First, since Jesus told Christians not to divorce, even in this situation the Christian may not initiate a divorce (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.12-13">7:12-13</a>). Second, since Christians are not to control or judge non-Christians (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.12-13">6:12-13</a>), the Christian does not need to continue the relationship if the non-Christian insists on a divorce (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.15">7:15</a>). Third, far from defiling the Christian (as the relationship in <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.15">6:15</a> does), the Christian will make the relationship holy, with positive results for the children and the possible salvation of the spouse (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.14,16">7:14, 16</a>). While this is no call to remain in situations of physical or sexual abuse, it is a call to remain faithful to a mixed marriage situation.</p>
<p>Paul does not believe that one normally needs to change one’s life situation to serve Christ (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.17-24">7:17-24</a>). Therefore, normally each person should remain in that state of life in which he or she was when called to Christ. Paul’s examples show that he was thinking in terms of marriage or singleness, Jew (circumcision) or Gentile, slave or free, not in terms of situations that might be immoral in themselves. In the case of slaves, they can accept freedom if it becomes available, but it does not make an essential difference in their real state before God or their ability to serve Christ (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.21-23">21-23</a>).</p>
<p>The second issue is that of the unmarried (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.25-40">7:25-40</a>). Paul argues that single people and widows may marry—it is not wrong. Yet he advises them to remain single. Since all in this age is passing away, it would be good to stay single so as to avoid the extra suffering to which marriage exposes a person (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.25-31">25-31</a>). What is more, marriage always divides one’s attention between the Lord and the legitimate needs of the spouse. One must not abandon the spouse or ignore his or her needs in order to serve the Lord, but one can remain single so that the Lord can be the sole focus of life and devotion (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.32-35">32-35</a>). Finally, if one is in a situation in which marriage is expected, the person must make his own decision as to whether he should marry the woman for her sake (and perhaps that of the wider family) or whether he can and should simply care for her as a single person (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.36-38">36-38</a>). Paul closes this section by repeating his general principles (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.39-40">39-40</a>).</p>
<p>The third issue Paul deals with is that of food that has been offered to idols (<a href="?bref=1Cor.8.1-11.1">8:1–11:1</a>). Most meat that was available in the marketplace came either from animals slaughtered as sacrifices in the temples or from groups of animals from which one was offered as a dedicatory sacrifice. To scrupulous Jews, all of this meat would be untouched. Furthermore, pagans invited Christians to feasts in their homes and to private feasts held in the precincts of pagan temples, where trade guilds also held feasts. Paul discusses these issues and uses them to teach wider principles of Christian conduct.</p>
<p>First, love, not knowledge, is the key to correct behavior (<a href="?bref=1Cor.8.1-13">8:1-13</a>). Some Corinthians felt superior because they were convinced that idols had no reality (there is only one God), and therefore any food offered to them was still fit to eat. Paul again accepts their slogans, but counters with the statement, “Knowledge puffs up, but love builds up” (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.8.1">1</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>). God is not concerned with what we know or eat, but he is concerned with whether or not we love our fellow Christians. The concern is not that a fellow Christian might become enraged because one indulged, but that he or she might have a vulnerable conscience and indulge himself, even though he believed it wrong and thus in his own eyes apostasizes from the faith (i.e., rebels against Christ). Such leading astray is not love. It would be better never to eat meat than to lead a fellow Christian into sin.</p>
<p>Second, he points out that one should subordinate one’s own interests to those of others, especially those of Christ and his gospel (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.1-23">9:1-23</a>). Both the examples of the apostles, who expected the church to support them and their families (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.10.5-7">Lk 10:5-7</a>), and Scripture prove that Paul had the right to demand support from the Corinthians. This had not been his practice, for he had normally made tents to support his ministry, though he did accept gifts from other churches. Paul did this to prevent people from thinking he was peddling religion for profit (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.12">9:12</a>) and for the personal satisfaction of doing more than he had to do (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.9.16-17">16-17</a>). This was part of Paul’s larger policy of subordinating his own personal preferences and interests to those of Christ and his gospel (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.9.19-23">19-23</a>).</p>
<p>Third, the bravado of the strong who demonstrate their liberty with disregard of fellow Christians is spiritually dangerous (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.24-10.22">9:24–10:22</a>). It is not who begins but who completes the Christian life that counts; therefore, it is a life of discipline, not relaxed license (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.24-27">9:24-27</a>). Israel in the wilderness presents an example of failure in this regard. They had “baptism” and “the Lord’s Supper” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.2-4">10:2-4</a>), just like the church, yet most of them did not make it to the Promised Land. The reason God destroyed them was simple: they turned to sin. Likewise, the Christian has to be careful not to be so proud about faith and freedom that he becomes careless about sin and falls from the faith (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.12">12</a>). On the other hand, Christians need not be fearful, for the temptation is not more powerful than they are; God has provided a way of escape, if they will take it (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.13">13</a>).</p>
<p>Another link between the Israelites and the Corinthians pertains to partaking of a sacrificial meal (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.14-22">10:14-22</a>). In the Lord’s Supper there is a sharing of the blood and body of Christ, just as real as Israel’s sacrifices on the altar. Food offered to idols is also a sharing, not with the supposed god, but with the real demon that is behind the idol. To try to share at both tables is to provoke God’s jealousy just as Israel did (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.22">22</a>).</p>
<p>A summary of the discussion draws the three chapters together (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.23-11.1">10:23–11:1</a>). Since the food is not changed by being offered to idols, and since all food really belongs to God, one may eat anything sold in the market—do not ask any questions (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.25-26">10:25-26</a>). Likewise, the Christian may eat anything served at a dinner in the home of an unbeliever. However, if someone points out that the food was offered to idols, the Christian should pass it by, not because it would hurt him, but because it is an issue with the person who raised the question, and the Christian is concerned about the good of his neighbor (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.27-30">27-30</a>). In other words, follow Paul’s example as he patterns himself in turn after Christ, who served others rather than himself. Act so that God’s reputation and character shine through even in what one eats (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.31">31</a>); try to offend no one but to benefit each person in moving him toward salvation (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.32">32</a>).</p>
<p>The fourth issue Paul deals with is that of order in church meetings (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.2-14.40">11:2–14:40</a>). The Corinthians’ house churches had lively meetings, but rather than showing unity in Christ, they demonstrated selfishness. Paul had no desire to change what they did; he did want to change how they did it.</p>
<p>The first problem in the meetings was the behavior of married women (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.1-16">11:1-16</a>). The sign of marriage in that day was the wearing of a veil or distinctive hairstyle, as a ring is today. Women praying and delivering prophecies in church was no issue for Paul, but the women may have felt that this loosed them from their husbands (cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.12.25">Mk 12:25</a>) and therefore was a reason to set aside their veils. Paul argues that husband and wife are intimately joined, just as humans are to God (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.3">1 Cor 11:3</a>). Therefore as humans should not shame but glorify God, so the wife should act toward her husband. Thus, while Paul approves of ministry by women, he puts marriage first.</p>
<p>The second problem in the meetings was that of making class distinctions (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.17-34">11:17-34</a>). Until the weekly Lord’s Supper began to be turned into the sacrifice of the Mass in the third and fourth centuries, it was a full shared meal. Middle- and upper-class Christians could come earlier to the church gatherings and also provide better food and drink for themselves. Following the customs of pagan clubs, they had no scruples against starting early and feasting as befit their class, so long as at least simple food was provided for the slaves and peasants who could not come as early (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.21">21</a>). This shamed the poorer Christians and made them feel class distinctions keenly (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.22">22</a>). This, argues Paul, is not the Lord’s Supper but a sham (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.20">20</a>).</p>
<p>Paul repeats the words of institution to point out that they all are participating in Christ’s body and blood (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.16-17">10:16-17</a>), not their own meal. To do it in an unworthy manner, with divisions and class distinctions among them, is to profane his meal by failing to demonstrate the unity of his body, the church (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.29">11:29</a>), and thus invite his judgment, which they were already experiencing. Instead, they should examine their own motives and truly gather as one to eat this common meal.</p>
<p>The third problem in their meetings was the use of spiritual gifts (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.1-14.40">12:1–14:40</a>). It is possible that some people in these house churches, under the influence of Gnostic ideas in which the spiritual is good and the material evil, and feeling inspired by a spirit, cried out, “Jesus [meaning the human Jesus as opposed to the spiritual Christ] be cursed.” It is not the Spirit of God saying this, argues Paul, for the Spirit in us cries the basic Christian confession, “Jesus is Lord.”</p>
<p>Others in these churches were exalting their own particular gift, especially the gift of tongues, shouting down others or refusing to give them a turn. There is only one Spirit and he gives all the gifts, Paul argues (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.4-6">12:4-6</a>). The Spirit manifests himself sovereignly in each Christian, not simply for the Christian’s own benefit, but for the good of all (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.7">7</a>). Since it is the Spirit, not a given manifestation, that the Christian has, the gifts manifested could change from meeting to meeting.</p>
<p>That same Spirit has made all Christians into one organic unity in Christ (<a href="?bref=1Cor.12.12-13">12:12-13</a>). Thus not only does the one Spirit give all the gifts—all are equally inspired—but all the gifts are equally needed for the proper functioning of the body of Christ (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.14-26">14-26</a>). No one can say that his lack of a given gift makes him less a part of the body; indeed, the less noticeable gifts may well be the more important. Thus, within the body of Christ, there are not only different manifestations of the Spirit through individuals in a given meeting, but different ministries or functions of individuals in the body (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.27-31">27-31</a>).</p>
<p>Therefore, it is not the demonstration of a particular gift that shows one’s spirituality, but how one demonstrates it—that is, whether one manifests it with love (<a href="?bref=1Cor.13.1-13">13:1-13</a>). Any gift exercised for selfish purposes may be a genuine gift of the Spirit, but it is worthless to the individual (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.13.1-3">1-3</a>). This is because love is the opposite of selfishness (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.13.4-7">4-7</a>). In fact, the gifts of the Spirit are only for the period between Jesus’ first coming and his second coming, when the kingdom of God will be perfectly revealed and the King will be present in person, and thus the intermediary gifts of the Spirit will be no longer necessary (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.13.10,12">10, 12</a>). It is not giftedness but faith and hope that will have a reward then, and love, which is the greatest, because it will continue as Christians live in perfect love with each other and with Jesus (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.13.13">13</a>).</p>
<p>Applying this to Corinth, Paul argues that while one should desire all the gifts, love dictates that prophecy should be the gift of choice in the church meetings (<a href="?bref=1Cor.14.1-25">14:1-25</a>). The Corinthians had evidently been stressing tongues. Tongues without interpretation is of little value to anyone except to the speaker himself. It does not build anyone up; its confusion seems madness to outsiders. Outside the church meetings there is a role for tongues, both as a sign of judgment (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.21">21</a>) and for private devotion (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.18">18</a>), but inside, only with interpretation. Prophecy, however, both builds up and convicts, and thus is to be sought in the meetings.</p>
<p>In the church meetings, then, both gifts and order are to prevail (<a href="?bref=1Cor.14.26-40">14:26-40</a>). All types of gifts are allowed expression with a goal of mutual edification, not selfish demonstration (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.26">26</a>). Tongues speakers must have an interpreter; both they and prophets must speak in turn, with time being taken to evaluate the utterances after every few speakers (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.27-33">27-33</a>). Furthermore, the women, who were perhaps chatting in the service (perhaps due to habits learned in Jewish synagogues, where they were segregated and did not participate) are to cease their chattering, pay attention, and learn, asking questions at home if they do not understand (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.34-36">34-36</a>). In his concluding summary, Paul states that all should be done in an orderly manner (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.37-40">37-40</a>).</p>
<p>The fifth issue Paul deals with is that of the resurrection of the dead (ch <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-58">15</a>). Some of the problems mentioned earlier concerning loose morals (chs <a href="?bref=1Cor.5.1-6.20">5–6</a>), ascetic denial, sexuality (ch <a href="1Cor.7.1-40">7</a>), or feeling one was resurrected already (ch <a href="1Cor.11.1-34">11</a>) point to the fact that some Corinthians did not believe in the resurrection of the body, though they apparently believed in the resurrection of Jesus and the immortality of the human soul.</p>
<p>Paul reaffirms that the resurrection of Jesus is an essential part of the gospel message (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-19">15:1-19</a>). The unified voice of the church was that Jesus not only died but rose again and appeared to numerous witnesses (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.3-11">3-11</a>). If they were consistent in their antiresurrection argument, Christ could not have been raised. Yet if this were the case, the whole gospel message is false and all their hopes for salvation are in vain (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.12-19">12-19</a>).</p>
<p>Since Christ has been raised, Christians will also be raised because of their solidarity with him (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.20-28">15:20-28</a>). As they had experienced the results of being in Adam, so now they will experience the results of being in Christ. But resurrection does not happen at once. There are progressive stages: (a) Christ was first; (b) Christians will be raised at his coming; (c) Christ must reign until he extends kingdom rule over the whole world, destroying all demonic powers (including death itself); and (d) then he will turn over the perfected kingdom to the Father (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.23-28">23-28</a>).</p>
<p>Resurrection hope also explains Christian practices such as baptizing people on behalf of others who had died (probably people who had turned to Christ but had died before they could be baptized, <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.29">15:29</a>), and willingness to risk death for Christ (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.30-32">30-32</a>).</p>
<p>Paul admits that there are intellectual problems involved, but these are solved when one realizes that resurrection includes both continuity and discontinuity (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.35-50">15:35-50</a>). Just as seed and plant are the same and yet different, and just as many types of bodies exist, so it is with the resurrection. What was perishable, dishonorable, weak, and physical (i.e., in Adam) will be raised imperishable, glorious, powerful, and spiritual (i.e., in Christ). Indeed, it is only as Christians thus become like Christ, the heavenly man, that they can become part of God’s kingdom.</p>
<p>With excitement Paul shares his real hope, that of transformation (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.51-58">15:51-58</a>). At the coming of Christ the dead will be raised and transformed. But the living will also need transformation, and this will happen in a split second, making all of them impervious to death. Then they will truly know the victory already present in Jesus’ resurrection (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.54-57">54-57</a>). A concluding summary draws the practical conclusion that this teaching should give them assurance of a reward for anything done for Christ now (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.58">58</a>).</p>
<p>The sixth issue Paul deals with is that of the collection for the needy Jerusalem church (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.1-4">16:1-4</a>). Because of famine in Judea in the 40s, the church there had become impoverished. Partly because of the need and partly to further the unity of the church, Paul took up a collection in some of his churches for the Judean church. He answers the Corinthians’ practical queries by stating that the collection should be made weekly according to ability, not all at once when Paul arrives (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.2">16:2</a>). When he comes, he will send off the money with their own messengers. Paul remains vague about whether or not he will accompany them, allaying suspicions that somehow he plans to profit from it (cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.8.1-9.15">2 Cor 8–9</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Final Remarks and Closing, <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.5-24">16:5-24</a></p>
<p class="fl">Having come to the end, Paul discusses his travel plans, including his intention for a lengthy visit whenever he leaves Ephesus (cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.1-24">2 Cor 1</a>). Timothy was either coming with the letter or else would arrive shortly after another mission; they were to respect him and help him return. Paul points out that he urged Apollos to visit Corinth, in case some suspect Paul is against him. A closing formal exhortation to firm faith and love leads into his final customary greetings. He praises the Corinthian messengers who had brought him their letter (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.15-18">16:15-18</a>) and sends greetings from Aquila and Prisca (Priscilla), his comissionaries who had helped him found the church in Corinth (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.2-3,18">Acts 18:2-3, 18</a>). Referring to the customary greeting in the church, he tells them to greet each other with a kiss on each cheek (<a href="?bref=1Cor.16.20">16:20</a>). Paul then takes the pen from the scribe, as was normal, and writes the closing exhortation—placing a curse on those who do not love Jesus, the common Aramaic expression used in the church “Come, O Lord” (<span class="ital">Marana tha,</span> perhaps used to close services), and providing an assurance of his own love for them (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.21-24">21-24</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ActsoftheApostlesBookofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Acts of the Apostles, Book of the</a>; <a href="?item=Corinth_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Corinth</a>; <a href="?item=CorinthiansSecondLettertothe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Corinthians, Second Letter to the</a>; <a href="?item=PaultheApostle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paul, The Apostle</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>