<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CounselCounselor">
  <title>Counsel, Counselor</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COUNSEL, COUNSELOR</p>
<p class="fl">Advice; adviser, especially on legal matters (such as a lawyer). In Bible times a counselor in a king’s court was like a U.S. cabinet member today. A counselor might at times have been in line to succeed the king. Ahithophel, counselor to David and Absalom, gave advice as sound as the “oracle of God” (<a href="?bref=2Sam.16.23">2 Sm 16:23</a>). The elders of Israel counseled King Rehoboam (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.6">1 Kgs 12:6</a>), as did the friends with whom Rehoboam had grown up (vv <a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.7-8">7-8</a>), although his friends gave poor advice. The Bible mentions official counselors in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Isa.19.11">Is 19:11</a>) and Babylon (<a href="?bref=Dan.3.2-3">Dn 3:2-3</a>).</p>
<p>A wise person seeks counsel when making plans: “Plans go wrong for lack of advice; many counselors bring success” (<a href="?bref=Pr.15.22">Prv 15:22</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). One’s counselors may be one’s parents (<a href="?bref=Pr.1.8">1:8</a>), older people (<a href="?bref=Ezek.7.26">Ez 7:26</a>), prophets (<a href="?bref=2Chr.25.16">2 Chr 25:16</a>), wise men (<a href="?bref=Jer.18.18">Jer 18:18</a>), or friends (<a href="?bref=Pr.27.9">Prv 27:9</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). Some counselors are evil, giving deceitful advice (<a href="?bref=Pr.12.5">Prv 12:5</a>).</p>
<p>According to the Bible, God also counsels. He frustrates the counsel of the nations who oppose him (<a href="?bref=Ps.33.10">Ps 33:10</a>), but his own counsel endures for many generations (v <a href="?bref=Ps.33.11">11</a>). No one may counsel the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.13">Is 40:13</a>). His Messiah is called “Wonderful Counselor” (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.6">9:6</a>).</p>
<p>According to the NT, the Spirit counsels or comforts believers (<a href="?bref=John.14.16-17">Jn 14:16-17</a>). Christ sends the Holy Spirit to his people (<a href="?bref=John.16.7">16:7</a>), and the Spirit, also called the Spirit of truth, bears witness to Christ (<a href="?bref=John.15.26">15:26</a>). The ascended Jesus Christ is seen as a counselor in God’s heavenly court (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.1">1 Jn 2:1</a>, “advocate”).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=SpiritofGod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Spirit of God</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>