<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="CoveringoftheHead">
  <title>Covering of the Head</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">COVERING OF THE HEAD</p>
<p class="fl">Issue pertaining to female decor discussed by the apostle Paul in <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.2-16">1 Corinthians 11:2-16</a>. In Paul’s day Jewish women always wore veils in public and Greek women generally went veiled—a practice that showed deference to authority and dignified the wearer.</p>
<p>Disagreement arose in the church at Corinth when women prayed publicly with uncovered heads. Since women had traditionally covered their heads out of respect for men (or “husbands”), it seemed shameful for a woman to pray or prophesy unveiled; it was viewed as if her head were shaven (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.5">5</a>), a sign of dishonor.</p>
<p>Paul responded to that confusion with a brief theological excursus about Creation (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.8">8</a>). An enigmatic reference to “angels” (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.10">10</a>) precedes his statement on the interdependence of men and women (vv <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.11-12">11-12</a>). Some interpret the word translated “veil” (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.10">10</a>) as a symbol of new authority, since in the synagogues women were permitted no part in Jewish worship services. In contrast, a Christian woman could participate in Christian worship provided she wore a veil.</p>
<p>Paul spoke of “nature” as teaching men and women on the subject. Some scholars think he meant that since a woman’s long hair was her pride (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.15">15</a>), she should cover her head. Some think that the phrase referred to hairstyle. Others believe Paul was saying that a veil was not needed since a woman’s hair is given to her for a covering (v <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.15">15</a>). Paul encouraged freedom but also insisted on order in the churches. He upheld certain customs to avoid offense (see <a href="?bref=1Cor.9.19-23">1 Cor 9:19-23</a>). Yet he challenged other customs for the sake of the gospel’s integrity (see <a href="?bref=Gal.6.12">Gal 6:12</a>).</p>
<p>In most church traditions, covering the head is considered necessary only in societies where it is considered proper for women to be veiled. Some groups, however, believe that all women should still wear hats or something on their heads in church services. In a few groups women regularly wear small “coverings” in their hair so they will always be able to pray with their heads “covered.”</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=CorinthiansFirstLettertothe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Corinthians, First Letter to the</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>