<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Palestine">
  <title>Palestine*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PALESTINE*</p>
<p class="fl">Country on the eastern shore of the Mediterranean Sea, also known as Canaan and Israel. Palestine was situated at the west end of the Fertile Crescent—that arching stretch of highly productive land that ran from the Persian Gulf through Mesopotamia and Syria to Egypt. Palestine lay in a unique position, for it constituted a land bridge between Mesopotamia and Egypt, the two primary cultural centers of the ancient Near East. It also served as a connection between the continents of Asia and Africa and as a continental link between Africa and Europe. Trade moved by well-defined routes as goods were brought into the Fertile Crescent from as far as northern Europe, India, and south of Egypt. The same roads were followed by prospective conquerors as they moved their armies from area to area in quest of power and wealth.</p>
<p>It was the land promised by God to Abraham and his descendants, the homeland of God’s chosen people, and the geographical scene for much of biblical history. It has become a land sacred to three great world religions: Judaism, Christianity, and Islam. Physically, Palestine is a kind of microcosm. In a stretch of 150 miles (241.4 kilometers) one can find almost every kind of climate and terrain known on the earth. It has fertile plains, sandy deserts, rocky wastes, forests, mountains, lakes, and rivers. With such a variety in so small an area, the land provides sharp contrasts. In the north, Mt Hermon stands perpetually snowcapped at an altitude of about 9,100 feet (2,773.7 meters), while a scant 100 miles (160.9 kilometers) distant in the subtropical depression of the Jordan Valley is the Dead Sea, representing the deepest spot on the earth.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Name">Name</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Territory">Territory</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Climate">Climate</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Geography">Geography</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Name">Name</p>
<p class="fl">This land has been known by many names over its long history. The country seems to have been named after the maritime region, perhaps because this was the area that most foreigners contacted. So the land was called Canaan and later named after Philistia. In the table of nations, Canaan is said to have extended from Sidon in the north toward Gerar as far as Gaza and east toward the Cities of the Plain (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.19">Gn 10:19</a>). The name Canaan appears in the Bible; the first occurrence of the name as that of a country or region is in <a href="?bref=Gen.11.31">Genesis 11:31</a>.</p>
<p>After the Israelite conquest of Canaan, the country was known as the land of Israel (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.19">1 Sm 13:19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.22.2">1 Chr 22:2</a>). With the division of the kingdom in the reign of Rehoboam (930 <span class="era">BC</span>), the name Israel went with the northern kingdom, and the southern kingdom was known as Judah (later, Judea).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Territory">Territory</p>
<p class="fl">The earliest reference to the extent of Palestine appears in the promise of the land to Abraham and to his descendants (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.18-21">Gn 15:18-21</a>). Here the borders are given as the River of Egypt (Wadi el-Arish) in the southwest to the Euphrates River in the northeast. It is further defined in terms of the peoples who occupied it at that time, 10 in all, including the Kenites, the Kenizzites, the Kadmonites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Rephaim, the Amorites, the Canaanites, the Girgashites, and the Jebusites. In <a href="?bref=Gen.17.8">Genesis 17:8</a> the land is called simply “all the land of Canaan.”</p>
<p>The Lord gave more detailed directions to Moses concerning the borders of the land that Israel was to occupy (<a href="?bref=Num.34.1-12">Nm 34:1-12</a>). The southern boundary was to be from the River of Egypt to the south of Kadesh-barnea and along the wilderness of Zin to the southern extremity of the Dead Sea. The western boundary was the Mediterranean, the northern border was set at the entrance to Hamath, and the eastern limit was the Jordan River and the Dead Sea.</p>
<p>The greatest extent of the Promised Land is seen in the Lord’s declaration to Moses that he would set the bounds of Israel from the Red Sea to the Sea of the Philistines (Mediterranean) and from the wilderness to the Euphrates River (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.31">Ex 23:31</a>). Historically, during the period of the judges and the reign of Saul, Israel did not conquer the land that had been given to the tribes in the division under Joshua. The military strength of David and the diplomacy of Solomon enabled them to achieve a marked expansion of Israelite rule. David defeated Hadadezer, king of Zobah, and thus pushed his northern frontier to the Euphrates River; he defeated Syria, Ammon, Moab, Edom, and Amalek, enlarging the kingdom also to the east and south (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.1-14">2 Sm 8:1-14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.18.1-13">1 Chr 18:1-13</a>). Solomon had a fleet of merchant ships stationed at Ezion-geber on the Gulf of Aqaba. He also engaged in copper mining in that area.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Climate">Climate</p>
<p class="fl">It has been said that the climate of Palestine is more varied than that of any other area of comparable size in the world. Generally, the climate may be described as temperate; at Jerusalem, for example, the temperature extremes range from 26°F (-3.3°C) to 107°F (41.6°C), and the average annual rainfall is about 20 inches (50.8 centimeters). The coastal plain is warmer and has been compared to the east coast of Florida. The average annual temperature at Jaffa (Joppa) is 67° F (19.4°C). The Jordan Valley in the area of the Dead Sea is subtropical; in summer its temperatures may reach 120°F (48.8°C).</p>
<p>Rainfall is seasonal, with rain coming in the cooler months of the year as the prevailing west wind brings moisture over the comparatively colder land area, much like the “lake effect” snows of the Great Lakes region of the United States. The rainy season extends from October to April. Within this time the Israelites singled out two periods (<a href="?bref=Jer.5.24">Jer 5:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.23">Jl 2:23</a>), the former rain and the latter rain, with the former rain occurring in the months of October and November and the latter rain falling in March and April. The coastal area receives about 28 inches (71.1 centimeters) of rain annually, while the average for the country in general is 22 to 24 inches (55.9–70 centimeters).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Geography">Geography</p>
<p class="fl">For purposes of description, the land of Palestine may be conveniently divided into five longitudinal sections:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. The Maritime or Coastal Plain</p>
<p class="list">2. The Shephelah</p>
<p class="list">3. The Western Plateau or Hill Country</p>
<p class="list">4. The Arabah or Jordan Valley</p>
<p class="list">5. The Eastern Plateau or Transjordan</p>
<p class="fl">These divisions are based essentially on differences in elevation, but other geographic elements also serve to mark their limits or otherwise distinguish them.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfJerusalemInJudea"/>
<p class="h3">The Maritime or Coastal Plain</p>
<p class="fl">The Maritime or Coastal Plain may be divided into three separate plains from south to north: the plain of Philistia, the plain of Sharon, and the plain of Acre.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. The plain of Philistia begins with the Wadi el-Arish, or River of Egypt, and extends north to the Nahr el-Auja, about five miles (8 kilometers) north of Joppa. This plain is about 70 miles (112.6 kilometers) long and reaches its greatest width in the latitude of Gaza, where it measures about 30 miles (48.3 kilometers). Along the Mediterranean there were dunes of sand, but for the most part, this area was very fertile and admirably suited for the production of grain.</p>
<p class="list">2. The plain of Sharon is not sharply demarcated from the Philistine plain and was probably under Philistine control, but the OT recognizes it as a separate entity (cf. <a href="?bref=Song.2.1">Sg 2:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.65.10">Is 65:10</a>). The plain extends north to Mt Carmel. On the coast are the town of Dor, which is mentioned in “The Tale of Wenamon,” and the city of Caesarea, where Herod the Great did much building.</p>
<p class="list">3. Beyond the promontory of Carmel lies a bay on which was situated the city named Ptolemais (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.7">Acts 21:7</a>), also known as Acre or Acco (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.31">Jgs 1:31</a>). Here a narrow plain stretches some 20 miles (32.2 kilometers) to the Ladder of Tyre (Ras en-Nakurah). The Kishon River (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.7,13">Jgs 4:7, 13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.40">1 Kgs 18:40</a>) flows through this plain to the sea.</p>
<p class="h3">The Shephelah</p>
<p class="fl">The Shephelah constitutes a kind of “midlands,” intermediate between the lowlands of the coastal plain and the highlands of the Western Plateau, with an elevation of about 500 to 1,000 feet (152.4– 304.8 meters) and a width of only a few miles. It extends from the valley of Aijalon to Beersheba.</p>
<p>The valleys of the Shephelah produced grain crops, while the hills were well suited for grapes and olives. The region was very important strategically, because it afforded approaches to Jerusalem.</p>
<p class="h3">The Western Plateau or Hill Country</p>
<p class="fl">The Western Plateau or Hill Country ranges from 1,000 to 4,000 feet (304.8–609.6 meters) in elevation and covers some 150 miles (241.4 kilometers) from Lebanon to Beersheba. It may also be divided into three areas: Galilee, Samaria, and Judea.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Galilee may be regarded as two parts, Upper Galilee (2,000–4,000 feet, or 609.6–1,219.2 meters) and Lower Galilee (below 2,000 feet, or 609.6 meters). The area was agricultural and pastoral, like much of Palestine, and was open to invasion. The highways that traversed Galilee made it a cosmopolitan district, so that <a href="?bref=Isa.9.1">Isaiah 9:1</a> calls it “Galilee of the nations.”</p>
<p class="list">2. Samaria was also suitable for crops and pasture. The brothers of Joseph were grazing their flocks in the plain of Dothan when Joseph visited them and became the victim of their conspiracy (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.17">Gn 37:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Judea has an elevation of about 2,000 to 3,500 feet (609.6–1,066.8 meters) and reaches some 60 miles (96.5 kilometers) from Bethel to Beersheba. The city of Jerusalem stands at an elevation of 2,654 feet (808.9 meters), surrounded by mountains and valleys that served as part of its defense system (<a href="?bref=Ps.125.2">Ps 125:2</a>). This was the heart of the nation, for from the time of David onward, the capital was here, and more important, the ark of the covenant had been brought here during David’s reign. As the Lord had long foretold, Jerusalem had become the center of his worship; here Solomon built the temple, one of the greatest structures ever made.</p>
<p class="h3">The Arabah or Jordan Valley</p>
<p class="fl">The Arabah or Jordan Valley presents the extremes of height and depth. Mt Hermon rises to 9,166 feet (2,793.8 meters), while the surface of the Dead Sea lies 1,275 feet (395 meters) below sea level, and at its deepest part the sea plunges another 1,300 feet (396.2 meters).</p>
<p class="list-space">1. The North Arabah or Upper Jordan Valley. The Jordan River has four sources, all near Mt Hermon. The Jordan flows through what was Lake Huleh, now partly drained and designated as a wildlife refuge. Two miles (3.2 kilometers) below the Huleh basin is the Bridge of Jacob’s Daughters, by which the old road to Damascus crossed the river. The Jordan then flows into a gorge some 1,200 feet (365.8 meters) deep.</p>
<p class="list">2. The Sea of Galilee, about 10 miles (16.1 kilometers) from Huleh, has an elevation of -685 feet (-208.8 meters). It measures 15 by 8 miles (24.1 by 12.9 kilometers), with a maximum depth of 750 feet (228.6 meters). The shape of the lake gave it the OT name, Chinnereth, meaning “harp” (<a href="?bref=Num.34.11">Nm 34:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.13.27">Jos 13:27</a>). In the NT it was also called the Lake of Gennesaret (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.1">Lk 5:1</a>) and the Sea of Tiberias (<a href="?bref=John.6.1">Jn 6:1</a>; <a href="?bref=John.21.1">21:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. The Middle Arabah, or Ghor. The name Jordan means “descender”; in the 60 miles or 96.5 kilometers (in a straight line) from the outlet of the Sea of Galilee to the northern end of the Dead Sea there is a fall of more than 600 feet (182.9 meters), or 10 feet per mile. The river flows in a series of S-curves or zigzags, so that its actual course between Galilee and the Dead Sea covers some 200 miles (321.8 kilometers).</p>
<p class="list-text">This stretch of the Jordan Valley is known as the Ghor, or Rift. Six miles (9.7 kilometers) below the Sea of Galilee the Yarmuk River enters from the east. Some smaller streams empty into the Jordan, but the next river of consequence is the Jabbok (<a href="?bref=Gen.32.22">Gn 32:22</a>). Just south of the Sea of Galilee the Ghor is about four miles (6.4 kilometers) wide; near Beth-shan it reaches seven miles (11.3 kilometers) wide; beyond that for some 15 miles (24.1 kilometers) the mountains close in on the river on both sides, narrowing the valley to two to three miles (3.2 to 4.8 kilometers); near Jericho it broadens to about 12 miles (19.3 kilometers).</p>
<p class="list">4. The Dead Sea is unique. Its surface is the deepest point on the face of the earth and its waters are of tremendous wealth. In the OT it is known as the Salt Sea (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.3">Gn 14:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.34.12">Nm 34:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.3">Jos 12:3</a>) and the Sea of Arabah (<a href="?bref=Josh.12.3">Jos 12:3</a>). Josephus calls it Lake Asphaltitis.</p>
<p class="list-text">This body of water is 46 miles (74 kilometers) long, 10 miles (16.1 kilometers) wide, and 1,300 feet (396.2 meters) deep and consists of about 25 percent mineral matter, making it a chemical deposit of great value. In addition to the flow of the Jordan, the Dead Sea receives the water of other streams, such as the Arnon River on the east. Much of the runoff of the seasonal rains also finds its way into the Salt Sea. Temperatures in the valley may reach 120° F (48.8° C) in summer; with the extreme humidity the climate is very debilitating and almost unbearable. It is estimated that the daily evaporation from the sea is 6 to 8 million tons (5.4–7.3 million metric tons).</p>
<p class="list">5. The Southern Arabah, mostly a barren wilderness, extends from the Dead Sea to the Gulf of Aqaba, a distance of 150 miles (241.4 kilometers). There is a gradual ascent from the Dead Sea to a watershed just west of Petra. Near the tip of the Gulf of Aqaba were the ports of Elath (modern Eilat) and Ezion-geber.</p>
<p class="h3">The Eastern Plateau or Transjordan</p>
<p class="fl">The Eastern Plateau, or Transjordan, was not named as part of the land of promise, but it was taken by the tribes of Reuben, Gad, and half of Manasseh. The region is better supplied with water than the Western Plateau and has perennial streams, such as the Yarmuk, Jabbok, and Arnon. A principal north-south road was the King’s Highway, followed by the Israelites during the exodus (<a href="?bref=Num.21.22">Nm 21:22</a>) and probably also the route taken by the invading kings of <a href="?bref=Gen.14.1-24">Genesis 14</a>.</p>
<p>The northern section of Transjordan was known as Bashan, noted for its cattle (<a href="?bref=Ps.22.12">Ps 22:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.18">Ez 39:18</a>) and for its oak trees (<a href="?bref=Isa.2.13">Is 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.11.2">Zec 11:2</a>).</p>
<p>Gilead, famed for its balm (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.25">Gn 37:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.8.22">Jer 8:22</a>), was often mentioned in the OT (e.g., <a href="?bref=Deut.3.10-16">Dt 3:10-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.11.1-40">Jgs 11</a>). It extended from the Yarmuk River to the city of Heshbon. This area was heavily forested in David’s time (cf. <a href="?bref=2Sam.18.8">2 Sm 18:8</a>).</p>
<p>In Palestine proper there were two important divisions: the plain of Esdraelon and the Negev. The plain of Esdraelon, often associated prophetically with Armageddon, lies between Galilee and Samaria. This is one of the most fertile areas of Palestine and also was the scene of numerous battles. The plain was guarded by fortress cities on its southern side (Megiddo, Ibleam, and Taanach). In the OT the valley of Jezreel was not regarded as a part of Esdraelon but as the valley between the hill of Moreh and Mt Gilboa. At the eastern end was the stronghold of Beth-shan.</p>
<p>In the extreme south of the land is the wilderness area called the Negev, or South Country. This begins in the region of Beersheba and extends roughly to Kadesh-barnea. A district of infrequent and irregular rainfall, its agriculture is restricted, although a nomadic pastoral life has been widely practiced there. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Arabah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Arabah</a>; <a href="?item=ConquestandAllotmentoftheLand_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Conquest and Allotment of the Land</a>; <a href="?item=DeadSea_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dead Sea</a>; <a href="?item=Decapolis_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Decapolis</a>; <a href="?item=SeaofGalilee_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sea of Galilee</a>; <a href="?item=JordanRiver_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jordan River</a>; <a href="?item=NegebNegev_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Negev</a>; <a href="?item=Shephelah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shephelah</a>; <a href="?item=Transjordan_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Transjordan</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>