<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Perfume">
  <title>Perfume</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PERFUME</p>
<p class="fl">Term covering a wide range of materials prepared from ground-up minerals, vegetable oils, and roots, which were used from the earliest times to enhance one’s personal presentation or to produce pleasing fragrances both for secular and religious purposes. The Bible mentions a wide variety of perfumes, such as aloes, balm, balsam, bdellium, cassia, cinnamon, frankincense, gum, myrrh, nard, sweet cane, spice, ointment, and so on. There must have been a vigorous perfume trade with such lands as Arabia (frankincense, myrrh), India (aloes, nard), Ceylon (cinnamon), Persia (the spice galbanum), and Somaliland (frankincense). In the Bible there are several references to those who traded in these items; for example, the Arabian (Ishmaelite) merchants who took Joseph to Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.25">Gn 37:25</a>), the caravans of the queen of Sheba (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.10">1 Kgs 10:10</a>), and the traders of Sheba and Raamah who brought spices to Tyre (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.22">Ez 27:22</a>).</p>
<p>There are several biblical references to those who prepared perfumes. For example, Bezalel prepared holy anointing oil and sacred incense for the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.37.29">Ex 37:29</a>). The holy anointing oil was a mixture of four constituents (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.22-25">30:22-25</a>): myrrh, cinnamon, aromatic cane, and cassia mixed in olive oil. In postexilic times, some priests were given the responsibility of mixing perfumes for incense (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.30">1 Chr 9:30</a>), and a perfumer is mentioned among those who built Nehemiah’s wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.8">Neh 3:8</a>).</p>
<p>Modern excavation has produced tangible evidence of a variety of cosmetic vessels and appliances, although, strangely enough, little is said in the Bible about these (<a href="?bref=Isa.3.20">Is 3:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.26.7">Mt 26:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.3">Mk 14:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.37">Lk 7:37</a>). The reference to alabaster containers gains support from their use in Egypt and from archaeology. Some ancient sites in Palestine have yielded numerous small decorated cosmetic bowls, often made of alabaster; small bottles for scents and oils; and palettes for mixing cosmetics. Some of these items are imports from lands like Egypt.</p>
<p>There was a wide range of uses for the various perfumes, whether powders or oils. Perfumed oils were regularly used to anoint the body in order to soothe sun-dried skin (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.20">2 Sm 12:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.3.3">Ru 3:3</a>). On one occasion, King Ahaz clothed, fed, and anointed men who returned home from captivity (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.15">2 Chr 28:15</a>). The rich in the land could afford the “finest oils” (<a href="?bref=Amos.6.6">Am 6:6</a>), although such extravagance could be costly (<a href="?bref=Pr.21.17">Prv 21:17</a>). This biblical picture is corroborated by evidence from Egypt and Mesopotamia. In particular, there was a lavish use of oils and ointments in the royal palaces of the East.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AnAlabasterVase"/>
<p>Ointments and oils of various kinds that gave off a pleasing fragrance were regularly used. The Song of Songs has many references to such ointments (<a href="?bref=Song.1.3">Sg 1:3</a>), some of which are specifically named: spikenard (<a href="?bref=Song.1.12">1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.13-14">4:13-14</a>), myrrh (<a href="?bref=Song.1.13">1:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.3.6">3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.6">4:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.5.1,5,13">5:1, 5, 13</a>), frankincense (<a href="?bref=Song.3.6">3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.6">4:6</a>), spices (<a href="?bref=Song.5.13">5:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.6.2">6:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.8.14">8:14</a>), henna (<a href="?bref=Song.1.14">1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.13">4:13</a>), fragrant powders (<a href="?bref=Song.3.6">3:6</a>), saffron (<a href="?bref=Song.4.14">4:14</a>), calamus, and cinnamon (<a href="?bref=Song.4.14">4:14</a>). And there are references in other parts of the Bible to perfumes and ointments of various kinds (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.2,10">1 Kgs 10:2, 10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.13">2 Kgs 20:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.27.9">Prv 27:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.3.24">Is 3:24</a>).</p>
<p>Perfumes were put on clothes (<a href="?bref=Ps.45.8">Ps 45:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.11">Sg 4:11</a>) and sprinkled on couches (<a href="?bref=Pr.7.17">Prv 7:17</a>). Perfumes and spices also played an important role in the burial of the dead. They were used in embalming (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.2-3,26">Gn 50:2-3, 26</a>) and were sprinkled on the bier or burned in the fire at some funerals (<a href="?bref=2Chr.16.14">2 Chr 16:14</a>). Nicodemus brought a mixture of myrrh and aloes to be used in wrapping the body of Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.19.39-40">Jn 19:39-40</a>). In the funeral of Herod the Great, 500 slaves carried the spices (Josephus’s <span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 17.8.3).</p>
<p>Besides the personal use of such materials, there was a wide range of oils, perfumes, and incense used in worship. A holy anointing oil was used to anoint the tabernacle and its furnishings and the Aaronic priests at their induction (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.22-25">Ex 30:22-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.133.1-3">Ps 133</a>). An interesting prescription for the sacred incense to be prepared by the perfumer is given in <a href="?bref=Exod.30.34-35">Exodus 30:34-35</a>. The items listed are well known both in Israel and in other parts of the ancient East.</p>
<p>The NT contains a number of figurative references. Christ gave himself as a fragrant offering to God (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.2">Eph 5:2</a>). The gifts of the Philippians to Paul were described as a fragrant offering (<a href="?bref=Phil.4.18">Phil 4:18</a>) and the prayers of the saints are described as bowls of incense (<a href="?bref=Rev.5.8">Rv 5:8</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Cosmetics_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cosmetics</a>; <a href="?item=Oil_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Oil</a>; <a href="?item=Ointment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ointment</a>; <a href="?item=Perfumer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Perfumer</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>