<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Persecution">
  <title>Persecution</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PERSECUTION</p>
<p class="fl">Infliction of suffering, injury, or death on others because of their identity or beliefs. The Bible begins with an account of the persecution of the righteous by the unrighteous (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.3-7">Gn 4:3-7</a>, “regard for Abel”; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.35">Mt 23:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.4">Heb 11:4</a>). The Wisdom of Solomon (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.2.12-20">Wisd of Sol 2:12-20</a>) dramatically illustrates the envy and guilt that prompt such persecution. Lot’s experience, likewise, illustrates the suffering involved in refusing to conform to popular behavior (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.9">Gn 19:9</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.7-8">2 Pt 2:7-8</a>). The ill-treatment of Israel in Egypt, like her later oppression by the Philistines, Midianites, and others, had economic and political grounds. For those refusing to accept the royal policy of syncretism, official tolerance of injustice, and pagan immoralities, persecution becomes frequent—from Elijah’s period onward (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.10">1 Kgs 19:10</a>). Later prophets, as spokesmen of uncompromising truth and the claims of divine law in the face of social evils, suffered severely at the hands of the ruling classes, so that persecution became, in Jewish eyes, the hallmark of the true prophet (<a href="?bref=2Chr.36.15-16">2 Chr 36:15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.5.12">Mt 5:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.29-37">23:29-37</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.7.52">Acts 7:52</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.32-38">Heb 11:32-38</a>).</p>
<p>Daniel’s stories illustrate persecution during the exile. On the return under foreign rule, strict Jews sought to preserve the nation’s identity and religion amid alien pressures and the compromises of lax Jews anxious for accommodation and prosperity (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.1.11-15">1 Macc 1:11-15</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.2.42-48">2:42-48</a>). The result was the social oppression and harassment that made the repeated pleas for vindication and divine intervention, in such psalms as <a href="?bref=Ps.10.1-18">10</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.69.1-36">69</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.140.1-13">140</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ps.149.1-9">149</a>, painfully relevant in postexilic worship. This persecution reached a horrifying climax of cruelty during the Maccabean age, provoking armed resistance in response (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Macc.6.1-7.42">2 Macc 6–7</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.35-38">Heb 11:35-38</a>).</p>
<p>Thus, despite her confidence in God’s sovereignty and “protection,” Israel learned that right does not always prosper in this world, that faithfulness to truth does not ensure immunity from suffering, sacrifice, or martyrdom.</p>
<p>This acceptance of the high cost of righteousness was inherited by Christianity. Jesus repeatedly warned of persecution, even within households, and urged “armed” preparation for it, promising the Spirit’s assistance at judicial examinations (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.11-12">Mt 5:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.10.16-23,34-36">10:16-23, 34-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.34">23:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.26">Lk 6:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.22.35-36">22:35-36</a>). Jesus was deeply angered by the murder of John the Baptist by Herod (<a href="?bref=Luke.23.9">Lk 23:9</a>), and he foresaw his own fate. Because he criticized the legalism and nationalism of the Pharisees, and the compromises of the Sadducees to protect their own privileges (<a href="?bref=John.11.47-50">Jn 11:47-50</a>), and because he disappointed the militaristic hopes set upon the Messiah by the common people, Jesus knew he would be rejected. His call to discipleship came to include warnings of danger, reviling, slander, accusation, flogging, arraignment before courts, hatred, and death. He frankly invited followers to prepare for his crucifixion, as the only way to life and the kingdom (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.21-26">Mt 16:21-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.20.17-22">20:17-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.29-30">Mk 10:29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=John.15.18-25">Jn 15:18-25</a>; <a href="?bref=John.16.1-4">16:1-4</a>). Jesus was killed on the charges of subverting the nation, forbidding payment of taxes to the Romans, and claiming to be king (<a href="?bref=Luke.23.2">Lk 23:2</a>).</p>
<p>The first persecution of the church by Jewish authorities was provoked mainly by Peter’s accusations concerning the murder of the Messiah. As apostolic influence increased, official action came to include imprisonment and beating (<a href="?bref=Acts.5.17,40">Acts 5:17, 40</a>). The powerful advocacy of the Hellenist Stephen provoked a Jewish mob to stone him (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.1-7.60">Acts 6–7</a>)—the signal for “a great persecution,” scattering most Christians from Jerusalem. The conversion of the archpersecutor Saul of Tarsus marked a resounding victory over opposition, and Herod’s sudden death just after attacking the church “to please the Jews” was another (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.1-3,20-24">Acts 12:1-3, 20-24</a>).</p>
<p>As Christianity moved into the Gentile world, a new cause of Jewish persecution arose as disturbances began to occur in the synagogues (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.44-45,50">Acts 13:44-45, 50</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.14.1-6,19">14:1-6, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.1,5,13">17:1, 5, 13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.4-6,12">18:4-6, 12</a>). In addition, the healing of the slave girl at Philippi led to the disciples’ imprisonment (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.19-24">16:19-24</a>); at Ephesus, the effect of Christian preaching on the trade of idol makers occasioned a dangerous threat, which the authorities averted (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.23-41">19:23-41</a>). Paul averted the plot of more than 40 men who vowed to ambush him and kill him (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.4-36">21:4-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.23.12-15">23:12-15</a>). And the book of Acts closes with Paul awaiting trial before Caesar (<a href="?bref=Acts.28.30-31">28:30-31</a>).</p>
<p>Throughout this period, persecution of Christians was sporadic, local, and mainly Jewish, provoked by envy of the church’s missionary success. Officially, Christianity, as a Jewish sect (<a href="?bref=Acts.24.5,14">Acts 24:5, 14</a>), shared the state’s legal recognition won by the Jews. Thus, Paul received Roman protection at Paphos, Philippi, Corinth, Ephesus, and Jerusalem from governors Felix and Festus and their adviser Herod Agrippa, as well as from the centurion conveying him to Rome. This explains Paul’s confident appeal to Caesar; an imperial acquittal would ensure Christianity freedom from harassment throughout the empire.</p>
<p>Paul’s attitude to persecution included regretful remembrance of his own persecuting days (<a href="?bref=Acts.22.4">Acts 22:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.9-11">26:9-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.22-24">Gal 1:22-24</a>), deliberate acceptance of risks in obedience to Christ (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.22-24">Acts 20:22-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.21.13">21:13</a>), continual warning that tribulation is inseparable from discipleship (<a href="?bref=Acts.14.22">Acts 14:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.5.3">Rom 5:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.12.12">12:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.3.4">1 Thes 3:4</a>), and assurance that in every form of tribulation Christians are more than conquerors (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.35-37">Rom 8:35-37</a>).</p>
<p>Almost certainly, Paul was beheaded during fierce persecution at Rome following the fire for which the Christians were blamed. Christians were often accused of “atheism” (rejecting polytheism), of appealing only to slave classes, of “scandalous” love feasts, and unsociable, austere behavior (cf. <a href="?bref=John.15.19">Jn 15:19</a>), making them a popular target for blame.</p>
<p>About this time, Peter warned Christians in the East of the danger confronting the church. For a little while, “various trials” only prove the genuineness of faith (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.6">1 Pt 1:6</a>). Slander should be answered by blameless living. Honor should be paid to the authorities. Suffering for righteousness should be accepted without fear. Let Christians prepare respectful defenses, with consciences clear of blame. If they suffer for doing right, remember that Christ did too—for them. Thus they must “arm” themselves for suffering (<a href="?bref=1Pet.4.1">4:1</a>), and not be surprised at persecution as “something strange” (v <a href="?bref=1Pet.4.12">12</a>). They are sharing Christ’s sufferings. His final word is “Stand fast!”</p>
<p>Mark, too, is thought to have written at this time for the benefit of the suffering Roman church. His Gospel dwells upon Christ’s conflict, its causes and forms, and vividly portrays Christ’s own heroic death. Like Peter, Mark meets persecution by pointing back to the suffering Lord.</p>
<p>Somewhat later, Christianity was exposed as an “illegal religion,” no longer a protected sect of Judaism, by the introduction into synagogue services of a prayer against “Nazarenes,” which Christians could not offer. Thereafter, the church was liable to official suppression. Rome readily incorporated old, national religions into state rituals for the sake of imperial unity, but she resisted new, nonconformist movements, especially those with secret meetings (i.e., the Eucharist), as politically dangerous (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.17.6-7">Acts 17:6-7</a>).</p>
<p>Toward the end of the century, faced with a growing church and political unrest, the state required public “worship” of “the genius of Rome” alongside any other religious rites. In Domitian’s reign (<span class="era">AD</span> 81–96) this became worship of the living emperor, with elaborate temples and an official priesthood. When Christians refused, acknowledging Jesus alone as divine Lord, official, and increasingly barbaric, persecution began. It is probable that Revelation reflects this situation (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.9">Rv 1:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.2.13">2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.6.9">6:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.13.1-18">13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.2">19:2</a>). So the Bible ends as it began, with the theme of the persecution of the people of God.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Suffering_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Suffering</a>; <a href="?item=Tribulation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tribulation</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>