<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Pestilence">
  <title>Pestilence</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PESTILENCE</p>
<p class="fl">Derivative of a Hebrew word referring to a contagious epidemic disease of devastating proportions. Pestilence is never portrayed in the Bible as an aimless, naturally occurring phenomenon. It is always regarded as a judgment or punishment sent by God.</p>
<p>Pestilence was one form of chastisement brought upon Israel for neglect of her covenant obligations (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.25">Lv 26:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.28.21">Dt 28:21</a>). This is the reason for the frequent use of the word by both Jeremiah and Ezekiel. These prophets were prosecuting God’s covenant lawsuit against his people. The sentence had been determined, and they announced that its infliction was impending. For this reason, pestilence almost always occurs as part of a list of scourges, such as the formula “sword, famine and pestilence” used throughout Jeremiah’s prophecy (<a href="?bref=Jer.14.12">Jer 14:12</a>, etc.). Because pestilence is a punishment for sin, it is not applied indiscriminately upon all. The one who remains faithful will be protected from its effects (<a href="?bref=Ps.91.1-3">Ps 91:1-3</a>). The enemies of Israel could also be objects of this form of judgment (<a href="?bref=Ps.78.50">Ps 78:50</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.23">Ez 28:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.38.22">38:22</a>).</p>
<p>Pestilence is not identical with plague in the OT. Plague often denotes such diseases as bubonic plague, measles, and smallpox, whereas pestilence might refer to cholera, typhus, typhoid, and dysentery—diseases often afflicting a city under siege. There is some overlap in the terms, however. The death of 70,000 Israelites after David’s census is an example of the severity and virulence of this form of divine chastisement (<a href="?bref=2Sam.24.13-15">2 Sm 24:13-15</a>).</p>
<p>The Greek word <span class="greek">loimos</span> occurs three times in the NT. In <a href="?bref=Acts.24.5">Acts 24:5</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) Tertullus used this term as a derogatory description of Paul—“a pestilent fellow.” Jesus predicted that the destruction of the temple would be preceded by several judgments, including pestilence or plague (<a href="?bref=Luke.21.11">Lk 21:11</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Disease_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Disease</a>; <a href="?item=Plague_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plague</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>