<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PilatePontius">
  <title>Pilate, Pontius</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PILATE, P<span class="lc">ontius</span></p>
<p class="fl">Appointed by Tiberius as the fifth prefect of Judea, Pilate served in that capacity from <span class="era">AD</span> 26–36. He appears prominently in the trial narratives of the Gospels as the Roman governor who authorized Jesus’ crucifixion. In addition, he appears in a variety of extrabiblical sources as a dispassionate administrator who relentlessly pursued Roman authority in Judea.</p>
<p>Tacitus (<span class="ital">Annals</span> 15.44) mentions Pilate in connection with the crucifixion of Jesus but adds little to the Gospel account. Josephus, on the other hand, provides three narratives. First, he describes Pilate’s arrival as the new prefect (<span class="ital">War</span> 2.9.2; <span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 18.3.1; cf. Eusebius’s <span class="ital">Histories</span> 2.6). Offending Jewish law, Pilate brought ensigns into Jerusalem that bore the image of Caesar. A large gathering of Jews then came to Caesarea in protest, fasting there for five days. Pilate called in troops to dismiss them, but he learned his first lesson about Jewish intransigence. The Jews were ready to die rather than tolerate the ensigns. Soon thereafter Pilate relented.</p>
<p>A second incident occurred when Pilate appropriated temple funds in order to construct a 35-mile (56.3-kilometer) aqueduct for Jerusalem (<span class="ital">War</span> 2.9.4; <span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 18.3.2). Again, there was a major protest. Pilate ordered his soldiers to dress in tunics and infiltrate the crowds in disguise. At his command, the troops used clubs to beat the offenders. Many Jews were killed. Josephus records the horror with which Jerusalem perceived the affair.</p>
<p>Finally, Josephus records the story of Pilate’s dismissal (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 18.4.1-2). In <span class="era">AD</span> 36 a Samaritan false prophet (pretending to be the <span class="ital">Taheb,</span> or Samaritan messiah) promised to show his followers sacred vessels hidden by Moses on Mt Gerizim. Pilate sent a heavily armed contingent of footmen and cavalry who intercepted the pilgrims and slaughtered most of them. The Samaritans complained to Vitellius, the prefect of Syria, whereupon Pilate was ordered to report to the emperor Tiberius. Another prefect, Marcellus, was then sent by Rome as Pilate’s replacement.</p>
<p>Philo records yet another event (<span class="ital">Leg. to Caius</span> 299-305). While extolling the liberal policies of Tiberius toward Judaism, he cites a negative example in Pontius Pilate. The prefect had erected gilded shields in Herod’s former palace in Jerusalem that bore the name of the emperor. Refusing to hear Jewish complaints, the sons of Herod appealed to Tiberius, who ordered Pilate to transfer the shields to the temple of Augustus in Caesarea. The similarities with the parallel story in Josephus have led many scholars to believe that Philo is merely recounting another version of the same event.</p>
<p>Luke mentions a minor incident that contributes to this same portrait. In <a href="?bref=Luke.13.1">Luke 13:1</a> some Jews tell Jesus about the Galileans whose blood Pilate had mixed with their sacrifices. While this story is not corroborated by any other witness, it conforms to the impressions of Pilate’s character given by Philo and Josephus. In fact, Luke adds another detail of interest in his trial narrative. In <a href="?bref=Luke.23.12">Luke 23:12</a> he says that prior to the crucifixion of Jesus, Herod Antipas (in Galilee) and Pilate had been at enmity with each other. This may have stemmed not simply from Pilate’s usual antagonism but particularly from the Galilean incident.</p>
<p>Pilate’s role in the death of Jesus is recorded in each Gospel (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.2">Mt 27:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.15.1">Mk 15:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.23.1">Lk 23:1</a>; <a href="?bref=John.18.29">Jn 18:29</a>) and was remembered as a historical datum in the preaching of the apostles (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.13">Acts 3:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.27">4:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.13.28">13:28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.6.13">1 Tm 6:13</a>). In order to secure the conviction and death of Jesus, Caiaphas and the Sanhedrin brought their charges to Pilate. While the accusations took on a political flavor to evoke the governor’s interest, he still could find no grounds for condemnation. In the end, Pilate unexpectedly accommodates the Jewish leaders and has Jesus crucified.</p>
<p>All of the Gospels and particularly John show Pilate’s repeated verdict of Jesus’ innocence. According to <a href="?bref=Matt.27.19">Matthew 27:19</a>, Pilate’s wife had an ominous dream about Jesus’ conviction, and she warned her husband. Pilate tried to have Jesus released, but the crowd cried for Barabbas. Matthew even records that Pilate washed his hands (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.24-25">27:24-25</a>), declaring his own innocence in this. And finally, John says that Pilate refused to alter the title over the cross (<a href="?bref=John.19.19-22">Jn 19:19-22</a>). These accounts, therefore, take the full blame for Jesus’ death from Pilate and place it on the Jewish leaders of the Sanhedrin. They are ultimately responsible.</p>
<p>But why would Pilate act in behalf of the Sanhedrin? Two answers are possible. First, there may have been collusion between Caiaphas and Pilate that stemmed from a long-standing relationship and coterminous reign. Ten of Caiaphas’s eighteen years in power were under Pilate, and when the prefect was dismissed in <span class="era">AD</span> 36, Caiaphas was simultaneously removed. Second, if Jesus’ trial occurred in <span class="era">AD</span> 33, Pilate may have been concerned about his impeachment. He had originally been appointed by Sejanus (prefect of the praetorians in Rome who had appointed men to colonial office under Tiberius), but in the autumn of <span class="era">AD</span> 31 Sejanus died. This explains why a Jewish delegation could report directly to Tiberius during the votive shield incident. Hence, the charge recorded in <a href="?bref=John.19.12">John 19:12</a> (“If you release this man, you are not Caesar’s friend”) would have had genuine power over Pilate. Pilate perceived his jeopardy and was anxious to pacify the Jews and please the emperor.</p>
<p>The history of Pilate after his dismissal in <span class="era">AD</span> 36 is unknown. Eusebius reports that Pilate ultimately committed suicide during the reign of the emperor Caligula, <span class="era">AD</span> 37–41 (<span class="ital">History</span> 2.7).</p>
  </body>
</item>