<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Pisidia">
  <title>Pisidia</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PISIDIA</p>
<p class="fl">Region included in the Roman province of Galatia at the time of the visit of Paul and Barnabas about <span class="era">AD</span> 48.</p>
<p>It is north of the Taurus mountain range that parallels the coastline of Cilicia and Pamphylia. Separated from these coastal provinces by the mountain range, it lies in the central plateau of Anatolia about 3,600 feet (1,097.3 meters) above sea level. The territory includes the foothills of the Taurus range and measures about 400 miles (643.6 kilometers) long and 165 miles (265.5 kilometers) wide. It was joined by the large province of Asia on the west, by Galatia on the north, and by Lycaonia on the east. The inhabitants of the mountainous terrain were predatory tribesmen who were subjugated with great difficulty over a period of years by the Seleucids and later by the Romans. To assist in controlling these tribes, the city of Antioch was founded by Seleucus I Nicator (312–280 <span class="era">BC</span>). Concern with security led Amyntas of Galatia to strengthen the city (c. 26 <span class="era">BC</span>). At his death in 25 <span class="era">BC</span>, Pisidia was absorbed into the province of Galatia. Augustus undertook the final phase of pacification of the populace by founding five cities in addition to Antioch: Crimma, Comana, Olbase, Parlais, and Lystra, all linked to Antioch by military roads. An inscription, discovered in 1912, indicates that Quirinius (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.2.2">Lk 2:2</a>) was administrator of the district and responsible to Augustus. Its capital, Antioch, was on the main road between Ephesus to the west and Derbe and Tarsus to the east. It was primarily a Roman colony and included a sizeable Jewish community, introduced by the Seleucids for the purpose of trade.</p>
<p>Paul and Barnabas passed through the country at least twice (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.14">Acts 13:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.14.24">14:24</a>) in the journey between Perga and Derbe. It was in Antioch of Pisidia that one of the most important decisions in the history of Christian missionary strategy was made and announced. After being rebuffed by a majority of his Jewish audience, accompanied by a more cordial response from the Gentiles, Paul and Barnabas announced, “Since you thrust it [the word of God] from you, and judge yourselves unworthy of eternal life, behold, we turn to the Gentiles” (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.46">13:46</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Henceforth, the strategy of Paul and his associates was oriented more specifically to the non-Jewish peoples, thus making Christianity a world religion rather than another Jewish sect.</p>
  </body>
</item>