<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Plants">
  <title>Plants</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PLANTS</p>
<p class="fl">Identifying biblical plants has always been a difficult task, partly because people continue to identify the biblical elm, sycamore, lily, rose, and vine with modern plants, and also because they assume that all the plants now growing in the Holy Land were there in ancient biblical days, or that the plants referred to in the Bible are still to be found there today. Unfortunately, many plants now quite common in the Holy Land were not there in biblical days. Many plants that once grew in abundance in the Holy Land are now extinct. Some have been driven out by foreign invaders; others have been exterminated or nearly exterminated by overcultivation of the land, the destruction of forests, and the resulting changes in climatic and other environmental conditions. At one time the Holy Land was a land of palm trees, with the date palm as abundant and characteristic there as it was in Egypt, but today the date palm is much less common. Similarly, in antiquity, the towering cedars clothed the slopes of Lebanon and other mountain ranges. Now the few remaining specimens must be carefully fenced in to protect them against trampling and the ravages of goats.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Acacia">Acacia</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Acanthus">Acanthus</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Algum">Algum</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Almond">Almond</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Almug">Almug</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Aloe">Aloe</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Apple">Apple</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Apricot">Apricot</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Ash">Ash</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Aspen">Aspen</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Balm">Balm</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Barley">Barley</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Bdellium">Bdellium</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Bean">Bean</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#BitterHerbs">Bitter Herbs</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#BoxthornEuropean">Boxthorn, European</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#BoxTree">Box Tree</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Bramble">Bramble</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Broom">Broom</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Buckthorn">Buckthorn</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Bush">Bush</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Buttercup">Buttercup</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Calamus">Calamus</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Cane">Cane</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#CaperPlant">Caper Plant</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#CarobTree">Carob Tree</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Cassia">Cassia</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#CastorOilPlant">Castor Oil Plant</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Cedar">Cedar</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Chicory">Chicory</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Cinnamon">Cinnamon</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#CitronTree">Citron Tree</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Coriander">Coriander</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Cotton">Cotton</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Cucumber">Cucumber</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Cummin">Cummin</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Cypress">Cypress</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Dandelion">Dandelion</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DarnelGrass">Darnel Grass</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Dill">Dill</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Ebony">Ebony</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Endive">Endive</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#FigFigTree">Fig, Fig Tree</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#FirTree">Fir Tree</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Flax">Flax</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Frankincense">Frankincense</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Galbanum">Galbanum</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Garlic">Garlic</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#GourdWild">Gourd, Wild</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Hedge">Hedge</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Henna">Henna</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Hyacinth">Hyacinth</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Hyssop">Hyssop</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Juniper">Juniper</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LaurelorSweetBay">Laurel or Sweet Bay</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Leek">Leek</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Lentil">Lentil</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Lettuce">Lettuce</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Lily">Lily</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LotusBush">Lotus Bush</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Mallow">Mallow</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Mandrake">Mandrake</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Melon">Melon</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Millet">Millet</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Mint">Mint</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Mulberry">Mulberry</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Mustard">Mustard</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Myrrh">Myrrh</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Myrtle">Myrtle</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Narcissus">Narcissus</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Nard">Nard</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Nettle">Nettle</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#NutmegFlower">Nutmeg Flower</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Oak">Oak</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#OilTreeOleaster">Oil Tree, Oleaster</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Oleander">Oleander</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#OliveOliveTree">Olive, Olive Tree</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Onion">Onion</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Palm">Palm</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Papyrus">Papyrus</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PineTree">Pine Tree</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Pistachio">Pistachio</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PlaneTree">Plane Tree</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Pomegranate">Pomegranate</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Poplar">Poplar</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Quince">Quince</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Reed">Reed</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Rue">Rue</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Rush">Rush</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Saffron">Saffron</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Sage">Sage</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Spelt">Spelt</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#StoraxTree">Storax Tree</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Sycamore">Sycamore</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Tamarisk">Tamarisk</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Terebinth">Terebinth</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#ThistleThorn">Thistle, Thorn</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Tulip">Tulip</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Tumbleweed">Tumbleweed</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Vegetable">Vegetable</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Vine">Vine</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Walnut">Walnut</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#WaterLily">Water Lily</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Wheat">Wheat</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Wormwood">Wormwood</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Acacia">Acacia <span class="ital">(Acacia tortilis</span> and <span class="ital">A. seyal)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any tree or shrub of the mimosa family of plants growing in warm regions. The plant referred to in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> as “shittah” (singular) or “shittim” (plural) is undoubtedly the acacia tree, the only timber tree of any considerable size in the Arabian desert. <span class="ital">Acacia tortilis</span> is by far the largest and most common tree in the desert in which the Israelites wandered for 40 years. It is especially conspicuous on Mt Sinai and was probably the species used for the tabernacle furnishings. <span class="ital">A. seyal</span> is less common, at least today. It can grow as high as 25 feet (7.6 meters), and bears yellow flowers on twisted branches. The wood is close grained, heavy and hard, orange-brown in color, and much valued in cabinetwork. The ancient Egyptians clamped shut mummy coffins with acacia wood.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Acanthus">Acanthus <span class="ital">(Acanthus syriacus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The acanthus, perhaps referred to in <a href="?bref=Job.30.7">Job 30:7</a> and <a href="?bref=Zeph.2.9">Zephaniah 2:9</a>, is a perennial thistlelike herb or small shrub about three feet (.9 meter) tall, and is a common weed in all Eastern countries. It has been used since time immemorial as a model for the leaf or scroll decorations in art.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Algum">Algum <span class="ital">(Juniperus excelsa Bieb)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The timber from Lebanon referred to in <a href="?bref=2Chr.2.8">2 Chronicles 2:8</a> is probably the juniper. Some translators hold, however, that algum and almug are Hebrew variants for the same tree (see <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg, <a href="?bref=2Chr.2.8">2 Chr 2:8</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Almug">Almug (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Almond">Almond <span class="ital">(Amygdalus communis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The almond is a peachlike tree with saw-toothed pointed leaves and gray bark. It grows to a height of from 10 to 25 feet (3 to 7.6 meters). It blooms very early in the year; its Hebrew name has its roots in “watch for.” To the Jews it was a welcome harbinger of spring (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.11">Jer 1:11</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AlmondTrees"/>
<p class="h2" id="Almug">Almug <span class="ital">(Pterocarpus santalinus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The precious wood imported by King Solomon and used in making the pillars for the temple and for making harps and psalteries (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.11-12">1 Kgs 10:11-12</a>). This timber was brought by sea from Ophir to Ezion-geber, near Elath. Modern authorities suggest that Ophir was either in Arabia, India, or East Africa near Mozambique. The reference to “algum“ in <a href="?bref=2Chr.2.8">2 Chronicles 2:8</a> is possibly to this tree. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="#Algum">Algum (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Aloe">Aloe <span class="ital">(Aloe succotrina, Aquilaria agallocha)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Chiefly African, lilylike plant of the genus <span class="ital">Aloes,</span> certain species of which yield a drug and a fiber. Aloe is an aromatic substance mentioned in the Bible, together with myrrh, balm, and other fragrant plants (<a href="?bref=Ps.45.8">Ps 45:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.7.17">Prv 7:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.14">Sg 4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.39">Jn 19:39</a>). Most scholars think these passages refer to two different plants. The OT plant is likely to have been <span class="ital">Aquilaria agallocha,</span> the eaglewood, a large tree growing up to 120 feet (36.6 meters) tall with a trunk 12 feet (3.7 meters) in circumference. It is native to northern India, Malaya, and Indochina. The decaying wood is highly fragrant, and as such is highly valued as perfume and incense and for fumigation.</p>
<p>The aloe of <a href="?bref=John.19.39">John 19:39</a> is thought to be the true aloe <span class="ital">(Aloe succotrina),</span> the juice of which was used by the Egyptians in embalming. Its smell, however, is not very agreeable, and it has a bitter taste. It is sometimes used by veterinarians as a horse medicine.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Apple">Apple <span class="ital">(Malus sylvestris)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The identity of the fruit identified by the Hebrew word <span class="hebrew">tappuach</span> (<a href="?bref=Pr.25.11">Prv 25:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.2.3,5">Sg 2:3, 5</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.7.8">7:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.8.5">8:5</a>) continues to be debated. In most English translations it has been rendered “apple” because of its close linguistic tie to the Arabic word <span class="ital">tuffah.</span> Many scholars identify this tree as the apricot, questioning whether apples fit the biblical description “apples of gold” and whether the apple tree was cultivated in ancient Palestine. Recent excavations at Kadesh-barnea, however, have uncovered carbonized apples, probably a crab apple <span class="ital">(Malus sylvestris),</span> dating to the ninth century <span class="era">BC</span>. This would certainly allow for this ornamental apple’s cultivation in Solomon’s gardens.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Apricot">Apricot (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Apricot">Apricot <span class="ital">(Prunus armeniaca)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The identification of the Hebrew word <span class="hebrew">tappuach</span> with the apricot continues to be debated. The apricot tree produces yellow-orange peachlike edible fruit and is native to western Asia and Africa. It is abundant in the Holy Land and probably has been so since early biblical times. The tree is a round-headed reddish-barked tree growing 30 feet (9.1 meters) tall. Most translations render this Hebrew word “apple,” though many scholars identify it with the apricot because of its descriptions in the biblical text (see <a href="?bref=Pr.25.11">Prv 25:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.2.3,5">Sg 2:3, 5</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.7.8">7:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.8.5">8:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.1.12">Jl 1:12</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Apple">Apple (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Ash">Ash <span class="ital">(Alhagi maurorum, Fraxinus ornus, Tamarix mannifera)</span></p>
<p class="fl">There are several ash trees found in the Near East. One of these, the prickly alhagi <span class="ital">(Alhagi maurorum),</span> is a member of the pea family. It is a low, many-stemmed, much-branched shrub growing about three feet (.9 meter) tall with somewhat hairy twigs and pealike flowers. During the heat of the day, leaves exude a sweet, gummy substance that hardens in the air and is collected by shaking the bushes over a spread-out cloth.</p>
<p>The manna tamarisk <span class="ital">(Tamarix mannifera)</span> is a multibranched shrub or a small tree 9 to 15 feet (2.7 to 4.6 meters) tall with rigid branches that have tiny pink flowers. It is found on deserts from the Holy Land to Arabia and the Sinai.</p>
<p>The flowering or manna ash <span class="ital">(Fraxinus ornus)</span> is a tree that grows from 15 to 50 feet (4.6 to 15.2 meters) tall. The fruits are very similar to those produced by our species of ash. The ash of <a href="?bref=Isa.44.14">Isaiah 44:14</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) is believed to be the Aleppo pine.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Aspen">Aspen <span class="ital">(Populus euphratica</span> or <span class="ital">P. tremula)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of several trees of the genus <span class="ital">Populus</span> with leaves attached by flattened leafstalks so that they tremble or “quake” in the wind.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Balm">Balm <span class="ital">(Balanites aegyptiaca, Pistacia lentiscus, Commiphora opobalsamum</span><span class="ital">)</span></p>
<p class="fl">An oily aromatic resin exuded by chiefly tropical trees and shrubs and used medicinally; trees and shrubs producing this substance. References in <a href="?bref=Gen.37.25">Genesis 37:25</a>, <a href="?bref=Jer.8.22">Jeremiah 8:22</a>, <a href="?bref=Jer.46.11">46:11</a>, and <a href="?bref=Jer.51.8">51:8</a> are thought to be either the Jericho balsam <span class="ital">(Balanites aegyptiaca)</span> or the lentisk or mastic tree <span class="ital">(Pistacia lentiscus).</span> The Jericho balsam is very common in Egypt, North Africa, the plains of Jericho, and the hot plains bordering on the Dead Sea. It is a small desert-loving plant, 9 to 15 feet (2.7 to 4.6 meters) tall, with slender, thorny branches and small clusters of green flowers.</p>
<p>The lentisk or mastic tree is native to the Holy Land, and the reference in <a href="?bref=Gen.43.11">Genesis 43:11</a> is probably to this plant, since the implication is that this is a native product of the Holy Land unknown in Egypt at the time. This tree is a shrubby or bushy tree 3 to 10 feet (.9 to 3 meters) tall with evergreen leaves. The “balm” is a fragrant gummy exudation of the sap secured by making incisions in the stems and branches, usually in August. The best grades are in the form of yellow-white translucent tears or drops; they are employed in medicine as an astringent. The poorer grades are used extensively as a varnish. Children in the East use it as chewing gum.</p>
<p>References to spices in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.10">1 Kings 10:10</a>, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.13">2 Kings 20:13</a>, <a href="?bref=Song.3.6">Song of Songs 3:6</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.39.2">Isaiah 39:2</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.17">Ezekiel 27:17</a> are thought to be the balm of Gilead <span class="ital">(Commiphora opobalsamum),</span> which in spite of its name is not a native of Gilead or even of the Holy Land but is indigenous to Arabia, especially the mountainous regions of Yemen. The trees were still in existence on the plain of Jericho at the time of the Roman conquest. The Roman conquerors carried branches to Rome as trophies of their victory over the Jews.</p>
<p>This tree is a small, stiff-branched evergreen tree seldom more than 15 feet (4.6 meters) high with straggling branches. The “balm” is obtained by making incisions in the stem and branches of the tree. The sap soon hardens into small irregular nodules that are collected. Gum is also procured from green and ripe fruit.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Myrrh">Myrrh (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Barley">Barley <span class="ital">(Hordeum distichon)</span></p>
<p class="fl">A cereal grass bearing bearded flower spikes and edible seeds. The common barley <span class="ital">(Hordeum distichon),</span> the winter barley <span class="ital">(H. hex</span><span class="ital">astichon),</span> and the spring barley <span class="ital">(H. vulgare)</span> have been cultivated in temperate regions of the world since time immemorial and today still constitute one of the principal grain foods. Barley and wheat were the two staple cereal crops of Egypt and the Holy Land. Being less expensive, barley was mostly used for feeding cattle, although it was also used by itself or mixed with wheat and other seed as food for man (<a href="?bref=Ezek.4.9-12">Ez 4:9-12</a>). Barley is mentioned in the Bible over 30 times, either as a plant growing in the fields or in reference to products made from it, such as barley meal, barley bread, barley cakes, and barley loaves. As the common food of the poor, barley was also regarded as a symbol of poverty and cheapness or worthlessness (<a href="?bref=Hos.3.2">Hos 3:2</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Bdellium">Bdellium <span class="ital">(Commiphora africana)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Aromatic gum resin similar to myrrh, produced by various trees of the genus <span class="ital">Commiphora</span> of Africa and western Asia. The reference in <a href="?bref=Gen.2.12">Genesis 2:12</a> and <a href="?bref=Num.11.7">Numbers 11:7</a> to bdellium is thought by most scholars today to refer to a gum resin, obtained from a shrub, <span class="ital">Commiphora africana</span>, that grows in south Arabia and northeastern Africa. The resin is yellowish, transparent, and fragrant, and looks like a pearl.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Bean">Bean <span class="ital">(Faba vulgaris)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The references in <a href="?bref=2Sam.17.27-28">2 Samuel 17:27-28</a> and <a href="?bref=Ezek.4.9">Ezekiel 4:9</a> are generally regarded as referring to the broad bean. This species, an annual plant, is thought originally to have grown in northern Persia, but it was extensively cultivated in western Asia in very early times as a food plant. Beans have been found in the mummy coffins of Egyptian tombs, and they were also cultivated by the Greeks and Romans.</p>
<p class="h2" id="BitterHerbs">Bitter Herbs <span class="ital">(Cichorium endivia, Taraxacum officinale, Lactuca sativa)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The “bitter herbs” of <a href="?bref=Exod.12.8">Exodus 12:8</a> and <a href="?bref=Num.9.11">Numbers 9:11</a> seem to have been plants like endive <span class="ital">(Cichorium endivia),</span> the common chicory <span class="ital">(Cichorium intybus),</span> lettuce <span class="ital">(Lactuca sativa),</span> or the common dandelion <span class="ital">(Taraxacum officinale).</span> These are all weedy plants common in modern Egypt and western Asia and are still eaten by people living there. The leaves of the ordinary garden lettuce are intensely bitter when bleached. This is also true of the common dandelion. Others suggest that the bitter herbs were derived from thorns and thistles.</p>
<p class="h2" id="BoxthornEuropean">Boxthorn, European <span class="ital">(Lycium europaeum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Various thorny shrubs, some species of which bear purplish flowers and brightly colored berries. The reference in <a href="?bref=Judg.9.14-15">Judges 9:14-15</a> is thought to be to the European boxthorn or desert-thorn. It is a thorny shrub 6 to 12 feet (1.8 to 3.7 meters) tall with clustered leaves and small violet flowers eventually producing small globular red berries. It is native to and common throughout the Holy Land, especially in the region from Lebanon to the Dead Sea.</p>
<p class="h2" id="BoxTree">Box Tree <span class="ital">(Buxus longifolia)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The long-leaved box tree is a hardy evergreen tree found in the mountainous regions of the northern part of the Holy Land, the Galilean hills, and Lebanon. It grows to a height of about 20 feet (6.1 meters) with a slender trunk seldom more than six to eight inches (15.2 to 20.3 centimeters) in diameter. Its wood is very hard and takes a fine polish. It was cultivated by the Romans for its hard wood, which they inlaid with ivory for cabinets and jewel caskets. Scriptural references include <a href="?bref=Isa.41.19">Isaiah 41:19</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.60.13">60:13</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Bramble">Bramble <span class="ital">(Rubus sanctus, R. ulmifolius)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The Palestinian bramble <span class="ital">(Rubus sanctus)</span> and the closely related elm-leaf bramble <span class="ital">(R. ulmifolius)</span> are prickly evergreen shrubs that spread by means of suckers. The stems and young shoots are covered with a characteristic bloom or whitish powder and short hairs. The prickles are strong, erect, and hairy. The flowers are white, pink, rose, or purple in color, and the fruit is round and black.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#ThistleThorn">Thistle, Thorn (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Broom">Broom <span class="ital">(Retama raetam)</span></p>
<p class="fl">A shrub native to Eurasia. The word translated “juniper” in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> has nothing to do with the true junipers but refers rather to a species of broom, known as the white broom <span class="ital">(Retama raetam).</span> Its branches are longer and flexible, forming an erect, dense bush 3 to 12 feet (.9 to 3.7 meters) tall. The leaves are small and sparse, yet it forms an agreeable shade in a desert region. The white pealike flowers are sweet and very fragrant and are borne in clusters along the twigs. It is a beautiful shrub that grows in the desert regions of Palestine, Syria, and Persia. In many desert areas it is the only bush that affords any shade (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.4-5">1 Kgs 19:4-5</a>).</p>
<p>The “juniper roots” of <a href="?bref=Job.30.4">Job 30:4</a> are not the roots of either the juniper or white broom. The roots of the latter are very nauseating and could not be eaten in the manner described by Job. Job’s “juniper roots” were probably an edible parasitic plant <span class="ital">(Cynomorium coccineum).</span> This plant grows in salt marshes and maritime sands. It is frequently eaten in times of food scarcity and at one time was highly prized for its supposed medicinal value in the treatment of dysentery.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Buckthorn">Buckthorn <span class="ital">(Rhamnus palaestina)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The Palestinian buckthorn is a shrub or small tree attaining a height of three to six feet (.9 to 1.8 meters) with velvety, thorny branches, evergreen leaves, and clusters of small flowers blooming in March or April. It grows in thickets and on hillsides from Syria and Lebanon through the Holy Land to Arabia and the Sinai.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Bush">Bush <span class="ital">(Acacia nilotica, Loranthus acaciae)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Low, branching, woody plant, usually smaller than a tree. There are differences of opinion in regard to the bush out of which the Lord appeared to Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.2-4">Ex 3:2-4</a>). From the biblical account, it seems most likely that the event was a miraculous one. However, some seek a natural explanation and believe that the burning bush may have been the crimson-flowered mistletoe or acacia strap flower <span class="ital">(Loranthus acaciae),</span> which grows in great profusion as a partial parasite on the various acacia shrubs, such as the thorny acacia <span class="ital">(Acacia nilotica),</span> in the Holy Land and Sinai. When in full bloom, the mistletoe imparts to the shrub or tree the appearance of being on fire because its brilliant flame-colored blossoms stand out against the green foliage and yellow flowers of the host plants.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Buttercup">Buttercup <span class="ital">(Ranunculus asiaticus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The Persian buttercup is one of the flowers or grasses of the field (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.28-30">Mt 6:28-30</a>). It is a showy plant blooming in all brilliant colors except blue, with double flowers sometimes measuring two inches (5.1 centimeters) across.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Calamus">Calamus <span class="ital">(Acorus calamus, Andropogon aroma</span><span class="ital">ticus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">A plant, or its aromatic root; any of a variety of tropical Asiatic palms. One of the plants that grew in Solomon’s garden (<a href="?bref=Song.4.14">Sg 4:14</a>). The sweet flag <span class="ital">(Acorus</span> <span class="ital">calamus)</span> and the beardgrass <span class="ital">(Andropogon aromaticus)</span> have been suggested as the plants from which calamus came. The sweet flag is highly aromatic and grows in Europe and Asia, but it is not known in the Holy Land. Indigenous to India, beardgrass is highly odoriferous when bruised and is thought to have furnished the calamus of the Bible. It yields an oil known as ginger-grass oil.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Cane">Cane <span class="ital">(Saccharum officinarum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">It is thought that there were two species of sugarcane indigenous to and growing wild in the Holy Land. One of these, <span class="ital">Saccharum sara,</span> is known to be only from Lebanon. The other native species is <span class="ital">S. biflorum,</span> which grows on the banks of ditches and streams from Syria and Lebanon through the Holy Land south to Stony Arabia and the Sinai. This may be the wild cane familiar to the Jews. Most authorities, however, think that the “sweet cane” of <a href="?bref=Isa.43.24">Isaiah 43:24</a> was the true sugarcane <span class="ital">(S. officinarum).</span> This plant is thought to have originated in the tropics of the eastern hemisphere. It has been cultivated by people since time immemorial and is not now known in the wild state anywhere. It is a tall, stout perennial grass, maizelike in aspect with many jointed stems and a large plumelike terminal cluster of flowers.</p>
<p class="h2" id="CaperPlant">Caper Plant <span class="ital">(Capparis sincula)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Spiny, trailing shrub of Mediterranean region; the flower bud of this shrub. The word “desire” in <a href="?bref=Eccl.12.5">Ecclesiastes 12:5</a> may actually refer to the caper berry. The common caper or caper berry grows profusely in Syria, Lebanon, the Holy Land, and in the mountain valleys of Sinai. The plant may sometimes grow upright but more generally spreads itself weakly over the ground like a vine, covering rocks, ruins, and old walls like ivy. The young flower buds, pickled in vinegar, were used by the ancients as a condiment for meat. The berries were also used in cooking.</p>
<p class="h2" id="CarobTree">Carob Tree <span class="ital">(Ceratonia siliqua)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Evergreen of the Mediterranean region having edible pods. Scholars generally agree that the pods of the carob or locust tree were the “husks” of Jesus’ parable of the prodigal son (<a href="?bref=Luke.15.16">Lk 15:16</a>). The carob is an attractive evergreen leguminous tree that is very common throughout the Holy Land, Syria, and Egypt. The pods are most abundant in April and May and contain numerous pealike seeds embedded in an agreeably flavored mucilaginous sweetish pulp. The pods are also used abundantly now as they were in antiquity for feeding cattle, horses, and pigs. In time of scarcity, they are used as human food and perhaps even regularly by the very poor. The carob is frequently mentioned in the Talmud as a source of good food for domestic animals. The seeds of the carob were formerly employed as a standard of weight and are the source of the term “carat.” Some commentators suggest that the “locusts” eaten by John the Baptist (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.4">Mt 3:4</a>) were not insects but the fruit of the carob tree.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Cassia">Cassia <span class="ital">(Cinnamomum cassia, Saussurea lappa)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Tree of tropical Asia with bark similar but inferior to cinnamon. The “cassia” of <a href="?bref=Exod.30.24">Exodus 30:24</a> and <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.19">Ezekiel 27:19</a> is the cassia bark tree, <span class="ital">Cinnamomum cassia.</span> In <a href="?bref=Ps.45.8">Psalm 45:8</a> the reference seems to be to the Indian orris, <span class="ital">Saussurea lappa.</span></p>
<p class="h2" id="CastorOilPlant">Castor Oil Plant <span class="ital">(Ricinus communis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Large plant, native to tropical Africa and Asia, cultivated for ornamental reasons and for extraction of oil from its seeds. The gourd of <a href="?bref=Jon.4.6-7">Jonah 4:6-7</a> was probably the ordinary castor bean. The castor bean is a tender shrub, growing 3 to 12 or more feet (.9 to 3.7 meters) tall with huge leaves that resemble the outstretched human hand. The castor bean plant is found in waste places, especially near water, in both Lebanon and the Holy Land and often is cultivated. In hot climates it becomes treelike and affords a dense shade by the abundance of its huge, umbrella-like leaves. It is known in the Orient for the rapidity of its growth. The oil extracted from the seeds of the castor bean was used by the Jews in ceremonial rites and is mentioned among the five kinds of oil that rabbinical tradition sanctioned for such use. The seeds themselves are poisonous when eaten.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Cedar">Cedar <span class="ital">(Cedrus libani)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of several coniferous evergreen trees of the genus native to the Old World. With few exceptions, the references to “cedar” are to the well-known cedar of Lebanon. This is a noble tree, the tallest and most massive with which the Israelites were acquainted. It grows quite rapidly, attaining a height of up to 120 feet (36.6 meters) with a trunk diameter of as much as 8 feet (2.4 meters). In Solomon’s day these trees were obviously abundant on the mountains of Lebanon, but now, because of excessive lumbering, they are very rare. The cedar of Lebanon was held in high esteem not only for its vigor, beauty, and age but also for the fragrance and remarkable lasting qualities of the wood. It symbolizes grandeur, might, majesty, dignity, lofty stature, and wide expansion. References in <a href="?bref=Ezek.17.3,22-24">Ezekiel 17:3, 22-24</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ezek.31.3-18">31:3-18</a> beautifully illustrate how these lofty kings of the forest symbolize and typify worldly strength, power, and glory.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Chicory">Chicory <span class="ital">(Cichorium intybus)</span></p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="#BitterHerbs">Bitter Herbs (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Cinnamon">Cinnamon <span class="ital">(Cinnamomum zeylanicum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Two varieties of trees of this genus, native to tropical Asia, with aromatic bark that, when ground, is used as a spice. The cinnamon of <a href="?bref=Exod.30.23">Exodus 30:23</a>, <a href="?bref=Pr.7.17">Proverbs 7:17</a>, <a href="?bref=Song.4.14">Song of Songs 4:14</a>, and <a href="?bref=Rev.18.13">Revelation 18:13</a> is undoubtedly <span class="ital">Cinnamomum zeylanicum.</span> The tree is a rather low-growing one, never getting more than 30 feet (9.1 meters) high, with a smooth, ash-colored bark and widespread branches and white flowers. Its shiny, beautifully veined evergreen leaves grow about nine inches (22.9 centimeters) long and two inches (5.1 centimeters) wide.</p>
<p>The Jews always regarded cinnamon as a deliciously fragrant substance and valued it highly as a spice and a perfume. It was one of the principal ingredients used in the manufacture of the precious ointments, or “holy oil,” that Moses was commanded to use in the tabernacle for anointing the sacred vessels and officiating priests. It was undoubtedly very costly and precious.</p>
<p class="h2" id="CitronTree">Citron Tree <span class="ital">(Tetraclinis articulata)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Tree native to Asia bearing lemonlike fruit with a thick, fragrant rind. It seldom exceeds a height of 30 feet (9.1 meters) and has hard, dark-colored, durable, fragrant wood that takes a fine polish. The wood was one of the most highly prized woods of the ancients, who employed it extensively for cabinetwork. It was commonly referred to as being worth its weight in gold. The wood, owing to its resinous properties, is slow to decay and remains practically uninjured by insects.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Coriander">Coriander <span class="ital">(Coriandrum sativum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The references in <a href="?bref=Exod.16.31">Exodus 16:31</a> and <a href="?bref=Num.11.7">Numbers 11:7</a> are clearly to the common coriander plant. The coriander was found quite commonly growing along with grain in cultivated fields throughout the Holy Land. It grows wild in Egypt and was used by the ancients both as condiment and as a medicine. The leaves are quite aromatic and are used in soups and for flavoring puddings, curries, and wines. The coriander is still used today as a spice by the Arabs. In Scripture it is mentioned only in connection with manna, which was said to resemble coriander seeds in size, shape, and color.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Cotton">Cotton <span class="ital">(Gossypium herbaceum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of various plants or shrubs of this genus grown in warm climates for the soft white fiber attached to their seeds and the oil from these seeds. The “green” of the <span class="sc">kjv</span> in <a href="?bref=Esth.1.6">Esther 1:6</a> is undoubtedly a reference to the Levant cotton <span class="ital">(Gossypium herbaceum)</span> that was cultivated since time immemorial in the Far East. Alexander the Great brought it back from India. It is probable that the Jews became acquainted with cotton during the period of their Persian captivity under King Ahasuerus.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Cucumber">Cucumber <span class="ital">(Cucumis chate, C. sativus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The cucumber is an annual climbing or trailing vine, the origin of which is unknown. It has been cultivated in all the warm countries of the Old World since prehistoric times. Cucumbers are usually eaten raw; a cucumber and a barley cake or some other kind of bread often constitute a meal. The reference to “a lodge in a garden of cucumbers” (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.8">Is 1:8</a>) refers to the crudely built small house or lodge often set up in Palestinian cucumber fields and vineyards.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Cummin">Cummin <span class="ital">(Cuminum cyminum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The references in <a href="?bref=Isa.28.25-27">Isaiah 28:25-27</a> and <a href="?bref=Matt.23.23">Matthew 23:23</a> are clearly to the cummin—a common, annual plant of the carrot family said to be native to Egypt and the region of the eastern Mediterranean. It has long been cultivated for its powerfully aromatic and pungent seeds, which are similar to caraway seeds but larger. They do not have as agreeable a taste as caraway seeds but nevertheless were used extensively as a flavor or spice and sometimes were even mixed with flour in making bread. Cummin was also used medicinally and as a condiment with fish and meats.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Cypress">Cypress <span class="ital">(Cupressus sempervirens horizontalis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The cypress is a massive, tall-growing evergreen with scalelike leaves and is widely distributed in the mountainous regions of the Holy Land. On Mt Lebanon and Mt Hermon it grows together with the cedar and oak. Its usual height is 50 to 60 feet (15.2 to 18.3 meters), but it may grow as tall as 80 feet (24.2 meters). It is said to have been used extensively in shipbuilding by the Phoenicians, Cretans, and Greeks. There is general agreement that the “gopher wood” of <a href="?bref=Gen.6.14">Genesis 6:14</a> is cypress because the wood is very durable.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Dandelion">Dandelion <span class="ital">(Taraxacum officinale)</span></p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="#BitterHerbs">Bitter Herbs (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DarnelGrass">Darnel Grass <span class="ital">(Lolium temulentum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">It is generally agreed that the “tares” of the <span class="sc">kjv</span> (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.24-30">Mt 13:24-30</a>) are the annual or bearded darnel grass. It is a strong grass closely resembling wheat or rye in appearance. The seeds are much smaller than those of wheat or rye, but it is extremely difficult to distinguish it from wheat or rye in its early stages. If it is not eradicated early but is left until the time of harvest, it is cut down with the wheat and the two are subsequently very difficult to separate. The seeds are poisonous, either due to some chemicals naturally present or because of a fungus that grows within the seeds.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Dill">Dill <span class="ital">(Anethum graveolens)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Dill is a weedy annual plant resembling parsley and fennel, 12 to 20 inches (30.5 to 50.8 centimeters) tall with yellow flowers. The reference in <a href="?bref=Matt.23.23">Matthew 23:23</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) to anise is probably a reference to dill. This plant is widely cultivated for seeds that are aromatic and carminative.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Ebony">Ebony <span class="ital">(Diospyros ebenaster, D. ebenum, D. mela</span><span class="ital">noxylon)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Chiefly tropical tree of southern Asia with hard, dark-colored heartwood. Ebony comes from the date plum or date tree <span class="ital">(Diospyros ebenaster</span> and <span class="ital">D. melanoxylon)</span> of India and is quite different from the date palm. It was sent by Phoenician ships across the Arabian Sea and up the Red Sea to the market in Tyre, from which it was carried overland by camel caravans. The outer wood of these trees is white and soft, but when old, the interior wood becomes hard, black, heavy, and durable and still constitutes most of the costly ebony of commerce. Ebony takes on a fine polish and is highly valued for cabinetwork, for turnery, for the manufacture of fancy ornamental articles and instruments, and as a veneer for other woods.</p>
<p>Ezekiel mentions ivory and ebony together (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.15">Ez 27:15</a>). Ebony was and still is frequently inlaid with ivory, with which it contrasts so strikingly in color.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Endive">Endive <span class="ital">(Cichorium endivia)</span></p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="#BitterHerbs">Bitter Herbs (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="FigFigTree">Fig, Fig Tree <span class="ital">(Ficus carica)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of several trees or shrubs of this genus, native to the Mediterranean region; its edible fruit. The common fig, mentioned some 60 times in the Bible, is one of the most important Bible plants. Its leaves are spoken of first in <a href="?bref=Gen.3.7">Genesis 3:7</a>. The fig is generally regarded as native to southwestern Asia and Syria, but already in early times it was also cultivated extensively in Egypt and the Holy Land, where it was one of the principal foods. <a href="?bref=1Sam.25.18">First Samuel 25:18</a> states that a part of the gift sent by Abigail to David consisted of 200 cakes of figs.</p>
<p>The fig tree has a very peculiar type of fruit called a syconium, which is actually a very much enlarged and fleshy receptacle. It is pollinated by a wasp, without which it cannot get its fruit; this was discovered when it was first transplanted to California.</p>
<p>The fig puts out its earliest fruit buds before its leaves, the former in February and the latter in April or May. When the leaves are out, the fruit ought to be ripe (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.19">Mt 21:19</a>).</p>
<p>Whenever the prophets of old berated the people for their wickedness, they often threatened that the vine and the fig crops would be destroyed. And when they held out the promise of great rewards, they said that the vine and fig crop would be restored (<a href="?bref=Jer.8.13">Jer 8:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.2.12">Hos 2:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.1.7,12">Jl 1:7, 12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.4.4">Mi 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.3.10">Zec 3:10</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="FirTree">Fir Tree <span class="ital">(Abies cilicica)</span></p>
<p class="fl">This a generic term for various evergreen trees having flat needles and erect cones. In all probability, most of the references in Scripture to the fir are references to the pine, cypress, or juniper. The only true fir in the Holy Land grows in the higher parts of Lebanon and the mountains northward. It attains a height of 30 to 75 feet (9.1 to 22.9 meters) and is widely cultivated.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Flax">Flax <span class="ital">(Linum usitatissimum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of several plants of this genus, one particularly being widely cultivated for the linseed oil from its seeds and the fine textile fibers from its stems. Flax is the oldest known of the textile fibers. Cotton is identified only once in the Bible (<a href="?bref=Esth.1.6">Est 1:6</a>). There is no mention of any other fiber plant being cultivated in Egypt or the Holy Land in biblical days, and for that reason it is thought that linen was the material out of which clothes other than woolen ones were made. Linen was also used for domestic purposes such as towels (<a href="?bref=John.13.4-5">Jn 13:4-5</a>), napkins (<a href="?bref=John.11.44">11:44</a>), girdles and undergarments (<a href="?bref=Isa.3.23">Is 3:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.51">Mk 14:51</a>), nets (<a href="?bref=Isa.19.8-9">Is 19:8-9</a>), and measuring lines (<a href="?bref=Ezek.40.3">Ez 40:3</a>). The priests serving in the temple were to wear nothing but linen clothes; a mixed cloth of wool and flax together was strictly forbidden to the Jews (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.19">Lv 19:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.22.11">Dt 22:11</a>).</p>
<p>At least three kinds of linen were used in biblical times, and apparently there were particular uses for each kind. Ordinary linen of coarsest texture is mentioned in <a href="?bref=Lev.6.10">Leviticus 6:10</a>, <a href="?bref=Ezek.9.2">Ezekiel 9:2</a>, <a href="?bref=Dan.10.5">Daniel 10:5</a>, and <a href="?bref=Rev.15.6">Revelation 15:6</a>. The second type of linen of superior quality is mentioned in <a href="?bref=Exod.26.1">Exodus 26:1</a> and <a href="?bref=Exod.39.27">39:27</a>. A third type of linen of finest texture and high cost is mentioned in <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.27">1 Chronicles 15:27</a>, <a href="?bref=Esth.8.15">Esther 8:15,</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.19.8">Revelation 19:8</a>.</p>
<p>The common flax plant grows from one to four feet (.3 to 1.2 meters) tall with a simple, slender, wirelike stem and numerous small, pale, lancelike green leaves. The failure of the flax crop is listed as one of God’s punishments (<a href="?bref=Hos.2.9">Hos 2:9</a>). The manufacture of linen from flax fibers was a domestic industry of Jewish women (<a href="?bref=Pr.31.13,19">Prv 31:13, 19</a>), ranging from ordinary clothing to the robes and aprons worn by the priest and temple attendants. Linen was also used for wicks in lamps (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.3">Is 42:3</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Frankincense">Frankincense <span class="ital">(Boswellia)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Aromatic genus resin used chiefly as incense. Frankincense is obtained from three species of a single genus of plants that grow in southern Arabia, Ethiopia, Somaliland, India, and the East Indies. The trees are large in size, related to the turpentine or terebinth tree and to those that produce balsam and myrrh. The gum has a bitter taste and gives off a strong odor in the form of a volatile oil when warmed or burned. It is obtained by successive incisions in the bark of the trunk and in the branches of living trees. It is thought that the Hebrews imported all their frankincense from Arabia, especially from the region about Sheba.</p>
<p>Frankincense is mentioned 21 times in the Bible (e.g., <a href="?bref=Exod.30.34">Ex 30:34</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.29">1 Chr 9:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.13.9">Neh 13:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.3.6">Sg 3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.6,14">4:6, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.2.11">Mt 2:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.18.13">Rv 18:13</a>) and was probably employed almost exclusively in the sacrificial services of the tabernacle and temple until the time of Solomon. It has always been the most important incense resin in the world.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Galbanum">Galbanum <span class="ital">(Ferula galbaniflua)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Galbanum is a malodorous yellowish or brownish gum resin containing the chemical substance umbelliferone, obtained from several species of plants related to the fennel, native to Syria and Persia. The gum is a natural exudation of the stem or is obtained by making a transverse incision in the young stem a few inches above the ground. The milky juice soon hardens and forms one of the kinds of commercial galbanum. Its odor is strongly balsamic, pungent, and disagreeable when burned. Galbanum was one of the ingredients used to form the “holy incense” (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.34">Ex 30:34</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Garlic">Garlic <span class="ital">(Allium sativum)</span></p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="#Onion">Onion (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="GourdWild">Gourd, Wild <span class="ital">(Citrullus colocynthis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">There has been considerable difference of opinion regarding the meaning of the words translated “wild gourds” (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.39">2 Kgs 4:39</a>) or “gall” (<a href="?bref=Deut.29.18">Dt 29:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.32.32">32:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.69.21">Ps 69:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.8.14">Jer 8:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.9.15">9:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.15">23:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.3.5,19">Lam 3:5, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.6.12">Am 6:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.27.34">Mt 27:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.8.23">Acts 8:23</a>). Most scholars today believe the plant referred to was the colocynth, a cucumber-like vine that trails on the ground or climbs over shrubs and fences. The fruit contains a soft spongy pulp, which is intensely bitter, strongly cathartic, and sometimes poisonous.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Hedge">Hedge <span class="ital">(Rhamnus palaestina, Balanites aegyptiaca, Lycium europaeum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Row of closely planted shrubs or low-growing trees forming a fence or boundary. A number of plants were used to provide hedges in Bible times. One of these was the Palestine buckthorn, <span class="ital">Rhamnus palaestina.</span> This plant is a shrub or a small tree growing from three to six feet (.9 to 1.8 meters) tall with velvety, thorny branches, evergreen leaves, and clusters of small flowers blooming in March and April. It grows in thickets and on hillsides from Syria through the Holy Land to Arabia and the Sinai. The Jericho balsam <span class="ital">(Balanites aegyptiaca)</span> and the European boxthorn <span class="ital">(Lycium europaeum)</span> are also prickly shrubs widely used as hedges in the Holy Land and may be the plants referred to in <a href="?bref=Pr.15.19">Proverbs 15:19</a> and <a href="?bref=Hos.2.6">Hosea 2:6</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Henna">Henna <span class="ital">(Lawsonia inermis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Tree or shrub of Asia and northern Africa with fragrant reddish or white flowers and leaves from which a reddish dye is made. The plant referred to in <a href="?bref=Song.1.14">Song of Songs 1:14</a> and <a href="?bref=Song.4.13">4:13</a> and translated as “camphire” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) is thought by scholars today to refer to the henna plant. It is a native of northern India and grows wild in the Sudan, Egypt, Arabia, Syria, Lebanon, and the Holy Land. It grows from 4 to 12 feet (1.2 to 3.7 meters) tall, and its scent is similar to that of roses.</p>
<p>Henna leaves are dried, crushed into a powder, mixed with water, and made into a paste that has been used since time immemorial as a cosmetic. A number of mummies have been found decorated with henna. Henna was used to provide a bright yellow, orange, or red color to the fingernails, toenails, the tips of the fingers, the palms of the hand, and the soles of the feet of young girls. Men also used it for coloring their beards and the manes and tails of horses. The dye had to be renewed once every two or three weeks. This use of henna as a cosmetic was common in Egypt at the time the children of Israel were there as slaves; they were undoubtedly familiar with it.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Hyacinth">Hyacinth <span class="ital">(Hyacinthus orientalis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The lily referred to in <a href="?bref=Song.2.1-2,16">Song of Songs 2:1-2, 16</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.5">4:5</a>; and <a href="?bref=Song.6.2-4">6:2-4</a> may well be the garden hyacinth. It is native to, and very common in, the fields and rocky places in the Holy Land, Lebanon, and northward. Its flowers in the wild form are always deep blue and very fragrant.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Lily">Lily (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Hyssop">Hyssop <span class="ital">(Origanum maru)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Woody plant native to Asia with spikes of small blue flowers and aromatic leaves used as a condiment and in perfumery. There is little agreement among botanists as to the exact identity of the biblical “hyssop.” Some have suggested <span class="ital">Hyssopus offici</span><span class="ital">nalis,</span> the well-known garden herb now called hyssop. However, this plant is not native either to the Holy Land or Egypt, being found only in southern Europe. Moreover, it does not fit the requirements of the biblical plant.</p>
<p>The “hyssop” of the OT is likely the Syrian or Egyptian marjoram <span class="ital">(Origanum maru).</span> It is referred to in <a href="?bref=Exod.12.22">Exodus 12:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.14.4-6,52">Leviticus 14:4-6, 52</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.19.6,18">Numbers 19:6, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.33">1 Kings 4:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.51.7">Psalm 51:7</a>; and <a href="?bref=Heb.9.19">Hebrews 9:19</a>. The marjorams are mints growing (under favorable conditions) about two or three feet (.6 to .9 meter) tall, but more often are dwarfed when growing in rock crevices and walls (cf. <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.33">1 Kgs 4:33</a>). An aromatic substance is obtained from the crushed and dried leaves. If gathered together in a bunch with leaves and flowers, the hairy stems of the marjoram would hold liquid very well and would make an excellent sprinkler.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="Hyssop"/>
<p>The hyssop of the crucifixion passage in the NT (<a href="?bref=John.19.29">Jn 19:29</a>) is probably the sorghum, a tall cereal plant grown primarily for food but also used for brushes and mops.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Juniper">Juniper <span class="ital">(Juniperus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Variety of evergreen tree or shrub. The plant referred to in <a href="?bref=Jer.17.6">Jeremiah 17:6</a> and <a href="?bref=Jer.48.6">48:6</a> and translated in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> “heath” is probably the savin or Phoenician juniper. The Phoenician juniper, <span class="ital">Juniperus phoenicia,</span> is found in the hills and rocky places of Arabia. The savin juniper, <span class="ital">J. sabina,</span> is common throughout the deserts, plains, and rocky places of Syria and Palestine. These references are to the brown-berried cedar, or sharp cedar.</p>
<p class="h2" id="LaurelorSweetBay">Laurel or Sweet Bay <span class="ital">(Laurus nobilis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Shrub or tree native to the Mediterranean region. While the reference in <a href="?bref=Ps.37.35">Psalm 37:35</a> may be to the cedar of Lebanon, most scholars refer the “green bay tree” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) of the psalmist to the sweet bay, a native of the Holy Land, inhabiting thickets and woods from the coast to the middle montane zone. It is an evergreen tree attaining a height from 40 to 60 feet (12.2 to 18.3 meters).</p>
<p>Even though the tree is abundant on Mt Carmel and around Hebron, it is generally not common in the Holy Land. Its leaves are still used as a condiment, and its fruit, leaves, and bark have long been used in medicine.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Leek">Leek <span class="ital">(Allium porrum)</span></p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="#Onion">Onion (below)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Lentil">Lentil <span class="ital">(Lens esculenta)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The lentil plant to which <a href="?bref=Gen.25.29-34">Genesis 25:29-34</a>, <a href="?bref=2Sam.17.27-29">2 Samuel 17:27-29</a>, <a href="?bref=2Sam.23.11">23:11</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ezek.4.9">Ezekiel 4:9</a> refer is a small, erect, annual, vetchlike plant with slender stems and tendril-bearing leaves. It produces small, white, violet-striped flowers with flat, pealike pods in which the lentils are borne.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Lettuce">Lettuce <span class="ital">(Lactuca sativa)</span></p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="#BitterHerbs">Bitter Herbs (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Lily">Lily <span class="ital">(Lilium)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of various plants of the genus <span class="ital">Lilium</span> having large, variously colored, trumpet-shaped flowers; and related plants. The lily is one of the most famous of all the plants in the Bible, but it is also one about which there has been considerable difference of opinion. It seems probable that several kinds of plants, perhaps five or six, are called lilies in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>. Most authorities regard the Palestine anemone or wind flower, <span class="ital">Anemone coronaria,</span> as the “lily of the field” (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.28">Mt 6:28</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>) that surpassed Solomon in all his glory. These flowers are found in every part of the Holy Land in profusion; the most common forms are scarlet or yellow, but the Palestine anemone may also be blue, purple, rose, or white in color. The flower attains a diameter of two and three-quarter inches (7 centimeters).</p>
<p>An alternative suggestion is the Palestinian chamomile, <span class="ital">Anthemis palaestina,</span> a common, white, daisylike plant. The chamomile is gathered like dry grass and thrown into the furnace when it dries up.</p>
<p>Another proposed plant is <span class="ital">Lilium chalcedonicum,</span> the scarlet or Martagon lily. The statement in <a href="?bref=Song.5.13">Song of Songs 5:13</a>—“his lips like lilies”—would better fit this plant than the Palestine anemone. The reference is apparently to a rare plant of exceptional beauty. The scarlet lily is rare in the Holy Land; indeed, some botanists doubt that it lives there.</p>
<p>The references in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.19,22,26">1 Kings 7:19, 22, 26</a> and <a href="?bref=2Chr.4.5">2 Chronicles 4:5</a> are probably to the water lily, <span class="ital">Nymphaea alba,</span> which served as the pattern. The water lily is quite common in Europe and also in the Holy Land and northern Africa.</p>
<p class="h2" id="LotusBush">Lotus Bush <span class="ital">(Zizyphus lotus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The “shady trees” of <a href="?bref=Job.40.21-22">Job 40:21-22</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>; cf. <span class="sc">nlt</span> “lotus plants”) may refer to the lotus bush of the Middle East, <span class="ital">Zizyphus lotus,</span> a shrub or low tree that grows to a height of about five feet (1.5 meters) with smooth, zigzag, whitish branches.</p>
<p>Other commentators believe that the shady trees of Job are large-leafed trees such as the plane tree, <span class="ital">Platanus orientalis,</span> or the oleander, <span class="ital">Nerium oleander.</span> This suggestion is based on the assumption that the animal described in <a href="?bref=Job.40.1-24">Job 40</a> is the hippopotamus, and it seems unlikely that the hippopotamus would live under a lotus bush or even be found in places where this shrub grows. These individuals regard the plane tree or the oleander as more likely.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Mallow">Mallow <span class="ital">(Atriplex)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The Hebrew word used in <a href="?bref=Job.30.4">Job 30:4</a> implies saltiness, and for this reason botanists believe that it refers to one of the species of the saltwort or orach. Twenty-one species of saltwort occur in the Holy Land, almost all of which are common and could well meet the requirements of the text. <span class="ital">Atriplex halimus</span> is the species usually suggested, a strong-growing bushy shrub related to the spinach.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Mandrake">Mandrake <span class="ital">(Mandragora officinarum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The mandrake or love apple is a stemless herbaceous perennial related to the nightshade, potato, and tomato. It has a large, beetlike, often forked taproot from the top of which arise many dark leaves about a foot (30.5 centimeters) long and four inches (10.2 centimeters) wide. The plant is slightly poisonous, and the thick taproots have some resemblance in shape to the lower parts of the human body. For this reason certain aphrodisiac properties were ascribed to it (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.30.14-16">Gn 30:14-16</a>).</p>
<p>The love apple was a common plant in deserted fields throughout the Holy Land. It is native to the entire Mediterranean region, southern Europe, and Asia Minor. The mandrake is mentioned in <a href="?bref=Song.7.13">Song of Songs 7:13</a>, though some scholars believe the writer may actually have been referring to the citron or to the common edible field mushroom, <span class="ital">Agaricus campestris.</span></p>
<p class="h2" id="Melon">Melon <span class="ital">(Cucumis melo, Citrullus vulgaris)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of several varieties of these two related vines having a hard rind and juicy flesh. The melons of <a href="?bref=Num.11.5">Numbers 11:5</a> may be either the muskmelon <span class="ital">(Cucumis melo)</span> or the watermelon <span class="ital">(Citrullus vulgaris).</span> It may be that both fruits are referred to.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="Melon"/>
<p class="h2" id="Millet">Millet <span class="ital">(Panicum miliaceum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">A grass grown in Eurasia for its edible seed. Millet seeds are the smallest of all the grass seeds cultivated as food but are produced profusely. Millet is an annual grass seldom more that two feet (.6 meter) tall. The small seeds of the millet are used on cakes and eaten uncooked by the poor of the land.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Mint">Mint <span class="ital">(Mentha)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of various plants of this family with aromatic foliage that is processed for flavoring. Quite a few mints are common in the Holy Land, but the horse mint <span class="ital">(Mentha longifolia)</span> is probably the one referred to in <a href="?bref=Matt.23.23">Matthew 23:23</a> and <a href="?bref=Luke.11.42">Luke 11:42</a>. Mints were employed by the ancient Hebrews, Greeks, and Romans for flavoring, as a carminative in medicine, and as a condiment in cooking.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Mulberry">Mulberry <span class="ital">(Morus nigra)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any tree of this family, some bearing dark-purple fruit and one bearing white fruit, having leaves used as food for silkworms. The sycamine tree of <a href="?bref=Luke.17.6">Luke 17:6</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) is evidently the black mulberry, <span class="ital">Morus nigra.</span> It is a low-growing, thick-crowned, stiff-branched tree standing from 24 to 35 feet (7.3 to 10.7 meters) tall, though rarely more than 30 feet (9.1 meters) tall. Originally native to northern Persia, it is now cultivated throughout the Middle East for its fruit. The Chinese or Indian species, <span class="ital">M. alba,</span> was until recently widely cultivated in Syria and the Holy Land but is not indigenous.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Mustard">Mustard <span class="ital">(Brassica nigra, B. arvensis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Various plants of this genus are native to Eurasia, some of which are cultivated for their edible seeds. While there is disagreement about the identity of the “mustard” of <a href="?bref=Matt.13.31-32">Matthew 13:31-32</a>, <a href="?bref=Matt.17.20">17:20</a>, <a href="?bref=Mark.4.31">Mark 4:31</a>, <a href="?bref=Luke.13.19">Luke 13:19</a>, and <a href="?bref=Luke.17.6">17:6</a>, it is generally thought to be the ordinary black mustard, <span class="ital">Brassica nigra.</span></p>
<p>The mustard Jesus referred to may be the charlock or wild mustard, <span class="ital">B. arvensis,</span> which normally grows from one to three feet (.3 to .9 meter) tall. Some have suggested that it was actually <span class="ital">Salvadora persica,</span> found in thickets around the Dead Sea. The plant has a pleasant aromatic taste resembling that of mustard, and if taken in considerable quantity, it will produce an irritation of the nose and eyes similar to that of mustard. However, this plant does not grow as far north as Galilee, and the fruits are rather large and stony, thus hardly fitting the description of the parable.</p>
<p>While the seeds of the mustard are not the smallest known, they were probably the smallest familiar to the common people who comprised Jesus’ audience in Galilee.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Myrrh">Myrrh <span class="ital">(Commiphora myrrha, C. kataf)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Shrub or tree exuding an aromatic gum resin used in perfume and incense. Most of the references in Scripture to myrrh are to <span class="ital">Commiphora myrrha,</span> although <span class="ital">C. kataf</span> may also be involved since it grows in the same region and is similar. The two trees are native to Arabia, Ethiopia, and the Somali coast of east Africa. They yield a gummy exudation that constitutes most of the myrrh of commerce. Both species are low, scrubby, thick- and stiff-branched thorny shrubs or small trees that grow in rocky places, especially on limestone hills. In the East it is highly regarded as an aromatic substance, perfume, and medicine. The ancient Egyptians burned it in their temples and embalmed their dead with it; the Jews also used it for embalming (<a href="?bref=John.19.39">Jn 19:39</a>). The Hebrews held it in high regard as a perfume (<a href="?bref=Ps.45.8">Ps 45:8</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="Myrrh"/>
<p class="h2" id="Myrtle">Myrtle <span class="ital">(Myrtus communis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The myrtle tree is common in the Holy Land, especially around Bethlehem, Lebanon, Hebron, and the slopes of Mt Carmel and Mt Tabor. It is native to western Asia and in good environments grows into a small evergreen tree 20 to 30 feet (6.2 to 9.1 meters) tall. More often, however, it is a straggling bush 1½ to 4 feet (.5 to 1.2 meters) tall.</p>
<p>In the Bible, myrtle is referred to chiefly as a symbol of God’s generosity. Branches of myrtle trees were included among those that Nehemiah ordered to be gathered for the Feast of Tabernacles (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.15">Neh 8:15</a>). The myrtle was symbolic not only of peace but also of justice.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="Myrtle"/>
<p class="h2" id="Narcissus">Narcissus <span class="ital">(Narcissus tazetta)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Widely cultivated plant of this family with narrow leaves and usually white or yellow flowers with a cup-crown or trumpet-shaped crown. The polyanthus narcissus <span class="ital">(Narcissus tazetta)</span> appears to be the plant referred to in <a href="?bref=Isa.35.1">Isaiah 35:1</a>. This narcissus grows abundantly on the plains of Sharon and elsewhere in Palestine. Being sweet-smelling, it is a great favorite.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Nard">Nard <span class="ital">(Nardostachys jatamansi)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The nard is a perennial herb with strong, pleasantly scented roots. It is native to high altitudes in the Himalayas, and its range extends from there into western Asia. The roots and spikelike wooly young stems are dried before the leaves unfold and are used for making perfume. It is still used in India as a perfume for the hair, and there is every reason to believe that the spikenard of Scripture (<a href="?bref=Song.1.12">Sg 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.13-14">4:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.3">Mk 14:3</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.3">Jn 12:3</a>) came originally from India.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Nettle">Nettle <span class="ital">(Urtica)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Plant of this genus having toothed leaves covered with hairs that exude a stinging flush. Four species of nettle are found in the Holy Land: the common or great nettle, <span class="ital">Urtica dioica;</span> the Roman nettle, <span class="ital">U. pilulifera;</span> the small nettle, <span class="ital">U. urens;</span> and <span class="ital">U. caudata,</span> which is similar to the small nettle. Some nettles attain a height of five to six feet (1.5 to 1.8 meters). They are common pests of waste places and fields. They are often seen occupying ground that was once cultivated but has since been neglected (<a href="?bref=Isa.34.13">Is 34:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.9.6">Hos 9:6</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="NutmegFlower">Nutmeg Flower <span class="ital">(Nigella sativa)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The “fitches” of <a href="?bref=Isa.28.25-27">Isaiah 28:25-27</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) are probably the nutmeg flower, an annual plant of the buttercup family. The plant grows wild in southern Europe, Syria, Egypt, north Africa, and other Mediterranean lands, where it is extensively cultivated for its strongly pungent, pepperlike aromatic seeds. These are sprinkled over some kinds of bread and cakes in the East and are used for flavoring curries and other dishes in the Holy Land and Egypt. Cummin and nutmeg flowers are still gathered in the Holy Land in the same way described by Isaiah.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Oak">Oak <span class="ital">(Quercus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">At least five species of oaks are found in Palestine. One of these is the kermes oak <span class="ital">(Quercus coccifera),</span> the host of the insect <span class="ital">Coccus ilicis,</span> which produces the scarlet dye used in coloring linen and wool (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.28-30">Gn 38:28-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.25.4">Ex 25:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.26.1">26:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.28.33">28:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.35.23">35:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.39.24">39:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.14.4-6,51-52">Lv 14:4-6, 51-52</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.19.6">Nm 19:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.2.7,14">2 Chr 2:7, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.3.14">3:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.18">Is 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.19">Heb 9:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.18.12">Rv 18:12</a>). The kermes oak grows from 6 to 35 feet (1.8 to 10.7 meters) tall and is found in the mountainous regions of Syria, Lebanon, and the Holy Land. When it grows alone, the kermes oak often becomes a large tree. It was regularly planted by tombs in the East. The oak was always respected and even venerated in biblical times for its large size and strength, and great men were usually buried in its shade. Abraham’s oak in Hebron is an example.</p>
<p>A second oak is the valonia oak <span class="ital">(Q. aegilops),</span> perhaps the oak of <a href="?bref=Isa.2.13">Isaiah 2:13</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.44.14">44:14</a>. It is common in the middle montane zones and probably was abundant in the area around Bashan. The oak of <a href="?bref=Gen.35.4,8">Genesis 35:4, 8</a> is thought to have been the holm oak <span class="ital">(Q. ilex),</span> an evergreen oak that grows to a height of 60 feet (18.3 meters). Still another oak is <span class="ital">Q. lusitanica,</span> the cypress oak, a small deciduous tree seldom more than 20 feet (6.1 meters) tall. The very large acorns of this tree were sometimes eaten.</p>
<p>The word translated “plain” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) in <a href="?bref=Gen.12.6">Genesis 12:6</a>, <a href="?bref=Gen.13.18">13:18</a>, <a href="?bref=Gen.14.13">14:13</a>, and <a href="?bref=Gen.18.1">18:1</a> should probably be translated “oak.” </p>
<p>The many references to “groves” in the OT, usually in connection with the worship of Baal or other heathen gods (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.13">Ex 34:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.16.21">Dt 16:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.3.7">Jgs 3:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.23">1 Kgs 14:23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.19">18:19</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.16">2 Kgs 17:16</a>—all <span class="sc">kjv</span>), were probably groves of sacred oak trees.</p>
<p class="h2" id="OilTreeOleaster">Oil Tree, Oleaster <span class="ital">(Elaeagnus angustifolia)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Small Eurasian tree with oblong silvery leaves, greenish flowers, and olivelike fruit. There is question as to which tree is referred to when <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.23,31-33">1 Kings 6:23, 31-33</a> and <a href="?bref=1Chr.27.28">1 Chronicles 27:28</a> refer to “olive trees.” The same word occurs in <a href="?bref=Isa.41.19">Isaiah 41:19</a> and <a href="?bref=Mic.6.7">Micah 6:7</a>. The plant referred to is probably the narrow-leaved oleaster <span class="ital">(Elaeagnus angustifolia),</span> a small stiff-branched tree or graceful shrub growing from 15 to 20 feet (4.6 to 6.1 meters) tall, common in all parts of the Holy Land except in the Jordan Valley. At one time it was particularly common on Mt Tabor and at Hebron and Samaria. The wood is hard and fine-grained and therefore well suited for carving of images and figures. The oil that it yields is a rather inferior type used in medication but not for food; this may be the oil of <a href="?bref=Mic.6.7">Micah 6:7</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Oleander">Oleander <span class="ital">(Nerium oleander)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any poisonous evergreen shrub of this genus growing in warm climates. One of the suggestions for the plants identified as “roses” in various translations (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.24.14">Ecclus 24:14</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>) is the oleander. This plant, originally native to the East Indies, has been cultivated throughout the warm regions of the world for centuries. It flourishes in the Holy Land today and forms dense thickets in some parts of the Jordan Valley. It is usually a shrub from 3 to 12 feet (.9 to 3.7 meters) tall. Every part of the plant is dangerously poisonous.</p>
<p class="h2" id="OliveOliveTree">Olive, Olive Tree <span class="ital">(Olea europaea)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Old world semitropical evergreen tree bearing edible fruit. The olive, <span class="ital">Olea europaea,</span> was unquestionably one of the most valuable trees known to the Jews. There are innumerable references to it in Scripture, as well as to olive oil, which was used for anointing. The tree is quite common in the Holy Land, and in many places it is the only tree of any substantial size. The branches of the wild olive are rather stiff and spinescent, and the typical cultivated tree is a multi-branched evergreen, 20 or more feet (6.1 meters) tall, with a gnarled trunk and smooth, ash-colored bark. The leaves are leathery and the flowers are small, yellow or white. The fruits are large, black or violet, ripening in September, and it is the outer fleshy parts of the fruit that yield the valuable olive oil of commerce. Thirty-one percent of the ripe fruit is oil. The ripe fruit is eaten raw, as is the green, unripe fruit. The wood of the trunk and limbs is hard, rich yellow or amber in color, and fine-grained, often handsomely variegated. It is still used today for the finest cabinetwork and turnery. The tree grows very slowly, but it attains a great age. It is difficult to kill the olive tree by cutting it down, because new sprouts are sent up from the root and all around the margins of the old stump, often forming a grove of two to five trunks, all from a single root that originally supported only one tree.</p>
<p class="h3" id="Onion">Onion <span class="ital">(Allium)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The onions referred to in <a href="?bref=Num.11.5">Numbers 11:5</a> are undoubtedly <span class="ital">Allium cepa,</span> the Egyptian onion, which is made up of a compact coated bulb formed of layers consisting of broad fleshy bases of closely overlapping leaves. The leaves are slender and hollow. The entire plant has a characteristic pungent taste and odor.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="LeeksAndOnions"/>
<p>Closely related to the onion is the garlic, <span class="ital">A. sativum.</span> The common garlic is a hardy, bulbous perennial plant that is cultivated in Europe, western Asia, and Egypt. The leaves are narrow, flat, and ribbonlike. It is extremely popular with people of the Mediterranean region.</p>
<p>Still another one of the onions is the leek, <span class="ital">A. porrum.</span> The bulb of the leek differs from that of the onion and garlic in that it is slender, cylindrical, and more than six inches (15.2 centimeters) in length. The flavor resembles that of the onion but is more pungent. The leaves are eaten as a relish or are cooked in soups. The bulbs are cut into small pieces and employed as seasoning for meat.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Palm">Palm <span class="ital">(Phoenix dactylifera)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The palm tree of the Bible is undoubtedly the date palm. At one time it was as characteristic of the Holy Land as it is still today of Egypt. It is characterized by a branchless, tapering stem of up to 80 feet (24.2 meters) or more in height and a large terminal cluster of feathery leaves, each six to nine feet (1.8 to 2.7 meters) or more long. Because of its height and unusual structure, it was natural that it should be used as a form of ornamentation in Eastern architecture. The stem and leaves were favorite subjects of architectural embellishment. The immense, branchlike leaves that are referred to as branches in the Bible were symbols of triumph and were used on occasions of great rejoicing (<a href="?bref=John.12.13">Jn 12:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.7.9">Rv 7:9</a>). The large leaves are still used to cover the roofs and sides of houses and to give solidity to reed fences. Mats, baskets, and even dishes are made of them. Small leaves are used as dusters, and the wood of the trunk is used for timber. Rope is made from the weblike integument in the crown. The fruit, borne in an immense drooping cluster, which may weigh from 30 to 50 pounds (13.6 to 22.7 kilograms), is the chief food of many natives of Arabia and north Africa. A single tree may yield up to 200 pounds (90.7 kilograms) of dates a year. They may be dried for future use.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Papyrus">Papyrus <span class="ital">(Cyperus papyrus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The Egyptian bulrush or papyrus (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.3-5">Ex 2:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.8.11">Jb 8:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.18.2">Is 18:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.19.6-7">19:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.35.7">35:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.58.5">58:5</a>) has smooth three-sided stems ordinarily attaining a height of 8 to 10 feet (2.4 to 3 meters), but sometimes even 16 feet (4.9 meters), and a thickness of two to three inches (5.1 to 7.6 centimeters) at the base with a large tuft of florets at the end. The papyrus formerly grew in great abundance along the banks of the Nile, forming what was almost a dense jungle. Today it is practically extinct in lower Egypt, although it is still found along the White Nile and in the Sudan. The papyrus still grows in parts of the Holy Land, especially around the north end of the plain of Galilee and the Huleh swamps.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="Papyrus"/>
<p>In addition to being used for making small vessels to float in water (<a href="?bref=Exod.2.3">Ex 2:3</a>), for mats, and for various other domestic purposes, it is best known as the source of ancient paper. In manufacturing paper from papyrus, the stems of the plant were first peeled and the pitch then cut longitudinally into thin slices that were laid side by side. These were then sprinkled with water and pressed to unite the whole into one piece. The sheet was then dried and cut into pieces of the required size. In the better grades of papyrus paper, several layers of stem slices were laid crosswise on each other.</p>
<p>The pale, fawn-colored, tassel-like inflorescences at the summit of the stems were used to adorn Egyptian temples and to crown the statues of gods. They were also worn as crowns by famous men and national heroes.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PineTree">Pine Tree <span class="ital">(Pinus brutia, P. halepensis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Various evergreen trees of this family with needle-shaped leaves in clusters and seed-bearing cones. While there is considerable confusion concerning the conifers of the Bible, it seems apparent that pines are referred to in such passages as <a href="?bref=Lev.23.40">Leviticus 23:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.8.15">Nehemiah 8:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.41.19">Isaiah 41:19</a>; and <a href="?bref=Isa.60.13">60:13</a>. One of the Holy Land’s pines is the Brutian pine <span class="ital">(Pinus brutia),</span> a mountain-inhabiting species of the northern regions of Palestine. It attains a height of 10 to 35 feet (3 to 10.7 meters) with a rather diffuse growth and branches in whorls.</p>
<p>Another of the pines is the Aleppo pine, <span class="ital">Pinus halepensis.</span> Most of the instances of the occurrence of “fir” or “fir tree” in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> probably refer to the Aleppo pine (<a href="?bref=2Sam.6.5">2 Sm 6:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.8,10">1 Kgs 5:8, 10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.34">6:34</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.23">2 Kgs 19:23</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.2.8">2 Chr 2:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.104.17">Ps 104:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.1.17">Sg 1:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.14.8">Is 14:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.37.24">37:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.55.13">55:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.60.13">60:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.5">Ez 27:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.31.8">31:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.14.8">Hos 14:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Nah.2.3">Na 2:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.11.2">Zec 11:2</a>). It grows from 9 to 60 feet (2.7 to 18.3 meters) tall with diffuse ascending branches and yellowish or brownish branchlets.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Pistachio">Pistachio <span class="ital">(Pistacia terebinthus, P. vera)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The Palestine terebinth or turpentine tree is a large deciduous tree with straggling boughs. In the winter, without its leaves, it looks much like the oak. It grows from 12 to 25 feet (3.7 to 7.6 meters) tall. Every part of the tree contains a fragrant, resinous juice. It is common on the lower slopes of the hills throughout Syria, Lebanon, Palestine, and Arabia, generally growing as a solitary tree and found mostly in localities too warm or too dry for the oak that it generally replaces. Since it is native to Gilead, it is quite probable that its resinous juice formed part of the spicery that the Israelites carried to Egypt from Gilead (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.25">Gn 37:25</a>).</p>
<p>The nuts of <a href="?bref=Gen.43.11">Genesis 43:11</a> are apparently pistachio nuts from the pistachio tree, <span class="ital">Pistacia vera,</span> closely related to the terebinth. It attains a height of 10 to 30 feet (3 to 9.1 meters) with a spreading top. It is found wild in many rocky parts of Lebanon and the Holy Land. The nut has a light-colored shell and the kernel has a sweet delicate flavor much relished wherever it grows.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PlaneTree">Plane Tree <span class="ital">(Platanus orientalis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of several trees of this family with bell-shaped fruit clusters and usually an outer bark that flakes off in patches or strips. The references in <a href="?bref=Gen.30.37">Genesis 30:37</a> and <a href="?bref=Ezek.31.8">Ezekiel 31:8</a> are apparently not to the chestnut tree, which is not indigenous to Palestine, but to the oriental plane tree, <span class="ital">Platanus orientalis.</span></p>
<p>The plane tree is a massive tree 60 feet (18.3 meters) or more tall with a trunk often of vast circumference, sometimes as much as 40 feet (12.2 meters). The outer bark peels off in sheets or scales, thus exposing a smooth whitish or yellowish inner bark. The tree is common throughout Lebanon, Syria, and the Holy Land, growing even in subalpine regions. However, it is primarily a tree of the plains and lowlands, growing on the edges of streams and lakes and in marshy places.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Pomegranate">Pomegranate <span class="ital">(Punica granatum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The pomegranate is usually a small, bushlike tree but may occasionally become a large, branching shrub or small tree reaching a height of 20 to 30 feet (6.1 to 9.1 meters). The branches are often thorny. The showy bell-like flowers are usually scarlet, though sometimes yellow or white. The globular fruit is as large as an orange or medium-size apple. It has a hard rind of a bright red or yellowish color when ripe and is surmounted by the dry sepals that resemble a crown. The fruit itself is a crimson juicy pulp in which many red seeds are imbedded. The flowers of the pomegranate undoubtedly served as a pattern for the golden bells referred to in <a href="?bref=Exod.28.33-34">Exodus 28:33-34</a> and <a href="?bref=Exod.39.24-26">39:24-26</a>, and the open flowers of <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.32">1 Kings 6:32</a>. The erect calyx lobes on the fruit served as a model for crowns of kings.</p>
<p>The pomegranate is native to Asia, but it has been cultivated since prehistoric times and is now quite common in the Holy Land, in Egypt, and along the shores of the Mediterranean. It is listed as one of the pleasant fruits of Egypt (<a href="?bref=Num.20.5">Nm 20:5</a>) and one of the promised blessings of the Holy Land (<a href="?bref=Deut.8.8">Dt 8:8</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Poplar">Poplar <span class="ital">(Populus euphratica, P. alba)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Fast-growing deciduous tree of the same genus as the aspen and cottonwood. The <span class="sc">kjv</span> references in <a href="?bref=2Sam.5.23-24">2 Samuel 5:23-24</a> and <a href="?bref=1Chr.14.14-15">1 Chronicles 14:14-15</a> to mulberry trees are more probably to the Euphrates poplar or aspen, <span class="ital">Populus euphratica.</span> This tree grows to a height of 30 to 45 feet (9.1 to 13.7 meters) with spreading branches. The Euphrates aspen is found only on rivers and stream banks throughout the area from Syria through the Holy Land to Stony Arabia. It is especially common in the Jordan Valley.</p>
<p>The white poplar <span class="ital">(Populus alba)</span> is common in wet places in Syria, Lebanon, the Holy Land, and Sinai. It attains a height of 30 to 60 feet (9.1 to 18.3 meters) with spreading branches. Some suggest that the altars of various pagan religions were usually erected on the top of a hill and in the shade of a poplar grove.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Quince">Quince <span class="ital">(Cydonia oblonga)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Tree native to western Asia, having white flowers and applelike fruit that is edible when cooked. Some believe that the “apples” of the OT were quinces, <span class="ital">Cydonia oblonga.</span> The quince tree is quite common in the Holy Land, though chiefly as a cultivated tree. It may occur wild in the northern parts of Syria. It is native to northern Persia and Asia Minor. The fruit is yellowish and highly fragrant, and it is the fragrance that caused it to be held in high regard by the ancients.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Reed">Reed <span class="ital">(Juncus, Scirpus, Typha angustata, Arundo donax)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Numerous species of the rush and bulrush grow in the Holy Land. There are at least 21 varieties of rushes. The common soft rush or bog rush <span class="ital">(Juncus effusus)</span> is found in wet places, even in the Sinai and other deserts. The sea or hard rush <span class="ital">(J. maritimus)</span> is found in damp places throughout the Holy Land and even in Sinai.</p>
<p>At least 15 kinds of bulrushes <span class="ital">(Scirpus)</span> are known in the Holy Land. The cluster-headed club rush <span class="ital">(Scirpus holoschoenus)</span> is common in damp places throughout the Holy Land to the Sinai. The lake club rush or tall bulrush <span class="ital">(S. lacustris)</span> is found in swamps and ditches throughout northern Africa to the Dead Sea. The sea club rush or salt marsh club rush <span class="ital">(S. maritimus)</span> is found in ditches and swamps in many places of the Holy Land. Any of these species may be the one referred to in <a href="?bref=Job.8.11">Job 8:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.9.14">Isaiah 9:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.19.6,15">19:6, 15</a>.</p>
<p>The reference in <a href="?bref=Gen.41.2">Genesis 41:2</a> to the feeding of cattle in the meadow seems to be to the tall reed <span class="ital">(Arundo donax),</span> which grows 18 feet (5.5 meters) or more in height. This plant is also known as the Persian reed and is common throughout the Holy Land, Syria, and the Sinai peninsula. It is a gigantic grass that may have a stem diameter of two or three inches (5.1 to 7.6 centimeters) at the base and is terminated by a plume of white flowers similar to those of the sugarcane or pampas grass. The plant was used for many purposes by the ancients: for walking sticks, fishing rods, measuring rods, and musical pipes. It is, therefore, quite possible that the “reed” of <a href="?bref=Matt.27.48">Matthew 27:48</a> and <a href="?bref=Mark.15.36">Mark 15:36</a> was a carpenter’s reed or measuring rod.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Papyrus">Papyrus</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Rue">Rue <span class="ital">(Ruta chalepensis, R. graveolens)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Aromatic Eurasian plant with evergreen leaves that yield an acrid, volatile oil once used in medicine. There is little question as to the correctness of the translation of “rue” in <a href="?bref=Luke.11.42">Luke 11:42</a>, but there is some doubt as to the exact species. Most writers think that it was the common rue <span class="ital">(Rue graveolens),</span> a perennial shrubby plant with erect stems two to three feet (.6 to .9 meter) tall and deeply cut leaves. A very strong odor emanates from the foliage. This species is native to the Mediterranean region and grows wild in the Holy Land, especially on Mt Tabor.</p>
<p>Rue was highly thought of by the ancients as a medicinal, supposed to prevent dizziness, dumbness, epilepsy, eye inflammations, insanity, and the “evil eye.” Rue was also used for seasoning dishes.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Rush">Rush <span class="ital">(Butomus umbellatus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Generic term for any of various grasslike marsh plants having pliant, hollow, or pithy stems. There is considerable uncertainty about the identification of the plant referred to in <a href="?bref=Gen.41.2">Genesis 41:2</a> translated in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> as “meadow,” and in <a href="?bref=Job.8.11">Job 8:11</a> as “flag.” Since it is mentioned along with the papyrus in the Job passage, it seems that it refers to a specific kind of plant rather than to an aggregate of plants in a meadow. From the description in Genesis as being a plant on which Pharaoh’s cattle might feed along the banks of the Nile and yet not the papyrus, it may refer to the flowering rush or water gladiola <span class="ital">(Butomus umbellatus),</span> which flourishes both in Egypt and in the Holy Land, along with the papyrus.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Reed_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Reed</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Saffron">Saffron <span class="ital">(Crocus sativus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Saffron, referred to in <a href="?bref=Song.4.14">Song of Songs 4:14</a>, is the product of several species of <span class="ital">Crocus,</span> especially of the blue-flowered saffron crocus <span class="ital">(C. sativus),</span> which is native to Greece and Asia Minor. The commercial product consists of the stigma and upper portions of the style, the top parts of the flower ovary, which are collected shortly after the flower opens. It requires at least 4,000 stigmas to make an ounce of saffron. After being gathered, the stigmas are dried in the sun, pounded, and made into small cakes. Saffron is used principally as a yellow dye and also as a fruit coloring for curries and stews.</p>
<p>Another, entirely different kind of dye-producing plant <span class="ital">(Carthamus tinctorius)</span> called carthamine, bastard saffron, or safflower is a member of the thistle family. Its red florets yield a dye used extensively for coloring silk, in cooking, and for adulterating genuine saffron. It is an annual spiny plant three to four and a half feet (1.4 meters) tall, native to Syria and Egypt. In Egypt the grave clothes of mummies were dyed with this material, and it is quite possible that this plant may also have been the saffron of the Bible.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Sage">Sage <span class="ital">(Salvia judaica)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The Judean sage grows to three feet (.9 meter) tall in the mountains and hills of Palestine. Its stems are four-angled, stiff, and rough. The plant grows from Syria south through Nazareth, Hebron, Tiberius, Samaria, and Judea.</p>
<p>This plant is the origin of the design of the seven-branched lampstand of <a href="?bref=Exod.37.17-18">Exodus 37:17-18</a>, which is known as the menorah, the traditional Jewish symbol. The inflorescence of the plant, when pressed flat, has almost exactly the same shape and form as the seven-branched candlestick, with its central spike and three pairs of side branches each bending upward and inward in a symmetrical fashion. On each branch of the plant’s inflorescence are whorls or buds that perhaps give the idea for the “knops” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) or “knobs” on the biblical golden candlesticks.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Spelt">Spelt <span class="ital">(Triticum aestivum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Hardy member of the wheat family. The rye of <a href="?bref=Exod.9.32">Exodus 9:32</a> and <a href="?bref=Isa.28.25">Isaiah 28:25</a>, as well as the fitches of <a href="?bref=Ezek.4.9">Ezekiel 4:9</a> (all <span class="sc">kjv</span>) are thought to be spelt. It is a hard-grained species of wheat with loose ears and grains triangular in cross-section, and was the most common form of wheat in early times. It has a stouter stem than wheat and strong spikes of grain. Bread made of its flour is much inferior to that made from wheat, but spelt will thrive in almost any kind of soil and will yield a crop on land that is unfit for wheat. The ancients preferred it to barley for bread.</p>
<p class="h2" id="StoraxTree">Storax Tree <span class="ital">(Styrax officinalis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Various trees of this genus yielding an aromatic resin. Today it is thought that the stacte of <a href="?bref=Exod.30.34">Exodus 30:34</a> was derived from the storax tree. It is an irregularly stiff-branched shrub or small tree 9 to 20 feet (2.7 to 6.1 meters) tall. This tree is abundant on low hills and rocky places from Lebanon through the Holy Land. Its gum is obtained by making incisions in the stems and branches. It is highly perfumed and is still prized today as a perfume.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Sycamore">Sycamore-fig <span class="ital">(Ficus sycomorus)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Tree of northeastern Africa and adjacent Asia, related to the fig. The word translated “sycamore” in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.27">1 Kings 10:27</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.27.28">1 Chronicles 27:28</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.1.15">2 Chronicles 1:15</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.9.27">9:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.47">Psalm 78:47</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.9.10">Isaiah 9:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.7.14">Amos 7:14</a>; and <a href="?bref=Luke.19.4">Luke 19:4</a> undoubtedly refers to the well-known sycamore-fig, which is also known as the mulberry-fig or fig-mulberry. It should not be confused with the common sycamore of the North American continent, which is actually a plane tree. The sycamore-fig of the Bible is a strong-growing, robust, wide-spreading tree growing 30 to 40 feet (9.1 to 12.2 meters) tall and sometimes attaining a trunk circumference of 20 feet (6.1 meters) or more with a crown 120 feet (36.6 meters) in diameter. It is a tree that is easily climbed and is frequently planted along roadsides, which accounts for the reference in <a href="?bref=Luke.19.4">Luke 19:4</a>. It produces an abundant amount of fruit in clusters on all parts of the tree, on both young and old branches and even on the trunk itself. It is very similar to the common fig, only smaller and much inferior in quality. In David’s day it was so valuable that he appointed a special overseer for the sycamore trees (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.28">1 Chr 27:28</a>). It is thought that Amos was not a gatherer of sycamore fruit but rather a dresser of sycamore trees.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Tamarisk">Tamarisk <span class="ital">(Tamarix)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The references in <a href="?bref=Gen.21.33">Genesis 21:33</a> and <a href="?bref=1Sam.22.6">1 Samuel 22:6</a> and <a href="?bref=1Sam.31.13">31:13</a> seem to be to the tamarisk. These trees or shrubs are small and fast-growing with a durable wood. They are abundant in deserts, dunes, and salt marshes. <span class="ital">Tamarix aphylla</span> is leafless and has small white flowers. These trees or shrubs often provide a soothing touch of green foliage and a promise of cooling shade to the traveler. Tamarisks are able to survive because they either have small, scalelike leaves, which lose little moisture by transpiration, or no leaves at all. The larger of the tamarisks are valued for their wood in a region where wood is scarce. The wood was used for building and also as a source of an excellent type of charcoal.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Terebinth">Terebinth <span class="ital">(Pistacia terebinthus)</span></p>
<p class="fl"><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="#Pistachio">Pistachio (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ThistleThorn">Thistle, Thorn <span class="ital">(Lycium europaeum, Solanum incanum, Centaurea, Silybum marianum, Ruscus aculeatus, Agrostemma githago, Paliurus spina-christi, Zizyphus spina-christi)</span></p>
<p class="fl">There are 22 different Hebrew and Greek words used in Scripture to refer to spiny or prickly shrubs or weeds, and these are translated as “bramble,” “brier,” “cockle,” “thorn,” and “thistle.” At present, there are about 125 species of thorns and thistles that grow in the Holy Land.</p>
<p>The bramble in the allegory of <a href="?bref=Judg.9.14-15">Judges 9:14-15</a> is believed to refer to the European boxthorn or desert-thorn, <span class="ital">Lycium europaeum.</span></p>
<p>The general consensus is that the “briers” of <a href="?bref=Isa.10.17">Isaiah 10:17</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.55.13">55:13</a>, <a href="?bref=Mic.7.4">Micah 7:4</a>, and <a href="?bref=Heb.6.8">Hebrews 6:8</a> are the Palestine nightshade <span class="ital">(Solanum incanum),</span> or “Jericho potato.”</p>
<p>The thistles of <a href="?bref=Gen.3.17-18">Genesis 3:17-18</a>, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.9">2 Kings 14:9</a>, <a href="?bref=2Chr.25.18">2 Chronicles 25:18</a>, <a href="?bref=Hos.10.8">Hosea 10:8</a>, and <a href="?bref=Matt.7.16">Matthew 7:16</a>, as well as the thorns of <a href="?bref=Matt.13.7">Matthew 13:7</a> and <a href="?bref=Heb.6.8">Hebrews 6:8</a>, are thought to be one of the species of the thistle, <span class="ital">Centaurea.</span> Among the more common thistles in the Holy Land are the true star-thistle <span class="ital">(Centaurea calcitrapa),</span> the dwarf centaury <span class="ital">(C. verutum),</span> the Iberian centaury <span class="ital">(C. iberica),</span> and the lady’s thistle <span class="ital">(Silybum marianum).</span> Some thistles attain a height of five to six feet (.9 to 1.8 meters). Thistles are characteristic of an area that is uncultivated and neglected. Many have beautiful flowers, but all are covered with sharp spines.</p>
<p>The references in <a href="?bref=Ezek.2.6">Ezekiel 2:6</a> to “briers” and <a href="?bref=Ezek.28.24">Ezekiel 28:24</a> to a “pricking brier” may be to the prickly butchers-broom or knee-holly, <span class="ital">Ruscus aculeatus.</span> The plant is common in rocky woods in the northern regions of the Holy Land, especially around Mt Tabor and Mt Carmel.</p>
<p>The cockle of <a href="?bref=Job.31.40">Job 31:40</a> (<span class="sc">nlt</span> “weeds”) perhaps refers to the corn cockle, <span class="ital">Agrostemma githago.</span> This plant is common in grainfields throughout the Holy Land. It is a strong-growing and troublesome weed in grainfields, growing from one to three feet (.3 to .9 meter) tall.</p>
<p>Many commentators think that the “thorns” out of which the crown of thorns (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.29">Mt 27:29</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.2">Jn 19:2</a>) was made were from the Christ-thorn <span class="ital">(Paliurus spina-christi).</span> This belief has led to its specific name; the Christ-thorn is a spiny plant that ordinarily grows as a straggling shrub three to nine feet (.9 to 2.7 meters) tall. The flexible branches are armed at the base of each leaf with a pair of unequal, stiff, sharp spines. The unusual pliable texture of the young branches renders it particularly easy to plait into a crownlike wreath.</p>
<p>The thorns of <a href="?bref=Judg.8.7">Judges 8:7</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.7.19">Isaiah 7:19</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.9.18">9:18</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.55.13">55:13</a>, and <a href="?bref=Matt.7.16">Matthew 7:16</a> may refer to the Syrian Christ-thorn <span class="ital">(Zizyphus spina-christi),</span> a shrub or small tree 9 to 15 feet (2.7 to 4.6 meters) tall, sometimes growing into a 40-foot (12.2-meter) tree with smooth white branches bearing a pair of stout, unequal, recurved spines at the back of each leaf.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="#Bramble">Bramble</a>; <a href="#Buckthorn">Buckthorn (above)</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Tulip">Tulip <span class="ital">(Tulipa montana, T. sharonensis)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of several bulbous plants of this family native to Asia. The rose of Sharon in <a href="?bref=Song.2.1">Song of Songs 2:1</a> may be the mountain tulip, <span class="ital">Tulipa montana,</span> or the closely related Sharon tulip, <span class="ital">T. sharonensis.</span> The former is an attractive plant that grows from a bulb and has leaves that are often wavy-margined. The species is common in the mountainous regions of Syria, Lebanon, and the Anti-Lebanon. It is primarily a mountainous species. The Sharon tulip <span class="ital">(T. sharonensis)</span> is found in sandy places on the Sharon coastal plains.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Tumbleweed">Tumbleweed <span class="ital">(Gundelia tournefortii, Anastatica hierochuntica)</span></p>
<p class="fl">The references in <a href="?bref=Ps.83.13">Psalm 83:13</a> to “whirling dust” and in <a href="?bref=Isa.17.13">Isaiah 17:13</a> to “wheel” or “rolling thing” (<span class="sc">niv</span> “tumbleweed”) seem to be to the Palestinian tumbleweed <span class="ital">(Gundelia tournefortii),</span> a member of the thistle family. It is a prickly herb with milky juice. It rolls over the land and gathers in tremendous heaps in hollows.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Vegetable">Vegetable</p>
<p class="fl">Scriptural references to vegetables are probably, in most cases, to the dried leguminous seeds of beans and lentils.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Vine">Vine <span class="ital">(Vitis vinifera)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any plant with a flexible stem that climbs, twines, or creeps along a surface or support. The common grapevine <span class="ital">(Vitis vinifera)</span> is mentioned throughout the Bible. The fruitful vine (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.5-10">Ez 17:5-10</a>) and the vine brought out of Egypt (<a href="?bref=Ps.80.8">Ps 80:8</a>) were symbolic of the Jewish people. Jesus compares himself to the true vine, of which his disciples were the branches (<a href="?bref=John.15.1-6">Jn 15:1-6</a>).</p>
<p>The grapevine of the Old World sometimes assumes the characteristics of a tree, with stems up to a foot and a half (45.7 centimeters) in diameter, the branches then being trained on a trellis and bearing bunches of grapes 10 to 12 pounds (4.5 to 5.4 kilograms) in weight, with the individual grapes the size of small plums. Bunches have been produced weighing as much as 26 pounds (11.8 kilograms). The vines of the Holy Land were always renowned both for the luxuriance of their growth and for the immense clusters of grapes they produced. Thus it does not seem improbable that the spies sent to the Promised Land should have employed a pole to transport some of the clusters home (<a href="?bref=Num.13.23-24">Nm 13:23-24</a>).</p>
<p>The wild grape <span class="ital">(Vitis orientalis)</span> is referred to in <a href="?bref=Isa.5.2-4">Isaiah 5:2-4</a>, <a href="?bref=Jer.2.21">Jeremiah 2:21</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ezek.15.2-6">Ezekiel 15:2-6</a>. It is known as the native wild fox grape and has small, black, acidic berries about the size of currants with little juice.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Walnut">Walnut <span class="ital">(Juglans regia)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of several trees of this genus having round, sticky fruit enclosing an edible nut. The reference in <a href="?bref=Song.6.11">Song of Songs 6:11</a> to “nuts” is thought to refer to the Persian or common walnut, <span class="ital">Juglans regia.</span> The tree is believed to have been indigenous to northern Persia, but it is actually found wild in many parts of northern India, eastward as far as China, and westward through Persia. At the time of Solomon, it was widely cultivated for its fruit throughout the East. Perhaps Solomon’s garden of nuts was a part of his extensive gardens at Etham, six miles (9.7 kilometers) from Jerusalem.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WaterLily">Water Lily <span class="ital">(Nymphaea)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Any of numerous aquatic plants of this genus with floating leaves and showy flowers. The carved lily ornamentation of <a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.19-26">1 Kings 7:19-26</a> and <a href="?bref=2Chr.4.5">2 Chronicles 4:5</a> was probably patterned after the flowers of the water lily. Few flowers can equal the Egyptian lotus or water lily <span class="ital">(Nymphaea lotus)</span> in beauty. It looks very much like a large white rose and at one time floated in profusion on the waters of the Nile.</p>
<p>The common European white water lily <span class="ital">(N. alba)</span> was also familiar to the children of Israel. It grows not only in Europe but also in the Holy Land and North Africa. It is, however, not as common in Egypt as is the white lotus.</p>
<p>Another water lily with which the Israelites were probably familiar is the blue lotus, <span class="ital">N. caerulea.</span> Its leaves are 12 to 16 inches (30.5 to 40.6 centimeters) across and it has light-blue flowers that are three to six inches (7.6 to 15.2 centimeters) in diameter.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Wheat">Wheat <span class="ital">(Triticum aestivum, T. compositum)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Various cereal grasses of this family widely cultivated for its edible grain. Five kinds of wheat are native to—and still wild in—the Holy Land, and at least eight others are cultivated there today; probably most, if not all, were known in Bible times. The wild varieties were probably more abundant then than they are today. Among these are the einkorn <span class="ital">(T. monococcum),</span> the thaoudar <span class="ital">(T. thaoudar),</span> and the wild emmer <span class="ital">(T. dicoccoides).</span> The composite wheat <span class="ital">(T. compositum),</span> with its branched spikes, often bearing as many as seven heads per stalk, is definitely referred to in <a href="?bref=Gen.41.5-57">Genesis 41:5-57</a>. It is depicted on numerous Egyptian monuments and on inscriptions and is still commonly seen in the Nile Delta, where it is known as “mummy wheat.” It is also cultivated in the Holy Land.</p>
<p>The most frequently mentioned wheat of the Bible is undoubtedly the commonly cultivated summer and winter wheat, <span class="ital">Triticum aestivum.</span> It is an abundant annual grass cultivated in Egypt and other Eastern lands since earliest times. The exact place of its origin is unknown. Grains of wheat have been found in the most ancient Egyptian tombs and in the remains of prehistoric lake dwellings in Switzerland. It was certainly the chief grain of Mesopotamia in Jacob’s time (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.14">Gn 30:14</a>).</p>
<p>Corn in biblical days often included a mixture of peas, beans, lentils, cummin, barley, millet, and spelt, but wheat was always its main constituent. Egypt was a great grain-producing country, and Abram (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.10">Gn 12:10</a>) and Joseph’s brothers (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.42.1-38">42</a>) naturally turned to Egypt for wheat when famine visited Canaan.</p>
<p>The mills, millstones, granaries, and threshing floors mentioned in the Bible all refer to equipment employed in processing grain to produce flour. The fine flour of which the showbread loaves were made (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.5">Lv 24:5</a>) was unquestionably wheat flour. Wheat intended for home consumption was often stored in the central part of the house; this explains the story told in <a href="?bref=2Sam.4.6">2 Samuel 4:6</a>. It was also sometimes stored in dry wells (<a href="?bref=2Sam.17.19">2 Sm 17:19</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Wormwood">Wormwood <span class="ital">(Artemisia judaica, A. herba-alba)</span></p>
<p class="fl">Wormwood is a general name given to a group of woody plants with a strong aromatic odor. Wormwood plants have a strong, bitter taste, and their young shoots and branch tips furnish the “wormwood” of commerce. Its bitter taste accounts for its being spoken of with gall—as being symbolic of bitter calamity and sorrow (<a href="?bref=Pr.5.4">Prv 5:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.9.15">Jer 9:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.15">23:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.3.15,19">Lam 3:15, 19</a>). <span class="ital">Artemisia herba-alba</span> is the common species of wormwood in the Holy Land today. It is strongly aromatic, smelling like camphor, and bitter. <span class="ital">A. judaica</span> occurs only in the Sinai.</p>
<p>Absinthe is made from species of this group. It first leads to greater activity and pleasant sensations and fills the mind with grandiose ideas (<a href="?bref=Lam.3.15">Lam 3:15</a>). The habitual use of it, however, brings on a stupor and gradual diminution of intellectual faculties, ending in delirium and even death. Perhaps the hemlock of <a href="?bref=Amos.6.12">Amos 6:12</a> was wormwood.</p>
  </body>
</item>