<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Polycarp">
  <title>Polycarp*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">POLYCARP*</p>
<p class="fl">Early Christian leader and martyr in the postapostolic era.</p>
<p>Born to a Christian family, Polycarp identified himself as a disciple of “John,” presumably the apostle. Polycarp was appointed bishop of Smyrna in Asia Minor. Ignatius of Antioch, on his way to Roman martyrdom (c. 116), wrote letters to Polycarp and to the church at Smyrna. Near the end of his life, Polycarp visited Rome. He was serving as representative of the Asia Minor churches in a discussion over the observance of Easter. Polycarp was later arrested by civil authorities, who attempted to convince him to renounce his faith. When he refused, he was burned at the stake. The story of Polycarp’s death (recounted in a letter from the church of Smyrna to the church of Philomelium) is the earliest record of Christian martyrdom outside the New Testament.</p>
<p>As bishop of Smyrna, Polycarp wrote many letters to various churches. Only one of Polycarp’s letters has survived, however. This letter, addressed to the Philippians, was written in response to a letter they had sent him. Apparently, while Ignatius was on his way to martyrdom in Rome, his guards chose to make a stop in Philippi. While there, Ignatius encouraged the local church to write to the church in Antioch. So they sent a letter by way of Polycarp. They also requested copies of Ignatius’s letters to the Asian churches.</p>
<p>Polycarp’s reply to Philippi is the document now called his <span class="ital">Epistle to the Philippians,</span> written around <span class="era">AD</span> 120. It is the only example of the writing of this early church father. In his letter Polycarp assumes that Ignatius had already suffered death, but it seems that he was not certain of this. He asks the Philippians to send him what news they may have of Ignatius.</p>
<p>In his epistle Polycarp mentions the fame of the Philippians among the churches from the early days to that time. He refers to the apostle Paul’s instructions for the church there, making reference to more than one letter from the apostle. Polycarp warns against the love of money, which caused the downfall of one of the leaders of the church (Judas Iscariot). He also warns against those who deny the resurrection of Christ, the Docetist heretics. Polycarp instructs the Philippians on the duties of church leaders and other Christians.</p>
<p>While many critics have labeled Polycarp’s letter “unoriginal,” containing no new theological insights, the letter does provide insight into the available NT writings for the churches. There are no citations from the OT in this epistle, but there are quotations and allusions to Matthew, Acts, Romans, 1 Corinthians, Galatians, Ephesians, 2 Thessalonians, 1 Timothy, and 1 Peter. He also makes use of Clement’s epistle and the Ignatian letters. It is interesting to note that Polycarp makes no reference to the Gospel of John, though tradition insists that he was a disciple of the apostle John.</p>
<p>The letter ends with Polycarp’s promise to forward the Philippians’ letter to Antioch. He also promises to send them Ignatius’s letters.</p>
  </body>
</item>