<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Poorthe">
  <title>Poor, the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">POOR, T<span class="lc">he</span></p>
<p class="fl">Those lacking material wealth.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PovertyasaBadThing">Poverty as a Bad Thing</p>
<p class="fl">At times the Bible gives a very simple explanation of why people are rich or poor. If a person delights in the law of the Lord, he or she will get wealth and riches. Such people will prosper in everything they do (<a href="?bref=Ps.1.3">Pss 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.112.3">112:3</a>). With regard to Israel in OT days, these ideas are not quite so naive as they might seem. There was indeed a connection between sin and poverty. Israelite society was built on rules laid down by God, so if there was poverty, that must mean that somewhere the rules were being broken.</p>
<p>Whether a person’s poverty was due to his or her own sin or to someone else’s, the OT saw it as an evil to be combated, and the law made many provisions for the relief of it (e.g., <a href="?bref=Exod.22.21-27">Ex 22:21-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.19.9-10">Lv 19:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.15.1-15">Dt 15:1-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.24.10-22">24:10-22</a>). God cared for the needy and expected his people to do the same.</p>
<p>During the period between the testaments, that care continued to be exercised within Jewish communities scattered around the Mediterranean, and it was in due course taken up as a practical responsibility by the Christian church (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.29">Acts 11:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.24.17">24:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.26">Rom 15:26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.1">1 Cor 16:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.10">Gal 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.15-16">Jas 2:15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.3.17">1 Jn 3:17</a>); for Christians also, the giving of alms was a duty plainly expected by their Lord (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.2-4">Mt 6:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.33">Lk 12:33</a>). It was not really a primitive communism that the early church practiced, for had they renounced personal possessions, they could not have done what they in fact did—namely, to <span class="ital">give</span> in cash or in kind “as any had need” (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.45">Acts 2:45</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.4.35">4:35</a>).</p>
<p>Poverty, then, although it provides the wealthy with a chance to show the virtue of generosity, is in itself (in the NT as in the OT) a bad thing.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PovertyasaGoodThing">Poverty as a Good Thing</p>
<p class="fl">As we can see, there is a certain sense in which righteousness will make people prosperous and sin will make them poor. But ordinary life is more complicated than that. <a href="?bref=Ps.1.1-6">Psalms 1</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.112.1-10">112</a>, referred to above, show only one side of the matter. What about the prosperity of the wicked (<a href="?bref=Ps.73.3">Ps 73:3</a>) and its corollary, the person who is righteous yet poor? The answer of Scripture (e.g., <a href="?bref=Job.21.1-34">Jb 21</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.37.1-40">Pss 37</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.49.1-20">49</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.73.1-28">73</a>) is that the wealth of bad people is a fleeting thing and that the righteous, though poor in worldly goods, have spiritual riches.</p>
<p>This thought—that far from being prosperous, the good person may often be poor—is sometimes curiously inverted. The righteous may be poor, but Scripture sometimes appears to reckon that to be poor is to be righteous. Of course, it is not automatically so (<a href="?bref=Pr.30.8-9">Prv 30:8-9</a>), but such references are frequent enough, especially in the Psalms (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.9.18">Pss 9:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.10.14">10:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.12.5">12:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.34.6">34:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.35.10">35:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.74.19">74:19</a>), to deserve careful consideration. And on reflection, they are not so strange. As God is specially concerned about the poor, so the poor may be specially concerned about God, for two good reasons. First, if there was poverty in Israel, it was because those with power were misusing it; therefore, the poor would claim God’s help first because it is his rule that was being flouted, and he must vindicate himself. And second, poverty turns people to God because in those circumstances there is no one else to turn to. In this way “poor” becomes almost a technical term. “The poor” are the humble, and the humble are the godly (<a href="?bref=Ps.10.17">Pss 10:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.14.5-6">14:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.37.11">37:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.3.12-13">Zep 3:12-13</a>). Just as being rich can foster self-indulgence, self-confidence, pride, and the despising and oppression of one’s fellow human beings, so being poor should encourage the opposite virtues.</p>
<p>Instead of being an evil to be shunned, poverty thus becomes an ideal to be sought. Following the OT use of “the poor” and “the pious” as almost interchangeable terms, personal property was renounced by many Jews during the period between the testaments. Among them were the sect of the Essenes and the related community that was set up at Qumran near the Dead Sea. The latter actually called themselves “The Poor.” This tradition continued into NT times. Possibly “the poor” at Jerusalem means a definite group within the church there (or even the Jerusalem church as a whole; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.26">Rom 15:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.10">Gal 2:10</a>). Certainly there emerged later a Jewish-Christian sect called the “Ebionites” (from a Hebrew word for “poor”).</p>
<p>The NT teaches clearly, of course, that what really matters is the attitude of the heart. It is quite possible to be poor yet grasping, or rich yet generous. Even so, with the OT background outlined above, the general sense of these words in the Gospels is that rich = bad, poor = good. On the one hand, the Sadducees are rich in worldly wealth and the Pharisees in spiritual pride, and men of property are selfish, foolish, and in grave spiritual peril (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.23">Mk 10:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.12.13-21">Lk 12:13-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.16.19-31">16:19-31</a>). On the other hand, it is devout and simple folk, like Jesus’s own family and friends, who generally represent the poor.</p>
<p>In truth, therefore, the two versions of the first beatitude (Matthew’s and Luke’s) amount to the same thing. Matthew’s has the depth: “Blessed are the poor in spirit” (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.3">Mt 5:3</a>). But Luke’s has the breadth. When he says simply “Blessed are you poor” (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.20">Lk 6:20</a>), he means those who in their need—in <span class="ital">any</span> kind of need—turn to the Lord. It was to bring the gospel to such people that Christ came into the world (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.5">Mt 11:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.4.18">Lk 4:18</a>). Jesus Christ himself embodies the same ideal. As Paul put it, “Though he was very rich, yet for your sakes he became poor, so that by his poverty he could make you rich” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.8.9">2 Cor 8:9</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Our helpless poverty is an evil from which he comes to rescue us; his deliberately chosen poverty is the glorious means by which he does so.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Alms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Alms</a>; <a href="?item=Riches_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Riches</a>; <a href="?item=Righteousness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Righteousness</a>; <a href="?item=Wages_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wages</a>; <a href="?item=Wealth_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wealth</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>