<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Power">
  <title>Power</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">POWER</p>
<p class="fl">Ability to do things, by virtue of strength, skill, resources, or authorization. In the Hebrew of the OT and the Greek of the NT, there are several different words used for power. What the Bible says about power may be subsumed under four headings: (1) the unlimited power of God; (2) the limited power God gives to his creatures; (3) the power of God seen in Jesus Christ; and (4) the power of God (by the Holy Spirit) in the lives of his people.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheUnlimitedPowerofGod">The Unlimited Power of God</p>
<p class="fl">God is almighty and all other power is derived from him and subject to him. Much that the Bible says is summed up in the words of <a href="?bref=1Chr.29.11-12">1 Chronicles 29:11-12</a> addressed to God in praise: “Thine, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, is the greatness, and the power, and the glory, and the victory, and the majesty; for all that is in the heavens and in the earth is thine; thine is the kingdom, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. . . . thou rulest over all. In thy hand are power and might; and in thy hand it is to make great and to give strength to all” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). Using human terms, the OT often speaks of God’s “mighty hand” and his “outstretched arm,” both being used for the power of God in action (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.6">Ex 6:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.7.4">7:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.44.2-3">Ps 44:2-3</a>). His power is seen in creation (<a href="?bref=Ps.65.6">Ps 65:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.26">Is 40:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.10.12">Jer 10:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.27.5">27:5</a>), in his rule over the world (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.6">2 Chr 20:6</a>), in his acts of salvation and judgment (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.6">Ex 15:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.26.8">Dt 26:8</a>), and in all that he does for his people (<a href="?bref=Ps.111.6">Ps 111:6</a>). The NT, as well as the OT, speaks of the mighty power of God. <a href="?bref=Eph.1.19">Ephesians 1:19</a> speaks of the immeasurable greatness of his power, and the words of Jesus in <a href="?bref=Matt.26.64">Matthew 26:64</a> show that the word could be substituted for the very name of God when he said that the Son of Man would be seen “seated at the right hand of Power.”</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheLimitedPowerGodGivestoHisCreatures">The Limited Power God Gives to His Creatures</p>
<p class="fl">Animals have power, as is particularly evident in the wild ox, the horse, and the lion (<a href="?bref=Job.39.11,19">Jb 39:11, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.30.30">Prv 30:30</a>). There is power in wind and storm, thunder and lightning. Power is given to humans: physical strength (<a href="?bref=Judg.16.5-6">Jgs 16:5-6</a>), power to fight (<a href="?bref=Judg.6.12">6:12</a>), and the power to do good and the power to do harm (<a href="?bref=Gen.31.29">Gn 31:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.3.27">Prv 3:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.2.1">Mi 2:1</a>). Rulers have God-given power and authority (<a href="?bref=Rom.13.1">Rom 13:1</a>). The Bible also speaks of the power of angels (<a href="?bref=2Pet.2.11">2 Pt 2:11</a>) and of spiritual beings known as “principalities and powers.” Certain powers are given to Satan (see <a href="?bref=Job.1.6-12">Jb 1:6-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.2.1-6">2:1-6</a>). Sin, evil, and death are allowed to have some power over men (<a href="?bref=Hos.13.14">Hos 13:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.22.53">Lk 22:53</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.3.9">Rom 3:9</a>). All of these, however, have only limited power, and God is able to give his people strength to conquer all these powers. He can save them from the power of animals (<a href="?bref=Dan.6.27">Dn 6:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.19">Lk 10:19</a>) and from the power of other people over them. To Pilate Jesus said, “You would have no power over me at all unless it were given to you from above” (<a href="?bref=John.19.11">Jn 19:11</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). He is able to deliver people from the power of sin and death, from Satan, and from all the spiritual forces of evil (<a href="?bref=2Cor.10.4">2 Cor 10:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.6.10-18">Eph 6:10-18</a>). The “ruler of this world” could ultimately have no power over Christ (<a href="?bref=John.14.30">Jn 14:30</a>) and so cannot have power over those who rely on him.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ThePowerofGodSeeninJesusChrist">The Power of God Seen in Jesus Christ</p>
<p class="fl">The Gospels and the book of Acts bear frequent witness to the power of Christ. Power was shown in his miracles (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.20">Mt 11:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.22">Acts 2:22</a>), in his works of healing and exorcism (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.36">Lk 4:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.17">5:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.19">6:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.38">Acts 10:38</a>). Power is shown supremely in his resurrection. Jesus speaks of his power to give up his life and power to take it again (<a href="?bref=John.10.18">Jn 10:18</a>), but the NT speaks most frequently of the power of God the Father shown in the raising of his Son from the dead (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.4">Rom 1:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.19-20">Eph 1:19-20</a>). In the end he will be seen coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.30">Mt 24:30</a>). With regard to his human life on earth, however, it may be noted in the light of what follows that he lived and did his mighty works in the power of the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.14">Lk 4:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.38">Acts 10:38</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="ThePowerofGodintheLivesofHisPeople">The Power of God in the Lives of His People</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT it is often said that the weak are made strong by the power of God. He empowers those who are weak (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.29">Is 40:29</a>) so that they may increase from strength to strength (<a href="?bref=Ps.84.7">Ps 84:7</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Ps.68.35">Pss 68:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.138.3">138:3</a>). We read in particular of his power being given to prophets (<a href="?bref=Mic.3.8">Mi 3:8</a>) and kings (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.10">1 Sm 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.21.1">Ps 21:1</a>), and it is said that in an outstanding way power will be given to the Messiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.6">Is 9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.11.2">11:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.5.4">Mi 5:4</a>). But to all God’s people power is offered that they may live for him and serve him (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.5">Is 49:5</a>). When we turn to the NT, we read of the gospel itself as being the power of God for salvation—to everyone who has faith (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.16">Rom 1:16</a>). “To all who received him [Jesus Christ], who believed in his name, he gave power to become children of God” (<a href="?bref=John.1.12">Jn 1:12</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). In that life as children of God, power is received from the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.8">Acts 6:8</a>), inner strength to live in his service (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.16">Eph 3:16</a>), power to be his witnesses (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.49">Lk 24:49</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.8">Acts 1:8</a>), power to endure suffering (<a href="?bref=2Tim.1.8">2 Tm 1:8</a>), power for ministry (<a href="?bref=Eph.3.7">Eph 3:7</a>), power in the face of weakness (<a href="?bref=2Cor.12.9">2 Cor 12:9</a>), power through prayer (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.16">Jas 5:16</a>), and power to be kept from evil (<a href="?bref=1Pet.1.5">1 Pt 1:5</a>). Those who do great things in the service of Christ do not do them in their own strength (<a href="?bref=Acts.3.12">Acts 3:12</a>); he sent out his disciples confident only in the assurance that all things are under his authority and that they would have the power of his unfailing presence with them (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.18-20">Mt 28:18-20</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=GodBeingandAttributesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Being and Attributes of</a>; <a href="?item=PrincipalitiesandPowers_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Principalities and Powers</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>