<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PraetoriumPraetorianGuard">
  <title>Praetorium*, Praetorian Guard*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PRAETORIUM*, PRAETORIAN GUARD*</p>
<p class="fl">Term appearing in the Greek NT in <a href="?bref=Mark.15.16">Mark 15:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.27.27">Matthew 27:27</a>; <a href="?bref=John.18.28,33">John 18:28, 33</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.9">19:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.23.35">Acts 23:35</a>; and <a href="?bref=Phil.1.13">Philippians 1:13</a>. It is a Latin word borrowed from the Romans, who dominated the Mediterranean world in NT times. It was used primarily in military and governmental affairs. Originally it designated the tent of the general <span class="ital">(praetor)</span> in a military encampment. The meaning was extended to include the residence of a governor or other Roman official, as, for example, that of Pontius Pilate, the procurator of Judea. In looser usage the term may also have referred to a part of the residence—for instance, the barracks of the soldiers.</p>
<p>In English translations of the NT, the variety of terms used by translators indicates the uncertainty about the specific reference. The general reference to the headquarters of the Roman representative and military force is clear, however. According to the Gospels of Matthew and Mark, the praetorium was the location of the Roman soldiers’ mocking of Jesus after his appearance before Pilate. Mark also calls this place a “palace” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>) or “courtyard” (<span class="sc">neb</span>, <span class="sc">tev</span>). According to the Gospel of John, the “praetorium” was the place within which Pilate examined Jesus about the charges brought against him. He went outside the praetorium to meet with the accusers who brought the charges.</p>
<p>Within Jerusalem, two locations are possible for Pilate’s headquarters. One is the fortress known as the Tower of Antonia at the northwest corner of the temple area. The other is the old palace of Herod the Great, in the western part of the city. Either one could have served as the praetorium, but the Gospel sources identify neither by name or description.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Acts.23.35">Acts 23:35</a>, on the other hand, the praetorium in which Paul is held in Caesarea (pending the arrival of his accusers) is called “Herod’s praetorium.” This probably means that the procurator Felix (and his predecessors) had taken over the old official residence of King Herod as their coastal headquarters.</p>
<p>The location of Paul’s imprisonment at the time he wrote to the Philippians is not clear. His mention of the “praetorium” in <a href="?bref=Phil.1.13">Philippians 1:13</a> suggests some center of Roman government. The phrase “the whole praetorium,” however, indicates that in this context he was referring to the personnel rather than to a building or a place. Recent translations reflect this meaning: “the whole praetorian guard” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>); “all at headquarters” (<span class="sc">neb</span>); “all the soldiers in the palace guard” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
  </body>
</item>