<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Praise">
  <title>Praise</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PRAISE</p>
<p class="fl">Honor, commendation, and worship.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ToWhomPraiseIsOffered">To Whom Praise Is Offered</p>
<p class="fl">The one Lord who is God over all is alone worthy of praise. Frequently, the OT stresses that the praise due him is not to be offered to other gods or to idols of any kind (e.g., <a href="?bref=Isa.42.8">Is 42:8</a>). There is a place for the commendation of men and women for their qualities of life and their right actions (<a href="?bref=Pr.31.28-31">Prv 31:28-31</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.14">1 Pt 2:14</a>). Ultimately, however, they should seek the praise and commendation of God (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.29">Rom 2:29</a>), not the praise of their fellows (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.1-6">Mt 6:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.43">Jn 12:43</a>), that others may be led to glorify God for whatever good is found in them (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.16">Mt 5:16</a>). Frequently the Bible speaks of praising “the name” of God (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.149.3">Ps 149:3</a>), meaning that he is to be praised for all that he is and has revealed himself to be. The often repeated word “Hallelujah” is simply the Hebrew equivalent of “Praise the Lord.”</p>
<p class="h2" id="ByWhomPraiseIsOffered">By Whom Praise Is Offered</p>
<p class="fl">God is praised perfectly by his angels in heaven (<a href="?bref=Ps.103.20">Pss 103:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.148.2">148:2</a>). They caroled their praise when Jesus was born (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.13-14">Lk 2:13-14</a>), and the book of Revelation (e.g., <a href="?bref=Rev.7.11-12">Rv 7:11-12</a>) speaks about their continual praise in heaven. All creation praises God in the sense that it shows his greatness as Creator (<a href="?bref=Ps.19.1-6">Ps 19:1-6</a>). <a href="?bref=Ps.148.1-14">Psalm 148</a> lists sun, moon and stars, fire and hail, snow, rain, wind and weather, mountains and hills, fruit trees and cedars, wild animals, cattle, snakes and birds—all these—as praising God together. Heaven and earth are spoken of as involved in the praise of God (<a href="?bref=Ps.89.5">Pss 89:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.96.11">96:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.98.4">98:4</a>). The Psalter closes with the words “Let everything that lives sing praises to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>!” (<a href="?bref=Ps.150.6">150:6</a>). In the OT we read of the special role of priests and Levites (<a href="?bref=Ps.135.19-20">Ps 135:19-20</a>) and of the temple singers (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.21">2 Chr 20:21</a>) and of those who, like Miriam (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.20">Ex 15:20</a>) and David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.6.14">2 Sm 6:14</a>), led others in God’s praise. But it was the duty of all God’s people to praise him; their praise was intended, moreover, to lead the nations to know and to praise him (<a href="?bref=Ps.67.2-3">Ps 67:2-3</a>). The NT has this same emphasis (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.7-12">Rom 15:7-12</a>), and it stresses that God’s gifts are given to his people to be used to his praise and glory (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.6,12,14">Eph 1:6, 12, 14</a>). It is by a life of righteousness as well as by word of mouth that people are to praise him (<a href="?bref=Phil.1.11">Phil 1:11</a>). The redeemed people of God are appointed to show forth the praises of him who has called them out of darkness into his marvelous light (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Pt 2:9</a>). The last book of the NT presents the praise of God in heaven, where the four living creatures (representing all creation) and the 24 elders (representing the people of God under the old and new covenants) unite in worship, adoring the mighty God who created them and the Lamb of God who redeemed them (<a href="?bref=Rev.4.1-5.14">Rv 4–5</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="WhenGodIstoBePraised">When God Is to Be Praised</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT there were times of special praise, Sabbaths, new moons, and festivals. In <a href="?bref=Ps.119.164">Psalm 119:164</a> the psalmist says he praised the Lord seven times a day. “Everywhere—from east to west—praise the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” is the exhortation of <a href="?bref=Ps.113.3">Psalm 113:3</a> (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). <a href="?bref=Ps.145.1">Psalm 145:1</a> says, “I will praise you, my God and King, and bless your name forever and ever” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). A dedication to a life of praise is expressed in <a href="?bref=Ps.146.2">Psalm 146:2</a>: “I will praise the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> as long as I live. I will sing praises to my God even with my dying breath” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). In the NT, likewise, there are special times of praise, but the whole of the Christian’s life is intended to be devoted, in word and action, to the praise of God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WherePraiseIstoBeOffered">Where Praise Is to Be Offered</p>
<p class="fl">In the OT the temple (and thus “Zion” or “Jerusalem,” where the temple was located) had a special place in the purpose of God: his people should praise him there. <a href="?bref=Ps.102.21">Psalm 102:21</a> pictures people declaring “in Zion the name of the Lord, and in Jerusalem his praise.” People are to praise God publicly before the congregation and before the leaders of the nation (<a href="?bref=Ps.107.32">Ps 107:32</a>), but they may also do so alone. For the whole of life is to be praise. Thus praise can come from unexpected places. Godly men and women can sing for joy as they lie on their beds (<a href="?bref=Ps.149.5">149:5</a>). Paul and Silas can sing praises to God in a Philippian prison (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.25">Acts 16:25</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="HowGodIstoBePraised">How God Is to Be Praised</p>
<p class="fl">As there is no limit to time or place, so there is no limit to the ways in which God may be praised. He may be praised with singing (<a href="?bref=Ps.47.7">Ps 47:7</a>), with dancing (<a href="?bref=Ps.149.3">149:3</a>), or with instruments of music (<a href="?bref=Ps.144.9">144:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.150.3-5">150:3-5</a>). The Psalter provides us with many songs of praise, and others are scattered throughout the OT. The NT speaks of “psalms and hymns and spiritual songs” (<a href="?bref=Col.3.16">Col 3:16</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Eph.5.19">Eph 5:19</a>), and examples of Christian songs of praise are probably to be seen in <a href="?bref=Eph.5.14">Ephesians 5:14</a>, <a href="?bref=Phil.2.6-11">Philippians 2:6-11</a>, <a href="?bref=1Tim.1.17">1 Timothy 1:17</a>, and <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.11-13">2 Timothy 2:11-13</a>.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WhyGodIstoBePraised">Why God Is to Be Praised</p>
<p class="fl">Creation provides impetus for the praise of God (<a href="?bref=Ps.8.3">Ps 8:3</a>), as does his preserving love and care (<a href="?bref=Ps.21.4">21:4</a>) and the fact that he is a prayer-answering God (<a href="?bref=Ps.116.1">116:1</a>). His redeeming work leads his people to worship him (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.1-2">Ex 15:1-2</a>). Some of the psalms (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.107.1-43">Ps 107</a>) list many reasons why he should be praised. With the coming of the Lord Jesus Christ, there is a fresh outburst of praise because the Messiah, the Savior, has come to his people (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.11">Lk 2:11</a>). All that he did by his life, death, and resurrection calls for praise. But ultimately praise will be made perfect when God reigns victorious over all. Thus John speaks in the book of Revelation (<a href="?bref=Rev.19.6">19:6</a>): “Then I heard again what sounded like the shout of a huge crowd, or the roar of mighty ocean waves, or the crash of loud thunder: ‘Hallelujah! For the Lord our God, the Almighty, reigns’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Prayer_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prayer</a>; <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>; <a href="?item=Worship_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Worship</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>