<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PrayerofManasseh">
  <title>Prayer of Manasseh*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PRAYER OF MANASSEH*</p>
<p class="fl">This short prayer, ascribed to King Manasseh of Judah, is often regarded as the finest composition in the entire English Apocrypha. During the Reformation, Protestants highly valued its piety. However, neither Protestants, Roman Catholics, nor the Eastern Orthodox regard it as Scripture.</p>
<p>The older title, The Prayer of Manasses King of Judah When He was Holden [Held] Captive in Babylon (<span class="sc">kjv</span>, <span class="sc">erv</span>), is more helpful than the one commonly used today (<span class="sc">rsv</span>, <span class="sc">neb</span>) or the Latin one, <span class="ital">Oration Manassae.</span> The older title alerts the reader to the supposed connection between this prayer and King Manasseh (696–642 <span class="era">BC</span>), who was taken captive to Babylon, where “at last he came to his senses and cried out humbly to God for help. And the Lord listened, and answered his plea by returning him to Jerusalem and to his kingdom!” (<a href="?bref=2Chr.33.12-13">2 Chr 33:12-13</a>, <span class="sc">tlb</span>; on the historicity of this account, see <a href="?item=ManassehPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Manasseh</a> #3). The writer of 2 Chronicles indicates that this prayer was available to him from national archives and from another work (<a href="?bref=2Chr.33.18-19">2 Chr 33:18-19</a>). The prayer was composed by an anonymous author, though the date is uncertain. On internal evidence it has been dated between 250 <span class="era">BC</span> and <span class="era">AD</span> 50. The oldest surviving Greek biblical manuscript containing it is Codex Alexandrinus (fifth century <span class="era">AD</span>), but the earliest evidence for its existence is its inclusion in a Syriac manual of church procedures known as <span class="ital">Didascalia</span> (third century <span class="era">AD</span>), which, in a revised and expanded form, also appeared as a part of the <span class="ital">Apostolic Constitutions</span> (<span class="era">AD</span> 380).</p>
<p>Most scholars believe that the prayer was originally composed in Greek, but for such a short book—about 400 words in English—the problem of determining the original language is difficult. Because the Prayer of Manasseh survives both in Greek and in Syriac, Latin (two forms), Ethiopic, Armenian, and Old Slavonic translation, it was clearly popular in the first three Christian centuries, among both Jews and Christians.</p>
<p>The Prayer of Manasseh is the prayer of a self-confessed sinner to a merciful God. The <span class="sc">rsv</span> (which is quoted below unless otherwise noted) and <span class="sc">neb</span> divide the Prayer of Manasseh into 15 verses. KJV and <span class="sc">erv</span> do not indicate verses, and a rarer system divides the prayer into 19 verses. The prayer uses several descriptions of God drawn from the OT. It begins by identifying God as “Lord Almighty” (Prayer of Manasseh 1:1; cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.6.18">2 Cor 6:18</a>) and “God of our fathers” (Prayer of Manasseh 1:1, cf. <a href="?bref=2Chr.20.6">2 Chr 20:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.33.12">33:12</a>) and of their righteous descendants. God is the Creator—glorious and powerful, wrathful yet merciful (Prayer of Manasseh 1:2-7a). He “made heaven and earth” (v 2; cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.20.11">Ex 20:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.6">Neh 9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.146.6">Ps 146:6</a>) “in their manifold array” (Prayer of Manasseh 1:2, <span class="sc">neb</span>). He “shackled the sea” and “confined the deep” (v 3; cf. <a href="?bref=Job.38.8-11">Jb 38:8-11</a>). No one can endure his glorious majesty (Prayer of Manasseh 1:5a; contrast <a href="?bref=2Pet.1.16-17">2 Pt 1:16-17</a>). His power makes every creature “shudder, and tremble” (Prayer of Manasseh 1:4), but his goodness is demonstrated in mercy and in salvation (vv 7, 14; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.63.7">Is 63:7</a> and <a href="?bref=Rom.2.4">Rom 2:4</a>), for he is compassionate, patiently long-suffering (forbearing), and very merciful (Prayer of Manasseh 1:7; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.86.5,15">Ps 86:5, 15</a>). God is “the Lord Most High” (Prayer of Manasseh 1:7; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.7.17">Ps 7:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.47.2">47:2</a>).</p>
<p>Even so, Manasseh confesses that “none can endure thy menacing wrath against sinners” (Prayer of Manasseh 1:5b, <span class="sc">neb</span>). He recognizes that his idolatry has been evil in God’s eyes all along, even though he has just become aware that he has been “piling sin upon sin” (v 10, <span class="sc">neb</span>). He also knows now that he finds himself in irons and rejected by God because his idolatry has provoked God’s wrath (v 10; cf. <a href="?bref=2Chr.33.6">2 Chr 33:6</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.107.10">Ps 107:10</a>). God’s mercy is his only hope. It is unmeasurable and unfathomable (Prayer of Manasseh 1:6), boundless (v 7, <span class="sc">neb</span>), and great (v 14). God’s mercy is also available, because the Lord himself has “appointed repentance for sinners, that they may be saved” (v 7; cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.5.31">Acts 5:31</a>), and for him in particular (v 8).</p>
<p>The heart of the prayer (vv 9-13a), in which he confesses his sin and appeals for forgiveness, contains three memorable lines: “My transgressions abound, O Lord, my transgressions abound. . . . Forgive me, O Lord, forgive me!” The turning point in the prayer comes in verse 11, after his confession of sin. The <span class="sc">rsv</span> preserves the figure of speech: “And now I bend the knee of my heart, beseeching thee for thy kindness.” Despite his unworthiness (vv 9, 14), he pleads with God not to destroy him, nor be eternally angry with him, nor condemn him to the grave, because the Lord is “the God of those who repent” (v 13). Manasseh becomes confident that God, in his goodness and mercy, will save him (v 14), and he shows the appropriate response of a forgiven sinner when he says, “I will praise thee continually all the days of my life” (v 15). A brief doxology about God’s praise and eternal glory concludes the prayer.</p>
<p>Despite its admirable parts, this prayer differs from Christian teaching in one significant way. The author erroneously assumes that there are two categories of people—those who are basically good (the righteous) and those who are basically bad (sinners). The prayer presents Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob as righteous men who did not sin and did not need to repent. This is not true, but it shows Jewish thinking prior to Christian preaching (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.9.13">Mt 9:13</a>). Paul made it quite plain that no person is righteous on his own merit, because every person has sinned (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.10-12,21-26">Rom 3:10-12, 21-26</a>). Abraham’s righteousness was not inherent; it came by faith (<a href="?bref=Rom.4.3">Rom 4:3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Phil.3.8-9">Phil 3:8-9</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Apocrypha_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Apocrypha</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>