<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Presbyter">
  <title>Presbyter*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PRESBYTER*</p>
<p class="fl">NT term referring to an elder in the church. Following the OT pattern of synagogues governed by a council of elders, the church of the NT had officers (<span class="greek">presbuteroi</span><span class="ital">,</span> “older persons”) whose task was to tend the flock of God that was under their care (<a href="?bref=1Pet.5.2">1 Pt 5:2</a>). Thus, they were called to labor in preaching and teaching (<a href="?bref=1Tim.5.17">1 Tm 5:17</a>); visit, pray over, and anoint the sick (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.14">Jas 5:14</a>); administer famine relief (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.29-30">Acts 11:29-30</a>); and generally oversee the affairs of the church (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.4">15:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.16.4">16:4</a>). There is evidence to suggest that all elders were of equal status and that the terms “presbyter” and “bishop” were at first used interchangeably (<a href="?bref=Acts.20.17,28">Acts 20:17, 28</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.1.1">Phil 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.5-7">Ti 1:5-7</a>). In the second century, however, the presiding presbyter gradually emerged as a distinctive figure with a position of preeminence and as the source of authority. As the years passed, the designation “presbyter” was contracted to that of “priest,” and in churches of the episcopal order it remains so today. It is significant, nevertheless, that the NT nowhere links priestly functions with the office of presbyter. With the spread and development of Christianity, the priest became a powerful figure. With eucharistic theology, there grew up unbiblical accretions. These were exposed and rejected when the Reformers triumphed in the 16th century and stressed the priesthood of all believers. In Protestantism priests became ministers, pastors, or (in more modern times) clergymen. In non-Roman Episcopal churches, “priest” is found again today. Even where it is interpreted differently from Roman usage, most evangelical Anglicans refuse to use it. In Presbyterian and similar churches, the elders (whether teaching or ruling) are still officially called presbyters, and all are of equal status.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Bishop_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bishop</a>; <a href="?item=DeaconDeaconess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Deacon, Deaconess</a>; <a href="?item=Elder_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Elder</a>; <a href="?item=Pastor_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Pastor</a>; <a href="?item=SpiritualGifts_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Spiritual Gifts</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>