<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Priesthood">
  <title>Priesthood</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PRIESTHOOD</p>
<p class="fl">Office or function of a priest. The modern word “priest” (in French <span class="ital">prêtre</span> and in German <span class="ital">priester</span>) is used of a clergyman in episcopalian churches (Roman, Orthodox, and Anglican). It is also used in the description of the whole church as “a royal priesthood” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.9">1 Pt 2:9</a>). To ascertain how this usage arose and to see what priesthood means, it is necessary to look briefly at both biblical and theological developments.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the covenant made between God and Israel, the whole people was seen as a “kingdom of priests” and thus a holy people (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.6">Ex 19:6</a>). Within this context, specific priestly activities belonged to three orders—high priest, priest, and Levite. “Priests” were male descendants of Aaron, who was a Levite (<a href="?bref=Num.3.10">Nm 3:10</a>), and “Levites” were other male members of the tribe of Levi. The chief functions of the priesthood took place in the temple. Priests looked after the ceremonial vessels and performed the sacrifices. In doing their duties they dressed in special, symbolic vestments. They were also teachers, passing on the sacred traditions of the nation as well as such matters as medical information (<a href="?bref=Lev.13.1-15.33">Lv 13–15</a>). The high priest was the spiritual head of Israel and he had special functions, such as entering the Holy of Holies on the Day of Atonement (ch <a href="?bref=Lev.16.1-34">16</a>). The Levites assisted the priests and served the congregation in the temple. They sang the psalms, kept the temple courts clean, helped to prepare certain sacrifices and offerings, and also had a teaching function. Through this threefold order, the priesthood of the nation was exercised. By it the people offered worship to God, made intercessions and petitions, and learned of God’s will. Thus what occurred in every pious home, as the head of the house guided his family in worship, occurred in a larger and more ceremonial way in the temple.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">It is remarkable that the term “priest” is never used in the NT of a minister or order in the church. Certainly the usage with reference to Judaism and paganism continues (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.1,6">Acts 4:1, 6</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.14.13">14:13</a>), but it is never introduced into the church. The Letter to the Hebrews presents the OT priesthood as fulfilled in Jesus Christ. First of all, he has been appointed high priest by God himself (<a href="?bref=Heb.5.4-6">Heb 5:4-6</a>). Yet his is a superior priesthood to that of Aaron (ch <a href="?bref=Heb.7.1-28">7</a>). Second, being totally sympathetic to the needs of sinful people and tempted in all points like them, he is without sin (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.15">4:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.7.26">7:26</a>). Third, instead of offering animal sacrifices to take away sin, he offers himself, as the sinless Lamb, to take away sin. This is a perfect atonement (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.27">7:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.24-28">9:24-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.10-19">10:10-19</a>).</p>
<p>Not only was the OT sacrificial system fulfilled; it was also finished by the unique, unrepeatable, and unlimited sacrifice of Christ. Having risen from the dead, he is a priest forever (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.17">Heb 7:17</a>) and he remains the same yesterday and today and forever (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.8">13:8</a>). Part of his high priesthood is to offer intercession for his people (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.25">7:25</a>). He is the mediator of a new and better covenant (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.22">7:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.8.6">8:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.9.15">9:15</a>). Only through him are sinful human beings able to enter the holy presence of God and be accepted as children of God (<a href="?bref=John.14.6">Jn 14:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.5.18-20">2 Cor 5:18-20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.2.5">1 Tm 2:5</a>). Therefore, whatever priesthood Christians have, they have it only in and through Christ, their high priest and Mediator.</p>
<p>The NT (quoted from the <span class="sc">rsv</span>) describes believers as “a holy priesthood, to offer spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.2.5">1 Pt 2:5</a>); “priests to his God and Father” (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.6">Rv 1:6</a>); “a kingdom and priests to our God” (<a href="?bref=Rev.5.10">5:10</a>); “priests of God and of Christ, and they shall reign with him a thousand years” (<a href="?bref=Rev.20.6">20:6</a>).</p>
<p>What, then, does the priesthood of all believers mean in the NT? The high priesthood of Christ may be defined as his complete dedication and obedience to God, his Father, and unlimited compassion for his fellow human beings. At the center is his sacrificial death on the cross. On this basis and in union with him, the priesthood of Christians is their sacrificial obedience to God; this involves spiritual worship and love of God and compassionate activity and prayer for their fellow human beings. Paul wrote, “Present your bodies as a living sacrifice, holy and acceptable to God, which is your spiritual worship” (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.1">Rom 12:1</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Each Christian offers his whole body to Christ and each local church offers itself wholly to Christ, and Christ offers his whole body (the church) to God the Father. Thus, in and by Christ, the priesthood of believers is exercised and made effectual. In the hearts of believers is the indwelling Spirit, and it is in his power that acceptable service and worship is offered. Christ is the pattern of priesthood as well as being high priest.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=OfferingsandSacrifices_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Offerings and Sacrifices</a>; <a href="?item=PriestsandLevites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Priests and Levites</a>; <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>; <a href="?item=Worship_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Worship</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>