<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PrincipalitiesandPowers">
  <title>Principalities and Powers*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PRINCIPALITIES AND POWERS*</p>
<p class="fl">Phrase familiarized by the <span class="sc">kjv</span>, occurring several times in Paul’s writings, and expressed by means of three Greek synonyms. The concept of principalities is signified by <span class="greek">exousia</span> and <span class="greek">archai</span><span class="ital">,</span> while powers is represented by <span class="greek">dunamis</span><span class="ital">.</span> In the NT, <span class="greek">exousia</span> describes the power inherent in authority as something confirmed by or derived from a position of prominence. There is nothing evil about this kind of authority; on the contrary, it is essentially right both morally and spiritually (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.23">Mt 21:23</a>). It thus applies most appropriately to the authority of the Messiah (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.6">Mt 9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.2.10">Mk 2:10</a>), of the apostles (<a href="?bref=2Cor.10.8">2 Cor 10:8</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.13.10">13:10</a>), and of human government (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.8.9">Mt 8:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.20">Lk 20:20</a>). <span class="greek">Archai</span> has several meanings but occurs 12 times in the sense of “command,” “rule,” or “sovereignty,” 9 of which (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.38">Rom 8:38</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.24">1 Cor 15:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.1.21">Eph 1:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.3.10">3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.6.12">6:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.16">Col 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.2.10,15">2:10, 15</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.1">Ti 3:1</a>) appear in Paul’s letters. Finally <span class="greek">dunamis</span><span class="ital">,</span> a common word for power, denotes the ability or strength to achieve an impressive goal (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.15">Mt 25:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.3.12">Acts 3:12</a>).</p>
<p>By using the expression “principalities and powers,” Paul was referring to the hierarchy of supernatural agencies, such as angelic beings, who worship and serve the Creator of the universe. Some commentators have divided this hierarchy into five categories, namely thrones, principalities, powers, authorities, and dominions. This categorization, however, can be arrived at only by general inference, since there is nothing in Scripture that points directly to such distinct groups. In using the phrase, Paul was probably expressing the cosmic lordship of Jesus in as colorful and dramatic a manner as possible.</p>
<p>In giving Jesus a name above every other name, Paul was demonstrating the supreme lordship of Christ over all created beings, whether good or bad (<a href="?bref=Rom.14.11">Rom 14:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.10">Phil 2:10</a>). As their Creator, the heavenly hosts were his subjects, acknowledging him as Lord of the universe. This affirmation was important for the Colossians, whose theology had apparently been tainted by unbiblical speculation (<a href="?bref=Col.2.8">Col 2:8</a>). The truth is that in Jesus there resided all the fullness of God, and this is transmitted to believers through the Lord’s Spirit.</p>
  </body>
</item>