<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ProstituteProstitution">
  <title>Prostitute, Prostitution</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PROSTITUTE, PROSTITUTION</p>
<p class="fl">Person guilty of illicit sexual relationships; figuratively, one who worships an idol. The term “prostitute” translates four different words found in the Bible. One type of prostitute was the man or woman, married or unmarried, who committed immoral acts (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.31">Gn 34:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.19.2">Jgs 19:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.23.27">Prv 23:27</a>). A different kind of prostitute was the temple prostitute of heathen religions in which fornication was part of the worship (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.21-22">Gn 38:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.23.17">Dt 23:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.4.14">Hos 4:14</a>). Such prostitution was forbidden by the law of Moses (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.29">Lv 19:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.21.9">21:9</a>). The “strange woman” was another kind of prostitute (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.1">1 Kgs 11:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.5.20">Prv 5:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.6.24">6:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.7.5">7:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.23.27">23:27</a>). There are different opinions for why that name was given to prostitutes. One explanation is that it referred to a man leaving his own wife for another, who ought to be a stranger to him (<a href="?bref=Pr.5.17-20">Prv 5:17-20</a>). It may also have referred to a foreign woman (<a href="?bref=Num.25.1">Nm 25:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.23.13">Jos 23:13</a>). “Prostitute” also refers to any woman, married or single, who practices unlawful sexual indulgence, whether for lust or monetary gain (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.31-32">Mt 21:31-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.15.30">Lk 15:30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.6.15-16">1 Cor 6:15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.31">Heb 11:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.25">Jas 2:25</a>).</p>
<p>Prostitution appeared early in Israel’s life and continued throughout biblical history. Most biblical passages strongly condemn the practice of prostitution in any form. The priestly law of <a href="?bref=Lev.21.9">Leviticus 21:9</a> provided that a priest’s daughter who practiced prostitution was to be burned to death. A priest could not marry a prostitute (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.29">Lv 19:29</a>), and the wages of prostitution could not be used to pay vows in the temple (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.18">Dt 23:18</a>). These prohibitions served to keep the worship of the Lord free from the practice of cult prostitution.</p>
<p>The sons of Jacob killed Hamor and his son Shechem, justifying their act by saying: “Should he treat our sister like a prostitute?” (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.31">Gn 34:31</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Amaziah’s wife was to become a prostitute (<a href="?bref=Amos.7.17">Am 7:17</a>) as punishment for his treatment of the prophet Amos.</p>
<p>In the first century, prostitutes and tax collectors were equally detested by the Jews (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.32">Mt 21:32</a>). According to Paul, the body of a Christian belongs to Christ and should not be joined to a prostitute’s body (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.15-16">1 Cor 6:15-16</a>). Proverbs is replete with warnings to those who would go in to prostitutes.</p>
<p>A few biblical passages do, however, seem to accept the prostitute as a member of the community. Tamar temporarily served as a prostitute to remind her father-in-law of his promise to her (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.14-15">Gn 38:14-15</a>). Rahab the prostitute had a special place in Hebrew history because she had befriended the Hebrew spies (<a href="?bref=Josh.2.4-16">Jos 2:4-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.31">Heb 11:31</a>).</p>
<p>The words “prostitute” and “prostitution” were used figuratively for idolatry, especially in the prophetic books (<a href="?bref=Jer.2.20">Jer 2:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.1,5,15-16">Rv 17:1, 5, 15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.2">19:2</a>). This figurative use was based on the marriagelike relationship of the Lord and his people (<a href="?bref=Jer.3.20">Jer 3:20</a>). When the people gave their allegiance to idols rather than to God, he charged that they were prostitutes for other gods (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.33">Jgs 8:33</a>). The same idea is found in the NT (<a href="?bref=Rev.17.1-18">Rv 17</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>