<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PtolemaicEmpire">
  <title>Ptolemaic Empire*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PTOLEMAIC EMPIRE*</p>
<p class="fl">Empire named from Ptolemy I Soter, a Macedonian general of Alexander the Great who got himself appointed satrap, or governor, of Egypt shortly after Alexander died in 323 <span class="era">BC</span>. At its height during the third century <span class="era">BC</span>, the empire included Egypt, Cyrenaica (Cyrene), south Syria, Palestine, Cyprus, the south coast of Asia Minor, and some Aegean islands. Throughout the history of the empire, the Ptolemaic dynasty (all taking the name Ptolemy) occupied the imperial chair.</p>
<p>Ptolemy Soter was forced to engage in numerous struggles with governors of other parts of Alexander’s empire. Generally successful, he felt secure enough to assume the title of king in 305 <span class="era">BC</span>. The following year he fought on the side of Rhodes against Macedonia. For saving Rhodes’s independence, he won the title of Soter (savior). The ancients did not number kings of the same name, as it is now customary to do, but distinguished them by titles instead.</p>
<p>Ptolemy Soter managed to win control of Palestine on his fourth invasion of the area (301 <span class="era">BC</span>), and his successors were destined to hold it for over a century. On his abdication (285 <span class="era">BC</span>), he left a well-ordered kingdom in which the Greek population was loyal to the administration and the native population had been wooed by efforts of conciliation. Alexandria had become his great capital. There he founded a famous library and museum and patronized the arts.</p>
<p>Ptolemy II Philadelphus (285–246 <span class="era">BC</span>) maintained a splendid court in Alexandria, which is often compared to that of Versailles under Louis XIV for its pageantry and its vices. He patronized the arts and scientific research and added to the library in the capital. Ptolemy II was also a formidable power in the ancient world, and he came to exercise naval control over the Mediterranean and the Aegean. His commercial efforts were extensive and included the shores of the Red Sea after he dug a canal linking the Nile and the Red Sea.</p>
<p>Ptolemy III Euergetes (246–221 <span class="era">BC</span>) continued to maintain the empire’s naval power but allowed the army to decline after successful ventures against the Seleucids in Mesopotamia early in his reign. In fact, under Ptolemy III the empire may be regarded as having reached its height. He was also a liberal patron of the arts and built numerous public buildings and temples.</p>
<p>Ptolemy IV Philopator (221–203? <span class="era">BC</span>) was a wretched and debauched person under whom the Ptolemaic Empire began its decline. During his rule, conflict with the Seleucids continued, but the Egyptians won a great victory over Antiochus III of Syria in 217 <span class="era">BC</span>. This Egyptian triumph was accomplished in part because the Greek administration armed native Egyptians. This fact gave rise to a series of native rebellions during the next 30 years.</p>
<p>Ptolemy V Epiphanes (203?–181 <span class="era">BC</span>) was only about five when he came to the throne. Antiochus III of Syria and Philip V of Macedon decided to take advantage of the weakness of Egypt at that time and divide the Ptolemaic Empire between them. In the process Syria took control of Palestine after a century of Ptolemaic rule. In this difficult period Egypt became quite closely linked with Rome, which intervened on Ptolemy’s behalf.</p>
<p>Ptolemy VI Philometor (181–145 <span class="era">BC</span>) likewise came to the throne as a minor and the country was further weakened under another regency. His regents launched a war against Syria to regain Palestine but were unsuccessful. When Syria invaded in 170 <span class="era">BC</span> and captured him, Rome intervened and restored him to his throne. Rome again intervened and restored Ptolemy VI to his throne when Ptolemy VII sought to unseat him in 163 <span class="era">BC</span>. As a kindly and reasonable man, Ptolemy Philometor is sometimes considered to be the best of the Ptolemies.</p>
<p>His successor, Ptolemy VII Physcon (145–116 <span class="era">BC</span>), is represented as just the opposite—as a cruel man untouched by natural affections and afflicted with a loathsome corpulence. After his death, the royal household was plunged into domestic strife for several years, and the dynasty was never again destined to be very stable. During the first century <span class="era">BC</span>, Rome increasingly intervened in Egyptian affairs on behalf of one or the other of the Ptolemies. After several weak reigns, Rome more effectively entered Egyptian affairs during the days of Ptolemy XII and Cleopatra VII, annexing Egypt after the suicide of Cleopatra in 30 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
  </body>
</item>