<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="PutPlace">
  <title>Put (Place)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">PUT (<span class="lc">Place</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Ancient nation, descended from a man of the same name. It is commonly identified as Libya, although it has been argued that it was the Punt of Egyptian records, somewhere along the northeast coast of Africa, perhaps Somalia. Its association with Egypt, Cush, and Canaan, and the usage of the name in the OT, make the Libyan location probable. In the OT the Libyan people are called Lubim, a name that always appears in the plural.</p>
<p>Ancient Libya was situated to the west of Egypt, the site of modern Libya, on the Mediterranean coast of North Africa. The Egyptians distinguished among several groups of Libyans. The Tjehenu, who inhabited the coastal region, were primarily herdsmen. They were represented in Egyptian art as having long hair and wearing only a belt and a penis sheath. They were listed among the Nine Bows—the nine traditional enemies of Egypt. The Tjemehu were nomads and were physically different from other African ethnic groups in that they had blond hair and blue eyes. Their relationships with Egypt date back to the Old Kingdom, and from time to time they tried to make their way into Egypt. The Libu (after whom the country was named) and the Meshwesh (western Libyans) are described as fair-skinned, tattooed, and with long leather garments.</p>
<p>The Egyptians had commercial and military contacts with Libya throughout its history. The Libyans periodically attempted to penetrate Egypt from the northwest. From the Middle Kingdom there is the story of Sinuhe (c. 2000 <span class="era">BC</span>), which begins with the death of Amenemhet I while his son, Senusert (Sesostris), was fighting the Libyans in the western Delta. Later, Libyans did infiltrate the Delta, but Seti I and Ramses II kept them under control. The Stele of Merneptah (c. 1224–c. 1214 <span class="era">BC</span>), which mentions Israel, is largely devoted to Egypt’s victory over the Libyans. Ramses III drove them out of the western Delta in connection with his victorious land and sea struggles with the Sea Peoples.</p>
<p>Eventually, Libyans gained control of Egypt and made up the 22d (Bubastite) dynasty (c. 946–c. 720 <span class="era">BC</span>) and the 23d (Tanitic) dynasty (c. 792–c. 720 <span class="era">BC</span>). Their kings bore foreign names like Sheshonk (the Shishak of the OT, <a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.40">1 Kgs 11:40</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.25">14:25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.12.2-9">2 Chr 12:2-9</a>), Osorkon, and Takelot.</p>
<p>The first occurrence of Put in the Bible is in the table of nations (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.1-32">Gn 10</a>), where Put is listed as a son of Ham, along with Cush (Nubia, Ethiopia), Egypt, and Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.6">Gn 10:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.8">1 Chr 1:8</a>).</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Jer.46.1-28">Jeremiah 46</a> speaks of the battle of Carchemish and refers to the warriors of Ethiopia (Cush) and Put, “who handle the shield,” among the hosts of Egypt (<a href="?bref=Jer.46.9">Jer 46:9</a>). Ezekiel names Persia, Lud, and Put as being in the army of Tyre (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.10">Ez 27:10</a>). Nahum mentioned “Put and the Libyans” among the allies of Thebes who were unable to stop the onslaught of the Assyrians against Egypt (<a href="?bref=Nah.3.9">Na 3:9</a>). Daniel predicts that the Antichrist will have the Libyans, Egypt, Cush, and others in submission (<a href="?bref=Dan.11.43">Dn 11:43</a>).</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Isa.66.19">Isaiah 66:19</a> the Hebrew text reads “Pul,” while the Greek version gives “Put,” which most of the English translations follow. (<span class="sc">nlt</span> reads “Libyans,” with footnote to Hebrew and Greek readings.) Here, Put is listed between Tarshish and Lud in a list of nations that will be told of the glory of God. In <a href="?bref=Ezek.30.5">Ezekiel 30:5</a> the Hebrew word <span class="hebrew">Put</span> is thought to be a country equivalent to Libya. However, other scholars consider <span class="hebrew">Cub</span> also to be Libya in this same verse (see <span class="sc">nlt</span>). In the records of King Xerxes of Persia (485–465 <span class="era">BC</span>), Libya is listed among the nations subject to Xerxes.</p>
  </body>
</item>