<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JamesPerson">
  <title>James (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JAMES (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. James, brother of Jesus; leading elder in the church at Jerusalem; author of the letter bearing his name.</p>
<p class="list-text">James is only mentioned twice in the Gospels, along with his brothers Joseph (or Joses in Greek), Simon, and Judas (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.55">Mt 13:55</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>). James may have been the oldest of the brothers after Jesus. The question has been raised whether these were full brothers of Jesus or not. But there seems to be no good reason to challenge the fact from Scripture. James, like his other brothers, apparently did not accept Jesus’ authority during Jesus’ life on earth (<a href="?bref=John.7.5">Jn 7:5</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">James’ conversion is not mentioned. It may have happened when Jesus appeared to him and others after his resurrection (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.7">1 Cor 15:7</a>). He became head of the church at Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.17">Acts 12:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.21.18">21:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.9">Gal 2:9</a>). Although Jesus had always taught the relative subordination of family ties (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.48-50">Mt 12:48-50</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.33-35">Mk 3:33-35</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.21">Lk 8:21</a>), it is hard to believe that James’ authority was not somehow enhanced because of his relationship to the Master.</p>
<p class="list-text">James was regarded as an apostle (<a href="?bref=Gal.1.19">Gal 1:19</a>), although he was not one of the Twelve. Some suggest he was a replacement for the martyred son of Zebedee; others widen the scope of the term “apostle” to include both “the Twelve” and “all the apostles” (see the two separate categories cited in <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.5,7">1 Cor 15:5, 7</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Tradition stated that James was appointed the first bishop of Jerusalem by the Lord himself as well as the apostles. What is certain is that he presided over the first Council of Jerusalem, called to consider the terms for admission of Gentiles into the Christian church, and he may have formulated the decree that was approved by all his colleagues and was sent to the churches of Antioch, Syria, and Cilicia (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.19-20">Acts 15:19-20</a>). James evidently regarded his own special ministry as being to the Jews. He had a mediating role in the controversy that arose in the young church around the place of the law for those who had become Christians, from both Gentile and Jewish origins.</p>
<p class="list-text">He continued to have strong Jewish-Christian sympathies, as can be seen from his request to Paul visiting Jerusalem for the last time (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.18-25">Acts 21:18-25</a>). This was also the last mention in Acts of James’ career. He is traditionally considered to be the author of the Letter of James, where he describes himself as “a slave of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.1">Jas 1:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">According to Hegesippus (c. 180), James was referred to as the “the Just,” because of his faithful adherence to the Jewish law and his austere lifestyle. It seems clear that James suffered martyrdom. Josephus places it in the year 61, when there was a Jewish uprising after the death of Festus the procurator and before his successor had been appointed.</p>
<p class="list">2. James, son of Alphaeus; one of the 12 apostles.</p>
<p class="list-text">James, son of Alphaeus, is always listed as one of the 12 apostles (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.3">Mt 10:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.18">Mk 3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.15">Lk 6:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.13">Acts 1:13</a>), but nothing is known for certain about him. Levi (also known as Matthew) is also described as the son of Alphaeus (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.14">Mk 2:14</a>), but it is not likely that he and James were brothers. Many scholars have identified him with the one called “James the less” or “James the smaller.” The description “the less” seems to have been given to distinguish him from the son of Zebedee, and it may signify that he was either smaller or younger than Zebedee’s son (the Greek word can cover both interpretations).</p>
<p class="list">3. James, son of Zebedee. One of the 12 apostles; the first of them to be martyred (<span class="era">AD</span> 44).</p>
<p class="list-text">James was a Galilean fisherman. We can suppose that he had a comfortable situation (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.19-20">Mk 1:19-20</a>). He was called to be one of the disciples at the same time as his brother John (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.21">Mt 4:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.19-20">Mk 1:19-20</a>). It is reasonable to assume that he was older than John, both because he is almost always mentioned first and because John is sometimes identified as “the brother of James” (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.2">Mt 10:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.17.1">17:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.17">Mk 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.5.37">5:37</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">James, John, and Simon Peter, were part of a fishing partnership that included Andrew, Simon’s brother (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.10">Lk 5:10</a>). The three attained, in a sense, a place of leadership among the disciples. They are found at the center of things—for example, when Jairus’ daughter was raised (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.37">Mk 5:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.51">Lk 8:51</a>), at the Transfiguration (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.1">Mt 17:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.2">Mk 9:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.28">Lk 9:28</a>), on the Mount of Olives (<a href="?bref=Mark.13.3">Mk 13:3</a>), and in the Garden of Gethsemane (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.37">Mt 26:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.33">Mk 14:33</a>). Moreover, James and John, had earlier accompanied Jesus to the home of Simon and Andrew (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.29">Mk 1:29</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Jesus gave James and John the nickname Boanerges, meaning “sons of thunder” (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.17">Mk 3:17</a>), when the Lord upbraided them for their explosive speech and for having totally misconceived the purpose of his coming. This may have been the consequence of their suggestion to pray for the destruction of the Samaritan village, because of the villagers’ rejection (<a href="?bref=Luke.9.54">Lk 9:54</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.9.38">Mk 9:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.9.49">Lk 9:49</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The two brothers demonstrated presumptuous and rash thinking when they asked for a place of honor in the kingdom. Jesus prophesied that James and his brother would drink the cup their Master was to drink (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.35-40">Mk 10:35-40</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.20.20-23">Mt 20:20-23</a>). It is assumed the two were present with the other disciples when the risen Christ appeared by the Sea of Galilee (<a href="?bref=John.21.1">Jn 21:1</a>), though curiously James’ name is nowhere mentioned in the fourth Gospel.</p>
<p class="list-text">We know nothing about James’ career subsequently until about the year 44, when Jesus’ prophecy was fulfilled: James was killed “by the sword” by Herod Agrippa I, and therefore became the first of the Twelve whose martyrdom was referred to in the NT (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.1-2">Acts 12:1-2</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The wife of Zebedee was Salome (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.56">Mt 27:56</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.15.40">Mk 15:40</a>), who may have been a sister of the Lord’s mother (<a href="?bref=John.19.25">Jn 19:25</a>). If this were so, it would mean that James and John were first cousins of Jesus and that they may have considered themselves to have been in a privileged position.</p>
  </body>
</item>