<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Jew">
  <title>Jew</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEW</p>
<p class="fl">Judean, belonging to Judah. The short form of the English word was developed from the French. The underlying Hebrew word is used first in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.6">2 Kings 16:6</a> as a national term, meaning citizens of Judah. It came into general use in the period of Jeremiah just before the exile (late sixth century <span class="era">BC</span>; see <a href="?bref=Jer.32.12">Jer 32:12</a>). It reflects a growing sense of national identity among foreign nations in an international world. In <a href="?bref=Jer.34.9">Jeremiah 34:9</a>, a statement concerning the national principle that an individual citizen had the right to freedom from slavery uses the term “Jew.” In <a href="?bref=Jer.52.28">Jeremiah 52:28</a> it is poignantly used in giving the number of deported citizens.</p>
<p>Once the people were in exile, the term’s national meaning was expanded with a religious one. The Jews were different from surrounding peoples in that they preserved a living religious tradition of one true God. A division between Jews and Gentiles emerged. Thus in <a href="?bref=Dan.3.8-12">Daniel 3:8-12</a> certain Jews are accused of deviating from otherwise acceptable Babylonian religious practices. The book of Esther is concerned with the problem of Jewish identity and survival in a hostile alien environment. <a href="?bref=Esth.8.17">Esther 8:17</a> speaks of Gentiles declaring themselves Jews in the religious sense of becoming proselytes (people who have converted).</p>
<p>After the exile, the strongly religious meaning of “Jew” is expressed in the prophecy of <a href="?bref=Zech.8.23">Zechariah 8:23</a> that the Jew would be courted by Gentiles because God was with him. In <a href="?bref=Ezra.4.12">Ezra 4:12</a> the term “Jews” is the national designation of the returned exiles, as it is in the book of Nehemiah (e.g., <a href="?bref=Neh.1.2">Neh 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.4.2">4:2</a>). In <a href="?bref=Neh.13.24">Nehemiah 13:24</a> there is a consciousness of the social exclusiveness of the Jews: on religious grounds, marriage to foreigners is deplored.</p>
<p>In the NT “Jew” continues to have the same national and/or religious meaning. Culturally, Jews have religious and other customs that NT documents addressed to Gentiles find it necessary to explain (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.3">Mk 7:3</a>; <a href="?bref=John.5.1">Jn 5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=John.19.40">19:40</a>). Jews are contrasted with Gentiles (<a href="?bref=Acts.11.19">Acts 11:19</a>), Samaritans (<a href="?bref=John.4.9,22">Jn 4:9, 22</a>), and proselytes (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.10">Acts 2:10</a>). Jewish Christians can be called “Jews” (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.13">Gal 2:13</a>), but there is an increasing emphasis on the religious distinctions between Jew and Christian. In <a href="?bref=Rom.2.17-29">Romans 2:17-29</a> Paul gives an interesting theological analysis of the term “Jew.” He emphasizes that the true meaning of the word isn't about outward religious displays but about one's inner relationship with God. Paul was certainly thinking of the inadequacy of his own life as a Jew before he was converted to the Christian faith (cf. <a href="?bref=Phil.3.3-6">Phil 3:3-6</a>). His mention of “praise” in <a href="?bref=Rom.2.29">Romans 2:29</a> is the climax of the passage. It is a forceful play on words: in Hebrew, Judah means praise (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.35">Gn 29:35</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.49.8">49:8</a>).</p>
<p>The apostle Paul is starting to consider Christianity as the true heir of the faith of the OT. <a href="?bref=Rev.2.9">Revelation 2:9</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.3.9">3:9</a> express similar sentiments: to be truly a Jew is much more than a matter of birth and synagogue observance. Underlying these passages in both Revelation and Romans is obviously the issue of the messianic claims of Jesus (cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.9.3-5">Rom 9:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.10.1-4">10:1-4</a>). The NT bears sad testimony to the opposition of Jews to the Christian message. The gospel proved a cause of offense to the Jews (<a href="?bref=1Cor.1.23">1 Cor 1:23</a>). Paul himself, despite his claim of impeccable Jewish credentials (<a href="?bref=Acts.26.4-7">Acts 26:4-7</a>), found himself the object of bitter Jewish attacks (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.11">21:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.23.12,27">23:12, 27</a>). <a href="?bref=Rev.2.9">Revelation 2:9</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.3.9">3:9</a> describe the Jews’ opposition as satanic: they were carrying out the work of God’s adversary, Satan.</p>
<p>These negative overtones are especially attached to the use of the word “Jew” in John’s Gospel. It is found about 70 times, versus about five or six instances in each of the synoptic Gospels. Some passages, such as those already cited, have no associations of hostility. But in most cases the fourth Gospel uses “Jews” in the sense of the religious authorities, especially those in Jerusalem, who were hostile to Jesus (see, e.g., <a href="?bref=John.5.18">Jn 5:18</a>; <a href="?bref=John.9.18">9:18</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.8">11:8</a>; <a href="?bref=John.18.36">18:36</a>). It is noteworthy that in <a href="?bref=John.9.22">9:22</a> the parents of the blind man, clearly Jews themselves, are said, literally, to fear the investigating Jews. In <a href="?bref=John.18.14">18:14</a> “Jews” stands for the chief priests and Pharisees of <a href="?bref=John.18.3">18:3</a>. It must be emphasized that the author, who was obviously a Jew himself, was thus not expressing an anti-Semitic viewpoint. He condemned not race or people but those who opposed Jesus. He gladly acknowledged that some Jews put their faith in Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.8.31">8:31</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.45">11:45</a>: <a href="?bref=John.12.11">12:11</a>). Nathanael is featured as a type of the Christian Jew, a true Israelite “in whom is no guile” (<a href="?bref=John.1.47">1:47</a>; cf. v <a href="?bref=John.1.31">31</a>; see <a href="?bref=Gen.27.35">Gn 27:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.32.28">32:28</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>; <a href="?item=Judaizers_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaizers</a>; <a href="?item=Pharisees_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Pharisees</a>; <a href="?item=PostexilicPeriod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Postexilic Period</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>