<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wages">
  <title>Wages</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WAGES</p>
<p class="fl">Payment received by a laborer in return for his work. Usually wages are calculated in terms of a medium of exchange, such as money, but they can be paid in any kind of goods or services. Jacob worked seven years in return for Laban’s younger daughter, Rachel (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.18-20">Gn 29:18-20</a>), and then had to work another seven years when Laban did not honor his agreement. Later, Jacob’s wages were sheep and goats (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.31-32">30:31-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.31.8">31:8</a>). Nebuchadnezzar was given the country of Egypt as wages for his work in capturing the city of Tyre (<a href="?bref=Ezek.29.18-20">Ez 29:18-20</a>).</p>
<p>Usually wages were agreed upon by employer and employee (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.15-19">Gn 29:15-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.20.2">Mt 20:2</a>), but sometimes the pay was at the discretion of the employer (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.4">Mt 20:4</a>). A fair wage for honest work is a biblical principle (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.7">Lk 10:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.5.18">1 Tm 5:18</a>). The Lord established laws to cover this principle and judged those who violated it. Wages were to be paid promptly (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.13">Lv 19:13</a>); the holding back of wages is condemned in the Scripture (<a href="?bref=Mal.3.5">Mal 3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.5.1-6">Jas 5:1-6</a>).</p>
<p>Wages were often a source of discontent and dispute between employer and employee. When soldiers came to John the Baptist to be baptized and asked about their future conduct, he urged them to be content with their wages (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.14">Lk 3:14</a>). Jacob and Laban had disagreements about wages and twice Jacob complained, “You have changed my wages ten times” (<a href="?bref=Gen.31.7,41">Gn 31:7, 41</a>).</p>
<p>The Bible also speaks of ill-gotten wages. The wages of a prostitute could not be brought into the house of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.18">Dt 23:18</a>), and people are warned against the error of Balaam, who corrupted Israel because he “loved the wages of unrighteousness” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.2.15">2 Pt 2:15</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Money_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Money</a>; <a href="?item=BankerBanking_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Banker, Banking</a>; <a href="?item=Poorthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Poor, The</a>; <a href="?item=Riches_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Riches</a>; <a href="?item=Work_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Work</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>