<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WaroftheSonsofLightagainsttheSonsofDarkness">
  <title>War of the Sons of Light against the Sons of Darkness*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WAR OF THE SONS OF LIGHT AGAINST THE SONS OF DARKNESS*</p>
<p class="fl">Scroll found in Cave One at Qumran (1947–48). It casts light on military regulations of the Jewish forces, on the religious life of the sectarians at Qumran, and particularly on their eschatological expectations. It was probably written about the middle of the first century <span class="era">BC</span> or the beginning of the first century <span class="era">AD</span>. Professor Sukenik of Hebrew University purchased the scroll, consisting of 19 sheets, from an antiquities dealer in Bethlehem (<span class="ital">see</span> discussion of discoveries at Wadi Qumran in <a href="?item=BibleManuscriptsandTextoftheOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bible, Manuscripts and Text of the (Old Testament)</a>), then edited the scroll. It was published posthumously in 1954.</p>
<p>The sectarians at Qumran divided all mankind into two camps: the Sons of Light and the Sons of Darkness. Only those in fellowship with the community at Qumran were reckoned to belong to the Sons of Light, and all other Jews, together with the Gentiles, belonged to Satan and his hosts. The scroll expresses the hope that the day of victory over the forces of darkness is approaching. The rule of the Romans (Kittim) “shall come to an end and iniquity shall be vanquished, leaving no remnants; [for the sons] of darkness there shall be no escape.” The Sons of Light will participate in the last battle.</p>
<p>In order to fight the Lord’s battle in the manner of the Lord, the Sons of Light have to be familiar with the rules of war. This scroll was written to indoctrinate the faithful in the biblical rules of war. Since the sabbatical years of rest must be observed, the faithful will fight against the evil forces only 35 out of 40 years.</p>
<p>Six priests in special dress were to proceed ahead of the forces while blowing a trumpet. On each of the trumpets is an inscription that bears out the belief that the battle is the Lord’s and that those who are called are summoned to avenge themselves on the enemies of the Lord and thus to vindicate his holiness. The priests, together with the Levites, blowing their horns, would confound the enemy. In the description of the ordering of the battle divisions, the priests again take up a prominent role. The priests and Levites were to go ahead of the battle formations. They were God’s appointed ministers, as representatives of God’s presence among the fighting forces. In the end, it was expected that God would conquer evil on behalf of the faithful remnant: “This is the day appointed by him for the defeat and overthrow of the Prince of the kingdom of wickedness, and he will send eternal succor to the company of his redeemed by the might of the princely Angel of the kingdom of Michael.”</p>
  </body>
</item>