<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wealth">
  <title>Wealth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEALTH</p>
<p class="fl">Abundance, usually of money or material goods, whose value is ordinarily expressed in terms of some understood unit, such as a national currency. It is virtually synonymous with riches, and both may refer to family, friends, or even moral qualities.</p>
<p>In the OT riches are a mark of favor with God (<a href="?bref=Ps.112.3">Ps 112:3</a>), and he gives power to acquire wealth (<a href="?bref=Deut.8.18">Dt 8:18</a>). Both the piety and the wealth of Job are well known (<a href="?bref=Job.1.1-3">Jb 1:1-3</a>). Solomon was perhaps the richest man who ever lived; God granted him “riches, possessions, and honor” because Solomon had asked for wisdom and discernment rather than material things (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.3.10-13">1 Kgs 3:10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.1.11-12">2 Chr 1:11-12</a>). But the Bible makes it clear that a person’s life does not consist in the abundance of his possessions (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.15">Lk 12:15</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT wealthy men are often seen as godless—for example, the rich farmer (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.16-21">Lk 12:16-21</a>) and the rich man who neglected the beggar Lazarus (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.19-31">16:19-31</a>). The wealthy are condemned for oppression and greed (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.1-6">Jas 5:1-6</a>). <a href="?bref=Luke.6.24">Luke 6:24</a> pronounces woe against the rich, and all three synoptic Gospels speak of the dangers of riches (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.22">Mt 13:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.19">Mk 4:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.14">Lk 8:14</a>). But not all rich men were bad. Jesus was buried in the tomb of a rich man from Arimathea, named Joseph (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.57">Mt 27:57</a>). Nicodemus, who provided lavishly for the burial of Jesus (<a href="?bref=John.19.39">Jn 19:39</a>), was “a ruler of the Jews” (<a href="?bref=John.3.1">3:1</a>) and probably a man of wealth.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Mammon_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mammon</a>; <a href="?item=Money_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Money</a>; <a href="?item=Poorthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Poor, The</a>; <a href="?item=Riches_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Riches</a>; <a href="?item=Wages_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wages</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>