<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WeightsandMeasures">
  <title>Weights and Measures</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WEIGHTS AND MEASURES</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Introduction">Introduction</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#WeightMeasures">Weight Measures</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LinearMeasuresintheOldTestament">Linear Measures in the Old Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LinearMeasuresintheNewTestament">Linear Measures in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#CapacityDryMeasureintheOldTestament">Capacity (Dry Measure) in the Old Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#CapacityDryMeasureintheNewTestament">Capacity (Dry Measure) in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LiquidMeasuresintheOldTestament">Liquid Measures in the Old Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#LiquidMeasuresintheNewTestament">Liquid Measures in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Introduction">Introduction</p>
<p class="fl">Units of measure in the ancient world were largely based on practical standards: the length of an arm, a day’s journey, how much a donkey could carry, and so forth. While this was a convenient system, it also suffered from a lack of standardization. Some arms were longer than others, and some donkeys could carry more than others. The history of weights and measures, therefore, becomes the story of seeking standards. This was not achieved in the OT but began to take place under Greek and Roman influences in NT times.</p>
<p>In the OT the measures that were used are frequently attested to in Mesopotamian, Egyptian, and Canaanite literature as well. The Israelites did not have their own unique set of measurements. Yet while the terms are shared, it is not unusual to find a particular term having one value in Israel and a noticeably different value in one of the other cultures.</p>
<p>By the time of the NT, other variables were added. The Israelites of this period were still using many of the measures that had been used and developed throughout the OT period. But added to that were the Greek and Roman systems of measurement. Sometimes these terms were adopted wholesale, while at other times Hebrew terms were adapted to Greco-Roman standards. On still other occasions, the Roman terms were apparently used when dealing with the government, whereas Hebrew terms were still used in everyday practice.</p>
<p>In most of the kinds of measurement, the base unit (i.e., the one that all of the others are fractions or multiples of) is the one about which there is the most uncertainty. So the cubit (length), the shekel (weight), the homer (dry volume), and the bath (liquid volume) are all to some degree uncertain. This makes all of the other measures based on them equally uncertain.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WeightMeasures">Weight Measures</p>
<p class="fl">The terms used for weights have benefited most from archaeological discoveries. Excavations provide stone weights that are occasionally inscribed with the unit they represent. When the stones are weighed, they frequently give a range of weights that have only a general consistency. However, comparing this data with that provided by the text has given the basis for fairly accurate determinations. The relative scale in any given location is more important than absolute values.</p>
<include_items src="../Charts/Charts.xml" name="TablesOfWeightsAndMeasures"/>
<p>There was standardization of weight measures, but precision was difficult to attain. The Israelite system is similar to that used by the Mesopotamians and the Canaanites. For most of the OT period, the weights system provided the monetary system. Minted coinage was the invention of the Persians. Up until that time, silver or gold or any other trading commodity had to be weighed out so that bartering or purchasing could take place. This made the weights system the core of the ancient economy. It also explains why the Scriptures speak so seriously against the use of false weights (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.36">Lv 19:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.25.13">Dt 25:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.16.11">Prv 16:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.10,23">20:10, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.11">Mi 6:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.12.7">Hos 12:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.5">Am 8:5</a>).</p>
<p>Stone weights were used on a set of balances for conducting business in the ancient marketplace. Scales or balances are mentioned half a dozen times in the OT, but none of those are in actual economic contexts (<a href="?bref=Job.6.2">Jb 6:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.31.6">31:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.62.9">Ps 62:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.12">Is 40:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.5.1">Ez 5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.5.27">Dn 5:27</a>). The scales used were generally of the beam-balance type with dishes on each end.</p>
<p class="h3">Talent</p>
<p class="fl">According to <a href="?bref=Exod.38.25-26">Exodus 38:25-26</a> the talent must have been equal to 3,000 shekels. (A hundred talents would then have been equal to 300,000 shekels, and if that is added to the 1,175 shekels in verse <a href="?bref=Exod.38.25">25</a>, the total is 301,775, or half a shekel for each of the 603,550 men—as verse <a href="?bref=Exod.38.26">26</a> states.) Excavated talents weigh from about 65 to 80 pounds (29.5 to 36.3 kilograms). In the OT the talent is used only for precious metals, usually silver or gold. According to <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.14">1 Kings 10:14</a>, the annual tribute income of Solomon’s kingdom was 666 talents, which apparently was considered quite extravagant. David bequeathed 100,000 talents of gold and 1,000,000 talents of silver to Solomon for the building of the temple (<a href="?bref=1Chr.22.14">1 Chr 22:14</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Mina</p>
<p class="fl">In the Canaanite material from Ugarit the mina equals 50 shekels, while in Babylon the mina equals 60 shekels. In <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.12">Ezekiel 45:12</a>, the mina is set at 60 shekels, but it is unclear whether this represents a change from previous standards.</p>
<p class="h3">Shekel</p>
<p class="fl">The shekel was the basic unit of weight. Besides the regular shekel, there was a “royal” shekel (<a href="?bref=2Sam.14.26">2 Sm 14:26</a>). Calculating by weights that have been excavated and found labeled as “beka” (one-half shekel), the shekel has been estimated to be about .4 ounce (11.4 grams).</p>
<p>The shekel is used in Scripture almost exclusively in contexts dealing with monetary value. Whether silver, gold, barley, or flour, the shekel valuation assigns the commodity a relative value in the economy. Exceptions to this are Goliath’s armor and spear (<a href="?bref=1Sam.17.5-7">1 Sm 17:5-7</a>), which are described in terms of their shekel weight.</p>
<p class="h3">Pim</p>
<p class="fl">The only reference to this unit is in <a href="?bref=1Sam.13.21">1 Samuel 13:21</a>, where it is the price charged to the Israelites by the Philistines for sharpening a plowshare. Excavated weights range from .25 to .3 ounce (7.1 to 8.5 grams), suggesting that the pim was two-thirds of a shekel.</p>
<p class="h3">Beka</p>
<p class="fl">Seven stones inscribed with this label range in weight from .2 to .23 ounce (5.7 to 6.5 grams). In <a href="?bref=Exod.38.26">Exodus 38:26</a> it is the amount levied on each individual for the census tax. There it is the equivalent of one-half shekel.</p>
<p class="h3">Gerah</p>
<p class="fl">Equal to one-twentieth of a shekel, or .02 ounce (.6 gram). The term is used five times (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.13">Ex 30:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.27.25">Lv 27:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.3.47">Nm 3:47</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.18.16">18:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.12">Ez 45:12</a>) and on each occasion is used to give a valuation to the shekel. Its use is strictly monetary in these contexts.</p>
<p class="h3">Litra</p>
<p class="fl">The NT uses the same weights that have already been identified in the OT usage, particularly the shekel, mina, and talent. There is one additional unit used: the litra, which is used in <a href="?bref=John.12.3">John 12:3</a> and <a href="?bref=John.19.39">19:39</a> with regard to spices. In Greek literature one litra is approximately 12 ounces (327 grams).</p>
<p class="h2" id="LinearMeasuresintheOldTestament">Linear Measures in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Measurements of length and depth generally were derived from a part of the body used to make the measurement. The basic unit was the cubit, and most others were related to it. Precise measurements of geographic distance are lacking in the OT and was most frequently stated in terms of the number of days it would take to arrive at a destination. A single day’s journey was mostly likely 20 to 25 miles (32.2 to 40.2 kilometers). A “pace” was equal to a “step”—about a yard (<a href="?bref=2Sam.6.13">2 Sm 6:13</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Cubit</p>
<p class="fl">The length from the tip of the forefinger to the elbow. There are both long and short cubits, which are used not only in Israel but in Mesopotamia and Egypt as well. <a href="?bref=Ezek.40.5">Ezekiel 40:5</a> identifies the long cubit as being the equivalent of a cubit plus a handbreadth (about 20 to 21 inches, or 50.8 to 53.3 centimeters). The inscription found inside the Siloam tunnel built by Hezekiah (715–686 <span class="era">BC</span>) indicates that the tunnel is 1,200 cubits long. The actual length of the tunnel was determined to be 1,749 feet (533.1 meters). This would yield a cubit of 17.49 inches (44.4 centimeters). All things considered, 17.5 inches (44.5 centimeters) is a good estimation of the length of the cubit in Israel. This would set the long cubit at approximately 20.5 inches (52.1 centimeters). The cubit was most frequently used to give the dimensions of buildings or objects (e.g., curtains, pillars, pieces of furniture, etc.). The largest structure measured in cubits was the ark that Noah built, which was 300 cubits long (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.15">Gn 6:15</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Span</p>
<p class="fl">The distance measured by the stretch of the hand from fingertip to fingertip, equal to one-half a cubit, or eight and three-quarters inches (22.2 centimeters). It is used only seven times in the OT, and four of those are to describe the dimensions of the high priest’s breastplate (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.15-16">Ex 28:15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.39.8-9">39:8-9</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Handbreadth</p>
<p class="fl">The width of the hand at the base, equal to one-sixth of a cubit, one-third of a span, or just under three inches (7.6 centimeters). The term is used only five times and gives the width of the rim around the table of showbread (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.25">Ex 25:25</a>) and Solomon’s molten sea (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.26">1 Kgs 7:26</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="LinearMeasuresintheNewTestament">Linear Measures in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the NT some of the units of length and depth represent Greco-Roman standards, while others are those used in the OT. Like the OT, the NT frequently uses imprecise designations for distance, such as a stone’s throw or a day’s journey. There are, however, a few occurrences of precise terms borrowed from Roman culture.</p>
<p class="h3">Cubit</p>
<p class="fl">For the Romans, the cubit was set at one and a half times their standard foot of 11.66 inches, equaling 17.5 inches (44.5 centimeters), just as the OT cubit.</p>
<p class="h3">Fathom</p>
<p class="fl">The distance between the fingertips of the left and right hand when the arms were outstretched. It is used only in <a href="?bref=Acts.27.28">Acts 27:28</a> and is considered to be about six feet (1.8 meters).</p>
<p class="h3">Furlong/Stadium</p>
<p class="fl">The length of the ancient Greek racecourse, equal to one-eighth of a Roman mile, or a little over 200 yards (182.9 meters). It is usually used to give approximate distance, but in <a href="?bref=Rev.21.16">Revelation 21:16</a> it is used to give the dimensions of the New Jerusalem and is measured with a measuring rod.</p>
<p class="h3">Mile</p>
<p class="fl">The only occurrence of this term, <a href="?bref=Matt.5.41">Matthew 5:41</a>, has reference to the Roman mile of 1,620 yards, about nine-tenths of a modern mile (1.4 kilometers).</p>
<p class="h2" id="CapacityDryMeasureintheOldTestament">Capacity (Dry Measure) in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Amounts of dry goods were oriented toward practical matters such as typical donkey loads, how much seed could be sown in a day, or how much seed would be needed to sow a certain size plot. As with the other types of measures, these then became standardized.</p>
<p class="h3">Cor/Homer</p>
<p class="fl">The most common dry commodity measure and the equivalent of one donkey load. Estimates of its standard size vary greatly, ranging from 3.8 bushels to 7.5 bushels (133.9 to 264.3 liters). Other than the seven occurrences in <a href="?bref=Ezek.45.11-14">Ezekiel 45:11-14</a>, the term occurs only four times in the OT. Three of these contexts feature seed or barley (<a href="?bref=Lev.27.16">Lv 27:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.10">Is 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.3.2">Hos 3:2</a>), while the fourth is in the context of Israelites gathering quail in the wilderness. A cor is used nine times and occurs with a variety of commodities, including oil, flour, wheat, and barley, in multiples all the way up to 20,000 (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.5.11">1 Kgs 5:11</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Lethek</p>
<p class="fl">Unit occurring only in <a href="?bref=Hos.3.2">Hosea 3:2</a>. The early versions of the Bible identified it as one-half of a cor, or homer.</p>
<p class="h3">Ephah</p>
<p class="fl">This is equal to one-tenth of a homer (<a href="?bref=Ezek.45.11">Ez 45:11</a>), or one-half of a bushel (17.6 liters). The term occurs dozens of times with all sorts of agricultural products. It seems to have been the unit most used in trading and selling. According to <a href="?bref=Zech.5.6-10">Zechariah 5:6-10</a>, the ephah refers to a container that would hold an ephah of produce, much like the modern-day bushel basket.</p>
<p class="h3">Seah</p>
<p class="fl">A fraction of the homer, which has a very wide range. The term measures flour, seed, barley, and grain, and is roughly one-third of an ephah. A bushel was about five seahs (<a href="?bref=1Sam.25.18">1 Sm 25:18</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg).</p>
<p class="h3">Omer/Issaron</p>
<p class="fl">The omer occurs only in the account of the collecting of manna by the Israelites (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.22">Ex 16:22</a>). It represents a day’s ration of manna and is identified as one-tenth of an ephah (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.36">Ex 16:36</a>). The issaron is a term that means a tenth. Its 25 occurrences are all in Exodus, Leviticus, and Numbers (mostly in <a href="?bref=Num.28.1-29.40">Nm 28–29</a>); it refers only to measures of fine flour.</p>
<p class="h3">Cab, Kab</p>
<p class="fl">This unit occurs only in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.25">2 Kings 6:25</a>. The estimate given by Josephus, one-eighteenth of an ephah (or about one-half of an omer), is usually accepted.</p>
<p class="h2" id="CapacityDryMeasureintheNewTestament">Capacity (Dry Measure) in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The following dry measures are used in the NT.</p>
<p class="h3">Choinix</p>
<p class="fl">Occurring only in <a href="?bref=Rev.6.6">Revelation 6:6</a> (see <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg), the choinix is a little more than a quart (1.1 liters). In Greek literature it was considered the amount of one man’s daily allowance of corn.</p>
<p class="h3">Modius</p>
<p class="fl">This is the “bushel” under which one’s lamp should not be hid (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.15">Mt 5:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.21">Mk 4:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.33">Lk 11:33</a>). It is actually equal to about a peck, 7.68 dry quarts (8.5 liters).</p>
<p class="h3">Saton</p>
<p class="fl">This is the equivalent of the OT seah and can therefore also be approximated at about a peck. It is used only twice in the NT in parallel passages of the parable of the leaven, which is like the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.33">Mt 13:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.21">Lk 13:21</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="LiquidMeasuresintheOldTestament">Liquid Measures in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Three basic measures were used for liquids in the OT.</p>
<p class="h3">Bath</p>
<p class="fl">The base unit for the measurement of liquids. The biblical data (<a href="?bref=Ezek.45.11-14">Ez 45:11-14</a>) sets it as the liquid equivalent to the dry measure, the ephah. It is one-tenth of a homer. Archaeology has also been able to provide some data for this determination. Jars inscribed as “bath of the king” were found at Lachish and Tell en-Nasbeh, and jars marked “bath” were found at Tell Beit Mirsim. The jars are not complete, so their capacity must be calculated based on a reconstruction. Using this data, the bath was approximately 5.5 gallons (20.8 liters). This estimate would provide acceptable results when factored into the information given in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.23-26">1 Kings 7:23-26</a>, where the “molten sea” of Solomon’s temple is described as being 30 cubits in circumference, 10 cubits in diameter, 5 cubits deep, and capable of holding 2,000 baths of water.</p>
<p class="h3">Hin</p>
<p class="fl">One-sixth of a hin of water was considered a person’s minimum daily requirement (<a href="?bref=Ezek.4.11">Ez 4:11</a>). A hin is equal to one-sixth of a bath, approximately one gallon (3.8 liters). It is used for a measure of oil, wine, and water, but no context ever mentions more than one hin. Rather, fractions of a hin are used. Occurrences are limited to Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Ezekiel and are therefore most commonly attested in the context of sacrificial libations.</p>
<p class="h3">Log</p>
<p class="fl">This unit occurs only in <a href="?bref=Lev.14.10-24">Leviticus 14:10-24</a> and equals one-twelfth of a hin, so about .3 quart or .3 liter.</p>
<p class="h2" id="LiquidMeasuresintheNewTestament">Liquid Measures in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The following liquid measures occur in the NT.</p>
<p class="h3">Bath</p>
<p class="fl">This is used only once (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.6">Lk 16:6</a>) and is the same as the OT bath.</p>
<p class="h3">Metretes</p>
<p class="fl">This is used only in <a href="?bref=John.2.6">John 2:6</a>, where it describes the containers in which water was turned to wine. Josephus identifies it as equivalent to a Hebrew bath, but in Greek usage it was the equivalent of about ten gallons (37.9 liters).</p>
<p class="h3">Sextarius/Xestes</p>
<p class="fl">A measure of capacity equal to about one and one-sixth pints (552 milliliters). In <a href="?bref=Mark.7.4">Mark 7:4</a> the word is translated “pitcher” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>) or “pot” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>, see mg).</p>
  </body>
</item>