<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Well">
  <title>Well</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WELL</p>
<p class="fl">Man-made reservoir fed either by subterranean springs or by rainwater. Because the majority of the biblical world ranges from arid to semiarid, wells were a critical source of water for humans, livestock, and the irrigation of crops. Unfortunately, most wells did not offer a reliable source of water, being dependent on the scarce rainfall or intermittent springs (<a href="?bref=Pr.25.26">Prv 25:26</a>). The discovery of a reliable source of water was therefore the cause of much rejoicing (<a href="?bref=Num.21.17-18">Nm 21:17-18</a>) and frequent conflict (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.25-30">Gn 21:25-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.26.19-22">26:19-22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.19">2 Kgs 3:19</a>). Successfully digging a well and defending one’s water rights often served as an important determinant of property rights (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.25-30">Gn 21:25-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.29.2-3">29:2-3</a>).</p>
<p>Good wells were generally considered signs of God’s providence (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.14">Gn 16:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.21.19">21:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.21.16-18">Nm 21:16-18</a>). Biblical writers therefore compared the water of spring-fed wells to God’s provision of salvation for his people (<a href="?bref=Isa.12.3">Is 12:3</a>; <a href="?bref=John.4.14">Jn 4:14</a>). The distinction between the relatively poor quality of water in cisterns that captured rainwater and the high quality of those wells that tapped springs of “living” (i.e., flowing) water helps clarify the dialogue between Jesus and the Samaritan woman when Jesus offered her “living water” (<a href="?bref=John.4.10-15">Jn 4:10-15</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Cistern_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cistern</a>; <a href="?item=JacobsWell_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jacob’s Well</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>