<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wilderness">
  <title>Wilderness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WILDERNESS</p>
<p class="fl">Land that is basically wild and sparsely inhabited or unfit for permanent human settlement. It may be desert, mountains, forest, or marsh.</p>
<p>In the Near East the wilderness is characteristically dry, desolate, and mostly rock and sand. It is rough, uneven, and interlaced with dry watercourses. The wilderness is not completely barren but provides seasonal pasture for flocks, depending on the rainfall.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Joel.2.22">Joel 2:22</a> declares that “the pastures of the wilderness are green,” and <a href="?bref=Ps.65.12">Psalm 65:12</a> states that the pastures of the wilderness drip with richness. But Jeremiah says that “the pastures of the wilderness are dried up” (<a href="?bref=Jer.23.10">Jer 23:10</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Joel.1.20">Jl 1:20</a>). And Job refers to the wilderness as a land where no human can live (<a href="?bref=Job.38.26">Jb 38:26</a>); it is a place for various animals and birds, such as wild asses, jackals, vultures, and owls (<a href="?bref=Ps.102.6">Ps 102:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.24">Jer 2:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.13.22">Is 13:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.13-15">34:13-15</a>).</p>
<p>Certain wilderness tracts are identified by name and are related to definite cities, persons, or events. Hagar wandered in the wilderness of Beersheba (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.14">Gn 21:14</a>). In the exodus from Egypt, the Israelites traversed the following wildernesses: Shur (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.22">Ex 15:22</a>), Etham (<a href="?bref=Num.33.8">Nm 33:8</a>), Sin (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.1">Ex 16:1</a>), Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.1-2">19:1-2</a>), Zin (<a href="?bref=Num.13.21">Nm 13:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.20.1">20:1</a>), Paran (<a href="?bref=Num.13.26">13:26</a>), Kadesh (<a href="?bref=Ps.29.8">Ps 29:8</a>), Moab (<a href="?bref=Deut.2.8">Dt 2:8</a>), and Kedemoth (v <a href="?bref=Deut.2.26">26</a>). When David was fleeing from Saul, David hid in the hill country of the wilderness of Ziph (<a href="?bref=1Sam.23.14-15">1 Sm 23:14-15</a>), in the wilderness of Maon (vv <a href="?bref=1Sam.23.24-25">24-25</a>), and in the wilderness of En-gedi (<a href="?bref=1Sam.24.1">24:1</a>).</p>
<p>In spite of the comparative desolation of the wilderness, villages or towns are sometimes associated with a wilderness setting. <a href="?bref=Josh.15.61-62">Joshua 15:61-62</a> lists the names of six cities and their villages “in the wilderness.” The future joy of the towns of the desert is proclaimed by Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Isa.42.11">Is 42:11</a>).</p>
<p>The wilderness is associated with both austerity and temptation. Elijah, by his way of life and his dress, is often thought of in connection with the wilderness. His successor, Elisha, had occasion to minister in the wilderness of Edom (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.3.4-27">2 Kgs 3:4-27</a>).</p>
<p>Isaiah prophesied of the message of John the Baptist, who preached in the wilderness of Judea (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.3">Is 40:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.3.1-3">Mt 3:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.2-4">Mk 1:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.1-6">Lk 3:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.23">Jn 1:23</a>). Jesus, full of the Holy Spirit, was led by the Spirit into the wilderness for 40 days. There he was tempted by the devil (cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.4.1-2">Lk 4:1-2</a>), but there also angels ministered to him (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.13">Mk 1:13</a>). The anchorites (hermits) of Egypt and the Qumran community near the Dead Sea used the wilderness as an escape from the evils of urban life. Jesus, however, used the wilderness as a place of prayer and communion with the Father (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.16">Lk 5:16</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Desert_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Desert</a>; <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>