<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Wine">
  <title>Wine</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WINE</p>
<p class="fl">Beverage made from fermented grape juice.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Origin">Origin</p>
<p class="fl">Noah was among the first to produce wine (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.21">Gn 9:21</a>), presumably on the slopes of Mt Ararat. But wine making was not confined to that region, because Egypt, and later Greece, had a fondness for the juice. In fact, wine making was known to have existed in the prehistoric period of Mesopotamia and was brought to Egypt before 3000 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The word “wine” may be identified with words for vine, vineyard, and black grapes. The vine, which brings forth the wine, was often identified in the Near Eastern world with the “tree of life.” In both Egypt and Mesopotamia a goddess was thought to protect the vine. The “mistress of the heavenly tree of life,” the goddess Siris, lived in the mountains of northwestern Assyria. First Enoch 32:4 calls the vine the tree of knowledge. According to Jewish tradition, the vine was saved from the Flood by Noah.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ProductionofWine">Production of Wine</p>
<p class="fl">Few ancient documents are extant on the art of wine making. Experience and the interests of a few early botanists appear to be the only source of knowledge available about the early vine growers. Aristotle’s gifted student Theophrastus of Eresos wrote a book entitled <span class="ital">Enquiry into Plants</span> showing a blend of practical experience and theory. Later, he followed with <span class="ital">On the Life of Plants,</span> a work giving detailed observations about wine making. His ideas on when to plant, how to prune, statements against grafting, and how to care for the vine demonstrate the Greek genius. They raised viticulture to a science that has changed little in the last 2200 years.</p>
<p>Great care was taken by Greek vine growers to ensure the success of their crops. The vines were close to the ground instead of being propped. In view of this, mice and foxes were especially undesirable, and much hoeing was needed to keep the soil free of weeds. But their method, overall, was very effective.</p>
<p>In early September the grapes were collected in the plains, and at the end of the month in the hills. With an initial festival of song and dance, the workers brought the bunches of grapes to the winepresses, low cement vats inclined toward one corner. After this, workers trod the grapes. The first <span class="ital">must</span> (juice from the crushing) was highly valued because it provided the choicest wines. The remaining juice was extracted by wringing the trodden grapes in a bag press usually made of cloth. A third class of wine was produced by mixing or even cooking the remaining grapes with some water and expressing the mixture. This type of wine was drunk only by the poor.</p>
<p>At a later time the Greeks invented a beam press in which a long beam, having a turning portion at one end and heavy stones on the other, compressed layers of grapes. The ancient Near East had these different methods of extracting wine, but the treading of grapes, even in Greece, was always the favorite method.</p>
<p>In Greece the fermentation period was usually six months, during which the liquid was constantly skimmed. However, in the ancient Near East the fermentation process was usually over in three or four days, the optimum growth temperature being 77 degrees. The ancients knew that any further fermentation would produce acid.</p>
<p>After desired fermentation, the wine was transferred to skins or pottery jars for transport or sale. The handles and stoppers were stamped to indicate the brand, the origin, and the vintage. At this time the wine was strained through perforated metal sieves or cloth to eliminate contaminates such as grit or insects.</p>
<p class="h2" id="KindsofWine">Kinds of Wine</p>
<p class="fl">Ancient poets discuss many different brands of wine, with Athenaeus mentioning 85 different varieties. Galen cites 60; Pliny mentions 150; and Strabo, 30. Wines are distinguished by different colors (black, red, white, or yellow) and by their taste (dry, harsh, light, or sweet). The biblical account enumerates various kinds of wine, such as the wines of Lebanon and Helbon. Hebron and Samaria were famous for their wine making. The Hebrew language has at least nine different words for wine, and the Greek has four that are mentioned in the NT.</p>
<p class="h2" id="NatureofWine">Nature of Wine</p>
<p class="fl">Few would question that at least some wine of the OT was fermented. Some scholars argue, however, that certain forms of wine in the ancient world were unfermented. They contrast two Hebrew words for wine, concluding that one particular Hebrew word that refers to fresh wine meant only grape juice (<a href="?bref=Pr.3.10">Prv 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.9.2">Hos 9:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.24">Jl 2:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.15">Mi 6:15</a>). The inconclusiveness of these arguments may be seen from the following points: (1) the Hebrew word is found in primarily neutral contexts; (2) often that particular word is found in contexts definitely including a fermented beverage (e.g., <a href="?bref=Gen.27.28">Gn 27:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.4.11">Hos 4:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.15">Mi 6:15</a>); (3) the Ugaritic parallel to the term in question refers with certainty to a fermented wine; (4) the Septuagint equivalents refer to fermented wine; (5) fermentation in the ancient Near East, unlike Greece, took only about three days; and (6) the Mishnah provides no such evidence of the practice of having unfermented wine. There seems to have been no attempts to preserve wine in an unfermented state; it may have been a near-impossible task. A careful examination of all the Hebrew words (as well as their Semitic cognates) and the Greek words for wine demonstrates that the ancients knew little, if anything, about unfermented wine.</p>
<p>Ample evidence is available to demonstrate that wine, though always fermented, was usually mixed with water in the classical and Hellenistic world. The wine was stored in large jugs called <span class="greek">amphorae</span><span class="ital">,</span> from which the wine was poured through a strainer into a large mixing bowl called a <span class="greek">krater</span><span class="ital">.</span> In the krater the wine was mixed with water. Then the drinking bowls or cups were filled.</p>
<p>The amount of wine per volume varied. The mixture that represented the greatest amount of water to wine was 20 to 1, apparently because the wine was so strong (Homer, <span class="ital">Odyssey</span> 10.208).</p>
<p>In the western Mediterranean world, the term “wine” referred to the mixture of wine and water. If one desired to mention wine without water, it was necessary to add the word “unmixed.” For the Greeks, to drink wine unmixed was regarded as barbaric. The evidence, however, seems to indicate that in the OT era wine was used without being mixed with water. The terminology of mixing water and wine is strikingly unattested. Wine diluted with water was symbolic of spiritual adulteration (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.22">Is 1:22</a>). By Roman times, this attitude had changed. The Mishnah assumes a ratio of two parts of water to one part wine; however, later Talmudic sources speak of three to one. A natural, nondistilled wine could reach as high as 15 percent alcohol content. If watered down three parts water to one part wine, the alcohol content would be 5 percent and still fairly potent.</p>
<p>Wine was mixed not only with water but also with other ingredients, similar to mixed drinks today. An example of this is seen in the Homeric “Hymn to Demeter,” where the goddess rejects straight wine and desires the drink mixed with meal, water, and a soft mint. Often strong wine was mixed into weak wine, resulting in a stronger drink. This is what is meant by “mixture” in the Bible (<a href="?bref=Ps.75.8">Ps 75:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.22">Is 5:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.18.6">Rv 18:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.13-15">19:13-15</a>). At times the fresh wine, high in sugar content, was evaporated, and this concentrated <span class="ital">must</span> was mixed with wine to obtain a higher alcohol content.</p>
<p>There is no mention of wine being mixed with water to make it safe for drinking, as is commonly accepted. Modern examples of pollution were not common in the ancient world, although this problem appeared occasionally. Examples are myriad concerning the fresh wells, springs, and moving bodies of water in biblical times, and methods were available to purify any impure water.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WineintheOldTestament">Wine in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The evidence, as seen above, suggests that wine in the OT was not mixed with water and was looked on with favor when taken in moderation. <a href="?bref=Judg.9.13">Judges 9:13</a> presents wine as that “which cheers God and men.” <a href="?bref=Ps.104.15">Psalm 104:15</a> portrays wine similarly: “wine which makes man’s heart glad” (cf. also <a href="?bref=Esth.1.10">Est 1:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.10.19">Eccl 10:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.55.1-2">Is 55:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.10.7">Zec 10:7</a>). The temperate use of wine was a normal and accepted part of life (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.18">Gn 14:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.19.19">Jgs 19:19</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.16.20">1 Sm 16:20</a>). Levitical priests in service at the temple (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.8-9">Lv 10:8-9</a>), Nazirites (<a href="?bref=Num.6.3">Nm 6:3</a>), and the Recabites (<a href="?bref=Jer.35.1-6">Jer 35:1-6</a>) were forbidden to drink wine.</p>
<p>Wine had many uses in the OT world. The “drink offering” was wine (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.40">Ex 29:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.23.13">Lv 23:13</a>), and the worshiper regularly brought wine when offering sacrifice (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.24">1 Sm 1:24</a>). In addition, a supply of wine was kept in the temple for sacrificial purposes (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.29">1 Chr 9:29</a>). At times, wine was used in helping the weak and sick (<a href="?bref=2Sam.16.2">2 Sm 16:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.31.6">Prv 31:6</a>).</p>
<p>The strong drink of the OT seems to be closely related to Mesopotamian date wine. This same date wine, high in sugar content, must have also been high in alcohol content. One Hebrew word is consistently used as strong drink (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.9">Lv 10:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.29.6">Dt 29:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.15">1 Sm 1:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.1">Prv 20:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.31.6">31:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.29.9">Is 29:9</a>). There is an equivalent word to this in Ugaritic, translated “drunk,” which parallels the normal word for wine.</p>
<p>Negative reactions to intemperate wine drinking abound in the OT. Isaiah condemned those who drank wine to excess (<a href="?bref=Isa.28.1-8">Is 28:1-8</a>). Many admonitions of drinking wine in excess are given in the Scriptures (<a href="?bref=Pr.20.1">Prv 20:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.21.17">21:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.23.20-21">23:20-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.23.32-34">23:32-34</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="WineintheNewTestament">Wine in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Wine in the NT was a fermented beverage that was mixed with various amounts of water. It was also mixed with gall (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.34">Mt 27:34</a>) and myrrh (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.23">Mk 15:23</a>). Evidence strongly suggests that the wine used at the Lord’s Supper was a mixture of water and wine, probably three to one in agreement with the dictates of the Mishnah. The phrase “fruit of the vine” (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.27-29">Mt 26:27-29</a>) is often interpreted to mean fresh grape juice. However, fresh grape juice would be all but impossible to find.</p>
<p>The NT, as the OT, argues forcefully against the unrestrained use of wine. The biblical admonition is not to be drunk with wine (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.18">Eph 5:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.4.3">1 Pt 4:3</a>). Leaders in the church were to practice moderation in the use of wine (<a href="?bref=1Tim.3.3,8">1 Tm 3:3, 8</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.7">Ti 1:7</a>); the Greek says that they should “not be addicted to wine.”</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=VinesVineyard_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Vines, Vineyard</a>; <a href="?item=Winepress_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Winepress</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>