<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WisdomofSolomon">
  <title>Wisdom of Solomon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WISDOM OF SOLOMON</p>
<p class="fl">Deuterocanonical work containing a treasury of wisdom. A theological and/or philosophical treatise, the Wisdom of Solomon seeks to blend the piety of orthodox Judaism with the best of Greek philosophy.</p>
<p>The book tries to give the impression that the whole is the work of Solomon (see <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.8.9-21">Wisd of Sol 8:9-21</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.9.7-2">9:7-2</a>), but this is simply a device to gain authority for the statements of the book concerning wisdom. Originally composed in Greek rather than in Hebrew, it is likely the production of a cultivated Jew deeply influenced by Greek culture and ideas, familiar with the Septuagint, and writing at Alexandria probably in the first century <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The book was regarded as canonical by some of the early church fathers, including such notable figures as Origen, Eusebius of Caesarea, and Augustine of Hippo; it was even incorporated into the Muratorian Canon of the second century. Historically, it has been favorably regarded by Protestants, although not considered canonical. The Roman Catholic Church gave it official recognition as Scripture at the Council of Trent in <span class="era">AD</span> 1546.</p>
<p>The author sought to rekindle the religious zeal of his fellow Jews who have departed from the faith of their fathers, to encourage and fortify them for a life of faith and godliness in the midst of perplexities and persecutions and to demonstrate the folly of idolatry and the truth of Judaism. The book begins with the author being exhorted to “love righteousness, . . . think of the Lord with uprightness, and seek him with sincerity of heart” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.1.1">1:1</a>). From there on in, the book encourages people to become religious and to know God. By knowing God and conforming to his will, a person can attain immortality (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.15.3">15:3</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>