<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Witness">
  <title>Witness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WITNESS</p>
<p class="fl">One who tells what he or she has seen or personally experienced, often in a court of law. The term may also refer to the testimony the person has given.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WitnessintheOldTestament">Witness in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the judicial procedure outlined in the OT, one witness was not adequate for personal testimony against anyone, but two or three witnesses were required (<a href="?bref=Deut.17.6">Dt 17:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.19.15">19:15</a>). This principle was incorporated into Jewish law and is reiterated in the NT (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.18.16">Mt 18:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.13.1">2 Cor 13:1</a>).</p>
<p>The truth of testimony is so important that the Bible expressly forbids false witness in the ninth commandment (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.16">Ex 20:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.20">Dt 5:20</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.10.19">Mk 10:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.18.20">Lk 18:20</a>). The practical wisdom of Proverbs speaks out frequently against the false witness (e.g., <a href="?bref=Pr.6.19">Prv 6:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.14.5">14:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.25.18">25:18</a>). Nevertheless, false witnesses did arise (<a href="?bref=Ps.27.12">Pss 27:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.35.11">35:11</a>), and there are notable examples of the bringing of more than one witness in order to bring about the death of an innocent person. The case of Naboth and his vineyard is notorious; here Jezebel, wife of King Ahab, bribed two men to bear false witness against Naboth so that he would be stoned to death and her wicked husband could take the vineyard he coveted so intensely (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.1-29">1 Kgs 21</a>).</p>
<p>Witnesses could be tested by the judges. If the testimony of an accuser was found to be false, that person was subjected to the punishment he had sought to have executed on the defendant (<a href="?bref=Deut.19.16-21">Dt 19:16-21</a>). Proverbs also speaks of the punishment of the false witness (<a href="?bref=Pr.19.5,9">Prv 19:5, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.21.28">21:28</a>).</p>
<p>The OT records several accounts of legal proceedings in which witnesses are mentioned. Most of these involve the purchase or transfer of property. <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.7-12">Ruth 4:7-12</a> relates the redemption of a field from Naomi by Boaz. Isaiah found “reliable witnesses” concerning a property title written on a large tablet (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.1-2">Is 8:1-2</a>). To confirm the prophecy of the return of the exiles from Babylon, Jeremiah bought and paid for a field in the presence of witnesses, who also signed the deed for the property (<a href="?bref=Jer.32.6-15">Jer 32:6-15</a>).</p>
<p>At the conclusion of his farewell message at Shechem, Joshua declared that the Israelites themselves were witnesses that they had chosen to serve the Lord; then he set up a large stone and declared that it also was a witness (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.22-27">Jos 24:22-27</a>). The people of Israel themselves were declared God’s witnesses (<a href="?bref=Isa.43.10">Is 43:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.44.8-9">44:8-9</a>). They were witnesses to the existence of God, to his uniqueness, holiness, power, and love. When they failed to acknowledge his uniqueness and holiness and turned to idolatry, he sent them into captivity, as he had warned, for they had failed in their witness and had given opportunity for the enemies of God to blaspheme.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WitnessintheNewTestament">Witness in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">In the NT the various words for witness are mainly related to the verb <span class="greek">martureo</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “to bear witness, be a witness.” The word “martyr” shows the ultimate form of witness in that Christians have sacrificed their lives because of their witness for Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>John the Baptist was both a witness and a martyr. As the forerunner of the Messiah, his mission was to bear witness to the light and to identify the Lamb of God (<a href="?bref=John.1.7-8,19-36">Jn 1:7-8, 19-36</a>). The followers of Jesus, and particularly the 12 apostles, were witnesses to the person and character of Jesus. They knew him intimately, heard his teachings and observed his miracles; three were witnesses of his transfiguration (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.1-2">Mt 17:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.1.17-18">2 Pt 1:17-18</a>) and many were witnesses to his resurrection (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.48">Lk 24:48</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.4-8">1 Cor 15:4-8</a>). At the time of his ascension, the disciples were specifically commissioned to be his witnesses (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.8">Acts 1:8</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>