<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="WordWordofGodWordsofGod">
  <title>Word, Word of God, Words of God</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WORD, WORD OF GOD, WORDS OF GOD</p>
<p class="fl">A “word” is an expression that communicates. On the level of human communication, “words “usually refer to verbal expression. When God “spoke” over the centuries, though, he communicated in various ways (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.1">Heb 1:1</a>), culminating in that epitome of all divine expression, Jesus Christ, his Son.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheImportanceofWords">The Importance of Words</p>
<p class="fl">In a mainly nonliterary society the dependability of the spoken word was all-important in law, trade, religion, marriage, and reputation. Receipts, agreements, and records had little usefulness. Personal integrity and sincere speech were essential to communication and, for most people, to self-expression and stable relationships. The words of poets, prophets, storytellers, and instructors were carefully preserved.</p>
<p>Words were diligently tested. Foolish words, flattery, deceit, words of enticement, lies, rumor, scandal, and blasphemous speech were all recognized as evil. The oath had to be inviolable in commercial, judicial, and civic affairs. The spoken blessing had power within itself and could not be withdrawn (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.30-38">Gn 27:30-38</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.10.12-13">Mt 10:12-13</a>); so also the vow (<a href="?bref=Judg.11.34-35">Jgs 11:34-35</a>) and the curse (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.12-13">Gn 27:12-13</a>). Equally powerful was the word of command—of priestly, judicial, or royal authority (<a href="?bref=Eccl.8.4">Eccl 8:4</a>).</p>
<p>This estimate of human words lingers in the NT. The word reveals the inner self, and so every careless, hurtful, deceitful word will be judged (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.34-37">Mt 12:34-37</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.5.22">5:22</a>), as will blasphemy (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.10">Lk 12:10</a>). Paul (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.29">Eph 4:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.5.4">5:4</a>) and James (<a href="?bref=Jas.3.1-12">Jas 3:1-12</a>) preserve this Hebrew reverence for the spoken word.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheWordsofGod">The Words of God</p>
<p class="fl">God’s spoken word has been preserved in Scripture. His word came to and through the prophets (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.22">1 Kgs 12:22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.17.3">1 Chr 17:3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.3.2">Lk 3:2</a>), who spoke and acted “by the word of the Lord.” His word also came in the law, which God “spoke” on Sinai (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.1">Ex 20:1</a>); hence, “statutes,” “commandments,” and “precepts” are synonyms for God’s “word” (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.119.1-176">Ps 119</a>).</p>
<p>Periods when no such divine communication came constituted “famine” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.3.1">1 Sm 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.11">Am 8:11</a>). Mingled with warnings and injunctions were divine promises. All God’s words were dependable (<a href="?bref=Isa.31.2">Is 31:2</a>), firmly fixed in heaven (<a href="?bref=Ps.119.89">Ps 119:89</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.8">Is 40:8</a>), and backed up by divine oath (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.12">Jer 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.110.4">Ps 110:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.12.25,28">Ez 12:25, 28</a>). A word, expressing the divine mind, was not threatening or burdensome; it was a delight, hope, joy, and protection against sin (<a href="?bref=Ps.1.1-6">Pss 1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.119.1-176">119</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.15.16">Jer 15:16</a>). Men can live by it (<a href="?bref=Deut.8.3">Dt 8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.4.4">Mt 4:4</a>).</p>
<p>God’s word has power to execute his will. It will not return to him “empty” but accomplish that which he purposes (<a href="?bref=Isa.55.11">Is 55:11</a>). By his speech alone, God created the world, and his word upholds it (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Gn 1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.33.6">Ps 33:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.1.2">Heb 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.11.3">11:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.3.5">2 Pt 3:5</a>). Eventually, this divine revelation was put into writing, which makes the Bible also “the word of God” (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.13">Mk 7:13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.16.29-31">Lk 16:29-31</a>; <a href="?bref=John.5.39">Jn 5:39</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus spoke the word of God. He was “mighty in word” (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.19">Lk 24:19</a>); he taught with authority (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.22,27">Mk 1:22, 27</a>), exercising power over the sea, disease, demons, and death (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.8,13">Mt 8:8, 13</a>). His “word of the kingdom” is the living seed, which, planted in the good soil of receptive hearts, bears fruit for God (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.19">Mt 13:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.14">Mk 4:14</a>). The word that Christ gives to his disciples cleanses them and frees them (<a href="?bref=John.8.31">Jn 8:31</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.48">12:48</a>; <a href="?bref=John.15.3">15:3</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.14">17:14</a>). The word of faith the church preaches (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.8-9,17">Rom 10:8-9, 17</a>) is variously described as the word of salvation, the word of grace, the word of reconciliation, the word of the gospel, the word of righteousness, and the word of life.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TheTitleWordInJohn11"/>
<p class="h2" id="TheWordofGod">The Word of God</p>
<p class="fl">Deliberately recalling <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1-31">Genesis 1</a>, the Gospel writer, John, named the Son of God “the Word.” As the Word, the Son of God fully conveys and communicates God. The Greek term is <span class="greek">logos</span><span class="ital">;</span> it was used in two ways by the Greeks. The word might be thought of as remaining within a person, when it denoted his thought or reason. Or it might refer to the word going forth from a person, when it denoted the expression of his thought, i.e., speech. As a philosophical term, the <span class="greek">logos</span> denoted the principle of the universe, even the creative energy that generated the universe. In both the Jewish conception and the Greek, the <span class="greek">logos</span> was associated with the idea of beginnings—the world began through the origination and instrumentality of the Word (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.3-31">Gn 1:3ff</a>., where the expression “God said” is used again and again). John may have had these ideas in mind, but most likely he originated a new term to identify the Son of God as the divine expression in human form (<a href="?bref=John.1.14">Jn 1:14</a>). He is the image of the invisible God (<a href="?bref=Col.1.15">Col 1:15</a>), the express image of God’s substance (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.3">Heb 1:3</a>). In the Godhead, the Son functions as the revealer of God and the reality of God, which is a central theme throughout John’s Gospel. John used a similar title in his first epistle: “the Word of life” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.1.1-3">1 Jn 1:1-3</a>). And in <a href="?bref=Rev.19.11-16">Revelation 19:11-16</a>, Jesus is presented as the King of kings and Lord of lords, who has a name on him: “the Word of God.”</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Bible_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bible</a>; <a href="?item=JohnGospelof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">John, Gospel of</a>; <a href="?item=Logos_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Logos</a>; <a href="?item=Revelation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Revelation</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>