<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Worship">
  <title>Worship</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">WORSHIP</p>
<p class="fl">Expression of reverence and adoration of God.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WorshipintheOldTestament">Worship in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The 1,500 years from the days of Abraham to the time of Ezra (c. 1900–450 <span class="era">BC</span>) saw many significant changes in the form of worship in ancient Israel. Abraham, the wandering nomad, built altars and offered sacrifices wherever God appeared to him. In Moses’ time the tabernacle served as a portable sanctuary for the Israelite tribes journeying through the wilderness. Solomon built a temple in Jerusalem that lasted more than three centuries until its destruction by the Babylonians in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. When the Jews returned from exile, they built a new temple, which was later renovated and enlarged by Herod the Great. Though all the temple buildings were destroyed by the Romans in <span class="era">AD</span> 70, the foundations remained. Jews still pray by the Western Wall (called the Wailing Wall).</p>
<p>If the form of worship changed with times and situations, its heart and center did not. God revealed himself to Abraham, promising that his children would inherit the land of Canaan. Abraham demonstrated his faith through prayer and sacrifice. Throughout the biblical period listening to God’s Word, prayer, and sacrifice constituted the essence of worship. The promises to Abraham were constantly recalled as the basis of Israel’s existence as a nation and its right to the land of Canaan.</p>
<p>From time to time every family visited the temple in Jerusalem. Eight days after a baby boy was born, he was circumcised to mark his membership in Israel. Then, a month or two later, the baby’s mother went to the temple to offer sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Lev.12.1-8">Lv 12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Luke.2.22-24">Lk 2:22-24</a>).</p>
<p>Animals were sacrificed in the lambing and calving season. The first lamb or calf born to every ewe or cow was presented in sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.30">Ex 22:30</a>). Similarly, at the beginning of the harvest season, a basket of the first fruits was offered, and at the end, a tenth of all the harvest, the tithe, was given to the priests as God’s representatives (<a href="?bref=Num.18.21-32">Nm 18:21-32</a>). <a href="?bref=Deut.26.5-15">Deuteronomy 26:5-15</a> gives a typical prayer for use on such occasions.</p>
<p>Sometimes a person would decide to offer a sacrifice for more personal reasons. In a crisis, vows could be made and sealed with a sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Gen.28.18-22">Gn 28:18-22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.10-11">1 Sm 1:10-11</a>). Then when the prayer was answered, a second sacrifice was customarily offered (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.3,14">Gn 35:3, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.24-25">1 Sm 1:24-25</a>). Serious sin or serious sickness were also occasions for sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.1-5.19">Lv 4–5</a>, <a href="?bref=Lev.13.1-15.33">13–15</a>).</p>
<p>The worshiper brought the animal into the temple court. Standing before the priest, he placed one hand on its head, thereby identifying himself with the animal, and confessed his sin or explained the reason for offering the sacrifice. Then the worshiper killed the animal and cut it up for the priest to burn on the great bronze altar. Some sacrifices (burnt offerings) involved the whole animal being burnt on the altar. In others, some of the meat was set aside for the priests, while the rest was shared by the worshiper and his family. But in every case the worshiper killed the animal from his own flock with his own hands. These sacrifices expressed in a vivid and tangible way the cost of sin and the worshiper’s responsibility. As the worshiper killed the animal, he recalled that sin would have caused his own death, had God not provided an escape through animal sacrifice.</p>
<p>Three times a year all adult men went to the temple to celebrate the national festivals (<a href="?bref=Exod.23.17">Ex 23:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.16.16">Dt 16:16</a>): Passover (held in April), the Feast of Weeks (held in May), and the Feast of Booths (in October). When possible, the whole family accompanied the men. But if they lived a long way from Jerusalem, they would go up for only one of the festivals (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.3">1 Sm 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.41">Lk 2:41</a>).</p>
<p>These festivals were tremendous occasions. Hundreds of thousands of people converged on Jerusalem. They would stay with relatives or camp in tents outside the city. The temple courts would be thronged with worshipers. The temple choirs sang psalms appropriate for the festival, while the priests and Levites offered hundreds (at Passover, thousands) of animals in sacrifice. Groups of worshipers carried away with emotion would break forth into dancing. Those of more sober temperament were content to join in the singing or simply pray quietly.</p>
<p>The major festivals were joyful occasions, for they celebrated the deliverance of Israel from Egypt. At Passover each family ate roasted lamb and bitter herbs to reenact the last meal their forefathers ate before leaving Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.1-51">Ex 12</a>). At the Feast of Booths, they built shelters of branches and lived in them for a week, as a reminder that the Israelites camped in tents during the 40 years of wandering in the wilderness (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.39-43">Lv 23:39-43</a>). These great festivals served as reminders of how God had delivered them from slavery in Egypt and had given them the land of Canaan as he had promised to Abraham.</p>
<p>Each of these three festivals lasted a week, but there was one day in the year that was totally different, the Day of Atonement, when everyone fasted and mourned for their sins. On this day the high priest confessed the nation’s sins as he pressed his hand on the head of a goat. Then the goat was led away into the wilderness, symbolizing the removal of sin from the people (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.1-34">Lv 16</a>).</p>
<p>Sometime after the destruction of the first temple, synagogues developed for public worship. The services were more like modern church worship, consisting exclusively of prayer, Bible reading, and preaching. There were no sacrifices made in the synagogues. When the second temple was destroyed in <span class="era">AD</span> 70, synagogues became the only places where Jews could worship in public. Then there were no more sacrifices at all. The NT pictures this as fitting, for Jesus was the true Lamb of God (<a href="?bref=John.1.29">Jn 1:29</a>); because of his death, there is no need for further animal sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.11-12">Heb 10:11-12</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="WorshipintheNewTestament">Worship in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The Jews had become far too dependent on a physical place, the temple, for their worship. When Jesus arrived on the scene, he proclaimed that he himself was the temple of God; in resurrection, he would provide the spiritual dwelling where God the Spirit and people, in spirit, could have spiritual communion (see <a href="?bref=Matt.12.6">Mt 12:6</a>; <a href="?bref=John.2.19-22">Jn 2:19-22</a>). In other words, worship would no longer be in a place but in a person—through Jesus Christ and his Spirit the worshipers could come directly to God (see <a href="?bref=John.14.6">Jn 14:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.10.19-20">Heb 10:19-20</a>).</p>
<p>This shift in worship—from physical to spiritual—is the theme of <a href="?bref=John.4.1-54">John 4</a>, a chapter that recounts Jesus’ visit to the Samaritans. After Jesus’ encounter with the Samaritan woman, she acknowledged that he must be a prophet, and then she launched into a discussion concerning the religious debate between the Jews and the Samaritans over which place of worship was the right one—Jerusalem or Mt Gerizim. The Samaritans had set up a place for worship on Mt Gerizim in accordance with <a href="?bref=Deut.11.26-29">Deuteronomy 11:26-29</a> and <a href="?bref=Deut.27.1-8">27:1-8</a>, while the Jews had followed David and Solomon in making Jerusalem the center of Jewish worship. The Scriptures affirmed Jerusalem as the true center for worship (<a href="?bref=Deut.12.5">Dt 12:5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.6.6">2 Chr 6:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.7.12">7:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.78.67-68">Ps 78:67-68</a>). But Jesus told her that a new age had come in which the issue no longer concerned a physical site. God the Father would no longer be worshiped in either place. A new age had come in which the true worshipers (Jew, Samaritan, or Gentile) must worship the Father in spirit and in truth.</p>
<p>“In spirit” corresponds to Jerusalem, and “in truth” corresponds to the Samaritans’ unknowledgeable ideas of worship, God, etc. Formerly, God was worshiped in Jerusalem, but now the true Jerusalem would be in a person’s spirit. Indeed, the church is called “the habitation of God in spirit” (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.22">Eph 2:22</a>). True worship required a people to contact God, the Spirit, in their spirit, as well as a people who knew the truth. New Testament worship must be in spirit and in truth. Since “God is Spirit,” he must be worshiped in spirit. Human beings possess a human spirit, the nature of which corresponds to God’s nature, which is spirit. Therefore, people can have fellowship with God and worship God in the same sphere that God exists in.</p>
<p>In a sense, <a href="?bref=John.4.1-54">John 4</a> anticipates <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-27">Revelation 21</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.22.1-21">22</a>, where God provides the rivers of the water of life to all the believers and where the Lamb and God are the temple in the New Jerusalem. The believers receive life from God and they worship in God. There is a profound, even mystical connection between drinking of the Spirit and worshiping God in the Spirit (see <a href="?bref=1Cor.12.13">1 Cor 12:13</a>). This is also described in <a href="?bref=Ezek.47.1-23">Ezekiel 47</a>, which pictures the river flowing from God’s temple as a symbol of God’s never-ending supply. In <a href="?bref=John.4.1-54">John 4</a>, Jesus provides the living waters to all who receive the gift of God, and he directs people to a new temple, a spiritual one, where God is worshiped in spirit.</p>
  </body>
</item>