<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DavidCityof">
  <title>David, City of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DAVID, City of</p>
<p class="list">1. In the OT, the city of Jerusalem. “City of David” referred originally to the old Jebusite stronghold captured by King David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.5.6-9">2 Sm 5:6-9</a>). David, Solomon, and many of their descendants who ruled over Judah were buried in the City of David (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.10">1 Kgs 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.43">11:43</a>). Solomon considered it a holy place because of the presence of the ark of the Lord. Therefore, he moved his pagan wife, Pharaoh’s daughter, away from the City of David and built a house for her in another place (<a href="?bref=2Chr.8.11">2 Chr 8:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">After Solomon’s time, the term “city of David” was also used in a larger sense to describe the entire city of Jerusalem, including the newly built temple area. The old section of Jerusalem below the temple site was still specifically designated as the “city of David,” however (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.15">Neh 3:15</a>). David’s tomb was close to the pool of Siloam and to the stairway that descended from the City of David (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.15-16">Neh 3:15-16</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Jerusalem_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jerusalem</a>; <a href="?item=Zion_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Zion</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. In the NT, the town of Bethlehem. Bethlehem was David’s birthplace and home until he went to Saul’s palace as a musician (<a href="?bref=1Sam.16.16-23">1 Sm 16:16-23</a>). When David became Judah’s king, he chose Hebron to be his capital, as the Lord had instructed him (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.1-11">2 Sm 2:1-11</a>). Bethlehem was the birthplace of Jesus, who was a descendant of David (<a href="?bref=Mic.5.2-4">Mi 5:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.11">Lk 2:11</a>).</p>
<p class="sp"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Bethlehem_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bethlehem #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>