<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DeadSea">
  <title>Dead Sea</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DEAD SEA</p>
<p class="fl">A large saltwater lake into which the river Jordan empties. Since the Greek era, Western civilization has referred to this mysterious body of water as the “Dead Sea.” However, the frequent OT term for this sea is the “Salt Sea” (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.3">Gn 14:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.34.3,12">Nm 34:3, 12</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.3.17">Dt 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.3.16">Jos 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.3">12:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.15.2,5">15:2, 5</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.18.19">18:19</a>), the name deriving from that most important and valuable commodity traded in antiquity. It is also designated the Sea of the Arabah (<a href="?bref=Deut.3.17">Dt 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.49">4:49</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.3.16">Jos 3:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.12.3">12:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.25">2 Kgs 14:25</a>) and the Eastern Sea (<a href="?bref=Ezek.47.18">Ez 47:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.20">Jl 2:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.14.8">Zec 14:8</a>). Apocryphal, classical, and Talmudic authors make reference to the Sea of Sodom, Sea of Asphalt, and Sea of Lot. The NT makes no reference at all to the sea.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AerialViewOfTheDeadSea"/>
<p>The sea lies in the great trough of the Jordan Valley, known also as the Rift Valley. This valley forms part of the longest and deepest crack in the earth’s crust, extending from the Taurus Mountains in southern Turkey, through Syria, Lebanon, Palestine, the Gulf of Aqaba, the Red Sea, and East Africa to Mozambique (there called the Great African Rift Valley). The chasm measures between 2 to 15 miles (3.2 to 24.1 kilometers) wide, and in its deepest spot, along the shoreline of the Dead Sea, it plummets to about 1,300 feet (396 meters) below sea level, marking this as the lowest area on the earth not covered by water. The sea itself is oblong in shape, measuring approximately 53 miles (85 kilometers) from the mouth of the Jordan River in the north to the Sebhka region in the south, and some 10 miles (16 kilometers) in width, enclosed on both sides by steep, rocky cliffs. It is divided into two basins by the eight and a half mile (13.7 kilometer) Lisan Peninsula, which juts out from the eastern shore. The northern basin is larger, and at its deepest point (in the northeast sector), has a water depth of about 1,300 feet (396 meters). The southern basin is flatter, and its water depth ranges between 3 and 30 feet (1 and 9 meters).</p>
<p>The forces of nature seem to have conspired against the Dead Sea. Fed by the Jordan River, four or five perennial streams, and numerous wadis (an average daily inflow totaling some 7 million tons, or 6.4 million metric tons), the sea possesses no outlet for this water except evaporation. This condition, coupled with aridity (with an average annual precipitation of from 2 to 5 inches, or 5 to 13 centimeters) and enormous heat (with the mercury sometimes soaring as high as 125 degrees Fahrenheit, or 52 degrees Celsius, in the summer), quite often creates an extremely high rate of evaporation and dense haze virtually impenetrable to human eyesight. Most of the streams that feed the Dead Sea are unusually saline, flowing through nitrous soil and sulphurous springs. At the same time, springs under the waters of the sea pump chemicals (especially bromine, magnesium, and calcium) into the sea. And along its shores are extensive sulphur deposits and petroleum springs. In the southeast corner there is a 300-foot-thick (91.4-meter-thick) rock-salt ridge, which is only the tip of an estimated 4,500-foot (1,371-meter) salt plug stretching some 5 miles (8 kilometers). Finally, the bed of the sea contains salt crystals. All these factors combine to produce a total salinity of approximately 26 percent, compared to the average ocean salinity of 3.5 percent. This makes the Dead Sea the earth’s most saline water body, completely devoid of marine life, with an ever-increasing solidity.</p>
<p>In ancient times the Dead Sea was valued for its salt and bitumen (a commodity prized for waterproofing properties, consisting of petroleum hardened by evaporation and oxidation). During the NT era, the Dead Sea bitumen trade was apparently controlled by the Nabateans, who also exported the product to Egypt for use in embalming. It has been suggested that Cleopatra’s desire to govern the Dead Sea region was stimulated by her desire to regulate the bitumen trade.</p>
<p>The ominous desolation and barrenness of the Dead Sea apparent to the gaze of the modern onlooker is also reflected in the pages of history. The events of <a href="?bref=Gen.19.1-38">Genesis 19</a>, the destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah, transpired in this vicinity. Mt Sedom, the salt plug located at the southeast corner of the sea, obviously reflects the name Sodom. The archaeologist Nelson Glueck affirms that the region surrounding Sedom was occupied by as many as 70 towns dating back to about 3000 <span class="era">BC</span>. The exact nature of the destruction rained upon Sodom and Gomorrah is variously interpreted either as a volcanic eruption or as the spontaneous explosion of subsurface pockets of bituminous soil. Karstic salt pillars, known as “Lot’s wife,” are a frequent phenomenon in this locality.</p>
<p>The howling wilderness that surrounds the sea provided a suitable refuge for the fugitive David (<a href="?bref=1Sam.23.29-24.29">1 Sm 23:29–24:1ff</a>.), the contemplative company of Qumran Essenes, and the disenfranchised Jewish insurgents of the second Jewish rebellion. On the other hand, Ezekiel envisioned (<a href="?bref=Ezek.47.1-12">Ez 47:1-12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Zech.14.8">Zec 14:8</a>) a time when even the briny waters of the Dead Sea would be recreated afresh and the stark, lifeless character of the sea would issue forth in life.</p>
  </body>
</item>