<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DebirPlace">
  <title>Debir (Place)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DEBIR (P<span class="lc">lace</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. Canaanite city originally held by the Anakim before being conquered by the Israelites (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.21">Jos 11:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.15.15">15:15</a>). There are two accounts of the conquest of Debir (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.38-39">10:38-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.15.13-17">15:13-17</a>). One of these lists Joshua as the conqueror, and the other lists Othniel as the conqueror (by request of Caleb). It is possible that the Othniel account is simply a further elaboration of the Joshua account, or it is possible that Debir was retaken by the Canaanites and the Othniel-Caleb account tells of the subsequent recapture by the Israelites. The latter explanation, however, does not seem to accord well with the apparent finality of the Joshua account. Thus, it would seem that the former explanation is more probable.</p>
<p class="list-text">Debir, with its pasturelands, was finally given to the priestly descendants of the Aaronites (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.15">Jos 21:15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.58">1 Chr 6:58</a>). This might seem fitting, since prior to its capture by the Israelites, Debir was known for its pagan temple. Debir was also known as Kiriath-sannah, meaning “city of the scribes” (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.49">Jos 15:49</a>), and Kiriath-sepher, meaning “city of the books” (v <a href="?bref=Josh.15.15">15</a>). Its exact location is disputed among scholars, but most likely it was located near Khirbet Rabud in the southern Judean hill country.</p>
<p class="list">2. Gadite town east of the Jordan River near the Sea of Galilee (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.26">Jos 13:26</a>). It is possibly the same site as Lo-debar (<a href="?bref=2Sam.9.4-5">2 Sm 9:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.17.27">17:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.6.13">Am 6:13</a>), where Mephibosheth once lived before David summoned him.</p>
<p class="list">3. Town on the northern border of Judah some 10 miles (16 kilometers) northeast of Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Josh.15.7">Jos 15:7</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>