<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Deborah">
  <title>Deborah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DEBORAH</p>
<p class="fl">Name of two OT women. The word in Hebrew means “honeybee” (<a href="?bref=Ps.118.12">Ps 118:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.7.18">Is 7:18</a>).</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Rebekah’s nurse (<a href="?bref=Gen.35.8">Gn 35:8</a>). Deborah died as she was traveling to Bethel with her master Jacob’s household. She was buried in a spot remembered as Allon-bacuth (“the oak of weeping”), indicating that she had been well loved. She was probably Rebekah’s longtime companion (see <a href="?bref=Gen.24.59-61">24:59-61</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Prophetess and judge (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.1-5.31">Jgs 4–5</a>). Deborah’s position as a prophetess, indicating that her message was from God, is not unique in the Bible, but it was unusual. Other prophetesses included Miriam (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.20">Ex 15:20</a>), Huldah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.14">2 Kgs 22:14</a>), and Anna (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.36">Lk 2:36</a>). Deborah was unique in that only she is said to have “judged Israel” <span class="ital">before</span> the major event that marks her narrative (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.4">Jgs 4:4</a>). Her husband, Lappidoth, is otherwise unknown.</p>
<p class="list-text">Deborah, heralded as a “mother in Israel” (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.7">Jgs 5:7</a>), remained in one location and the people came to her for guidance. Evidently over 200 years later, when the book of Judges was compiled, a giant palm tree still marked the spot. Though residing within the boundary of Benjamin (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.5">Jgs 4:5</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Josh.16.2">Jos 16:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.18.13">18:13</a>), Deborah was probably from the tribe of Ephraim, the most prominent tribe of northern Israel. Some scholars, however, place her in the tribe of Issachar (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.14-15">Jgs 5:14-15</a>). At that early time, the tribes were loosely organized and did not always occupy the territory they had been allotted.</p>
<p class="list-text">Under Deborah’s inspired leadership, the poorly equipped Israelites defeated the Canaanites in the plain of Esdraelon (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.15">Jgs 4:15</a>); flooding of the Kishon River evidently interfered with the enemy’s impressive chariotry (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.21-22">5:21-22</a>). The Canaanites retreated to the north, perhaps to Taanach near Megiddo (v <a href="?bref=Judg.5.19">19</a>), and never reappeared as an enemy within Israel. The Song of Deborah (ch <a href="?bref=Judg.5.1-31">5</a>) is a poetic version of the prose narrative in <a href="?bref=Judg.4.1-24">Judges 4</a>.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Barak_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Barak</a>; <a href="?item=DeborahSongof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Deborah, Song of</a>; <a href="?item=JudgesBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judges, Book of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>