<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DeborahSongof">
  <title>Deborah, Song of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DEBORAH, Song of</p>
<p class="fl">Ancient poem found in <a href="?bref=Judg.5.1-31">Judges 5</a>, celebrating an Israelite victory over the Canaanites. Similar to Moses’ song (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.1-18">Ex 15:1-18</a>), and paralleling a prose account in <a href="?bref=Judg.4.1-24">Judges 4</a>, the Song of Deborah describes the miraculous defeat of a powerful Canaanite king, Jabin of Hazor, and of Sisera, his general. The song’s poetic style and occasional use of archaic Hebrew forms are reflected in slightly differing translations in modern versions of the Bible. The poem’s vigorous language suggests that it was composed by an eyewitness of the battle, probably Deborah herself.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Judg.5.2">Judges 5:2</a> addresses Israel with an exhortation to praise the Lord. A second exclamation exhorts foreign kings to learn of Israel’s God and his exploits. It is not clear whether verses <a href="?bref=Judg.5.4-5">4-5</a> describe the present battle or refer to God’s previous appearance to Moses at Mt Sinai. Verse <a href="?bref=Judg.5.5">5</a> could be translated, “The mountains quaked at the presence of the One of Sinai.”</p>
<p>Deborah is first introduced in verse <a href="?bref=Judg.5.7">7</a>. Verse <a href="?bref=Judg.5.8">8</a> could mean either that Canaanite oppression prevented open displays of Israelite weaponry or, more likely, that the Canaanites had wiped out all weapon-making industry in Israel (cf. <a href="?bref=1Sam.13.19">1 Sm 13:19</a>). In an atmosphere of fear, indecision, and isolationism, Deborah, a judge, urged the Israelite tribes to battle. When Deborah appealed to the whole nation for help, some tribes were apathetic, but others gave assistance. The battle took place at Taanach, 15 miles (24.1 kilometers) southwest of Mt Tabor. The Canaanites had mobilized in that vicinity (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.13">Jgs 4:13</a>), so the Israelites lost whatever advantage their mountain position would have afforded. Deborah’s song, however, implies the Lord’s intervention, perhaps through a severe storm. Divine aid is also alluded to in <a href="?bref=Judg.4.14">Judges 4:14</a> (“for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is marching ahead of you,” <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The stars that fought Sisera and the flooding of the river Kishon represent the forces of nature helping Israel (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.20-21">5:20-21</a>). In addition, any advantage of the Canaanites’ chariotry was nullified after Jael, a heroic Hebrew woman, killed Sisera, the chariot leader (vv <a href="?bref=Judg.5.24-27">24-27</a>). Sisera’s death fulfilled Deborah’s prophecy to the Israelite commander, Barak, that a woman, not he, would receive glory for that feat (<a href="?bref=Judg.4.9">4:9</a>).</p>
<p>Sisera’s mother is seen pathetically awaiting his return. In contrast to the sardonic portrayal of that Canaanite woman, the last words of Deborah’s song are a fervent prayer for future safety. Although Jael was blessed (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.24">Jgs 5:24</a>) and Deborah acclaimed, the God of Israel (vv <a href="?bref=Judg.5.1-3">1-3</a>) received the glory.</p>
  </body>
</item>