<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Demon">
  <title>Demon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DEMON</p>
<p class="fl">Fallen angel who, under the leadership of Satan, rebelled against God. Demonism is the activity of demons, while demonology is the study of demons and their activity for the purpose of knowing the tactics of the enemy (<a href="?bref=2Cor.2.11">2 Cor 2:11</a>) in order to properly exercise authority over them (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.19">Lk 10:19</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="WhoDemonsAre">Who Demons Are</p>
<p class="fl">The English word “demon” is derived from the Greek <span class="greek">daimon</span><span class="ital">,</span> which essentially means “a divinity, a deity” (i.e., a false deity, a demon; cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.10.20">1 Cor 10:20</a>). Any deity other than the one true God is a spirit opposed to him; therefore, such a spirit is an evil spirit, or demon. The word “demon” does not appear in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>, which mistranslates <span class="greek">daimon</span> as “devil.” There is only one devil (Greek <span class="greek">diabolos</span>), who is known by a variety of names, titles, and epithets in the Bible. He is the prince or ruler of all the other demons, who are subject to him.</p>
<p>Often in the Bible the word “spirit” is used for demon, along with a descriptive or identifying phrase; for example, “evil spirit” (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.12-13">Acts 19:12-13</a>), “unclean spirit” (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.1">Mt 10:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.23,26">Mk 1:23, 26</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.16">Acts 5:16</a>), “spirit of infirmity” (<a href="?bref=Luke.13.11">Lk 13:11</a>), “dumb and deaf spirit” (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.25">Mk 9:25</a>) (all quotes from the <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Spirits may be identified by their specific role or function, such as a spirit of murder, suicide, lust, depression, fear, lying, etc., associating them with various sins or attitudes contrary to God.</p>
<p>In the Hebrew OT there is no word for “demon.” The term “evil spirit” occurs (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.23">Jgs 9:23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.16.14-23">1 Sm 16:14-23</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.18.10">18:10</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.19.9">19:9</a>). In the <span class="sc">kjv</span> there are references to “a lying spirit” (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.22-23">1 Kgs 22:22-23</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.18.20-22">2 Chr 18:20-22</a>), “familiar spirit” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.10.13">1 Chr 10:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.33.6">2 Chr 33:6</a>), “perverse spirit” (<a href="?bref=Isa.19.14">Is 19:14</a>), “spirit of deep sleep” (<a href="?bref=Isa.29.10">29:10</a>), and “spirit of whoredoms” (<a href="?bref=Hos.4.12">Hos 4:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.5.4">5:4</a>).</p>
<p>A specific powerful demon referred to by title in the OT is “the prince of the kingdom of Persia,” who hindered the archangel Gabriel from coming to bring information to Daniel, so that the archangel Michael came to Gabriel’s assistance (<a href="?bref=Dan.10.13">Dn 10:13</a>).</p>
<p>The number of demons is unknown; it appears that it is a vast number, perhaps incalculable. From <a href="?bref=Rev.12.4">Revelation 12:4</a> it is inferred that one-third of the angels were led astray by Satan. This means that the hosts of heaven outnumber Satan’s powers by two to one. <a href="?bref=Eph.6.12">Ephesians 6:12</a> suggests an order or rank of demons: “principalities,” “powers,” “world rulers of this present darkness,” “spiritual hosts of wickedness in the heavenly places” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Demons are created beings—personal, immortal, and incapable of reconciliation with God. They have great power as compared with humans, but little power as compared with God. God has given us authority over them, so that in the name of Jesus they must obey God’s people, even as they must obey the Lord himself.</p>
<p class="h2" id="WhatDemonsDo">What Demons Do</p>
<p class="fl">Angels were created to worship and praise God, to serve him, and to act as his messengers. The Bible states that they are “spirits sent from God to care for those who will receive salvation” (<a href="?bref=Heb.1.14">Heb 1:14</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The fallen angels have a similar function but a different master. Their allegiance is to the devil, whom they serve out of fear and delusion. They desire to work with human beings, but their purpose is to carry out the schemes of Satan and to oppose God. They tempt, deceive, and delude people so as to bring them to eternal damnation. In opposing God they attack, oppress, hinder, and accuse the people of God.</p>
<p>Since Satan is not omnipresent, he uses his demonic hosts to execute his will; for example, in the parable of the sower (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.3-9">Mt 13:3-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.1-20">Mk 4:1-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.4-15">Lk 8:4-15</a>) they snatch away the word before it can take root (<a href="?bref=Mark.4.15">Mk 4:15</a>). By persecution, Satan causes some to fall away before they have made a genuine commitment (v <a href="?bref=Mark.4.17">17</a>). By the cares of the world and the delight in riches and the desire for material things, he chokes the word so that little or no fruit is produced (v <a href="?bref=Mark.4.19">19</a>).</p>
<p>Basically, demons operate according to the pattern set by Satan in his threefold approach with Eve: (1) they deny the truth of the word of God and challenge its statements; (2) they deny the reality of death (typically they substitute something like reincarnation); and (3) they appeal to human vanity and pride by telling men and women that they can become like God or be gods (<a href="?bref=Gen.3.1-5">Gn 3:1-5</a>). These also are the basic methods and teachings underlying most cults and false religions.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheFinalDestinyofDemons">The Final Destiny of Demons</p>
<p class="fl">It is written concerning the angels who sinned that God “cast them into hell and committed them to pits of nether gloom to be kept until the judgment” (<a href="?bref=2Pet.2.4">2 Pt 2:4</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The Lord spoke of the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels, into which the cursed among humans are also to go (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.41">Mt 25:41</a>). Eventually Satan and his host will be thrown into the lake of fire (<a href="?bref=Rev.20.10">Rv 20:10</a>), which is also the place of eternal torment for all whose names are not written in the Book of Life (vv <a href="?bref=Rev.20.12-15">12-15</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DemonPossession_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Demon-possession</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>