<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Dibon">
  <title>Dibon</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DIBON</p>
<p class="list">1. City in Moab, east of the Dead Sea and north of the Arnon River. It was located on the King’s Highway in Amorite territory and was a camping station for the Israelites during the exodus. Israel asked permission of Sihon, the Amorite king, to pass through his territory, but he refused. Israel then fought and defeated Sihon, thus gaining control of Dibon (<a href="?bref=Num.21.30">Nm 21:30</a>). Following the Hebrew conquest of Palestine and its division among the 12 tribes, Dibon was given to Gad (<a href="?bref=Num.32.3,34">32:3, 34</a>), being also referred to as Dibon-gad (<a href="?bref=Num.33.45-46">33:45-46</a>). One biblical reference assigns it to Reuben (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.17">Jos 13:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">During the period of the judges, Moab under King Eglon oppressed Israel and apparently retook Dibon. It was probably recovered under the leadership of Ehud (<a href="?bref=Judg.3.12-30">Jgs 3:12-30</a>). Subsequently, Dibon was ruled by Israel under King David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.2">2 Sm 8:2</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">In the preexilic period Dibon was again under Moabite influence (<a href="?bref=Isa.15.2">Is 15:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.48.18,22">Jer 48:18, 22</a>). Isaiah condemned Dibon (Dimon) as chief among the wicked cities of Moab (<a href="?bref=Isa.15.9">Is 15:9</a>). Dimon is probably a play on words (from the root “blood”) predicting Dibon’s bloody and disastrous fate.</p>
<p class="list-text">In 1868 excavations uncovered the famous Moabite Stone at Dibon, erected by Mesha, king of Moab, who built “Qarhah” as his capital. This may have been a new capital city replacing Dibon, or a renaming of Dibon by Mesha. Most likely “Qarhah” referred to the fact that Dibon was built on two elevations. The higher one was Qarhah, the defensive citadel of the city, surrounded by a wall and possessing a water reservoir, several cisterns, the royal palace, and a shrine (“high place,” <a href="?bref=Isa.15.2">Is 15:2</a>) to Chemosh, the principal god of Moab.</p>
<p class="list-text">Excavations conducted in 1950–56 at Dibon (modern Dhiban) uncovered remains of the city from a period about 3000 <span class="era">BC</span>. Evidence indicated that it contained only a nomadic population in the period 2100–1300 <span class="era">BC</span> and that it was settled again about 1300 <span class="era">BC</span>. The earliest excavations found five city walls, the oldest dating to about 3000 <span class="era">BC</span>. The heaviest wall was from 7½ to almost 11 feet (2 to 3 meters) thick, built with large, well-squared blocks, and is considered to have been built in Mesha’s time.</p>
<p class="list">2. Town in the Negev of Judah inhabited by Babylonian exiles who returned to Palestine during Nehemiah’s time (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.25">Neh 11:25</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>