<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Darkness">
  <title>Darkness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DARKNESS</p>
<p class="fl">Absence of light or brightness. Although the Bible rarely refers to literal darkness, a number of words translated “darkness” are used in a figurative or metaphorical sense.</p>
<p>When God created the world, there was no light until he commanded that light appear. He then made distinction between light and its opposite, darkness, which he called night (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.2,4-5,18">Gn 1:2, 4-5, 18</a>). Literal darkness is also mentioned in the account of the plagues God inflicted on Egypt; the ninth plague was an intense darkness that could be “felt” (<a href="?bref=Exod.10.21-23">Ex 10:21-23</a>). That darkness lasted three days and was selective; wherever Egyptians were, it was dark, but where the Israelites were, there was light. The Israelites left Egypt accompanied by a cloud that separated them from their enemy, evidently giving light to the Israelites but making darkness for the Egyptians (<a href="?bref=Exod.14.20">Ex 14:20</a>). The Bible notes that thieves or adulterers are likely to do their evil deeds in the dark or at night (<a href="?bref=Job.24.16-17">Jb 24:16-17</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT “darkness” is used twice in its literal sense. At the crucifixion of Jesus, for a three-hour period from noon to three o’clock, there was not light (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.45">Mt 27:45</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.15.33">Mk 15:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.23.44">Lk 23:44</a>). The other reference is to Christ’s second coming, when “the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light” (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.29">Mt 24:29</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Several biblical passages speak of a darkness surrounding God, evidently moving from a literal sense of absence of light to a more profound meaning. God spoke to Moses on Mt Sinai in a dense, black cloud (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.21">Ex 20:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.4.11">Dt 4:11</a>) or from the darkness (<a href="?bref=Deut.5.23">Dt 5:23</a>). Darkness is pictured as a shelter or cloak around God (<a href="?bref=2Sam.22.12">2 Sm 22:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.18.11">Pss 18:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.97.2">97:2</a>). God sets a boundary for light and darkness (<a href="?bref=Job.26.10">Jb 26:10</a>), brings darkness (<a href="?bref=Ps.104.20">Pss 104:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.105.28">105:28</a>), and creates light and darkness (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.7">Is 45:7</a>). God dwells in thick darkness (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.12">1 Kgs 8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.6.1">2 Chr 6:1</a>), and thick darkness is under his feet (<a href="?bref=2Sam.22.10">2 Sm 22:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.18.9">Ps 18:9</a>).</p>
<p>Most figurative references to darkness appear in poetic material, such as Job, Psalms, and Isaiah. Generally, such darkness illustrates ignorance about God’s will. Knowledge of God is “light”; hence, lack of such knowledge is “darkness” (<a href="?bref=Job.12.24-25">Jb 12:24-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.4.16">Mt 4:16</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.5">Jn 1:5</a>; <a href="?bref=John.8.12">8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.35,46">12:35, 46</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.1.5">1 Jn 1:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.8-9,11">2:8-9, 11</a>).</p>
<p>Job spoke of darkness as equivalent to nothingness (<a href="?bref=Job.3.4-6">Jb 3:4-6</a>). In other references darkness stands for death, a land of shadows and gloom, the dwelling place of the dead far from the light of day (<a href="?bref=Job.10.21-22">Jb 10:21-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.15.24">15:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.17.12-13">17:12-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.18.18">18:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.6.4">Eccl 6:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.11.8">11:8</a>).</p>
<p>Darkness frequently stands for distress and anxiety, or for the confusion and destruction experienced by the wicked (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.12">Gn 15:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.5.14">Jb 5:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.12.25">12:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.15.22,30">15:22, 30</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.19.8">19:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.22.11">22:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.35.6">Pss 35:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.107.10,14">107:10, 14</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.5.17">Eccl 5:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.30">Is 5:30</a>). Moral depravity is sometimes described as darkness (<a href="?bref=Pr.2.13">Prv 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.4.19">4:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.20">Is 5:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.60.2">60:2</a>). In the NT darkness is generally a metaphor of moral depravity and spiritual ignorance (<a href="?bref=Matt.4.16">Mt 4:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.6.23">6:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.79">Lk 1:79</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.35">11:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.22.53">22:53</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.2.19">Rom 2:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.1.13">Col 1:13</a>).</p>
<p>A major theme of OT prophets was the Day of the Lord, often associated with darkness (<a href="?bref=Ezek.32.8">Ez 32:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.2,31">Jl 2:2, 31</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.5.18,20">Am 5:18, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.15">Zep 1:15</a>). The NT also links darkness with judgment in connection with Christ’s second coming (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.12">Mt 8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.22.13">22:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.25.30">25:30</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.17">2 Pt 2:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Jude.1.6,13">Jude 1:6, 13</a>). Those who come to know God are said to come out of darkness (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.2">Is 9:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.29.18">29:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.42.7">42:7</a>); darkness cannot be a hiding place from God (<a href="?bref=Job.34.22">Jb 34:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.139.11-12">Ps 139:11-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.29.15">Is 29:15</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Light_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Light</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>