<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DeadPlaceofthe">
  <title>Dead, Place of the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DEAD, Place of the</p>
<p class="fl">Term covering a number of descriptive biblical images of the whereabouts of those who have died. Those images include Sheol and “the pit” in the OT, plus hades, Gehenna, paradise, and “Abraham’s bosom” in the NT. As their understanding advanced, the Hebrews’ idea of what happens at death changed from rather hazy beginnings to a developed concept found in the NT.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The OT contains little information about the dead. At death, according to some OT passages, one descends to Sheol (often translated as “grave,” “hell,” “pit,” or simply “the dead”), which at times simply means that one is laid in a grave (<a href="?bref=Num.16.30,33">Nm 16:30, 33</a>), but more often indicates an underworld. The abode of the dead is pictured as a place beneath the earth to which one “goes down” (<a href="?bref=Gen.42.38">Gn 42:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.15.24">Prv 15:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.26.20">Ez 26:20</a>) and as a place of gloomy darkness (<a href="?bref=Job.10.21-22">Jb 10:21-22</a>), silence (<a href="?bref=Ps.94.17">Pss 94:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.115.17">115:17</a>), and forgetfulness (<a href="?bref=Ps.88.12">Ps 88:12</a>). God is not remembered there and his praises are never sung (<a href="?bref=Ps.6.5">Pss 6:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.30.9">30:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.115.17">115:17</a>). Even God himself, it was believed, does not remember those who are there (<a href="?bref=Ps.88.5,11">Ps 88:5, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.38.18">Is 38:18</a>). The dead were seen as permanently cut off from contact with the Lord and from participating in his activity in history. Even though the border between life and death was considered fluid (as shown by a resurrection in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.32-37">2 Kgs 4:32-37</a> and by Samuel’s ghost in <a href="?bref=1Sam.28.7-25">1 Sm 28:7-25</a>), communication with the dead was forbidden to the Jews (<a href="?bref=Deut.18.11">Dt 18:11</a>). (Worshiping the dead was a common practice in the nations surrounding Israel.)</p>
<p>Although one’s fate in the underworld could not properly be called life, it was a kind of existence, perhaps even in the company of one’s countrymen and ancestors (<a href="?bref=Gen.25.8">Gn 25:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.32.17-30">Ez 32:17-30</a>). The realm of the dead was not beyond the reach of God’s power (<a href="?bref=Ps.139.8">Ps 139:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.9.2">Am 9:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Jon.2.2">Jon 2:2</a>). Although Sheol was pictured as a hungry monster wolfing down the living (<a href="?bref=Pr.27.20">Prv 27:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.30.16">30:16</a>), God’s power could save one from its grasp (<a href="?bref=Ps.49.15">Pss 49:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.86.13">86:13</a>). By the end of the OT period, there was even hope that one would finally be delivered from Sheol (<a href="?bref=Job.14.13-22">Jb 14:13-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.19.25-27">19:25-27</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.49.15">Pss 49:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.73.23-28">73:23-28</a>), although only Daniel expressed that hope clearly (<a href="?bref=Dan.12.1-2">Dn 12:1-2</a>). So although the ancient Hebrews never looked forward to death in the same way that the apostle Paul could in the NT (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.1-8">2 Cor 5:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.1.21-23">Phil 1:21-23</a>), nevertheless they did come to understand that death was not a hopeless state.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheIntertestamentalWritings">In the Intertestamental Writings</p>
<p class="fl">Between the exile and the beginning of the NT period (586 <span class="era">BC</span>–<span class="era">AD</span> 30, overlapping with the end of the OT), contact with the religions of Persia and Greece stimulated the Jews to clarify their ideas about life after death. When the OT was translated into Greek, the Greek name for the underworld, “hades,” was used to translate the Hebrew “Sheol.” In the NT, hades was carried over to become the common name for the abode of the dead.</p>
<p>Along with new names came new ideas. Many different notions circulated about the place of the dead. A common one appears in the pseudepigraphal 1 Enoch 22, where the dead are said to be kept in hollow places in a great mountain waiting for the final judgment. One relatively pleasant section was reserved for the righteous and one full of torments for the wicked. Other writers continued the OT concept of hades or Sheol as a place of separation from God and from happiness (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.14.12,16">Ecclus 14:12, 16</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.17.27-28">17:27-28</a>).</p>
<p>During that period, the Jews also began to use a new term, “Gehenna” (Hebrew “Hinnom”), the name of a valley south of Jerusalem. The valley was noted in the OT period for the abomination of child sacrifices (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.3">2 Kgs 16:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.6">21:6</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.10">23:10</a>) and in the NT period for being a place where garbage was burnt. Gehenna became a designation for the final place of the wicked dead, a place of fiery torment (1 Enoch 90:20-27; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Esd.7.70">2 Esd 7:70</a>). Over against that place of punishment stood “paradise” (a Persian name for a pleasure garden), a place where the righteous would enjoy blessedness.</p>
<p>All those concepts—hades, Gehenna, paradise—were molded by NT writers into forms most appropriate to the revelation of Christ.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Although the NT uses a variety of terms for the abode of the dead, it contains surprisingly few references to it—about 35 verses in all. Those passages are concentrated in the Gospels and the book of Revelation. The apostle Paul said a lot about heaven, but only Jesus and John said much about hell.</p>
<p>The word “hades” is attributed to Jesus only once, in the parable of the rich man and Lazarus (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.23">Lk 16:23</a>). In that parable hades is a place of torment where the wicked go at death. The torment is described as a “flame” that afflicts a person physically despite bodily death. All comfort is refused to those in agony.</p>
<p>Although the wicked go to hades as soon as they die, their ultimate destination is Gehenna, a place of fire and worms, both indicating corruption (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.22,29-30">Mt 5:22, 29-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.18.9">18:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.48">Mk 9:48</a>, quoting from <a href="?bref=Isa.66.24">Is 66:24</a>). Jesus also referred to Gehenna as “the outer darkness” where there will be “weeping and gnashing of teeth” (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.12">Mt 8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.22.13">22:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.25.30">25:30</a>). Evidently, after the final judgment, the wicked are sent there at the command of Christ (<a href="?bref=John.5.22,27">Jn 5:22, 27</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.42">Acts 10:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.17.31">17:31</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.4.1">2 Tm 4:1</a>). That place of torment picks up the negative side of the OT concept of Sheol as a place of separation from God.</p>
<p>As a preacher of repentance, Jesus stressed the danger of Gehenna. He had much less to say about the place of the righteous when they die. Ultimately, though, the righteous would enter into “the kingdom,” instead of Gehenna, after the last judgment (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.34">Mt 25:34</a>). Jesus twice indicated that the righteous enter a blessed state immediately at death. <a href="?bref=Luke.16.22">Luke 16:22</a> refers to the dead Lazarus as being in “Abraham’s bosom,” a place of comfort and peace. <a href="?bref=Luke.23.43">Luke 23:43</a> calls the same place paradise in a promise that the dying thief would join Jesus there at death. Paul’s wording about paradise seems to align it with heaven (<a href="?bref=2Cor.12.2-3">2 Cor 12:2-3</a>), and John associates paradise with the new heaven and new earth (<a href="?bref=Rev.2.7">Rv 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.1-2">21:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.22.1-2">22:1-2</a>).</p>
<p>Paul and other writers of the NT epistles had little to say about the abode of the wicked dead. Paul spoke only in passing of “the abyss”—his term for the pit of Sheol (<a href="?bref=Rom.10.7">Rom 10:7</a>). His reference to Christ’s descent to the “lower parts of the earth” (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.9">Eph 4:9</a>) is probably only his way of saying that Christ, having died, went to the place of the dead. (“The lowest earth” was a term used by Jewish rabbis for Sheol/hades/Gehenna.) Peter spoke of Christ’s going in “spirit” after his death to some “prison” where he “preached to the spirits” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.3.18-20">1 Pt 3:18-20</a>). Interpretations of that passage differ. Some think that Christ entered hades and preached to the fallen angels of Noah’s day (“sons of God,” <a href="?bref=Gen.6.1-4">Gn 6:1-4</a>), not that he preached to imprisoned human spirits. In <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.4">2 Peter 2:4</a> the prison for spirits (usually translated “hell”) comes from “Tartarus,” another Greek name for the underworld.</p>
<p>Paul had much to say about the abode of the righteous dead. In his earliest letters he never mentioned their location, only that they would be resurrected (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.1-58">1 Cor 15</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.13-17">1 Thes 4:13-17</a>). After facing almost certain death himself (<a href="?bref=2Cor.1.8-11">2 Cor 1:8-11</a>), he began to discuss where the dead “went.” To die means to be with Christ, Paul said, and thus is better than life (<a href="?bref=Phil.1.23">Phil 1:23</a>). To be “away from the body” is to be “at home with the Lord” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.8">2 Cor 5:8</a>). Paul probably meant that the righteous dead went directly to paradise to be with Jesus (cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.12.2-4">2 Cor 12:2-4</a>, where Paul called paradise “the third heaven”). Death has absolutely no power to separate Christians from Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.38-39">Rom 8:38-39</a>). Instead, it brings them into the presence of God.</p>
<p>The book of Revelation contains much about the abode of the dead, especially the wicked dead. It uses two names for that place: “the abyss,” the home or prison of all evil spirits; and “hades,” the name for the place of the human dead. From the abyss (or bottomless pit) come the demonic forms that torment humanity (<a href="?bref=Rev.9.1-11">Rv 9:1-11</a>) and the satanic “beast,” who kills the two witnesses and carries the “great prostitute” on its back (<a href="?bref=Rev.11.7">11:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.17.1-18">17</a>). There Satan himself will be imprisoned (<a href="?bref=Rev.20.2-3">20:2-3</a>). Jesus described it as a place prepared for the devil and his angels (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.25.41">Mt 25:41</a>). The good news for Christians is that the abyss, or hades, is not an autonomous realm. The book of Revelation begins with Jesus’ announcement that he has the keys to hades (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.18">Rv 1:18</a>), and in the end he will force it to give up its dead (<a href="?bref=Rev.20.13">20:13</a>). Until then, the key to the abyss is not in the hand of Satan, but hangs on a heavenly key ring to be distributed only to the messengers of God (<a href="?bref=Rev.9.1">9:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.20.1">20:1</a>). In the end, hades, death, and the wicked will be cast into the lake of fire (Gehenna), where they will suffer eternal torment (<a href="?bref=Rev.19.20">19:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.20.10,14-15">20:10, 14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.21.8">21:8</a>).</p>
<p>John, the writer of the Revelation, agreed with Paul that the righteous will not share the fate of the wicked at death. Instead of going to hades, they go to heaven. The martyrs appear under the altar, calling to God to avenge them (<a href="?bref=Rev.6.9-11">Rv 6:9-11</a>). In another image innumerable Christians appear before the throne of God, praising him (<a href="?bref=Rev.7.9-17">7:9-17</a>). Those believers, shepherded by Christ himself, suffer no hunger, thirst, discomfort, or sorrow.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Conclusion">Conclusion</p>
<p class="fl">In summary, the place of the dead began in the OT as an undifferentiated, hazy idea of a place of separation from life and God. Later writers came to see that instead of one place for all (Sheol), there must be two. According to Christian teaching, the wicked enter the underworld, hades, a place of torment, where they suffer until the time of judgment; ultimately they will be cast into Gehenna, the lake of fire. Christ—not the devil—is in control of hades, as he is of the rest of creation. The righteous do not go to hades, but go directly to paradise (“Abraham’s bosom” or heaven). There they are with Christ; faith has become sight, suffering has become blessedness, and prayer has become praise. Christians believe that death, although fearful as the “last enemy,” has no torment for them. It has no power to separate them from their Lord. Rather, it brings them face-to-face with the One they love.</p>
<p>This meeting may occur as soon as one dies or as soon as one is resurrected—the intervening time is of no consequence, because it is nothing more than just a time of sleep. In other words, the very next experience after death for the believer will be that of meeting Christ.</p>
<p>Both Old and New Testaments speak of death as sleep. Commonly in the OT, when a person dies, he is said to go to sleep with his fathers (e.g., <a href="?bref=Deut.31.16">Dt 31:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.7.12">2 Sm 7:12</a>). Jesus himself spoke of death as sleep (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.24">Mt 9:24</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.11">Jn 11:11</a>). So did the apostle Paul (<a href="?bref=1Cor.11.30">1 Cor 11:30</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.20,51">15:20, 51</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.14">1 Thes 4:14</a>). At least in some of these references it would seem that it is the temporary nature of death that is the reason why it is spoken of as sleep. Even in the OT passage <a href="?bref=Dan.12.2">Daniel 12:2</a>, it is said that death is a sleep, until the dead rise up—some to everlasting life and some to shame and everlasting contempt.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Gehenna_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Gehenna</a>; <a href="?item=Hades_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hades</a>; <a href="?item=Heaven_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Heaven</a>; <a href="?item=Hell_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hell</a>; <a href="?item=IntermediateState_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Intermediate State</a>; <a href="?item=Paradise_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paradise</a>; <a href="?item=Sheol_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sheol</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>