<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="DemonPossession">
  <title>Demon-Possession</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DEMON-POSSESSION</p>
<p class="fl">Demonic occupation of a human being. The term “possession” is misleading and is not the best translation for the Greek word <span class="greek">daimonizomai</span><span class="ital">,</span> which literally means to be “demonized” and can often best be translated as “to have a demon.”</p>
<p>Demons can enter the body of a person (<a href="?bref=Luke.8.30">Lk 8:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.22.3">22:3</a>), in order to control the individual’s thoughts and actions. Sometimes a distinction is made between demonic oppression and demonic possession; this supposedly differentiates an attack from without and control from within. Although a non-Christian may be said to be “possessed” by a demon, the Christian cannot be possessed that way, for he belongs to Christ and his human spirit has been sealed by the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Eph.1.13">Eph 1:13</a>). Demonic spirits somehow know and acknowledge this seal.</p>
<p>Demons can also enter the bodies of animals, as in the case of the swine in <a href="?bref=Mark.5.13">Mark 5:13</a>. Demons are associated with books of magic (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.19">Acts 19:19</a>), idols (<a href="?bref=1Cor.10.19-21">1 Cor 10:19-21</a>), and fetishes. Demons often cause illness or physical disability; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.11">Luke 13:11</a> tells of a woman who had “been crippled by an evil spirit” for 18 years but was delivered and healed by Jesus. Since evil spirits often attack the mind and the emotions, many symptoms of mental illness may be the result of their activity. The boy whom Jesus delivered just after the Transfiguration showed symptoms of epilepsy. Paranoia may be the work of a spirit of fear. Some individuals suffering from schizophrenia (split or multiple personality) may in reality be demonized by a number of spirits. It is possible for a person to have many demons. Jesus cast seven of them out of Mary Magdalene (<a href="?bref=Luke.8.2">Lk 8:2</a>). The spirit in the Gerasene demoniac gave his name as Legion, “for we are many” (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.9">Mk 5:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.30">Lk 8:30</a>). In the time of Augustus a Roman legion consisted of 6,000 foot soldiers, usually accompanied by an equal number of auxiliary troops.</p>
<p>Demonization occurs in various ways. Some people are demonized by a hereditary curse, which may continue to the third or fourth generation (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.5">Ex 20:5</a>). The curse against illegitimacy was particularly strong, for an illegitimate child could not enter the congregation of Israel until the tenth generation (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.2">Dt 23:2</a>). Curses may also be placed upon someone by spells, incantations, or similar practices such as voodoo or other forms of witchcraft. <a href="?bref=Gal.3.13">Galatians 3:13</a> speaks of redemption from the curse of the law through Christ, Jesus having “become a curse” for us. Usually believers are not affected by curses made against them, unless they have given grounds to the devil (<a href="?bref=Eph.4.27">Eph 4:27</a>). Such grounds may be provided through drugs, illicit sex, the occult, or any other avenue forbidden in the Bible. Involvement with tarot cards, horoscopes, or any other form of fortune-telling may give demons opportunity to enter. Such contacts may seem harmless, but Satan utilizes the smallest foothold to gain advantage over people.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Manifestation">Manifestation</p>
<p class="fl">Often demons prefer to hide rather than to make their presence known. That way, they can exercise control without restriction. When they do manifest themselves, often when challenged, all sorts of strange and frightening things may occur. They possess supernatural powers (cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.16.14">Rv 16:14</a>), which they exhibit directly or through their victims. The Gerasene demoniac had superhuman physical strength, so that he couldn’t be bound with fetters or chains (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.4-5">Mk 5:4-5</a>); he lived in tombs and went screaming night and day, and injuring himself with stones.</p>
<p>The spirit in the demonized boy in <a href="?bref=Mark.9.1-50">Mark 9</a> made him dumb and deaf, threw him on the ground, and caused him to roll around and to foam at the mouth (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.18-20">9:18-20</a>). The demon caused him to grind his teeth and become rigid; he had tried to kill the boy by throwing him into the fire and into the water on various occasions (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.9.18-22">18-22</a>). Before leaving at the command of Jesus, the demon cried out (cf. <a href="?bref=Mark.1.26">Mk 1:26</a>), shook the boy terribly, and left him lying like a corpse. Jesus took him by the hand and raised him up (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.27">9:27</a>). Similar manifestations take place today.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Exorcism">Exorcism</p>
<p class="fl">Casting out demons, or exorcism, was a regular and frequent part of the ministry of Jesus, and he taught and commanded his followers to do the same. This command has never been revoked, and the ministry of deliverance should be even more important today, when the forces of evil are so prevalent. The following principles come from the practice of Jesus, the Scriptures, and personal observation and involvement.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Jesus spoke to demons and commanded them to come out (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.25">Mk 1:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.25">9:25</a>). He cast them out “with a word” (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.16">Mt 8:16</a>). Jesus gave his followers authority to use his name in casting them out and used this as a sign of the believer (<a href="?bref=Mark.16.17">Mk 16:17</a>). His name is not a magical formula, and its use depends on the relationship between the Lord and the person using his name. The sons of Sceva found it out at their own expense (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.11-18">Acts 19:11-18</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Jesus cast out demons by the Spirit of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.28">Mt 12:28</a>). God anointed Jesus of Nazareth with the Holy Spirit and with power to heal all who were oppressed by the devil (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.18-19">Lk 4:18-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.10.38">Acts 10:38</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. The Lord gave clear teaching about “the binding of the strong man” in deliverance (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.29">Mt 12:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.27">Mk 3:27</a>) and about binding and loosing (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.18">Mt 18:18</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Prayer is an important weapon in spiritual warfare. When the disciples asked (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.28">Mk 9:28</a>) why they could not cast out a demon, Jesus replied that this kind comes out only with prayer.</p>
<p class="list">5. <a href="?bref=Rev.12.11">Revelation 12:11</a> testifies to the power of “the blood of the Lamb” in overcoming Satan. Demons do not like to hear of the blood of Jesus and often become agitated at the mention of it.</p>
<p class="list">6. God has equipped the believer with armor for defense in spiritual battle (<a href="?bref=Eph.6.10-17">Eph 6:10-17</a>).</p>
<p class="list">7. The Lord answered Satan with correctly applied texts from the Bible. We have been given the sword of the Spirit, the Word of God (<a href="?bref=Eph.6.17">Eph 6:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.12">Heb 4:12</a>), as a means of defense and for attack against the enemy.</p>
<p class="list">8. We must come against the hosts of hell from our position in the heavenly places (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.6">Eph 2:6</a>), not from our limited earthly station.</p>
<p class="list">9. We must recognize that the ultimate victory has already been won by Jesus, who came to destroy the works of the devil (<a href="?bref=1Jn.3.8">1 Jn 3:8</a>) and to destroy him who has the power of death (<a href="?bref=Heb.2.14-16">Heb 2:14-16</a>). When Jesus cried out on the cross, “It is finished,” he meant that the redemptive work was done; when he arose from the dead, he demonstrated his power over death. We win only as we enter into his victory.</p>
<p class="sp"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Demon_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Demon</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>