<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Desert">
  <title>Desert</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">DESERT</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="SinaiDesert"/>
<p class="fl">Empty waste place, often arid, sandy, and incapable of sustaining vegetable life, as for example the Negev of southern Palestine. A desert frequently includes local areas where marginal life is possible. The most common Hebrew term for desert means “wilderness” and is perhaps related to a verb meaning “to drive,” as a shepherd drives sheep to pasturage. The Greek word commonly used in the NT and in the Septuagint (ancient Greek translation of the OT) implies an unenclosed, uncultivated area where wild beasts roam (<a href="?bref=Deut.32.10">Dt 32:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.24.5">Jb 24:5</a>). The wilderness is also sometimes a place of pasturage (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.1">Ex 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.65.12">Ps 65:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.23.10">Jer 23:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.22">Jl 2:22</a>).</p>
<p>The Bible often refers to wilderness regions (e.g., <a href="?bref=Gen.16.7">Gn 16:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.21.20">21:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.17.28">1 Sm 17:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.3.1">Mt 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.13">Mk 1:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.15.4">Lk 15:4</a>). “Wilderness” is usually a place with no settled population (<a href="?bref=Num.14.33">Nm 14:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.32.10">Dt 32:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.38.26">Jb 38:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.21.19">Prv 21:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.9.2">Jer 9:2</a>) but is the dwelling place of wildlife: the vulture (<a href="?bref=Ps.102.6">Ps 102:6</a>), wild asses (<a href="?bref=Job.24.5">Jb 24:5</a>), jackals (<a href="?bref=Mal.1.3">Mal 1:3</a>), and ostriches (<a href="?bref=Lam.4.3">Lam 4:3</a>). The term is also used figuratively (<a href="?bref=Hos.2.3">Hos 2:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.31">Jer 2:31</a>).</p>
<p>Another Hebrew term for desert, from a root meaning “to be arid,” refers to an infertile, desolate, bare steppe (<a href="?bref=Job.24.5">Jb 24:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.33.9">Is 33:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.51.43">Jer 51:43</a>). The plural form of that word describes topographical features of the desert plains of Moab (<a href="?bref=Num.22.1">Nm 22:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.3,63">26:3, 63</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.34.1">Dt 34:1</a>) and of Jericho (<a href="?bref=Josh.4.13">Jos 4:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.5.10">5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.5">2 Kgs 25:5</a>). With the definite article, that word (the Arabah) is the plain of the Jordan Valley and of the environs of the Dead Sea. The geography of that region contains sharp contrasts; the Jordan Valley, dense with a junglelike forest sheltering wild beasts (including lions in biblical times), gives way to the steppe lands of the Dead Sea area, which have always been desert.</p>
<p>Two other Hebrew terms, meaning “waste” and “ruin,” refer to districts or settlements once inhabited but later devastated (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.7">Is 1:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.9">5:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.6.11">6:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.42.18">Jer 42:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.35.7">Ez 35:7</a>). They are also used more generally for any desolate or waste place (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.31,33">Lv 26:31, 33</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.3.14">Jb 3:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.9.6">Pss 9:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.109.10">109:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.17">Is 5:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.44.26">44:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.51.3">51:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.52.9">52:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.7.34">Jer 7:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.5.14">Ez 5:14</a>). One of them is also used once for the wilderness of the exodus (<a href="?bref=Isa.48.21">Is 48:21</a>). Another word meaning “waste” (<a href="?bref=Ps.78.40">Ps 78:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.43.19-20">Is 43:19-20</a>), when prefixed with the definite article, is a proper name for Jeshimon, a tract of land west of the Dead Sea (<a href="?bref=Num.21.20">Nm 21:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.23.24">1 Sm 23:24</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.26.1">26:1</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT the noun for “wilderness” and the adjective “desert” (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.1">Mt 3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.26">24:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.16">Lk 5:16</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.31">Jn 6:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.8.26">Acts 8:26</a>) come from the same Greek root.</p>
<p>The whole of biblical history has been interpreted as having a desert or wilderness motif. It can be seen in the realm of disobedient human experience outside the Garden of Eden; in the wandering of Israel during the exodus; in the struggle between pure faith in the desert and soft, idolatrous city life. The desert is viewed as a realm of demons and death (<a href="?bref=Deut.32.17">Dt 32:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.34.13-14">Is 34:13-14</a>); its demonic wildness resembles the primeval chaos of the Creation (<a href="?bref=Gen.1.2">Gn 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.26.7">Jb 26:7</a>). Several moving passages of Scripture deal with renewal of life in a desert valley (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.1-28">Ez 37</a>), or with transformation of arid land into a productive garden (<a href="?bref=Isa.41.18-20">Is 41:18-20</a>).</p>
<p>The desert is also a place where God is close to his people (<a href="?bref=Deut.32.10-12">Dt 32:10-12</a>), both watching over them and testing their obedience (<a href="?bref=Jer.2.2">Jer 2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.2.14-15">Hos 2:14-15</a>). Finally, the desert is a place of refuge, cleansing, and consecration. In the Gospels the desert theme of the exodus recurs in the 40 days and nights in which Jesus was tempted in the wilderness (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.13">Mk 1:13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.91.1-16">Ps 91</a>). The desert fathers of the early church and the hermits of the Middle Ages imitated the prophet Elijah and John the Baptist (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.4-8">1 Kgs 19:4-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.3.1-6">Mt 3:1-6</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=NegebNegev_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Negeb, Negev</a>; <a href="?item=Palestine_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Palestine</a>; <a href="?item=Wilderness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>