<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Immanuel">
  <title>Immanuel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">IMMANUEL</p>
<p class="fl">Hebrew masculine name that means “God with us.” It appears only twice in the OT (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">Is 7:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.8.8">8:8</a>) and once in the NT (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.23">Mt 1:23</a>), where it is sometimes transliterated “Emmanuel.” In the OT the name was given to a child born in the time of Ahaz as a sign to the king that Judah would receive relief from attacks by Israel and Syria. The name symbolized the fact that God would demonstrate his presence with his people in this deliverance. The greater application is that this is a prophecy of the birth of the incarnate God, Jesus the Messiah, as shown in Matthew.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheProphecyinIsaiahsDay">The Prophecy in Isaiah’s Day</p>
<p class="fl">In focusing on the birth of Jesus as Immanuel, there has been some neglect of the historical fulfillment that occurred in the time of Ahaz. Ahaz was the son of a good king, Jotham and the grandson of another godly ruler, Uzziah, but his reign was marked by apostasy and idolatry. He made “molten images” for the Baals, offered incense in the Hinnom Valley, and even burned his sons as an offering (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.2-4">2 Chr 28:2-4</a>). Because of this, the Lord gave him into the hand of Rezin, king of Syria, and of Pekah, king of Israel. The Edomites also invaded Judah, and the Philistines attacked the Shephelah and the Negev and took several cities (vv <a href="?bref=2Chr.28.17-18">17-18</a>).</p>
<p>Ahaz appealed to Tiglath-pileser III of Assyria (745–727 <span class="era">BC</span>) for help against Israel and Syria. Tiglath-pileser accepted tribute from Ahaz, but attacked him instead of helping him (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.20-21">2 Chr 28:20-21</a>). When he went to Damascus to meet the Assyrian king, Ahaz saw an altar, upon which he made offerings to the gods of Syria (v <a href="?bref=2Chr.28.23">23</a>). He had a replica of this made and placed in the temple of Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.10-12">2 Kgs 16:10-12</a>). The prophet Isaiah was directed to accost Ahaz at the end of the conduit of the upper pool. God’s message to the king was to “take heart,” for the attacking kings would fall (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.7-9">Is 7:7-9</a>). Isaiah directed Ahaz to ask the Lord for a sign of this, but the king demurred, having a sudden attack of piety (v <a href="?bref=Isa.7.12">12</a>).</p>
<p>Upon this refusal, the Lord gave to Ahaz a sign: a young woman would conceive and bear a son and call his name Immanuel (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">Is 7:14</a>). That son would be able to distinguish good from evil by the time he was old enough to eat curds and wild honey, but even before that, the two kings would be removed and the king of Assyria would devastate their lands. The people would be taken away captive, so that the land would lie desolate and uncultivated. A man would have a cow to provide milk for curds, and wild honey would be gathered from the tangle of brush in the untended land.</p>
<p>The identity of this woman and child in Isaiah’s time is uncertain. It has been proposed that the woman was Abijah, the wife of Ahaz, and that their son, Hezekiah, was this Immanuel. This is not demonstrable, and it seems inappropriate that a man like Ahaz should be the father of Immanuel.</p>
<p>It has also been suggested that the wife of Isaiah was the mother of Immanuel. <a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">Isaiah 7:14</a> tells of the prospective birth of Immanuel; <a href="?bref=Isa.8.3">8:3</a> tells of the conception and birth of Isaiah’s son, whose name, Maher-shalal-hash-baz (“swift to plunder and quick to spoil”) is related to the prediction of the fall of Judah’s enemies, for before the child would learn to talk, the lands of Syria and Israel would be taken by the king of Assyria (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.4">Is 8:4</a>). Isaiah’s statement that he and his children were “signs and portents in Israel from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (v <a href="?bref=Isa.8.18">18</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) enhances the view that it was his son who was also named Immanuel.</p>
<p>The Lord then directed a message to Immanuel (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.5-10">Is 8:5-10</a>). Because the people had refused the gracious invitation of the Lord, the Assyrians would scourge and fill the land of Immanuel. The plotting and plans of the people would come to nothing, for “God is with us” <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">‘immanu’el</span><span class="ital">).</span> This is a play on words, using the name Immanuel to express the truth of the Lord’s presence.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheProphecyFulfilledinJesus">The Prophecy Fulfilled in Jesus</p>
<p class="fl">In the fullness of time God sent forth his son; more than 700 years after Ahaz, Jesus was born and here all ambiguities fade away. His mother was a virgin from Nazareth named Mary (Miriam), betrothed to a solid citizen named Joseph. <a href="?bref=Matt.1.23">Matthew 1:23</a> cites <a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">Isaiah 7:14</a> as being fulfilled in the birth of Jesus. The Scripture is very explicit in stating that Mary had no sexual contact with her husband prior to the birth of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.25">Mt 1:25</a>). The same precision is seen in the Gospel of Luke. When the announcement of this child’s conception was made to Mary, she asked, “How can this be, since I have no husband?” (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.34">Lk 1:34</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The angelic messenger explained that this conception would be brought about by the coming of the Holy Spirit upon her and by the overshadowing power of the Most High (v <a href="?bref=Luke.1.35">35</a>). For this reason the child would be not only Jesus and Immanuel but he would be called holy, the Son of God, God manifest in the flesh (<a href="?bref=John.1.18">Jn 1:18</a>); the child would be unique, being both God and man.</p>
<p>There were great distinctions between the Immanuel of Isaiah’s day and Immanuel the son of Mary. The first was a type; the other, the antitype. The first was the shadow; the other, the reality. The one symbolized deliverance from foreign oppression; the second was the Deliverer from the oppressor. The first represented God’s presence for but a few years; the second Immanuel is the son who lives forever.</p>
<p>The concept of “God with us” was often reiterated by Jesus. He told his disciples that where two or three gathered in his name he would be present (<a href="?bref=Matt.18.20">Mt 18:20</a>). Before his ascension, he assured them that he would be with them until the end of the age (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.20">28:20</a>).</p>
<p>He spoke also of the promise of the Holy Spirit, who “lives with you now and later will be in you” (<a href="?bref=John.14.17">Jn 14:17</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>), who will abide with them forever (v <a href="?bref=John.14.16">16</a>). The “God with us” indwelling is spoken of in <a href="?bref=Col.1.27">Colossians 1:27</a>: “Christ lives in you.” In the consummation of all things, as shown to the apostle John, the Lord said: “Look, the home of God is now among his people! He will live with them, and they will be his people. God himself will be with them” (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.3">Rv 21:3</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=GodNamesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Names of</a>; <a href="?item=Messiah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Messiah</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>