<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Incense">
  <title>Incense</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">INCENSE</p>
<p class="fl">Fragrant spices and oils or sacrifice that sends up perfumed smoke to God in order to please him.</p>
<p>People of every age have loved fragrant odors. In ancient times, sacrifices included sweet smells to make the deity happy. The aroma was a crucial factor in whether the god would accept the offering. Therefore, aromatic plants and exotic perfumes were precious for both secular and religious purposes.</p>
<p>Spices and precious oils were valued along with silver and gold. The queen of Sheba brought spices to Solomon as a gift (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.2">1 Kgs 10:2</a>). Incense was kept in the royal treasury (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.13">2 Kgs 20:13</a>). The price of spices and oils was extremely inflated because of the difficult work of extracting the juices, transportation costs to import them from faraway places, and high profits for merchants who sold the perfumes.</p>
<p>Consequently, lovers sometimes compared their beloved to “myrrh,” a “mountain of myrrh” and a “hill of frankincense” (<a href="?bref=Song.1.13">Sg 1:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.6">4:6</a>). The fragrance of incense set the right mood (<a href="?bref=Song.1.12">1:12</a>). Every spice known to a merchant burned beside the couch of Solomon (<a href="?bref=Song.3.6">3:6</a>). A bridegroom delighted in the perfumes of his beloved. She was his own private garden of incense (<a href="?bref=Song.4.10-14">4:10-14</a>). Even a prostitute burned incense beside her bed (<a href="?bref=Ezek.23.41">Ez 23:41</a>). No wonder wise men said that “fragrant oil” makes the heart glad and the “sweetness of friendship” comforts the soul (e.g., <a href="?bref=Pr.27.9">Prv 27:9</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TypesofIncense">Types of Incense</p>
<p class="fl">Frankincense is mentioned most often in the Bible. It was imported from India, Somaliland, and Arabia Felix. Myrrh also came from Arabia Felix. Cinnamon was another important fragrance from Ceylon and China. Galbanum, tragacanth (gum), and laudanum all were grown in the mountains of Asia Minor. Galbanum was the most popular of these three, for it was also found in Turkestan, Persia, Syria, and Crete. Henna, saffron, and balsam came from aromatic plants native to Israel. In postexilic times other plants were introduced to Palestine and cultivated there: the rose, narcissus, and jasmine. Onycha seems to have been produced from the local fauna, and musk (muskin) may have been extracted from a gland of the musk deer.</p>
<p>Incense itself came in many forms. It might be used as granules placed in a bag hung around the neck (<a href="?bref=Song.1.13">Sg 1:13</a>). In the main, however, perfumes were in a liquid form, dissolved in olive oil. A good example of this is the “holy anointing oil” (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.31">Ex 30:31</a>). Such oils were used to anoint the priests and kings of Israel. Only priests were allowed to prepare and administer them. The incense contained raw spices beaten into a fine consistency and seasoned with salt to make them holy. Stacte, onycha, galbanum, and pure frankincense were mixed in equal proportions, all according to the art of the perfumer (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.34-37">Ex 30:34-37</a>). The spices and incense for the sanctuary were donated as gifts (<a href="?bref=Num.7.14-86">Nm 7:14-86</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.17.26">Jer 17:26</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.41.5">41:5</a>) and kept in the temple (<a href="?bref=Neh.13.5,9">Neh 13:5, 9</a>). Josephus described the incense of his day as a much more complicated compound. He listed 13 ingredients in the best incense of the Herodian era.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IncenseOffering">Incense Offering</p>
<p class="fl">Archaeology has demonstrated that incense offerings were common throughout the ancient Near East from the earliest times of organized worship. Egyptian paintings and reliefs from the New Kingdom occasionally show a man holding a censer of burning incense. Incense seems to have been used as well in the rituals of Assyria, Babylonia, and Arabia. Canaanite altars found at Megiddo and Tell Beit Mirsim have horned limestone altars (10th century <span class="era">BC</span>) that may have been designed to hold a bowl of incense. Hence, it is safe to assume that incense offerings also played some part in the worship of Israel from the beginning.</p>
<p>Incense offerings seem to have served a multitude of purposes. They may have been used to drive away evil spirits and thereby sanctify all the utensils of the place of worship (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.26-29">Ex 30:26-29</a>). Undoubtedly, the sweet smell of incense provided an antidote to the putrid odor of the animal sacrifices. Therefore, if God was to receive a sweet savor and thereby be pleased with an offering, incense was necessary to compensate for the smell of the sacrifices. However, spices were never added to the flesh of the animals or birds.</p>
<p>In some instances, incense itself became a sacrifice. As a supplement to other sacrifices, frankincense alone was burned. To alleviate a plague, Aaron performed a ritual of burning incense (<a href="?bref=Num.16.46-47">Nm 16:46-47</a>). On the Day of Atonement, the high priest carried burning incense and hot coals on a pan (censer) into the Holy of Holies (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.12-13">Lv 16:12-13</a>). The burning incense was thought to protect the life of the high priest, perhaps because the smoke kept him from seeing the full glory of God.</p>
<p>Frankincense was added to grain for offerings on the altar of burnt offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.2.1,15-16">Lv 2:1, 15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.15">6:15</a>). It also accompanied the bread of the Presence (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.7">24:7</a>) in two dishes. The bronze serpent destroyed by Hezekiah in his reform had become a profane object to which incense was burned (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.4">2 Kgs 18:4</a>).</p>
<p>Except on the Day of Atonement, the incense was offered on a special altar (<a href="?bref=Lev.4.7">Lv 4:7</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.30.9">Ex 30:9</a>), where it burned morning and evening and came to be called “perpetual incense” (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.7-8">Ex 30:7-8</a>). Probably the altar of gold in Solomon’s temple (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.20-22">1 Kgs 6:20-22</a>) was the incense altar.</p>
<p>Offering incense was a holy ritual, and persons who offered it with disrespect for procedures were condemned (<a href="?bref=Lev.10.1-2">Lv 10:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.16.6-50">Nm 16:6-50</a>). Uzziah, the king of Judah, became a leper because he dared to offer incense (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.16-21">2 Chr 26:16-21</a>). The burning of incense at “high places” is often criticized (e.g., <a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.43">1 Kgs 22:43</a>), either because the sanctuaries were idolatrous or because their priests did not take proper care as did the priesthood in Jerusalem. Prophets who criticized the offering of incense (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.13">Is 1:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.66.3">66:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.20">Jer 6:20</a>) did so to condemn a formalism that was void of devotion to the God of Israel.</p>
<p class="h2" id="MeaningofIncense">Meaning of Incense</p>
<p class="fl">Since incense was such a precious commodity, incense was a fitting offering to God (<a href="?bref=Mal.1.11">Mal 1:11</a>). Incense offerings also provided a tangible sense of God’s holiness in which the people could experience atonement for sin (<a href="?bref=Num.16.46-47">Nm 16:46-47</a>). The smoke rising to the sky symbolized the prayers of the people (<a href="?bref=Ps.141.2">Ps 141:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.10">Lk 1:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.5.8">Rv 5:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.8.3-4">8:3-4</a>). At the same time, the smoke in the temple symbolized the presence of God as it had been portrayed by the cloud in the wilderness (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.18">Ex 19:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.33.9-10">33:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.11.25">Nm 11:25</a>). Together with the rising sun, the smoke provided a powerful symbol for the glory of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-7">Is 6:1-7</a>).</p>
<p>The significance of incense is further enhanced by NT allusions. The Christian’s testimony about Christ is paralleled with the offering of incense (<a href="?bref=2Cor.2.14-15">2 Cor 2:14-15</a>). The sweet smell of the gospel is contrasted with the smell of death that leads to doom. Likewise, money from the Philippian Christians came to Paul in the spirit of an incense sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Phil.4.18">Phil 4:18</a>), a costly expression of love and devotion. Finally, incense seems to sanctify and accompany the prayers of the saints into the presence of God (<a href="?bref=Rev.5.8">Rv 5:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.8.3-4">8:3-4</a>). None of the NT references call upon the Christian to offer incense, but rather to learn the devotion and dedication to holiness signified by the burning of this precious substance.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants</a> (<a href="?item=Aloe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Aloe</a>; <a href="?item=BalmBalsam_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Balm</a>; <a href="?item=Calamus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Calamus</a>; <a href="?item=Cinnamon_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Cinnamon</a>; <a href="?item=Frankincense_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Frankincense</a>; <a href="?item=Galbanum_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Galbanum</a>; <a href="?item=Henna_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Henna</a>; <a href="?item=Hyssop_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hyssop</a>; <a href="?item=Myrrh_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Myrrh</a>; <a href="?item=Nard_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Nard</a>; <a href="?item=StoraxTree_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Storax Tree</a>); <a href="?item=Perfume_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Perfume</a>; <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>