<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="IsaiahPerson">
  <title>Isaiah (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ISAIAH (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Eighth-century <span class="era">BC</span> prophet during the reigns of the Judean kings Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah; author of the biblical book of Isaiah. Isaiah was the son of Amoz (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.1">Is 1:1</a>) and may have been a relative of King Amaziah. Growing up in Jerusalem, Isaiah received the best education the capital could supply. He was also deeply knowledgeable about people, and he became the political and religious counselor of the nation. He had easy access to the monarchs and seems to have been the historiographer at the Judean court for several reigns (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.22">2 Chr 26:22</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.32.32">32:32</a>).</p>
<p>Isaiah’s wife is referred to as a prophetess (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.3">Is 8:3</a>) and they had at least two sons, Shear-jashub (<a href="?bref=Isa.7.3">7:3</a>) and Maher-shalal-hash-baz (<a href="?bref=Isa.8.3">8:3</a>). Isaiah’s customary attire was a prophet’s clothing, that is, sandals and a garment of goat’s hair or sackcloth. At one point during his ministry, the Lord commanded Isaiah to go naked and barefoot for a period of three years, (wearing only a loincloth) (<a href="?bref=Isa.20.2-6">20:2-6</a>). This must have been humiliating in a society that measured status by meticulous dress codes.</p>
<p>Isaiah worked to reform social and political wrongs. Even the highest members of society did not escape his censure. He berated soothsayers and denounced wealthy, influential people who ignored the responsibilities of their position. He exhorted the masses to be obedient rather than indifferent to God’s covenant. He rebuked kings for their willfulness and lack of concern.</p>
<p>Isaiah’s writings express a deep awareness of God’s majesty and holiness. The prophet denounced not only Canaanite idolatry but also the religious observances of his own people that were external ceremonies only and lacking sincerity (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.10-17">1:10-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.29.13">29:13</a>). He preached impending judgment on the idolatrous Judeans, declaring that only a righteous remnant would survive (<a href="?bref=Isa.6.13">6:13</a>).</p>
<p>Isaiah foretold the coming of the Messiah, the “peaceful prince,” and the ruler of God’s kingdom (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.1-11">11:1-11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.9.6-7">9:6-7</a>). He also depicted this Messiah as a suffering, obedient servant (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.3-12">53:3-12</a>). Isaiah was preeminent among the prophets for the variety and grandeur of his imagery. His imagination produced forceful, brilliant figures of speech.</p>
<p>Isaiah prophesied during the last three decades of the northern kingdom of Israel but because he lived in Jerusalem, in Judah, he made little direct reference to Israel. However, when that kingdom fell, Judah lay open to conquest by Assyria. Isaiah advised King Ahaz to avoid foreign entanglements and depend on God to protect his people. Ignoring that advice, Ahaz made an alliance with Assyria.</p>
<p>It was Hezekiah, Ahaz’s pious son, who sought to remove Judah from this dangerous situation. When the Assyrians under Sennacherib approached Jerusalem, Isaiah inspired Hezekiah and the Judeans to rely on the Lord for the city’s defense, and “the angel of the Lord” destroyed Sennacherib’s army (<a href="?bref=Isa.37.36-38">37:36-38</a>), securing a short period of peace for Hezekiah and the Judeans.</p>
<p>Hebrew prophecy reached its pinnacle with Isaiah, who was greatly esteemed in both OT and NT times. One indication of that esteem is the collection of apocryphal literature associated with his name.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=IsaiahBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Isaiah, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=Prophecy_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophecy</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetProphetess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophet, Prophetess</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>