<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="VisionVisions">
  <title>Vision, Visions</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">VISION, VISIONS</p>
<p class="fl">Visual experiences of any kind, but in the Bible the word usually refers to supernatural revelations of a prophet. In early OT prophecy there are cases of extraordinary sight, which was regarded as evidence of the visionary endowment of a prophet. Samuel was a “seer” or visionary; he was able to “see” where Saul’s lost donkeys were and to tell him their whereabouts (<a href="?bref=1Sam.9.19-20">1 Sm 9:19-20</a>). Elisha was able to follow Gehazi’s wrongful actions “in spirit” and confront him on his return (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.5.26">2 Kgs 5:26</a>). This psychic gift was given only to the prophets.</p>
<p>Apart from these kinds of visions of present happenings occurring elsewhere on earth, there are revelatory visions—visions concerning the future that are given by God to various prophets. Sometimes God communicated these visions through dreams. Both experiences are legitimate channels of divine revelation. Presumably visions are distinguished from dreams as being daytime experiences.</p>
<p>There are different types of revelatory vision. At one end of the spectrum is the ecstatic vision of Ezekiel. He experienced a psychic trance that could supernaturally transport him to other places (<a href="?bref=Ezek.8.3">Ez 8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.40.2">40:2</a>). Daniel’s vision (<a href="?bref=Dan.8.1-27">Dn 8</a>) was probably of the same type, and so perhaps was Jeremiah’s experience (<a href="?bref=Jer.13.4-7">Jer 13:4-7</a>). At the other end of the spectrum is what has been called symbolical perception. In this, a prophet sees an ordinary object that is part of the natural world, but sees it with a heightened significance. The basket of summer fruit that God “caused” Amos “to see” (<a href="?bref=Amos.8.1-2">Am 8:1-2</a>) seems to fall into this category, and so probably do Jeremiah’s visions of the almond branch and the tilting pot (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.11-13">Jer 1:11-13</a>). An intermediate type includes the pictorial heavenly visions that Isaiah received (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.19-22">1 Kgs 22:19-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.6.1-13">Is 6</a>), as well as those of the apostle John, when he wrote the book of Revelation.</p>
<p>Actually, prophecy could come via either an auditory or a visual experience. Typically, in the course of a vision a verbal message was communicated, so that the seeing and hearing took place within the same supernatural experience. This was the case with Isaiah, who both “saw the Lord” and heard his voice. But an auditory experience could itself be called a vision, for the divine word is a revelation from God. It is often difficult to know whether the term “vision” includes a predominant element of hearing or is used in the wider sense of revelation (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ezek.12.21-28">Ez 12:21-28</a>). Often “vision” is apparently used simply as a technical term for a verbal communication from God. Thus Samuel’s call is literally called a “vision” (<a href="?bref=1Sam.3.15">1 Sm 3:15</a>). Several of the prophetic books have the word “vision” in their headings (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.1">Is 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Obad.1.1">Ob 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Nah.1.1">Na 1:1</a>). Nathan’s prophecy of God’s covenant with David is described as a vision (<a href="?bref=2Sam.7.17">2 Sm 7:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.17.15">1 Chr 17:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.19">Ps 89:19</a>). In <a href="?bref=Dan.9.24">Daniel 9:24</a> “to seal both vision and prophet” means to authenticate the prophecy of Jeremiah referred to in verse <a href="?bref=Dan.9.2">2</a>. In the famous proverb traditionally rendered “Where there is no vision, the people perish” (<a href="?bref=Pr.29.18">Prv 29:18</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>), the term “vision” refers to prophetic revelation, the divine gift of prophecy that was intended to be a guiding influence in Israel’s life. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Apocalypse_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Apocalypse</a>; <a href="?item=Dreams_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dreams</a>; <a href="?item=Prophecy_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophecy</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>