<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JamesLetterof">
  <title>James, Letter of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JAMES, Letter of</p>
<p class="fl">First letter of the General Epistles.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurposeofWritingandTheologicalTeaching">Purpose of Writing and Theological Teaching</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">According to the salutation, this letter was written by “James, a slave of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.1">Jas 1:1</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). But who was this James? Of the several mentioned in the NT, only two have ever been proposed as the author of this letter—James the son of Zebedee, and James the Lord’s brother.</p>
<p>The James who wrote this epistle was probably not James the son of Zebedee, for he was martyred too early (<span class="era">AD</span> 44) to have written it (see <a href="?bref=Acts.12.1-2">Acts 12:1-2</a>). Most scholars have identified this James as Jesus’ brother (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.19">Gal 1:19</a>), the prominent elder of the church in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.13,19">Acts 15:13, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.21.17-25">21:17-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.12">Gal 2:12</a>). The whole character of the epistle coincides with what we know of this James’s legalism and Jewishness.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientPapyrusManuscriptOfJames"/>
<p>As an elder of Jerusalem writing to the 12 tribes of the dispersion (which came as a result of the persecution noted in <a href="?bref=Acts.11.19">Acts 11:19</a>), James set forth the gospel in its relation to the law, which the Jews revered. As Paul’s epistles are a commentary on the doctrines flowing from the death and resurrection of Christ, so James’s epistle has a close connection with Christ’s teaching during his life on earth, especially his Sermon on the Mount. In both the Sermon on the Mount and the Epistle of James, the law is represented as fulfilled in love, and the very language is remarkably similar (cf. <a href="?bref=Jas.1.2">Jas 1:2</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.5.12">Mt 5:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.1.4">Jas 1:4</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.5.48">Mt 5:48</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.1.5">Jas 1:5</a> and <a href="?bref=Jas.5.14-15">5:14-15</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.7.7-11">Mt 7:7-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.13">Jas 2:13</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.5.7">Mt 5:7</a> and <a href="?bref=Matt.6.14-15">6:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.10">Jas 2:10</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.5.19">Mt 5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.4.4">Jas 4:4</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.6.24">Mt 6:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.4.11">Jas 4:11</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.7.1-2">Mt 7:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.5.2">Jas 5:2</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.6.19">Mt 6:19</a>). The whole spirit of this epistle breathes the same gospel-righteousness that the Sermon on the Mount inculcates as the highest realization of the law. James’s own character as “the Just” suited this coincidence (cf. <a href="?bref=Jas.1.20">Jas 1:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.10">2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.3.18">3:18</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.5.20">Mt 5:20</a>). It also fitted him for presiding over a church still zealous for the law (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.18-24">Acts 21:18-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.2.12">Gal 2:12</a>). If any could win the Jews to the gospel, he was the most likely one because he presented a pattern of OT righteousness, combined with evangelical faith (cf. also <a href="?bref=Jas.2.8">Jas 2:8</a> with <a href="?bref=Matt.5.44,48">Mt 5:44, 48</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</p>
<p class="fl">Many scholars confirm an early date for James’s epistle, even as early as <span class="era">AD</span> 45–49, because the whole orientation of the epistle fits the early history of the church, an era in which many Jewish Christians had not made a complete severance from Judaism. Thus, James uses the terms “the twelve tribes” (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.1">Jas 1:1</a>) and “the synagogue” (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.2">2:2</a>, Greek); he speaks as an OT prophet (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.1-20">5:1ff</a>.) and as one fond of OT proverbs (cf. <a href="?bref=Jas.1.5">Jas 1:5</a> with <a href="?bref=Pr.2.6">Prv 2:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.1.19">Jas 1:19</a> with <a href="?bref=Pr.29.20">Prv 29:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.3.18">Jas 3:18</a> with <a href="?bref=Pr.11.30">Prv 11:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.4.13-16">Jas 4:13-16</a> with <a href="?bref=Pr.27.1">Prv 27:1</a>; and <a href="?bref=Jas.5.20">Jas 5:20</a> with <a href="?bref=Pr.10.12">Prv 10:12</a>). James’s message, as was noted earlier, closely follows Jesus’ sermons. His message does not deal with the Jewish/Gentile problems that arose in the 50s and 60s. Moreover, he, unlike Peter, Jude, and John (in their epistles), did not deal with false teachings. All these facts point to an early date. This date is probably before <span class="era">AD</span> 50, when the first Jerusalem Council assembled to discuss the Jewish/Gentile problem (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.1-41">Acts 15:1ff</a>.). Also, the date is probably after <span class="era">AD</span> 44, the time of the persecution instigated by Herod Agrippa (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.1">12:1</a>). This persecution would have caused many Jewish Christians to leave Jerusalem and thereby be “the dispersed” (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.1">Jas 1:1</a>). Thus, James should be dated <span class="era">AD</span> 45–49. As such, the Epistle of James was the first NT book to be written. If these dates are not accurate, then we are, at least, sure that it was written before <span class="era">AD</span> 61 or 62, the time of James’s martyrdom, according to Josephus.</p>
<p>Although a number of suggestions have been made from time to time about the origin of the book, there can be little doubt that the letter was written in Palestine. The author makes allusions that are Near Eastern generally and Palestinian particularly (cf. “the early and late rain,” <a href="?bref=Jas.5.7">5:7</a>; the spring of brackish water, <a href="?bref=Jas.3.11">3:11</a>; the fig, olive, and vine, <a href="?bref=Jas.3.12">3:12</a>; and the “scorching heat,” <a href="?bref=Jas.1.11">1:11</a>).</p>
<p>The contents of the letter indicate clearly that James was writing to Jewish Christians. They are called “the twelve tribes,” a title of Israel (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.1">1:1</a>); their Christianity is assumed in <a href="?bref=Jas.2.1">2:1</a>; their place of meeting is called a synagogue (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.2">2:2</a>); and they are told about the compassion of “the Lord Almighty” (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.4">5:4</a>)—a name for God used in the OT. In the shorter, disconnected passages of the letter, it is impossible to discover anything about the readers’ circumstances. Most of these exhortations are general and relate to social and spiritual conditions one might find among any group of Christians in any age. The more extended passages that deal with social conditions (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.1-12">2:1-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.5.1-11">5:1-11</a>) do provide information about the readers’ situation. James is addressing poor Christians who are employed as farm laborers by wealthy landowners. A few rich may be included among his Jewish Christian readers (cf. <a href="?bref=Jas.4.13-17">4:13-17</a>), but James is primarily concerned with the poor. His statements denouncing the rich are reminiscent of the OT prophets, especially Amos.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeofWritingandTheologicalTeaching">Purpose of Writing and Theological Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">The letter of James was written (1) to strengthen Jewish Christians undergoing trial (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.2-4,13-15">Jas 1:2-4, 13-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.5.7-11">5:7-11</a>); (2) to correct a misunderstanding of the Pauline doctrine of justification by faith (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.14-26">2:14-26</a>); and (3) to pass down to first-generation Christians a wealth of practical wisdom.</p>
<p>James’s theology is not dogmatic; it omits the great theological themes that dominate Paul’s writings and play such an important role in the rest of the books of the NT. James makes no mention of the Incarnation, and the name of Christ appears only twice (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.1">1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.2.1">2:1</a>). No mention is made of Christ’s sufferings, death, or resurrection.</p>
<p>James’s theology is practical and has a decided Jewish flavor. The distinctive Christian features, of course, are there. James has simply mingled the two to produce a Jewish-Christian document.</p>
<p>The outstanding theological themes of the letter are as follows:</p>
<p class="h3">Temptations and Trials</p>
<p class="fl">The typically Jewish teachings—joy in trials and the use of trials for the building and perfecting of character—are both found in the letter (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.2-4">1:2-4</a>). James also discusses the origin of temptation (vv <a href="?bref=Jas.1.13-15">13-15</a>). Here the author comes into conflict with contemporary Jewish theology. The rabbinical solution to the problem of the origin of sin was that there was an evil tendency in man that enticed man to sin. The rabbis reasoned that since God is the Creator of all things, including the evil impulse in people, they are not responsible for their sins. No, says James. “And remember, no one who wants to do wrong should ever say, ‘God is tempting me.’ God is never tempted to do wrong, and he never tempts anyone else either. Temptation comes from the lure of our own evil desires” (vv <a href="?bref=Jas.1.13-14">13-14</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p class="h3">Law</p>
<p class="fl">The entire letter is concerned with ethical teaching; there is no mention of the central gospel truths of Christ’s death and resurrection. James presupposes the gospel and presents the ethical side of Christianity as a perfect law. He seems to be reassuring his Jewish-Christian readers that for them there is still law (the priceless possession of every Jew).</p>
<p>The law (ethical teaching of Christianity) is a perfect law (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.25">1:25</a>) because it was perfected by Jesus Christ. It is also a law of freedom—that is, a law that applies to those who have freedom, not from law, but from sin and self through the “word of truth.” Thus “law” is a Palestinian-Christian Jew’s way of describing the ethical teaching of the Christian faith, the standard of conduct for the believer in Jesus Christ.</p>
<p>This tendency to describe Christian ethical teaching as law is found in <a href="?bref=Jas.2.8-13">2:8-13</a>, a passage that arises out of a rebuke against the favoritism that James’s readers were showing toward the rich. This favoritism was being condoned by an appeal to the law of love to one’s neighbor. So James writes, “It is good when you truly obey our Lord’s royal command” (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.8">2:8</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The “royal command” is for those who are of God’s kingdom; it is the rule of faith for those who have willingly subjected themselves to God’s rule. The identification of law with the ethical side of Christianity runs through the entire letter.</p>
<p class="h3">Faith and Works</p>
<p class="fl">Faith plays an important role in the theology of James. The basic element of piety (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.3">1:3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jas.2.5">2:5</a>) is belief in God—not merely belief in his existence but belief in his character as being good and benevolent in his dealings with mankind (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.6">1:6</a>). Faith includes belief in the power of God and in his ability to perform miraculous acts; it is closely associated with prayer (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.15-16">5:15-16</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jas.1.6">1:6</a>). James has a dynamic concept of faith and clearly goes beyond Judaism when he speaks of faith directed toward the Lord Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.1">2:1</a>).</p>
<p>Similarities exist between the concept of faith in James and that concept in the teachings of Jesus. For the Lord Jesus, also, faith meant gaining access to the divine power and is often associated with healing (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.21.22">Mt 21:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.5.34">Mk 5:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.11.24">11:24</a>).</p>
<p>The best-known passage in which faith is mentioned is <a href="?bref=Jas.2.14-26">James 2:14-26</a>, where it is contrasted with works. From a close study of this passage, it can be determined that James is not contradicting Paul. For both James and Paul, faith is directed toward the Lord Jesus Christ; such faith will always produce good works. The faith of which James speaks is not faith in the Hebraic sense of trust in God that results in moral action. This is not recognized as <span class="ital">true</span> faith by James (cf. “if a man says he has faith,” <a href="?bref=Jas.2.14">2:14</a>), and Paul would agree with him.</p>
<p>James’s use of the word “works” differs significantly from Paul’s. For James, “works” are works of faith, the ethical outworking of true spirituality and include especially the “work of love” (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.8">2:8</a>). (Paul would probably call such works “the fruit of the Spirit.”) When Paul uses the word “works,” he usually has in mind the works of the law whereby people attempt to establish their own righteousness before God. It is against such theological heresy that Paul’s strongest polemics are addressed in the letters to the Galatians and Romans.</p>
<p class="h3">Wisdom</p>
<p class="fl">James’s concept of wisdom also reveals the Jewish background of the letter. Wisdom is primarily practical, not philosophical. It is not to be identified with reasoning power or the ability to apprehend intellectual problems; it has nothing to do with the questions <span class="ital">how</span> or <span class="ital">why.</span> It is to be sought by earnest prayer and is a gift from God (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.5">Jas 1:5</a>). Both of these ideas find their roots in the Wisdom Literature of the Jews (cf. <a href="?bref=Pr.2.6">Prv 2:6</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.7.7">Wisd of Sol 7:7</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.1.1">Ecclus 1:1</a>). The wise man demonstrates his wisdom by his good life (<a href="?bref=Jas.3.13">Jas 3:13</a>), whereas the wisdom that produces jealousy and selfishness is not God’s kind of wisdom (vv <a href="?bref=Jas.3.15-16">15-16</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Doctrine of the End Time</p>
<p class="fl">Three important end-time themes are touched upon in the letter.</p>
<p class="h4">The Kingdom of God</p>
<p class="fl">Mention of the kingdom of God grows out of a discussion of favoritism in the first half of chapter <a href="?bref=Jas.2.1-26">2</a>. No favoritism is to be shown to the rich, for James asks, “Hasn’t God chosen the poor in this world to be rich in faith? Aren’t they the ones who will inherit the kingdom God promised to those who love him?” (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.5">2:5</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). This echoes our Lord’s teaching in <a href="?bref=Luke.6.20">Luke 6:20</a>: “God blesses you who are poor, for the Kingdom of God is given to you” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). The kingdom is the reign of God partially realized in this life but fully realized in the life to come (cf. “promised,” <a href="?bref=Jas.2.5">Jas 2:5</a>).</p>
<p class="h4">Judgment</p>
<p class="fl">This is a dominant end-time theme of the letter. In <a href="?bref=Jas.2.12">2:12</a>, the readers are admonished to speak and act, remembering that they will be judged under the law of liberty, and they are reminded that judgment is without mercy to one who has shown no mercy. In other words, judgment will be administered according to “works of love.” In <a href="?bref=Jas.3.1">3:1</a>, James addresses teachers and reminds them that privilege is another basis on which God judges.</p>
<p>The theme of judgment again appears in <a href="?bref=Jas.5.1-6">5:1-6</a>, and here the author reaches prophetic heights. God’s judgment will fall on the wealthy landowners who have lived self-indulgent, irresponsible lives. Not only have they cheated their poor tenant farmers; they have even “condemned and killed good people who had no power to defend themselves against you [the landowners]” (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.6">5:6</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). All this has made them ripe for judgment (“your hearts are nice and fat, ready for the slaughter”—v <a href="?bref=Jas.5.5">5</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>The final passage on judgment (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.9">5:9</a>) is addressed to those who are exploited or suffering. James’s word of exhortation is that they are not to grumble against each other. Judging is God’s business, and the Judge is close at hand.</p>
<p class="h4">The Second Coming</p>
<p class="fl">The hope of Christ’s coming is presented as the great stimulus for Christian living. Every kind of suffering and trial must be endured because the coming of Christ is at hand (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.8">5:8</a>). This expectancy is powerful and immediate—like that found in the Thessalonian letters.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="fl">In the true spirit of Wisdom Literature, James touches upon many subjects. His short, abrupt paragraphs have been likened to a string of pearls—each is an entity in itself. Some transitions exist, but they are often difficult to find and James moves quickly from one subject to another.</p>
<p>The author begins by identifying himself as the “slave of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ,” and his readers as the “twelve tribes in the dispersion” (see <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg)—that is, the Jewish Christians who left Jerusalem and Israel due to persecution.</p>
<p>His first word is one of encouragement. Trials are to be counted as joy because they are God’s way of testing the believer, and they produce spiritual maturity. If the reason for a trial is not clear, God can and will give the answer. He is a lavish giver of wisdom to those who really want it (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.5-8">1:5-8</a>).</p>
<p>A poor Christian should be proud of his exalted position in Jesus Christ, and a rich Christian should be glad that he has discovered there are more important things than wealth. Riches are transitory, like quickly wilting flowers under the hot Palestine sun (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.9-11">1:9-11</a>).</p>
<p>God promises life to those who endure trials. One must not blame God for temptation, for it is contrary to his very nature either to be tempted or to tempt people. Temptation has its origin in people’s selfish desire—a desire that, when brought to full fruition, produces death (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.12-15">1:12-15</a>). God is not the origin of temptation but the source of all good. He has given people his best gift, the gift of new life, and this has come through the gospel (vv <a href="?bref=Jas.1.16-18">16-18</a>).</p>
<p>The proper attitude toward the Word of Truth is receptivity, not anger, and effective listening to that word involves spiritual preparation of heart and mind. Such a reception of the word brings salvation (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.19-21">1:19-21</a>). The word is to be acted upon, not merely listened to. To be a passive hearer is to be like a man who sees himself in a mirror, and because he takes such a fleeting glance, forgets what he sees. An active hearer, one who takes a long look in the mirror of God’s Word, will become a doer, and God will bring great blessing into his life (vv <a href="?bref=Jas.1.22-25">22-25</a>).</p>
<p>True religion is an intensely practical thing. It involves such things as controlling one’s tongue, looking after the needs of orphans and widows, and adopting a nonworldly lifestyle (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.26-27">1:26-27</a>).</p>
<p>Favoritism and faith in Jesus Christ do not go together. It is wrong to show favoritism to a rich man when he comes into the assembly and to ignore a poor man. God has chosen poor people to be heirs of his kingdom. Furthermore, to show favoritism to the rich does not make sense, since they are the very ones who drag Christians into court and blaspheme the name of Christ (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.1-7">2:1-7</a>). If, by showing deference to the rich, the royal law—to love one’s neighbor as oneself —is fulfilled, well and good. But to show favoritism is sin, and such sin will be judged by God. In order to be a lawbreaker one has only to break a single law (vv <a href="?bref=Jas.2.8-13">8-13</a>).</p>
<p>Can a faith that does not produce works save a person? What good is a faith that does not respond to human need? Such a faith is dead. Someone will object by saying that there are “faith Christians” and there are “works Christians.” But this is not so. True faith is always demonstrated by works. It is not enough to have orthodox beliefs. Even the demons are theologically orthodox! Abraham, by offering up Isaac, is an example of how true faith and works go together. Even Rahab the prostitute demonstrated her faith by protecting the spies at Jericho. So faith and works are inseparable (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.14-26">2:14-26</a>).</p>
<p>Not many people should become spiritual teachers, because of the awesome responsibility involved. All of us are subject to mistakes, especially mistakes of the tongue, because the tongue is almost impossible to control. It is like a destructive blaze set by hell itself. The tongue is also inconsistent; it is used both to praise God and to curse men. Such inconsistency ought not to be (<a href="?bref=Jas.3.1-12">3:1-12</a>).</p>
<p>True wisdom will always evidence itself in ethical living, whereas false wisdom produces jealousy and selfish ambition (<a href="?bref=Jas.3.13-18">3:13-18</a>).</p>
<p>Strife and conflict arise out of illegitimate desires. Failure to have what one wants arises either from not asking God for it or from asking for the wrong thing. To be a friend of the world is to be an enemy of God, for God is a jealous God and will brook no rivals. He also opposes the proud but offers abundant grace to the humble (<a href="?bref=Jas.4.1-10">4:1-10</a>).</p>
<p>To speak against a brother or sister, or to judge them, is to speak against God’s law and to judge it. The Christian’s proper role is to be a doer of the law, not a judge. The role of judge belongs to God alone (<a href="?bref=Jas.4.11-12">4:11-12</a>).</p>
<p>Life is uncertain. Therefore, plans for traveling or doing business should be made with the realization that all are subject to the will of God. To do otherwise is to be boastful and arrogant. When what is right is clearly known and one fails to do it, that is sin (<a href="?bref=Jas.4.13-17">4:13-17</a>).</p>
<p>Judgment is coming to the rich because they are hoarding their wealth instead of using it for good purposes. God is not unmindful of the cries of the poor whom the rich have cheated and unjustly condemned. He is preparing the selfish, unscrupulous rich for a day of awful judgment (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.1-6">5:1-6</a>).</p>
<p>In the midst of suffering and injustice, the poor are to be patient for Christ’s coming, as the farmer must be patient as he waits for God to send the rains to cause his crops to grow and ripen. The return of Christ is at hand and therefore complaining and judging one another must cease. Job is a good example of patience and endurance in suffering. One need not use oaths to guarantee the truthfulness of his statements. A single yes or no is sufficient (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.7-12">5:7-12</a>).</p>
<p>Suffering should elicit prayer, cheerfulness, and praise. When believers are sick, they should call the elders of the church to pray for them and anoint them with oil. God has promised to answer such prayers. If the sickness is due to personal sin, and if that sin is confessed, God will forgive. Elijah is a classic example of how the prayer of a righteous man has powerful results (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.13-18">5:13-18</a>).</p>
<p>If a Christian sees that another Christian has strayed from the truth and is able to bring him or her back into fellowship with Christ and his church, the consequences will be (1) that the sinner will be saved from death, and (2) that God will forgive the erring Christian (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.19-20">5:19-20</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BrothersofJesus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Brothers of Jesus</a>; <a href="?item=JamesPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">James (Person)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>