<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Jehiel">
  <title>Jehiel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEHIEL</p>
<p class="list">1. KJV spelling of Jeiel, King Saul’s ancestor, in <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.35">1 Chronicles 9:35</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Jeiel_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jeiel #2</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. KJV spelling of Jeiel, Hotham’s son, in <a href="?bref=1Chr.11.44">1 Chronicles 11:44</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Jeiel_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jeiel #3</a>.</p>
<p class="list">3. A Levite musician who, along with other Levites appointed by David, played a psaltery at the removal of the ark to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.18-20">1 Chr 15:18-20</a>). Afterward, he was appointed to a permanent ministry of music in the sanctuary (<a href="?bref=1Chr.16.5">1 Chr 16:5</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Levite of the family of Gershon; a chief of the house of Ladan (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.8">1 Chr 23:8</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg). He was in charge of the temple treasury during David’s reign—an office that seems to have continued in the family (<a href="?bref=1Chr.29.8">29:8</a>)—and founder of a priestly family called Jehieli or Jehielites (<a href="?bref=1Chr.26.21-22">26:21-22</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Hacmoni’s son who, with David’s uncle Jonathan (a counselor and a scribe), was appointed to take care of the king’s sons as a tutor and adviser (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.32">1 Chr 27:32</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Son of King Jehoshaphat of Judah, placed by his father over one of the fortified cities of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.21.2">2 Chr 21:2</a>). He and five brothers were slain by Jehoram when Jehoram became king.</p>
<p class="list"> 7. One of the Kohathite Levites from the family of Heman who assisted in King Hezekiah’s reforms (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.14">2 Chr 29:14</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span> “Jehuel”). He may be the same Levite who was assigned to oversee the reception and distribution of the sacred offerings (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.13">2 Chr 31:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. One of the chief officers of the temple at the time of Josiah’s religious reformation (<a href="?bref=2Chr.35.8">2 Chr 35:8</a>); he contributed many sacrifices for the great Passover service.</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Father of Obadiah from Joab’s house; he returned with Ezra from Babylon (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.9">Ezr 8:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. One of the sons of Elam and father of Shecaniah. He was associated with Ezra’s marriage reforms (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.2">Ezr 10:2</a>) and was perhaps the same Jehiel who was among those who divorced their foreign wives (v <a href="?bref=Ezra.10.26">26</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Priest who was among those Ezra persuaded to divorce their foreign wives (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.21">Ezr 10:21</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>