<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Jehoiachin">
  <title>Jehoiachin</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEHOIACHIN</p>
<p class="fl">King of Judah for a very brief time (598–597 <span class="era">BC</span>). He was the son of Jehoiakim and Nehushta, the daughter of Elnathan of Jerusalem (possibly the Elnathan mentioned by Jeremiah, cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.26.22">Jer 26:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.36.12,25">36:12, 25</a>). The name Jehoiachin means “Yahweh will uphold,” and variations include Coniah (<a href="?bref=Jer.22.24,28">Jer 22:24, 28</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.37.1">37:1</a>), Jeconiah (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.16-17">1 Chr 3:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.2.6">Est 2:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.24.1">Jer 24:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.27.20">27:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.28.4">28:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.29.2">29:2</a>), and Jechoniah (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.11-12">Mt 1:11-12</a>; <span class="sc">kjv</span> “Jechonias”). Jehoiachin was 18 years old when he was installed as king upon his father’s death, and he ruled for only three months and ten days in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.8">2 Kgs 24:8</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Chr.36.9">2 Chr 36:9</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg). He inherited a vassal kingdom in revolt. Besieged by the armies of the Babylonian overlord Nebuchadnezzar, Jehoiachin had little choice but to capitulate in the face of insurmountable odds. According to the Babylonian Chronicle, records based on the official annals of the Babylonian kings, Nebuchadnezzar entered Syro-Palestine in December of 598 <span class="era">BC</span> and took Jerusalem on March 16, 597. The Babylonians plundered the palace and temple treasuries. Along with Jehoiachin, his family, prominent military leaders, royal officials, and artisans were taken prisoner and led away to exile in Babylon. Before returning to Babylon, the victorious king placed Jehoiachin’s uncle Mattaniah, now named Zedekiah, on the throne in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.12-17">2 Kgs 24:12-17</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Chr.36.10">2 Chr 36:10</a>).</p>
<p>According to Jeremiah, the trauma caused by the Babylonian invasion of Judah, and the consequent political upheaval prompted by a succession of three kings in four months, had little impact on the people spiritually (<a href="?bref=Jer.37.1-38.28">Jer 37–38</a>). This same prophet of God forecast Jehoiachin’s exile and predicted he would have no descendants succeeding him on the throne (<a href="?bref=Jer.22.24-30">22:24-30</a>). In contrast, the false prophet Hananiah prophesied Jehoiachin would be restored to the throne of Judah within two years (<a href="?bref=Jer.28.3-4,11">28:3-4, 11</a>; cf. vv <a href="?bref=Jer.28.12-17">12-17</a>).</p>
<p>Jehoiachin’s continuing royal status as the legitimate claimant to the Judahite kingship was reflected in the fact that Ezekiel’s oracles are dated to the year of Jehoiachin’s exile, not Zedekiah’s reign (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.2">Ez 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.8.1">8:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.1">20:1</a>; etc.). Babylonian records confirm this recognition of Jehoiachin’s former position; he retained his title of king and received favorable treatment from the Babylonians. He is certainly the “Yaukin, king of the land of Yahuda” listed in one of the cuneiform tablets; this tablet contains inventories of rations of oil and barley for the king and his five sons and implies they were not imprisoned but living a fairly normal life in Babylonia. At some point Jehoiachin must have been imprisoned, however, because later, during the reign of Evil-merodach, he was released from prison and granted dining privileges with the Babylonian king (c. 562 <span class="era">BC</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.27-30">2 Kgs 25:27-30</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.52.31-34">Jer 52:31-34</a>). Whether he was imprisoned for attempting to escape or because of Judah’s rebellion against Babylon under Zedekiah is unclear.</p>
<p>Jehoiachin’s name appears in Matthew’s genealogy of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.11-12">Mt 1:11-12</a>), and some contend that this contradicts Jeremiah’s oracle of judgment against the king’s descendants (<a href="?bref=Jer.22.30">Jer 22:30</a>). Yet it is possible to understand Haggai’s blessing of Zerubabbel (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.20-23">Hg 2:20-23</a>) as a reversal of Jeremiah’s curse and the reinstatement of Jehoiachin’s line on the Davidic—and ultimately messianic—throne (cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.56.3-5">Is 56:3-5</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>; <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>