<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Jehu">
  <title>Jehu</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEHU</p>
<p class="list">1. Prophet and son of the “seer” Hanani (<a href="?bref=2Chr.16.7">2 Chr 16:7</a>), who denounced Baasha for following in the ways of Jeroboam (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.1-7">1 Kgs 16:1-7</a>). In addition to continuing the heretical worship of the golden calves at Bethel and Dan, Baasha also assassinated Nadab, the son of Jeroboam (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.25-32">15:25-32</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Jehu later rebuked Jehoshaphat, king of Judah, for helping Ahab the king of Israel in his wars against the Arameans (<a href="?bref=2Chr.19.1-2">2 Chr 19:1-2</a>). The writings of this prophet were included in one of the records of the reign of Jehoshaphat, <span class="ital">The Book of the Kings of Israel</span> (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.34">2 Chr 20:34</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Important army officer during the reigns of Ahab and Jehoram (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.25">2 Kgs 9:25</a>), who in reaction to the economic and religious abuses of the house of Omri was anointed as king of the northern kingdom of Israel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.16-17">1 Kgs 19:16-17</a>). In the following revolution he exterminated the royal house of Israel, the king of Judah, and a royal party from the south (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.1-10.36">2 Kgs 9–10</a>). He executed the worshipers of Baal in order to revive true worship in Israel. As king, he ruled in Samaria 28 years (841–814 <span class="era">BC</span>) and began a dynasty that lasted some 100 years.</p>
<p class="list-text">In the time of Jehu the prophets were engaged in a religious equivalent of war with the adherents of the Tyrian Baal. Elijah met and defeated the Canaanite priests on Mt Carmel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.17-40">1 Kgs 18:17-40</a>). Later he and then Elisha were commissioned to anoint Jehu as king. The prophets waited until the time was right (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.1-10">2 Kgs 9:1-10</a>), at which time Elisha sent a “son of the prophets” to Ramoth-gilead to designate Jehu as the monarch.</p>
<p class="list-text">Jehu left his siege of Ramoth-gilead in northern Transjordan to meet the king of Israel in Jezreel. There he killed King Jehoram and Ahaziah, the king of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.17-28">2 Kgs 9:17-28</a>). His bloody ways continued as he extinguished the royal house of Ahab (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.1-17">10:1-17</a>) and 42 ambassadors of goodwill from Judah (apparently without provocation, vv <a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.12-14">12-14</a>). Israel’s bloodbath finally ended in Samaria. There Jehu cunningly vowed to serve Baal with a zeal greater than that of Ahab. Unsuspecting devotees of Baal gathered in great numbers to join in a festival sacrifice. Instead, the devotees themselves became the sacrifice, and the house of Baal in Samaria was destroyed and desecrated by turning its ruins into a latrine (vv <a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.18-27">18-27</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Political and economic problems also contributed to the unrest. Under the reign of Ahab and Jezebel, justice was corrupted. The poor lost their land in the drought and their property rights were ignored (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.18.5-6">1 Kgs 18:5-6</a>). Jehu threw the body of Jehoram into the field of Naboth the Jezreelite (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.9.25-26">2 Kgs 9:25-26</a>) as justice for the crime of Ahab and Jezebel (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.19">1 Kgs 21:19</a>; cf. v <a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.13">13</a>). But religious passions dominated the cause. Jehu called his slaughter of the house of Omri his “zeal for the Lord.” Jehonadab, a Recabite, joined Jehu as he traveled toward Samaria (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.15-17">2 Kgs 10:15-17</a>). Recabites opposed social and economic developments that took place in the northern kingdom under Ahab. They followed a strict moral code and lived a simple life (<a href="?bref=Jer.35.1-19">Jer 35</a>). Since Recabites represented the most conservative elements of Yahwism, they became natural allies for the reform of Jehu.</p>
<p class="list-text">Jehu’s revolution seriously weakened the worship of Baal. Although not all of the adherents were eliminated, Baalism no longer remained the official religion of the state (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.28">2 Kgs 10:28</a>). Rather, Baalism united with Yahwism to form the sinister syncretistic religion that was denounced by Hosea.</p>
<p class="list-text">Politically, the revolt of Jehu was disastrous. The triple alliance between Tyre, Israel, and Judah was shattered by the atrocities. Israel, now isolated, became easy prey for Assyria and Syria. Jehu attempted to buy some help from Assyria by paying tribute to Shalmaneser III. That event is pictured on the Black Obelisk in a relief from the campaign of 841 <span class="era">BC</span>. An inscription names “Jehu, son of Omri,” as the one kneeling before Shalmaneser.</p>
<p class="list-text">After the Assyrian threat dissipated in 838 <span class="era">BC</span>, Hazael, king of Aram-Damascus, conquered all of Israelite Transjordan as far as the Arnon (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.32-33">2 Kgs 10:32-33</a>). In a second campaign in 815 <span class="era">BC</span>, Hazael moved across the Jordan River, through the Jezreel plain, and down the coast, conquering the land as far as Gath in the northern Shephelah. There the son of Jehu, Jehoahaz, paid tribute to Hazael (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.12.18">12:18</a>). The revolution weakened Israel both politically and economically.</p>
<p class="list-text">Later generations spoke of the massacre of the house of Omri with horror (<a href="?bref=Hos.1.4">Hos 1:4</a>). Jehu did not destroy the golden calves of Jeroboam, and so continued the syncretistic worship at Bethel and Dan. In the final analysis the revolution, which was meant to purge Israel of oppression and false religion, succeeded in doing neither.</p>
<p class="list">3. Member of Judah’s tribe, the son of Obed and Azariah’s father (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.38">1 Chr 2:38</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Prince of Simeon’s tribe, and the son of Joshibiah, who, along with others, migrated from the approaches to the valley of Gedor eastward in search of good pasture (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.35">1 Chr 4:35</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. One of the skilled warriors who joined David at Ziklag. Interestingly, he was of Saul’s tribe, Benjamin, and from Anathoth, to which Abiathar of the priests of Eli was later banished (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.3">1 Chr 12:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>