<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JeremiahPerson">
  <title>Jeremiah (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JEREMIAH (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. Prophet to Judah before its fall in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>; his name is also spelled “Jeremias” (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.14">Mt 16:14</a>) and “Jeremy” (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.17">Mt 2:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.27.9">27:9</a>) in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>.</p>
<p class="list-text">Jeremiah was born in the village of Anathoth, about three miles (4.8 kilometers) northeast of Jerusalem. His father’s name was Hilkiah, and he belonged to the tribe of Benjamin. His call came in the 13th year of King Josiah (640–609 <span class="era">BC</span>). He refers to himself as “a child” when called (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.6">Jer 1:6</a>), but the Hebrew word is not the same as used in <a href="?bref=Jer.30.6">Jeremiah 30:6</a> and <a href="?bref=Jer.31.8">31:8</a> and cannot be limited to preadolescence. He was probably referring to his inexperience rather than to his age. Jeremiah was born about 657 <span class="era">BC</span> during the reign of the wicked king Manasseh, while the great Ashurbanipal, who had shaken the world by sacking the ancient Egyptian city of Thebes in 663 <span class="era">BC</span>, ruled a world empire from Assyria.</p>
<p class="list-text">God informed Jeremiah that he had consecrated and appointed him before birth (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.4-5">Jer 1:4-5</a>). Jeremiah first shrank with a sense of inadequacy and fear: “O Sovereign <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, . . . I can’t speak for you! I’m too young!” (v <a href="?bref=Jer.1.6">6</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). God would not allow Jeremiah to excuse himself. He was assured that words would be given him to speak, and guidance given for the way (v <a href="?bref=Jer.1.7">7</a>). He was promised protection (v <a href="?bref=Jer.1.18">18</a>) and deliverance (v <a href="?bref=Jer.1.8">8</a>) despite opposition (v <a href="?bref=Jer.1.19">19</a>). God touched his mouth, signifying divine inspiration of his words, and gave the sign of a branch from an almond tree, explaining that the Lord is watching (see <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg). The third sign was the boiling pot (v <a href="?bref=Jer.1.13">13</a>) facing from the north, picturing the source and fury of impending disaster.</p>
<p class="list-text">Thus the tone of Jeremiah’s life ministry was set: judgment, disaster, danger, defeat, and impending death for the nation.</p>
<p class="h2-list">Early Ministry</p>
<p class="list-text-fl">The messages given by Jeremiah during his first five years of ministry may have been instrumental in the great revival of 622 <span class="era">BC</span>. Those cooperating with King Josiah in the reformation and friendly with Jeremiah included Ahikam and his father, Shaphan (<a href="?bref=Jer.26.24">Jer 26:24</a>); Gedaliah, Ahikam’s son (<a href="?bref=Jer.39.14">39:14</a>), who later became governor; Acbor, son of Micaiah, also called Abdon, whose son Elnathan joined the opposition (<a href="?bref=Jer.26.22">26:22</a>) but later repented (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.25">36:25</a>); and Asaiah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.34.20">2 Chr 34:20</a>). The prophets Nahum and Zephaniah also influenced the reform movement, which must have climaxed under the preaching of Habakkuk and Jeremiah, the priestly ministry of Hilkiah, and the prophecies of Huldah the prophetess. During the reign of King Josiah, Jeremiah spoke without the fear of persecution that plagued his later ministry. Though the content of the book of Jeremiah sometimes appears to be fragmentary, most of chapters <a href="?bref=Jer.1.1-19.15">1–19</a> date to the time of Josiah.</p>
<p class="list-text">The finding of the lost Book of the Covenant in the temple debris may be the reason for the words in <a href="?bref=Jer.15.16">Jeremiah 15:16</a>: “Your words are what sustain me. They bring me great joy and are my heart’s delight” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). The words “So be it, <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (<a href="?bref=Jer.11.5">Jer 11:5</a>) in a context recalling the words of Moses in the Torah may be Jeremiah’s response after hearing King Josiah read the newly found book.</p>
<p class="list-text">Small towns and rural areas, including his hometown, heard Jeremiah’s denunciation of high places and idolatry. They sought to kill the young prophet, or at least to intimidate him (<a href="?bref=Jer.11.21">11:21</a>). Instead of being silent, Jeremiah asserted that his motivation was for their good and condemned their resistance to the truth as their greatest danger.</p>
<p class="list-text">Shortly after Jeremiah began his ministry, a number of world-changing events took place. Ashurbanipal died and the Assyrian Empire rapidly declined. Nabopolassar began a 21-year reign in Babylon, leading an expansion that culminated in his son Nebuchadnezzar’s subjugation of the known world. As the world news filtered in, Jeremiah turned more toward Jerusalem. His first temple speeches (chs <a href="?bref=Jer.7.1-10.25">7–10</a>) may have been uttered at this time.</p>
<p class="list-text">Nabopolassar felt his strength sufficient to launch an attack against Assyrian territory in 616 <span class="era">BC</span>, but he advanced cautiously because Psamtik I (Psammetichus) of Egypt appeared ready to aid Assyria. Cyaxares of Media pounced on Assyria when Babylon hesitated and took its most sacred city, Asshur, in 614 <span class="era">BC</span>. Babylon joined Media, along with Scythia, and waged an assault against Nineveh, which fell late in the summer of 612 <span class="era">BC</span>. The Assyrian Empire had shriveled to two small holdings, Haran and Carchemish.</p>
<p class="list-text">Nabopolassar took Haran in 610, and Ashuruballit, having escaped, appealed to Egypt for help at Carchemish. Neco, who had become pharaoh within the year, responded immediately. He marched through Judah without giving Josiah prior notice and asked that the Jews not bother him in view of his haste to go northward (<a href="?bref=2Chr.35.21">2 Chr 35:21</a>). Ignoring the request, Josiah pursued them to Megiddo and was wounded in the ensuing battle; he died in Jerusalem.</p>
<p class="h2-list">Ministry during the Reign of Jehoiakim</p>
<p class="list-text-fl">In place of Jehoahaz, Josiah’s fourth son, who reigned only three months, Pharaoh Neco enthroned Jehoiakim (Eliakim). Neco demanded heavy indemnity payments from Judah and took Jehoahaz prisoner as collateral to assure payment (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.31-33">2 Kgs 23:31-33</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Early in the reign of Jehoiakim, Jeremiah, moved by God’s Spirit, delivered his third temple speech (<a href="?bref=Jer.26.1-24">Jer 26</a>) on the occasion of one of the annual Jewish feasts. He called for the people to repent and to act on the basis of the revelation they had heard repeatedly from the Book of the Law. The barb of the sermon came in the warning: “This is what the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> says: If you will not listen to me and obey the law I have given you, and if you will not listen to my servants, the prophets—for I sent them again and again to warn you, but you would not listen to them—then I will destroy this Temple as I destroyed Shiloh, the place where the Tabernacle was located. And I will make Jerusalem an object of cursing in every nation on earth” (<a href="?bref=Jer.26.4-6">26:4-6</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Shiloh had been the heart of Jewish worship from Joshua to Samuel, but after being destroyed by the Philistines, it never revived. It served as an example of complete desolation following God’s judgment in the days of Eli.</p>
<p class="list-text">Crowds gathered rapidly and reacted angrily against Jeremiah. Priests and princes hurried to the New Gate, where a court was established to bring order and to control violence. Jehoiakim would be no help to Jeremiah, for he had refused to listen to God’s messages (<a href="?bref=Jer.22.21">Jer 22:21</a>). The priests and false prophets spoke against Jeremiah, calling him a traitor. Then some of the elders spoke to the people about Uriah, who had prophesied the same message. Rather than risk disaster, Ahikam persuaded the court to spare Jeremiah.</p>
<p class="list-text">Egypt controlled Palestine and Syria after the decay of the Assyrian Empire. In 606 <span class="era">BC</span> Egypt succeeded in annihilating a garrison city of Babylonian soldiers south of Carchemish and then reoccupied Carchemish to await the return blow from Babylon. This Egyptian victory meant persecution for Jeremiah, who was often accused of false prophecy (cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.20.1-18">Jer 20</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Jeremiah never had confidence in Egypt. Each time a Jewish leader would call for a new alliance with Egypt, Jeremiah repeated God’s message against it. Whenever a Jewish group fled to Egypt for security, Jeremiah warned of worse things in that land of false refuge (see <a href="?bref=Jer.44.26-27">Jer 44:26-27</a>). Jeremiah’s ode and prophecy in chapter <a href="?bref=Jer.46.1-28">46</a> poetically describe Egypt’s defeat at Carchemish, when Nabopolassar sent his son Nebuchadnezzar to destroy them (605 <span class="era">BC</span>). After smashing the Egyptian army at Carchemish, Nebuchadnezzar pursued the enemy through Judah. “Not a single man escaped to his own country,” reads the exaggerated Babylonian record. His father’s death, however, prevented him from invading Egypt, and he returned to Babylon to assume the throne. The following year Nebuchadnezzar, now king of Babylonia, returned to accept the homage of the rulers of Judah, Syria, and Phoenicia. On this occasion God gave Jeremiah his great 70-year prophecy (<a href="?bref=Jer.25.11-12">Jer 25:11-12</a>), which became the basis of <a href="?bref=Dan.9.2,24-27">Daniel 9:2, 24-27</a>.</p>
<p class="list-text">A year after the decisive battle at Carchemish, Baruch, Jeremiah’s scribe, finished recording all the dictated words of Jeremiah and was reading from this scroll at the temple. A report reached the king, who sent Jehudi, a servant, to fetch the scroll and read it to him. When this was done, Jehoiakim burned the scroll in spite of his counselors, who pleaded that the king not do it (<a href="?bref=Jer.36.23-25">Jer 36:23-25</a>). God’s message, soon rewritten, added a promise of fearful judgment on Jehoiakim (vv <a href="?bref=Jer.36.27-31">27-31</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Ambitious young Nebuchadnezzar determined to add Egypt to his dominion. In 601 <span class="era">BC</span> he led his forces through Judah again, but Neco had advance warning and was prepared for the onslaught. In the desert of Shur, Nebuchadnezzar suffered defeat. Encouraged by this display of Egyptian defensive strength, the pro-Egyptian parties in Judah asserted themselves, persuading Jehoiakim to lead them to freedom from Babylon by making an alliance with Egypt (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.1">2 Kgs 24:1</a>). But help from Egypt did not come (v <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.7">7</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">In 599 <span class="era">BC</span>, Nebuchadnezzar armed those surrounding the rebel Jewish kingdom to harass the Jews, which they willingly did (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.2">2 Kgs 24:2</a>). Evidently Jehoiakim lost his life in one of these raids. Since the people despised him, his body was thrown out without honorable burial, as Jeremiah had predicted (<a href="?bref=Jer.22.19">Jer 22:19</a>).</p>
<p class="h2-list">Ministry during the Reign of Zedekiah</p>
<p class="list-text-fl">Nebuchadnezzar’s siege of Jerusalem in 598 <span class="era">BC</span> lasted only a short time because the new king, Jehoiachin, crowned at age 18, knew resistance was useless. He gave himself up, with all his family and court, in March of 597 <span class="era">BC</span>, after serving as king about three months. The Babylonian Chronicle reads: “He [Nebuchadnezzar] seized the city and captured the king.”</p>
<p class="list-text">Jehoiachin was carried to Babylon along with 8,000 (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.16">2 Kgs 24:16</a>; cf. v <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.14">14</a>) officers, artisans, and executives (Ezekiel among them) and much booty. In his place Nebuchadnezzar appointed Zedekiah, Jehoiachin’s uncle, to rule. Zedekiah proceeded to organize his government with the less capable and inexperienced help left after the deportation.</p>
<p class="list-text">Jeremiah took up his thankless ministry, calling on the Jews to believe God, obey the laws of Babylon, and reject false hopes in Egypt. Zedekiah turned a deaf ear to these appeals, listening rather to the unwise advice of his counselors (<a href="?bref=Jer.37.1-2">Jer 37:1-2</a>). During the first year of Zedekiah’s rule, Jeremiah received the vision of the two baskets of figs. The Jews carried to Babylon were like good figs, while Zedekiah and those who trusted in Egypt were like rotten figs (<a href="?bref=Jer.24.1-8">24:1-8</a>). The reason for this reproachful description was that the Jews began plotting rebellion against Babylon along with Edom, Moab, Ammon, Tyre, and Sidon from the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah (<a href="?bref=Jer.27.1-3">27:1-3</a>), thus breaking their oath of loyalty to Nebuchadnezzar and repudiating God’s message through Jeremiah.</p>
<p class="list-text">In Egypt the pharaoh began to renew plans to organize dissidents within the Babylonian Empire to revolt. He hired Jewish soldiers to aid him in protecting his southern border. The Jewish soldiers settled on a Nile island called Elephantine, or Yeb (593–410 <span class="era">BC</span>). Jeremiah addressed an oracle to these Jews (ch <a href="?bref=Jer.44.1-30">44</a>). The treaty for Jews to help in Egypt evidently also assumed that Egyptians would aid Israel. When the Babylonians besieged Jerusalem in 589, Pharaoh Hophra came to the aid of Zedekiah. Nebuchadnezzar, ruling from Riblah, commanded that the siege against Jerusalem be lifted in order to make a surprise attack on Hophra (<a href="?bref=Jer.37.5">37:5</a>). The release gave Jeremiah an opportunity to journey to Anathoth to secure some family property (v <a href="?bref=Jer.37.12">12</a>). However, Irijah, captain of the guard, arrested Jeremiah in the Gate of Benjamin for defecting to the enemy, and he was beaten and flung into a dungeon. King Zedekiah brought him out after many days to obtain a prognostication. With characteristic boldness, Jeremiah told the king he would shortly become a captive. At the same time, Jeremiah requested relief from injustice for himself. He gained part of his request but continued as prisoner in the court of the guard.</p>
<p class="list-text">The Babylonian army chased Pharaoh Hophra back to Egypt and returned to crush Jerusalem without further mercy. The siege, which began in 589 <span class="era">BC</span>, was restored with rigor in January of 588, Zedekiah’s ninth year (<a href="?bref=Jer.39.1">39:1</a>). During this time, the Lord gave Jeremiah foreknowledge of a visit from a cousin who wished to sell a field near Anathoth (<a href="?bref=Jer.32.7-9">32:7-9</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.37.12">37:12</a>). Jeremiah bought the field as an object lesson to verify the message of restoration after a captivity of 70 years (<a href="?bref=Jer.29.10">29:10</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The armies of Babylon cut off all supplies from Jerusalem and were able to destroy the last two outlying Jewish fortresses of Lachish and Azekah (<a href="?bref=Jer.34.7">34:7</a>). Food became scarce. Disease spread. Undisposed-of sewage and impure cistern water caused pestilence. With increased distress came Jeremiah’s increased appeal for the city to surrender.</p>
<p class="list-text">Jeremiah remained in the prison court until the Babylonians breached the city wall in July of 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. The king escaped by night and succeeded in reaching the plains of Jericho but was captured there and taken to Riblah. Zedekiah’s family and counselors were killed; he himself was blinded and taken in chains to Babylon, where he died soon after (<a href="?bref=Jer.39.6-7">39:6-7</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Back in Jerusalem, Nebuzaradan, the Babylonian general, sent most of the Jews into captivity. Jeremiah, however, was granted special consideration; after being released from prison, he was placed under the care of Gedaliah, son of Ahikam.</p>
<p class="h2-list">After the Fall of Jerusalem</p>
<p class="list-text-fl">A month after the fall of Jerusalem, the city was burned and the walls broken down. Gedaliah was appointed governor of the remaining agricultural community, with headquarters at Mizpah. Jeremiah returned to Jerusalem, where, according to tradition, he took up his abode in a grotto near what is now known as Gordon’s Calvary. There he wrote the book of Lamentations.</p>
<p class="list-text">The Ammonite king Baalis, plotting rebellion against Babylon, instigated the murder of Gedaliah (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.13">40:13</a>). In the reaction that followed, the remaining people followed the leader Johanan ben Kareah to a camp near Bethlehem, intending to go to Egypt. They asked Jeremiah, at Jerusalem, to give guidance from the Lord, promising obedience. Jeremiah’s message required that they remain in Israel and not go to Egypt. Disobedience was complete and immediate. Fearing Babylon, they departed from Judah, taking Jeremiah with them, and entered Egypt (<a href="?bref=Jer.41.16-43.7">41:16–43:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Jeremiah did not stop his ministry in Egypt. His message at Tahpanhes (<a href="?bref=Jer.43.8-12">43:8-12</a>) assured a victorious conquest of the land by Nebuchadnezzar, which took place in 568–567 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="list-text">Jews from all parts of Egypt gathered to discuss their future as exiles. Jeremiah took the opportunity to denounce their idolatry. Jewish women as well as men argued that they had enjoyed prosperity while serving idols but had suffered since stopping. Jeremiah condemned their obdurate blindness to reality and gave God’s indictment. For a verifying sign, Jeremiah predicted that Pharaoh Hophra of Egypt would be assassinated (<a href="?bref=Jer.44.30">44:30</a>), which happened in 466 <span class="era">BC</span>. No later record of Jeremiah’s acts exists in the Bible. Tradition says Jeremiah was stoned to death by the people of the Jewish exile settlement in Tahpanhes.</p>
<p class="list-text">Though Jeremiah suffered continued rejection during his life, he has been honored by numerous apocryphal and traditional embellishments to his history. Jesus could well have had Jeremiah in mind when he said, “You build tombs for the prophets your ancestors killed and decorate the graves of the godly people your ancestors destroyed. . . . [You are] the descendants of those who murdered the prophets” (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.29-31">Mt 23:29-31</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=JeremiahBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jeremiah, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetProphetess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophet, Prophetess</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Family head in the Transjordan portion of Manasseh whom Tiglath-pileser took captive (<a href="?bref=1Chr.5.23-26">1 Chr 5:23-26</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.29">2 Kgs 15:29</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Father of Hamutal, a wife of King Josiah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.31">2 Kgs 23:31</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.18">24:18</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Ambidextrous Benjamite bowman and slinger who joined David at Ziklag (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.4">1 Chr 12:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5, 6. Two Gadite soldiers who joined David’s army (<a href="?bref=1Chr.12.10,13">1 Chr 12:10, 13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">7. Postexilic priest who with Nehemiah set his seal to the covenant, renewing the people’s promise to obey God’s laws (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.2">Neh 10:2</a>). He is mentioned again (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.34">12:34</a>) as part of the procession for the dedication of the new wall of Jerusalem.</p>
<p class="list">8. Priest who returned from exile with Zerubbabel (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.1">Neh 12:1</a>) and became head of a family of priests (v <a href="?bref=Neh.12.12">12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">9. Father of Jaazaniah, a Recabite who refused to drink wine (<a href="?bref=Jer.35.3">Jer 35:3</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>