<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JeshuaPerson">
  <title>Jeshua (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JESHUA (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. Levite and head of the ninth of 24 divisions of priests formed during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.24.11">1 Chr 24:11</a>). He was perhaps the forefather of 973 descendants who returned with Zerubbabel to Judah following the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.36">Ezr 2:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.39">Neh 7:39</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. One of the Levites assisting Kore in the distribution of the offerings among his fellow priests living in the priestly cities of Judah during the days of King Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.31.15">2 Chr 31:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Son of Jozadak (alternately “Jehozadak”) the high priest. Jozadak was deported by Nebuchadnezzar to Babylon (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.14-15">1 Chr 6:14-15</a>). Jeshua, Jozadak’s successor as high priest, returned with Zerubbabel to Jerusalem after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.2">Ezr 2:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.7">Neh 7:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.12.1">12:1</a>). Upon arrival, he led his fellow priests in making the altar of God (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.2">Ezr 3:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.5.2">5:2</a>) and eventually headed up a construction program to rebuild the temple (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.8">3:8</a>). Confirmed as God’s leader by Haggai and Zechariah (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1-14">Hg 1:1-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.2,4">2:2, 4</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.3.1-9">Zec 3:1-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.11">6:11</a>), Jeshua (alternately “Joshua” in these passages) resolutely resisted attempts by adversaries to infiltrate his people and hinder the work on the temple (<a href="?bref=Ezra.4.3">Ezr 4:3</a>). Joiakim was Jeshua’s son and successor as high priest, serving in the days of Nehemiah and Ezra (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.12,26">Neh 12:12, 26</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Descendant of Pahath-moab and the forefather of a family of Jews who returned with Zerubbabel to Judah following the Babylonian captivity (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.6">Ezr 2:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.11">Neh 7:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Father of a family of Levites who returned to Jerusalem with Zerubbabel (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.40">Ezr 2:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.43">Neh 7:43</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.12.8">12:8</a>). He and his sons were responsible for overseeing the workmen building the temple (<a href="?bref=Ezra.3.9">Ezr 3:9</a>; this Jeshua may be identical with #3 above).</p>
<p class="list">6. Levite and Jozabad’s father. Jozabad assisted Meremoth, Eleazar, and Noadiah with taking inventory of the temple’s precious metals and vessels during the days of Ezra (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.33">Ezr 8:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list">7. Ezer’s father. Ezer was ruler of Mizpah, who repaired a section of the Jerusalem wall during the days of Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.19">Neh 3:19</a>).</p>
<p class="list">8. Azaniah’s son and a leader of the Levites in the days of Ezra and Nehemiah. Jeshua assisted Ezra with teaching the people the law (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.7">Neh 8:7</a>) and later set his seal on Ezra’s covenant (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.9">10:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">9. Alternate spelling of Joshua, the son of Nun, in <a href="?bref=Neh.8.17">Nehemiah 8:17</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=JoshuaPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Joshua (Person) #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>