<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JoelPerson">
  <title>Joel (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JOEL (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list"> 1. Levite from the family of Kohath. He was Azariah’s son and an ancestor of Elkanah, the father of Samuel the prophet (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.1">1 Sm 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.36">1 Chr 6:36</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Oldest son of Samuel the prophet. He and his brother Abijah so corrupted the office of judge that the elders increased their demands for a king (<a href="?bref=1Sam.8.2-5">1 Sm 8:2-5</a>). He was the father of Heman the singer (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.33">1 Chr 6:33</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.17">15:17</a>). His name has been mistakenly translated “Vashni” in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> in <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.28">1 Chronicles 6:28</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Prince from one of the Simeonite families that emigrated to the valley of Gedor (<a href="?bref=1Chr.4.35">1 Chr 4:35</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Member of Reuben’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.5.4,8">1 Chr 5:4, 8</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Chief of Gad’s tribe residing in Bashan (<a href="?bref=1Chr.5.12">1 Chr 5:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Third of Izrahiah’s four named sons and a chief of Issachar’s tribe in David’s time (<a href="?bref=1Chr.7.3">1 Chr 7:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Nathan’s brother and one of David’s mighty men (<a href="?bref=1Chr.11.38">1 Chr 11:38</a>). He is alternately called Igal the son of Nathan in <a href="?bref=2Sam.23.36">2 Samuel 23:36</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Igal_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Igal #2</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Levite from the family of Gershon who participated in the royal procession that brought the ark of God to Jerusalem during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.7-11">1 Chr 15:7-11</a>). He may have administered the treasuries of the temple in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=1Chr.26.22">1 Chr 26:22</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Pedaiah’s son, who acted as tribal chieftain over the west half of Manasseh’s tribe during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.20">1 Chr 27:20</a>)</p>
<p class="list">10. Levite from the family of Kohath who assisted in King Hezekiah’s reform of the temple in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=2Chr.29.12">2 Chr 29:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Nebo’s son, who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife during the postexilic period (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.43">Ezr 10:43</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. Zicri’s son and the supervisor of 128 Benjaminites who moved to postexilic Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.9">Neh 11:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">13. Prophet who wrote the second book of the Minor Prophets. Little is known about him except that he was Pethuel’s son (<a href="?bref=Joel.1.1">Jl 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.2.16">Acts 2:16</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=JoelBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Joel, Book of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>