<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JohntheBaptist">
  <title>John the Baptist</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JOHN THE BAPTIST</p>
<p class="fl">Forerunner of the Messiah who prepared the people for Jesus’ coming, proclaimed the need for forgiveness of sins, and offered a baptism symbolizing repentance. His ministry included the baptism of Jesus in the Jordan River, where he testified to Jesus being the Expected One from God. John was arrested and beheaded by Herod Antipas in approximately <span class="era">AD</span> 29, while Jesus was still ministering.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#BirthInfancyandBoyhood">Birth, Infancy, and Boyhood</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#AppearanceandIdentity">Appearance and Identity</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#JohnsProclamation">John’s Proclamation</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#JohnsBaptism">John’s Baptism</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#JohnsViewofJesus">John’s View of Jesus</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#JesusViewofJohn">Jesus’ View of John</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#ArrestImprisonmentandMartyrdom">Arrest, Imprisonment, and Martyrdom</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#TheDisciplesofJohn">The Disciples of John</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="BirthInfancyandBoyhood">Birth, Infancy, and Boyhood</p>
<p class="fl">Luke’s Gospel is our only source of information concerning the birth and boyhood of John. The Gospel writer states that John was born in the hill country of Judah (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.39">Lk 1:39</a>) of priestly descent, being the son of Zechariah, a priest of the order of Abijah, and Elizabeth, a descendant of Aaron (v <a href="?bref=Luke.1.5">5</a>). Both parents were righteous in the sight of God, following all the commandments closely (v <a href="?bref=Luke.1.6">6</a>). Like the birth of Jesus, only to a much lesser degree, the birth of John the Baptist is described in Luke as extraordinary. The angel Gabriel announced the coming birth to Zechariah in the temple; to the older, barren Elizabeth it came as an answer to prayer (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.1.8-13">8-13</a>). John’s name is announced to Zechariah by the angel, even as his purpose as forerunner is revealed before birth (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.1.13-17">13-17</a>). Such a consecration from birth is reminiscent of the call of the OT prophet Jeremiah (cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.1.5">Jer 1:5</a>).</p>
<p>There existed some familial relationship between the families of John and Jesus. Elizabeth is described as a relative of Mary (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.36">Lk 1:36</a>), which may connote cousin or aunt, or may only mean being from the same tribe.</p>
<p>John’s childhood, as that of Jesus, is left quite vague in the Gospel account. All that is said is that “John grew up and became strong in spirit. Then he lived out in the wilderness until he began his public ministry to Israel” (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.80">Lk 1:80</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). Some scholars have suggested that John might have been adopted as a boy by the Essenes (as was their practice) at Qumran and reared in their wilderness community, adjacent to the Dead Sea and near the Jordan River. There are some similarities between the activities of the Qumran sect, known through the Dead Sea Scrolls, and the later ministry of John the Baptist. Both practiced a type of asceticism and removed themselves from the life of Jerusalem. Both practiced baptism and associated this rite with initiation and repentance. Finally, John and the Qumran group were both eschatologically minded, awaiting God’s final end-time activity in history. Nevertheless, many significant differences exist between John and the Qumran sect.</p>
<p class="h2" id="AppearanceandIdentity">Appearance and Identity</p>
<p class="fl">Mark’s Gospel begins with an account of John the Baptist’s appearance: “John the Baptist . . . lived in the wilderness and was preaching that people should be baptized to show that they had turned from their sins and turned to God to be forgiven” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.4">Mk 1:4</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). A rich OT background lies behind John’s association with the wilderness, in this case the wilderness of Judea. It was in the wilderness that God revealed himself to Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.3.1-22">Ex 3</a>), gave the law, and entered into the covenant with Israel (ch <a href="?bref=Exod.19.1-25">19</a>). It was also the site of refuge for David (<a href="?bref=1Sam.23.1-26.25">1 Sm 23–26</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.63.1-11">Ps 63</a>) and Elijah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.1-21">1 Kgs 19</a>), and in this light became the anticipated site of God’s future deliverance (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.3-5">Is 40:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.47.1-12">Ez 47:1-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.2.14-15">Hos 2:14-15</a>).</p>
<p>The unusual dress of John the Baptist—“clothing made of camel’s hair, with a leather belt around his waist” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.6">Mk 1:6</a>, <span class="sc">niv</span>)—may have suggested to his audience an association with Elijah in particular (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.1.8">2 Kgs 1:8</a>) or with the prophets in general (<a href="?bref=Zech.13.4">Zec 13:4</a>). His diet, “locusts and wild honey” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.6">Mk 1:6</a>), was Levitically clean, reflecting one who lived off the desert (such food was also eaten at Qumran) and formed part of the broader asceticism practiced by John and his disciples (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.14">Mt 9:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.11.18">11:18</a>).</p>
<p>Who did John understand himself to be? In answer to questions by the multitude whether he was the Messiah, Elijah, or the expected prophet (<a href="?bref=John.1.20-23">Jn 1:20-23</a>), John only identified himself as “a voice crying in the wilderness, ‘Prepare the way of the Lord’ ” (<a href="?bref=Isa.40.3">Is 40:3</a>). The background for the question lies at the end of the OT period. Prophecy, on the one hand, was considered to have ceased (<a href="?bref=Zech.13.2-6">Zec 13:2-6</a>); yet, on the other hand, it was expected to appear again before the coming of the messianic kingdom (see <a href="?bref=Joel.2.28-29">Jl 2:28-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.3.1-4">Mal 3:1-4</a>). Some anticipated this final prophet to be one who was like Moses (<a href="?bref=Deut.18.15">Dt 18:15</a>), others a returning Elijah as foretold in <a href="?bref=Mal.4.5-6">Malachi 4:5-6</a>. While John personally refrained from identifying himself with these specific expectations (<a href="?bref=John.1.20-23">Jn 1:20-23</a>), it is clear that his dress, lifestyle, and message caused the people to identify him with this end-time prophet (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.5">Mt 14:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.11.32">Mk 11:32</a>). Jesus also saw John as this final “Elijah-like” prophet (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.7-15">Mt 11:7-15</a>), who from Malachi’s prophecy was to be a forerunner to the coming of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Mal.3.1-4">Mal 3:1-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.4.5-6">4:5-6</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="JohnsProclamation">John’s Proclamation</p>
<p class="fl">John’s proclamation involved three elements: a warning of imminent judgment at the hands of the Coming One, a call for repentance in light of the coming kingdom of heaven, and a demand to express this repentance in concrete ethical terms. Many Jews looked forward confidently to the messianic judgment as a time of blessing for themselves and destruction for the gentile oppressors. John, however, warned that Jewish ancestry was false security in the coming judgment (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.8">Lk 3:8</a>); true repentance was the only means of escaping destruction (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.2">Mt 3:2</a>). John anticipated this judgment at the hands of the Coming One, who would baptize the nation with “the Holy Spirit and with fire” (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.16">Lk 3:16</a>). Fire represented the OT means of destruction in the end time (<a href="?bref=Mal.4.1">Mal 4:1</a>) as well as purification (<a href="?bref=Mal.3.1-4">Mal 3:1-4</a>), while the outpouring of the Holy Spirit in the end time connoted blessing (<a href="?bref=Isa.32.15">Is 32:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.29">Ez 39:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.28">Jl 2:28</a>) and purification (<a href="?bref=Isa.4.2-4">Is 4:2-4</a>). The judgment anticipated by John was therefore twofold: destruction for the unrepentant, and blessing for the penitent and righteous (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.12">Mt 3:12</a>).</p>
<p>In light of this imminent event John called for repentance on the part of his listeners (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.2">Mt 3:2</a>), a true “turning back” or “turning toward” God in obedience that would bring forgiveness of sin. Such a turnabout in an individual’s relation with God should be lived out in one’s everyday dealings: fairness on the part of tax collectors (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.12-13">Lk 3:12-13</a>) and soldiers (v <a href="?bref=Luke.3.14">14</a>), and the general requirement of compassion for the poor (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.3.10-11">10-11</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="JohnsBaptism">John’s Baptism</p>
<p class="fl">The Gospels record that John baptized those repentant of their sins at several locations: the Jordan River (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.5">Mk 1:5</a>), Bethany beyond the Jordan (<a href="?bref=John.1.28">Jn 1:28</a>), and Aenon near Salim (<a href="?bref=John.3.23">Jn 3:23</a>). This practice was an integral part of John’s call for repentance, given in light of the approaching judgment and the appearance of the Coming One. The baptism of the penitent symbolized desire for forgiveness of sin, a renunciation of past life, and a desire to be included in the coming messianic kingdom.</p>
<p>What was the background for John’s practice of baptism? From the OT we know of ceremonial lustrations or washings that guaranteed ritual purity (<a href="?bref=Lev.14.1-15.33">Lv 14–15</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.19.1-22">Nm 19</a>). Unlike John’s baptism, these washings were repetitive in nature and referred predominantly to ritual rather than moral cleansing. The prophets, however, urged a moral purification associated with the washing of water (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.16-18">Is 1:16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.4.14">Jer 4:14</a>). More significantly, the prophets anticipated a cleansing by God in the end times preceding the Day of Judgment (<a href="?bref=Ezek.36.25">Ez 36:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.13.1">Zec 13:1</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.44.3">Is 44:3</a>), an eschatological element that John may have assumed was being fulfilled in his water baptism.</p>
<p>Another precedent for John’s practice may have been proselyte baptism, a rite (along with circumcision and the offering of sacrifices) that constituted the conversion of a Gentile to Judaism. Common to both proselyte baptism and John’s baptism were the emphasis on an ethical break with the past, a once-for-all character, and the similarity of immersion. Notable differences were that John’s baptism was for Jews, not Gentile converts, and that it had a marked eschatological character as a preparation for the new age. Unless John, in light of the imminence of the messianic age, consciously treated all Jews as “pagan” in need of a baptism of repentance (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.3.7-10">Mt 3:7-10</a>), it is doubtful that proselyte baptism formed the primary background for John’s baptismal ministry.</p>
<p>If John’s baptism had a clear association with the forgiveness of sin, the question naturally arises as to why Jesus, the Son of God, sought baptism from John. John himself asks this very question of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.14">Mt 3:14</a>), to which Jesus responds, “It must be done, because we must do everything that is right” (v <a href="?bref=Matt.3.15">15</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). First, it is clear that Jesus’ baptism represented an act of obedience on his part to God’s will as he saw it. Second, by submitting to the baptism of John, Jesus was clearly validating the ministry and message of John. The imminent coming of the kingdom and its Messiah, and the need for repentance in anticipation of this event that John proclaimed, were affirmed by Jesus through baptism. Third, by being baptized, Jesus condemned the self-righteous for their lack of repentance and took a stand with the penitent publicans and sinners awaiting the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.29-30">Lk 7:29-30</a>). Fourth, Jesus stepped forward for baptism not as an individual in need of forgiveness but as one who represented the people of God. His baptism, therefore, demonstrated solidarity with the people in their need of deliverance, even as he is judged in their place on the cross. Finally, the voice from heaven (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.11">Mk 1:11</a>) and the descent of the Spirit (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.21-22">Lk 3:21-22</a>) signify the inauguration of Jesus’ own ministry through his baptism by John.</p>
<p class="h2" id="JohnsViewofJesus">John’s View of Jesus</p>
<p class="fl">Throughout his ministry John pointed beyond himself to one “who is far greater than I am—so much greater that I am not even worthy to be his slave” (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.7">Mk 1:7</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). His self-understanding apparently sprang from the application of <a href="?bref=Isa.40.3">Isaiah 40:3</a> to himself, that he was the preparer or forerunner for God’s coming activity through the Messiah (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.4-6">Lk 3:4-6</a>). When asked by curious spectators, John firmly denied that he was the Messiah, and according to the Gospel accounts, subordinated himself to the Coming One (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.7-8">Mk 1:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.26-28">Jn 1:26-28</a>; <a href="?bref=John.3.28-31">3:28-31</a>). The coming of Jesus to baptism seems to represent the first time John identified these expectations with Jesus himself (<a href="?bref=John.1.35-36">Jn 1:35-36</a>). His recognition of Jesus as the Messiah prior to baptism (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.14">Mt 3:14</a>) was confirmed by the descent of the Holy Spirit as a dove and the voice from heaven quoting a phrase from an OT messianic psalm (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.11">Mk 1:11a</a>, from <a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Ps 2:7</a>), together with a phrase from a Suffering Servant song of Isaiah (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.11">Mk 1:11b</a>, from <a href="?bref=Isa.42.1">Is 42:1</a>). In the fourth Gospel, John the Baptist goes even further in acknowledging Jesus to be the “Lamb of God” (<a href="?bref=John.1.29">Jn 1:29</a>), in anticipation of Jesus’ sacrificial role on the cross. And John recognized him as “God’s Chosen One” (v <a href="?bref=John.1.34">34</a>, <span class="sc">neb</span>—another term for the Messiah; <a href="?bref=Ps.2.7">Ps 2:7</a>, see <a href="?bref=Mark.1.11">Mk 1:11</a>).</p>
<p>In light of John’s strong affirmation, it is at first difficult to understand his questioning of Jesus while imprisoned: “Are you he who is to come, or shall we look for another?” (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.3">Mt 11:3</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Some have suggested that John was merely asking for the sake of his disciples, or that the question reflected John’s despondency with being imprisoned. It is more likely, however, that the question represents John’s own confusion with the activity expected of the Messiah. John had proclaimed a Coming One who would bring a baptism of fire and judgment upon the wicked (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.16">Lk 3:16</a>). It may have been difficult for him to understand Jesus’ different emphases on forgiveness and acceptance of sinners (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.9-13">Mt 9:9-13</a>) and his healing of the sick (<a href="?bref=Matt.8.1-9.38">Mt 8–9</a>). When John’s disciples brought their master’s question to Jesus, asking whether or not he was the Messiah, Jesus responded by quoting <a href="?bref=Isa.35.5-6">Isaiah 35:5-6</a> (see also <a href="?bref=Isa.61.1">Is 61:1</a>). This text proclaims the activities of healing and proclaiming salvation to the poor to be fulfillments of the Messiah’s role, even though they may not have been what John or countless other Jews expected.</p>
<p class="h2" id="JesusViewofJohn">Jesus’ View of John</p>
<p class="fl">That Jesus highly regarded John the Baptist is indicated by his baptism by John. It is also explicitly stated on several occasions. Jesus called him the greatest man to have ever lived (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.28">Lk 7:28</a>). (Of course, he was not as great as Jesus, the God-man.) Jesus also said that John was a burning and shining lamp (<a href="?bref=John.5.33-35">Jn 5:33-35</a>) and that he practiced a baptism divinely ordained (<a href="?bref=Luke.20.1-8">Lk 20:1-8</a>).</p>
<p>John’s uniqueness, however, lies in the fact that he stood at the turning of the ages. He was the last of the old era, the period of the law and the prophets (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.16">Lk 16:16</a>), which was to precede the coming of the messianic age (the kingdom of God). John was the last of the prophets, the greatest of them, the Elijah figure who would prepare the way for the judgment of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.13-15">Mt 11:13-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.17">Lk 1:17</a>). Because John belonged to the era of the law and the prophets, however, he was not as great as the “least” already in the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.11">Mt 11:11</a>)—that is, those who belonged to the era of the kingdom’s appearance in Jesus.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ArrestImprisonmentandMartyrdom">Arrest, Imprisonment, and Martyrdom</p>
<p class="fl">To understand why John was arrested and beheaded by Herod Antipas, one has to grasp the messianic excitement caused by John’s appearance and message (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.15-18">Lk 3:15-18</a>). Herod and other secular rulers were obviously suspicious of anyone who might stir up the crowds with predictions of a coming messianic ruler. Other messianic movements had arisen before John, which resulted in outbreaks of violence against the Roman-Herodian rulership. Moreover, Herod Antipas was under heavy criticism for his marriage with Herodias, the ex-wife of his brother Philip. His first marriage, with the daughter of Aretus II, constituted a political alliance between the Herodian family and the Nabatean kingdom of Perea. His new relationship with Herodias was perceived as a breach of the political alliance and led to friction between the two families. John’s denunciation of Herod’s new marriage (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.3-12">Mt 14:3-12</a>) could thus have been interpreted by Herod as a subversive rousing of sentiment against his authority. The Jewish historian Josephus states that Herod did, in fact, arrest John because he feared John’s influence over the crowds. According to Josephus, John was imprisoned at the fortress Machaerus on the eastern side of the Dead Sea. That he was not killed immediately was due to Herod’s personal fear of the righteous John (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.2">Mk 6:2</a>) and of the people’s reaction (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.5">Mt 14:5</a>). On a point about which Josephus is silent, the Gospels record that it was Herodias’s feelings against John (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.17">Mk 6:17</a>) and her plot, through the dancing of her daughter, which brought about the beheading of John (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.6.21-29">21-29</a>). John was beheaded at Herodias’s request in approximately <span class="era">AD</span> 29 or 30.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheDisciplesofJohn">The Disciples of John</p>
<p class="fl">While it is clear that a band of disciples formed around John in his lifetime (<a href="?bref=John.1.35">Jn 1:35</a>), to suggest that he intended to begin a continuing movement is contradicted by his message on the imminent Day of Judgment. Apparently, John’s disciples consisted of a small group of those who had been baptized by him and were awaiting the coming Messiah. Some transferred their loyalty to Jesus after John had identified Jesus as the Coming One (<a href="?bref=John.1.37">Jn 1:37</a>). Others, however, apparently stayed on with their teacher, communicating with the imprisoned John concerning the activities of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.18-23">Lk 7:18-23</a>) and, after his death, taking the body for burial (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.29">Mk 6:29</a>).</p>
<p>We know little about the activities and practices of the band of disciples clustered around John. We do know, however, that fasting was one practice specifically associated with the group, and one that marked them as similar to the Pharisees (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.14">Mt 9:14</a>). In this practice they no doubt followed the example of John himself (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.33">Lk 7:33</a>). Prayer and fasting were often linked in late Judaism. The disciples of John were also known for the prayers taught by their master (<a href="?bref=Luke.11.1">11:1</a>). Seeing this practice, the disciples of Jesus asked the Lord to teach them to pray, to which Jesus responded with the Lord’s Prayer (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.11.2-4">2-4</a>).</p>
<p>After his death it is likely that other disciples of John joined the followers of Jesus (see <a href="?bref=Luke.7.29-30">Lk 7:29-30</a>). Not all did so, however, as disciples of John were encountered by Paul and other Christians approximately 25 years later in Ephesus (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.24-29.7">Acts 18:24–29:7</a>). Upon hearing witness to Jesus, these followers of John proclaimed Jesus as Messiah. When Paul baptized them in the name of Jesus they received the Holy Spirit (<a href="?bref=Acts.19.4-7">19:4-7</a>). Even so, it is apparent from later documents that various groups continued to honor John, even considering him the Messiah, centuries after the NT period.</p>
  </body>
</item>