<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Jonathan">
  <title>Jonathan</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JONATHAN</p>
<p class="list"> 1. Levite from Bethlehem in Judah, a descendant of Gershom, son of Moses (cf. <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.14-15">1 Chr 23:14-15</a>); he was a priest first to Micah in Ephraim and later to Dan’s tribe during the period of the judges (<a href="?bref=Judg.17.7-10">Jgs 17:7-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.18.30">18:30</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Benjamite, the firstborn son of Saul and the father of Meribbaal (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.49">1 Sm 14:49</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.8.33-34">1 Chr 8:33-34</a>). Jonathan was a valiant warrior (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.2-4">1 Sm 13:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.14.1-15">14:1-15</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.1.22">2 Sm 1:22</a>) and a devoted friend to David (<a href="?bref=1Sam.18.1-5">1 Sm 18:1-5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.19.1-7">19:1-7</a>). He was eventually killed, along with his brothers, by the Philistines at Mt Gilboa (<a href="?bref=1Sam.31.2">1 Sm 31:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.10.2">1 Chr 10:2</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Son of the high priest Abiathar and one of David’s loyal servants (<a href="?bref=2Sam.15.27,36">2 Sm 15:27, 36</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.17.17,20">17:17, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.1.42-43">1 Kgs 1:42-43</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Shimei’s son and the nephew of David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.21">2 Sm 21:21</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.20.7">1 Chr 20:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Son of Shagee the Hararite and one of David’s mighty warriors (<a href="?bref=2Sam.23.33">2 Sm 23:33</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.11.34">1 Chr 11:34</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Judahite, Jada’s son, the brother of Jether, and the father of Peleth and Zaza (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.32-33">1 Chr 2:32-33</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Son of Uzziah and one of David’s treasurers (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.25">1 Chr 27:25</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. David’s relative who served as counselor and scribe in the royal household (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.32">1 Chr 27:32</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Ebed’s father. Ebed returned with Ezra to Judah following the Babylonian captivity (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.6">Ezr 8:6</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Asahel’s son, who, with Jahzeiah, opposed Ezra’s suggestion that the sons of Israel should divorce the foreign woman they had married since returning to Palestine from exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.15">Ezr 10:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Levite, the son of Joiada, the father of Jaddua, and a descendant of Jeshua, the high priest (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.11">Neh 12:11</a>). He is perhaps the same man as Jehohanan (or Johanan), Eliashib’s grandson, in <a href="?bref=Ezra.10.6">Ezra 10:6</a> (cf. <a href="?bref=Neh.12.23">Neh 12:23</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Jehohanan_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jehohanan #4</a>.</p>
<p class="list">12. Priest and the head of Malluch’s house during the days of Joiakim the high priest (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.14">Neh 12:14</a>).</p>
<p class="list">13. Priest, father of Zechariah, and a descendant of Asaph (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.35">Neh 12:35</a>).</p>
<p class="list">14. Secretary in whose house Jeremiah was at one point imprisoned during the reign of King Zedekiah of Judah (<a href="?bref=Jer.37.15,20">Jer 37:15, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.38.26">38:26</a>).</p>
<p class="list">15. Kareah’s son who sought protection under Gedaliah (<a href="?bref=Jer.40.8">Jer 40:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list">16. Youngest son of Mattathias and brother of Judas Maccabeus. When Judas Maccabeus was killed in battle with Bacchides (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.9.18">1 Macc 9:18</a>), his brother Jonathan became his successor (vv <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.9.28-31">28-31</a>). Jonathan continued the struggle against Syria for three years with a small band of guerrillas. But the Syrians were busy with an internal struggle for political power, and so, in 157 <span class="era">BC</span>, made peace with him. The political machinations in Syria worked to Jonathan’s advantage, and five years later he became high priest in Jerusalem and administrator of Judea (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.10.1-11">10:1-11</a>). Under his management, Jewish territory and power increased. This occurred partly because Jonathan was able to play the Syrian political rivals against one another. One of these was Tryphon, a pretender to the Syrian throne who saw that his influence was threatened by Jonathan’s power. So in 143 <span class="era">BC</span> he decided to overthrow the Jewish leader. Jonathan was taken prisoner by Tryphon through treachery and eventually killed, leaving his brother Simon to lead the Jews (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.12.1-13.53">1 Macc 12–13</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>