<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Joseph">
  <title>Joseph</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JOSEPH</p>
<p class="list">1. Jacob’s 11th son and the firstborn son of Rachel. Rachel named the boy Joseph, meaning “may he add,” expressing her desire that God would give her another son (<a href="?bref=Gen.30.24">Gn 30:24</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Nothing more is said about Joseph until, at the age of 17, he is seen tending his father’s flocks with his brothers (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.2">Gn 37:2</a>). Joseph was the favorite of his father, since he was the son of his old age (v <a href="?bref=Gen.37.3">3</a>) and the firstborn son of his favorite wife. Because of this, his brothers hated Joseph. This envy was magnified when Jacob gave Joseph a ground-length, long-sleeved, multicolored robe (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.37.3-4">3-4</a>). (This type of garment is illustrated by the paintings in the Asiatic tombs of Khnumhotep II at Beni Hasan and of the nobles at Gurneh, near Luxor.) The animosity of his brothers increased still more when Joseph revealed to them his dreams of dominion over them (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.37.5-11">5-11</a>). Subsequently, when Joseph was sent to check on his brothers and the flocks near Shechem, his brothers sold him to a caravan of traders going down to Egypt (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.37.25-28">25-28</a>). His brothers then took his robe, dipped it in goat’s blood, and brought it to Jacob, who concluded that Joseph had been killed by wild animals (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.37.31-33">31-33</a>); Jacob was overwhelmed with grief (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.37.34-35">34-35</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">In Egypt, Joseph was sold to Potiphar, an Egyptian officer of the guard (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.36">Gn 37:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.39.1">39:1</a>), who eventually put Joseph in charge of his entire household. However, trouble arose from Potiphar’s wife, who was attracted to the young Hebrew and tried to seduce him (<a href="?bref=Gen.39.6-10">39:6-10</a>). He steadfastly resisted her advances, protesting that to comply with her wishes would be a disservice to his master and a sin against God (v <a href="?bref=Gen.39.9">9</a>). One day she seized his garment, but he left the garment behind and fled. Potiphar’s wife accused Joseph of attempted rape; her report was believed, and Joseph was incarcerated in the king’s prison (v <a href="?bref=Gen.39.20">20</a>), where Pharaoh’s butler and baker were also confined. While in prison, Joseph, with the Lord’s help, interpreted these men’s troublesome dreams. As Joseph had foretold, the baker was executed and the butler was restored to royal favor (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.40.1-23">40</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Two years later Pharaoh had two dreams that his magicians and wise men could not interpret. The butler, remembering Joseph, had him summoned from prison. God revealed to Joseph that the dreams foretold seven years of abundance, followed by seven years of famine (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.25-36">Gn 41:25-36</a>). Pharaoh, impressed with Joseph’s interpretation, made him ruler of Egypt, second only to himself (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.41.39-44">39-44</a>). Joseph was given a new name, Zaphenath-paneah, and a wife, Asenath, the daughter of Potiphera (v <a href="?bref=Gen.41.45">45</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Joseph was 30 years old when he became ruler of Egypt. During the seven years of prosperity, he gathered the good supplies for the seven years of famine to come (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.53-56">Gn 41:53-56</a>). When the famine eventually became severe in Palestine, Jacob sent all his sons, except Benjamin, his youngest son, to Egypt to purchase grain. Appearing before Joseph in Egypt, they did not recognize him. But he knew them and remembered his dreams of years before (<a href="?bref=Gen.42.8-9">42:8-9</a>). After listening to the report of their family, he accused them of being spies (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.42.9-14">9-14</a>) and insisted that they leave one of their brothers as hostage and return with Benjamin to verify the truthfulness of their report (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.42.19-20">19-20</a>). Thus Simeon was bound and left in Egypt (v <a href="?bref=Gen.42.24">24</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">After the famine worsened in Palestine, Jacob asked his sons to go back to Egypt to buy more grain (<a href="?bref=Gen.43.1-2">Gn 43:1-2</a>); reluctantly agreeing to the conditions that the Egyptian administrator had placed on them, Jacob allowed Benjamin to go with them (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.43.11-13">11-13</a>). When they arrived in Egypt, they were taken to Joseph’s house, where Simeon was restored to them (v <a href="?bref=Gen.43.23">23</a>) and a meal was prepared for them (v <a href="?bref=Gen.43.33">33</a>). Joseph at last disclosed his identity and declared that God had sent him before them to preserve their lives (<a href="?bref=Gen.45.4-8">45:4-8</a>). Arrangements were then made to send for Jacob; wagons were provided, along with provisions for the journey (v <a href="?bref=Gen.45.21">21</a>). When Jacob came to Goshen in the Nile Delta, Joseph went out to meet him, and another great reunion took place (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.28-29">46:28-29</a>). He also presented his father and brothers to Pharaoh, who let them live in the land of Goshen (<a href="?bref=Gen.47.6">47:6</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Upon learning that his father was ill, Joseph took his two sons, Manasseh and Ephraim, to him for his blessing. He presented the sons so that the older would be at Jacob’s right hand and the younger at his left in order that Manasseh would receive the blessing of the firstborn. Jacob, however, crossed his hands and with his right hand on Ephraim gave him the greater blessing (<a href="?bref=Gen.48.14-20">Gn 48:14-20</a>). He also gave to Joseph the land that he had taken from the Amorites (v <a href="?bref=Gen.48.22">22</a>). At Jacob’s death, Joseph made the funeral arrangements; and after the customary funerary practices were carried out, a great funeral procession went to Canaan, where Jacob was buried by his sons in the cave of Machpelah near Hebron (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.1-12">50:1-12</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">When Joseph was 110 years old, he called his brothers and told them that he was about to die. He made them take an oath that when they returned to Canaan they would take his bones with them. So he died, was embalmed, and was placed in a coffin in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Gen.50.26">Gn 50:26</a>). Many years later, during the exodus, Moses took the bones of Joseph with him from Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.13.19">Ex 13:19</a>). Joseph’s remains were eventually interred at Shechem in the parcel of land that Jacob had bought from Hamor, the father of Shechem (<a href="?bref=Gen.33.18-20">Gn 33:18-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.32">Jos 24:32</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=PatriarchsPeriodofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Patriarchs, Period of the</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Igal’s father from Issachar’s tribe. Igal was one of the 12 spies sent by Moses to search out the land of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Num.13.7">Nm 13:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Asaph’s second son and the leader of the first course of priests serving in the sanctuary during David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.25.2,9">1 Chr 25:2, 9</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. One of Binnui’s descendants who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.42">Ezr 10:42</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Priest and family leader from Shebaniah’s line during the days of Joiakim, the high priest (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.14">Neh 12:14</a>).</p>
<p class="list">6. Descendant of David (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.16">Mt 1:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.23">Lk 3:23</a>) and the husband of Mary, the mother of Jesus. Joseph was betrothed to Mary, a young woman of the city of Nazareth. Mary had learned from the angel Gabriel that she was to bear the Son of God, whom she was to name Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.31">Lk 1:31</a>) and that this conception was to be a work of the Holy Spirit (v <a href="?bref=Luke.1.35">35</a>). Joseph was not aware of this, so when he learned that Mary was pregnant, he decided to divorce her quietly, for he was a just man and did not want to humiliate her publicly (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.19">Mt 1:19</a>). An angel subsequently appeared to him in a dream to tell him what was happening (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.21">Mt 1:21</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.7.14">Is 7:14</a>). The text of Matthew makes it clear that there was no sexual union between Joseph and Mary until after Jesus was born (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.18,25">Mt 1:18, 25</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Luke.1.34-37">Lk 1:34-37</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">When Caesar Augustus issued a decree that everyone had to register in his native city for purposes of taxation, Joseph and Mary returned to Bethlehem, where Jesus was subsequently born (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.1-6">Lk 2:1-6</a>). Later, Joseph and Mary took the infant Jesus to the temple to present him to the Lord (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.2.22,33">22, 33</a>). After the visit of the wise men, an angel appeared to Joseph in a dream and instructed him to take Jesus and Mary to Egypt to protect the child from King Herod (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.13">Mt 2:13</a>). Upon the death of Herod, an angel similarly advised him to return to Israel, so the family went to live in Nazareth. The last recorded event that involves Joseph is the incident of Jesus at the temple at age 12 (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.41-51">Lk 2:41-51</a>). Joseph is not mentioned by name, but Mary told Jesus that she and his father had been looking for him anxiously.</p>
<p class="list-text">Jesus was identified by people around Nazareth as “Joseph’s son” (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.22">Lk 4:22</a>; <a href="?bref=John.1.45">Jn 1:45</a>; <a href="?bref=John.6.42">6:42</a>). It is only through references identifying Jesus that we learn of Joseph’s trade. Twice Jesus is referred to as “the carpenter’s son” (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.55">Mt 13:55</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>). Joseph was not a carpenter in our sense of the word, for houses were built mostly of stone and earth. He was a woodworker or artificer in wood, and probably most of his work was with furniture and agricultural implements.</p>
<p class="list-text">During the ministry of Jesus, it was his mother and his brothers who came to look for him (<a href="?bref=Matt.12.46-50">Mt 12:46-50</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.31-35">Mk 3:31-35</a>), so it is assumed that by this time Joseph was dead. Joseph was most likely the father of James, Joseph, Simon, Judas, and unnamed sisters (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.55">Mt 13:55</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mk 6:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BrothersofJesus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Brothers of Jesus</a>; <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
<p class="list">7. Joseph and Mary’s son and the brother of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.55">Mt 13:55</a>); alternately called Joses in <a href="?bref=Mark.6.3">Mark 6:3</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=BrothersofJesus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Brothers of Jesus</a>.</p>
<p class="list">8. Native of Arimathea and the follower of Jesus who provided for his burial. He was a rich man from the town of Arimathea and a respected member of the Sanhedrin, or council (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.43">Mk 15:43</a>). He was a good and righteous man and did not go along with the decision to crucify Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.23.50-51">Lk 23:50-51</a>). Joseph had been a secret follower of Jesus because he was afraid of the Jews (<a href="?bref=John.19.38">Jn 19:38</a>), but after the Crucifixion he took courage and went to Pilate to ask for Jesus’ body. He and Nicodemus took the body, treated it with spices, and wrapped it in linen cloths, according to the Jewish burial customs. In a nearby garden was Joseph’s own new rock-cut tomb in which no one had ever been buried. Here they placed Jesus and sealed the tomb with a large stone.</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Mattathias’s son and an ancestor of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.25">Lk 3:25</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
<p class="list">10. KJV rendering of Josech, an ancestor of Jesus, in <a href="?bref=Luke.3.26">Luke 3:26</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Josech_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Josech</a>.</p>
<p class="list">11. Jonam’s son and an ancestor of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.30">Lk 3:30</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
<p class="list">12. Disciple of Jesus who was “called Barsabbas” and “surnamed Justus” (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.23">Acts 1:23</a>). Joseph was one of the candidates put forward by the 11 apostles to replace Judas Iscariot. It was Matthias, however, who was chosen.</p>
<p class="list">13. Cypriot Levite who sold a field and gave the proceeds to the apostles. He was surnamed “Barnabas,” meaning “son of encouragement,” by the apostles (<a href="?bref=Acts.4.36">Acts 4:36</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Barnabas_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Barnabas</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>