<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="JoshuaPerson">
  <title>Joshua (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JOSHUA (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. Son of Nun, Moses’ assistant and successor, and the military leader whom God chose to lead the Israelites in the conquest of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Num.13.16">Nm 13:16</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span> “Jehoshua”; also spelled “Jehoshuah” in <a href="?bref=1Chr.7.27">1 Chr 7:27</a> and “Jeshua” in <a href="?bref=Neh.8.17">Neh 8:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Early in the exodus, Joshua was sent by Moses to fight against the Amalekites (<a href="?bref=Exod.17.8-15">Ex 17:8-15</a>). Joshua defeated Amalek, and Moses wrote of the event and built an altar that he called “The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Is My Banner” (v <a href="?bref=Exod.17.15">15</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">When Moses sent 12 men from Kadesh-barnea to spy out the land of Canaan, Joshua represented the tribe of Ephraim (<a href="?bref=Num.13.8">Nm 13:8</a>). At that time Joshua was called Hoshea, but Moses changed his name to Joshua (vv <a href="?bref=Num.13.8,16">8, 16</a>). Joshua and Caleb were the only two spies to bring back an affirmative report concerning an Israelite invasion of the land (<a href="?bref=Num.14.6-9">14:6-9</a>). Consequently, of all the adult Israelite males to leave Egypt in the exodus, only these two crossed the Jordan River and entered the Promised Land (v <a href="?bref=Num.14.30">30</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">When the Lord announced to Moses his impending death, Moses asked about his successor, and the Lord appointed Joshua to that position (<a href="?bref=Num.27.12-23">Nm 27:12-23</a>). After the death of Moses on Mt Nebo, Joshua’s leadership was confirmed (<a href="?bref=Num.34.17">34:17</a>), and the Lord told Joshua to go over the Jordan and take the land (<a href="?bref=Josh.1.1-2">Jos 1:1-2</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">From the Transjordan, Joshua sent two men across the river to reconnoiter Jericho (ch <a href="?bref=Josh.2.1-24">2</a>). In Jericho they were concealed by Rahab and later safely made their way back to Joshua to report that the people of the land were fainthearted because of the Israelites (vv <a href="?bref=Josh.2.23-24">23-24</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">When Israel had crossed the river, the Lord instructed Joshua to set up a circle of 12 stones at Gilgal to commemorate this passage (<a href="?bref=Josh.4.1-7">Jos 4:1-7</a>). The Lord then commanded all of the males who had been born during the exodus to be circumcised (<a href="?bref=Josh.5.2-9">5:2-9</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">While camped at Gilgal, near Jericho, Joshua was confronted by a man with a drawn sword. When Joshua challenged the man, he learned that it was the Lord, who told him to remove his shoes, for the ground was holy (<a href="?bref=Josh.5.13-15">Jos 5:13-15</a>). The Lord gave Joshua directions for the destruction of Jericho; these were followed explicitly and the city fell (ch <a href="?bref=Josh.6.1-27">6</a>). The attack on Ai ended in temporary defeat, until the matter of Achan’s sin was discovered and judged (<a href="?bref=Josh.7.10-26">7:10-26</a>). Then Ai was taken and destroyed.</p>
<p class="list-text">Joshua built an altar on Mt Ebal (<a href="?bref=Josh.8.30-32">Jos 8:30-32</a>), and the blessings and curses were read, as commanded by God through Moses (<a href="?bref=Josh.8.33-35">Jos 8:33-35</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.27.1-28.68">Dt 27–28</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Because the Israelites failed to ask direction from the Lord (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.14">Jos 9:14</a>), Joshua was tricked into making a covenant of peace with the Hivites of Gibeon. Joshua then reduced them to doing menial tasks in Israel (vv <a href="?bref=Josh.9.21-27">21-27</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The kings of the various Canaanite cities allied themselves against the Israelite threat (<a href="?bref=Josh.9.1-2">Jos 9:1-2</a>) and a league of five Amorite cities (Jerusalem, Hebron, Jarmuth, Lachish, and Eglon) attacked Gibeon (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.1-5">10:1-5</a>). The Gibeonites appealed to Joshua for help; he responded quickly against this Amorite confederation and routed the Amorite forces. It was on this occasion that Joshua commanded the sun and the moon to stand still so that Israel could have more time to defeat these adversaries (vv <a href="?bref=Josh.10.12-14">12-14</a>). This victory was followed by a series of successful attacks on enemy towns (vv <a href="?bref=Josh.10.28-43">28-43</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">A northern alliance headed by Jabin, king of Hazor, was the next opposition (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.1-5">Jos 11:1-5</a>). The Lord assured Joshua of success, and the city of Hazor was taken and destroyed by fire (vv <a href="?bref=Josh.11.6-15">6-15</a>). <a href="?bref=Josh.11.23">Joshua 11:23</a> summarizes the conquest of the land, and chapter <a href="?bref=Josh.12.1-24">12</a> enumerates the kings who were conquered.</p>
<p class="list-text">Joshua was now old, and the Lord told him that much land remained to be possessed. These territories are listed, but the Lord directed Joshua to proceed with the division of the land among the nine and a half tribes (<a href="?bref=Josh.13.7">Jos 13:7</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Josh.13.8-18.28">13:8–18:28</a>). Joshua himself was given the city he asked for, Timnath-serah, in the hill country of Ephraim, which he rebuilt and settled (<a href="?bref=Josh.19.49-50">19:49-50</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">The Lord told Joshua to appoint cities of refuge to which a person guilty of manslaughter could flee to escape the avenger of blood (<a href="?bref=Josh.20.1-9">Jos 20</a>). Then the Levites came to Eleazar the priest and Joshua to request that they be given their cities, as the Lord had commanded through Moses (<a href="?bref=Josh.21.1-42">21:1-42</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="JoshuasFinalDays"/>
<p class="list-text">In his advanced years Joshua summoned all Israel and solemnly charged them to continue in faithfulness to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Josh.23.1-16">Jos 23</a>). Finally, he called all Israel to Shechem, where he gave them his farewell message. He summed up the Lord’s dealings with them from the time of Abraham and again challenged them to serve the Lord, putting before them the well-known choice and decision: “Choose today whom you will serve. . . . As for me and my family, we will serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>” (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.15">24:15</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Joshua died at the age of 110 years and was buried in the land of his inheritance at Timnath-serah (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.29-30">Jos 24:29-30</a>; the parallel account in <a href="?bref=Judg.2.8-9">Jgs 2:8-9</a> reads “Timnath-heres,” <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg). Israel served the Lord during all the days of Joshua and the elders who outlived him (<a href="?bref=Josh.24.31">Jos 24:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.2.7">Jgs 2:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ConquestandAllotmentoftheLand_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Conquest and Allotment of the Land</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=JoshuaBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Joshua, Book of</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Inhabitant of Beth-shemesh. It was his grainfield into which the cart carrying the ark sent by the Philistines came. It stopped by a large stone which was then used to commemorate this event (<a href="?bref=1Sam.6.14,18">1 Sm 6:14, 18</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Governor of Jerusalem during King Josiah’s reign (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.8">2 Kgs 23:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list">4. Jozadak’s son and high priest during the days of Zerubbabel in postexilic Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1-14">Hg 1:1-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.2-4">2:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.3.1-9">Zec 3:1-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.11">6:11</a>; <span class="sc">nlt</span> “Jeshua”). Joshua is alternately called Jeshua in Ezra and Nehemiah. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=JeshuaPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jeshua (Person) #3</a>.</p>
<p class="list">5. Eliezer’s son and an ancestor of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Luke.3.29">Lk 3:29</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>