<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Jotham">
  <title>Jotham</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JOTHAM</p>
<p class="list">1. Youngest of Gideon’s 70 sons and the only survivor of Abimelech’s slaughter of Jotham’s brothers at Ophrah (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.5">Jgs 9:5</a>). Upon learning of Abimelech’s intrigue with the Shechemites, which led to the death of his brothers, Jotham traveled to Shechem and addressed its people from atop nearby Mt Gerizim. Using a parable, he portrayed Abimelech’s rise as king and concluded his denunciation by issuing a curse on both his half brother (see <a href="?bref=Judg.8.31">8:31</a>) and the people of Shechem for their treachery (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.7">9:7</a>). Jotham then fled to Beer for fear of a reprisal from Abimelech (v <a href="?bref=Judg.9.21">21</a>). Later, God fulfilled Jotham’s curse; the people of Shechem were killed in a revolt and Abimelech was struck down at the hands of a woman (v <a href="?bref=Judg.9.57">57</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Eleventh king of Judah (750–735 <span class="era">BC</span>). He was the son of King Azariah (Uzziah) of Judah and Jerusa, daughter of Zadok (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.7">2 Kgs 15:7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.26.21">2 Chr 26:21</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.27.1">27:1</a>), and the father of Ahaz. Jotham, at 25 years of age, ascended Judah’s throne in the second year of King Pekah of Israel (752–732 <span class="era">BC</span>) and ruled for 16 years in Jerusalem. Initially he reigned as co-regent with Azariah, who was stricken with leprosy for tolerating pagan worship, until his father’s death (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.5">2 Kgs 15:5</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Jotham was considered a righteous king in the eyes of the Lord. However, he also failed to cleanse the temple of its pagan influences, and subsequently the people of Judah continued in their evil ways (<a href="?bref=2Chr.27.2-6">2 Chr 27:2-6</a>). His building projects included the Upper Gate of the temple, work on the wall of Ophel, and the fortification of numerous towns in Judah’s hill country (vv <a href="?bref=2Chr.27.3-4">3-4</a>). Jotham also defeated the troublesome Ammonites in battle (v <a href="?bref=2Chr.27.5">5</a>) and registered by genealogy the families of Gad living east of the Jordan (<a href="?bref=1Chr.5.17">1 Chr 5:17</a>). He was buried in Jerusalem after his death (<a href="?bref=2Chr.27.9">2 Chr 27:9</a>). The prophets Isaiah and Micah ministered to Judah, and Hosea to Israel, during his tenure as king. Jotham is listed as an ancestor of Jesus Christ in Matthew’s genealogy (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.9">Mt 1:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ChronologyoftheBibleOldTestament_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Chronology of the Bible (Old Testament)</a>; <a href="?item=GenealogyofJesusChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Genealogy of Jesus Christ</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>.</p>
<p class="list">3. Second of Jahdai’s five sons (<a href="?bref=1Chr.2.47">1 Chr 2:47</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>