<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Judaism">
  <title>Judaism</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">JUDAISM</p>
<p class="fl">Religion and culture of the Jewish people from the beginning of the postexilic period (538 <span class="era">BC</span>) to modern times. The term “Judaism” is derived from “Judah,” the name of the southern kingdom of ancient Israel, while “Jew” is a shortened form of “Judeans.”</p>
<p class="h2" id="ThePeriodoftheSecondTemple">The Period of the Second Temple (515 <span class="era">BC</span>–<span class="era">AD</span> 70)</p>
<p class="h3">Historical Survey</p>
<p class="fl">The united kingdom of Israel under Saul, David, and Solomon came to an end shortly after the death of Solomon. Rehoboam, his son, provoked a revolt about 930 <span class="era">BC</span> on the part of the 10 northern tribes by levying unreasonably high taxes (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.12.1-33">1 Kgs 12</a>). From that time on, the kingdoms of Israel (or Samaria, the northern kingdom) and Judah (the southern kingdom) maintained a separate existence. The northern kingdom fell to the Assyrians in 722 <span class="era">BC</span>, and thousands of captives, primarily members of the upper class, were exiled forcibly and taken to Assyria, where they presumably intermarried with the native population and disappeared from history. The kingdom of Judah survived as an independent state until 597 <span class="era">BC</span>, when it came under the control of the Babylonians under Nebuchadnezzar. The temple was finally destroyed in 586 <span class="era">BC</span> and many captives were carried off to Babylonia, beginning a period of exile that was to last two generations. The Babylonians were defeated by Cyrus the Persian in 539 <span class="era">BC</span>, and the following year the king issued a decree permitting all captive peoples to return to the lands of their origin (<a href="?bref=2Chr.36.22-23">2 Chr 36:22-23</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.1.1-11">Ezr 1</a>). At least four waves of Jewish expatriates returned from Mesopotamia to Judea during the century following the decree of Cyrus, under such leaders as Sheshbazzar, Zerubbabel, Ezra, and Nehemiah. Many Jews, however, chose to remain in their adopted Mesopotamian homeland. The dedication of the second temple in the spring of 515 <span class="era">BC</span> provided a formal end to the exilic period of 70 years (<a href="?bref=Jer.29.10">Jer 29:10</a>), and was a direct result of the prophetic exhortations of Haggai and Zechariah.</p>
<p>In Judea the Jewish people were ruled by governors who held office at the pleasure of the Persian king. One of the earlier governors was Zerubabbel (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1">Hg 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.1-2">2:1-2</a>), a descendant of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.10-19">1 Chr 3:10-19</a>). In some way he shared rule with the high priest Jeshua ben Jehozadak. Palestine was part of one of the 20 satrapies of the Persian Empire, which lasted from 539 to 331 <span class="era">BC</span>, when it fell to the Greeks under Alexander the Great. Little is known about the historical developments in Palestine during most of the Persian period. When Alexander died in 323 <span class="era">BC</span>, his empire was divided up among his generals; Egypt and Palestine fell to Ptolemy I. The Ptolemies were benevolent despots who allowed the Jews of Palestine a measure of freedom and autonomy. After the battle of Paneion in 198 <span class="era">BC</span>, Palestine came under the rule of the Seleucid Empire, founded by Seleucus I, another of Alexander’s generals.</p>
<p>The Seleucid Empire embraced a very large area with a diverse population, extending from Asia Minor and Palestine in the west to the borders of India on the east. Antiochus IV (Epiphanes) ascended the Seleucid throne in 175 <span class="era">BC</span> and attempted to unify his vast empire by Hellenizing it (i.e., by forcing the adoption of Greek language and culture). Local cultures and religions were forcibly suppressed as a result of this policy, and the Jewish state in Palestine was perhaps the hardest hit of all. In 167 <span class="era">BC</span> Antiochus IV dedicated the temple in Jerusalem to Olympian Zeus, sacrificed a sow on the altar, destroyed scrolls containing the Jewish Scriptures, and forbade the rite of circumcision. This repression triggered a revolt led by an aged priest named Mattathias and his sons. The Seleucids were repulsed, and finally in 164 <span class="era">BC</span> the temple was retaken by Mattathias’s son Judas the Maccabee (an epithet meaning “the hammer”). This Jewish victory has been commemorated annually by the festival of Hanukkah (“dedication”). Judas and his brothers, called Maccabees or Hasmoneans (Mattathias was of the house of Hasmon), and their descendants ruled Judea from 164 to 63 <span class="era">BC</span>, when Palestine fell to the Roman general Pompey. Thereafter, Palestine remained a vassal of Rome.</p>
<p>Hyrcanus, a Hasmonean, was high priest after the conquest of Judea by the Romans, though Antipater (an Idumean) was the real power behind Hyrcanus. The sons of Antipater, Phasael and Herod, were governors of Jerusalem and Galilee, respectively. Upon the assassination of Antipater in 43 <span class="era">BC</span>, and through his connections in Rome, Herod (later called Herod the Great) was named king of Judea by the Roman senate; he reigned from 37 to 4 <span class="era">BC</span>. When he died, Palestine was divided up by the emperor Augustus (27 <span class="era">BC</span>–<span class="era">AD</span> 14) and placed under the governorship of three of Herod’s sons: Herod Archelaus (ethnarch of Judea, Idumea, and Samaria from 4 <span class="era">BC</span> to <span class="era">AD</span> 6), Herod Antipas (tetrarch of Galilee and Perea from 4 <span class="era">BC</span> to <span class="era">AD</span> 39), and Herod Philip (tetrarch of Batanea, Trachonitis, and other small states from 4 <span class="era">BC</span> to <span class="era">AD</span> 34). These territories were generally placed under Roman procurators after the sons of Herod had died or been deposed. For a brief period (<span class="era">AD</span> 41–44), Herod Agrippa I, the grandson of Herod the Great, ruled virtually the same territory as his grandfather. Upon his death (narrated in <a href="?bref=Acts.12.20-23">Acts 12:20-23</a>), his territories were placed under Roman procurators. The greed and ineptitude of these procurators provoked the Jewish populace to rebel. The ill-fated Jewish revolt of <span class="era">AD</span> 66–73 resulted in the destruction of the second temple by the tenth Roman legion under Titus in <span class="era">AD</span> 70. The revolt was completely quelled in <span class="era">AD</span> 73, when more than 900 Jews under siege in the desert fortress of Masada near the Dead Sea committed mass suicide rather than fall into Roman hands. These tragic events ended permanently the temple cult and the priestly system in Judaism.</p>
<p class="h3">Social and Religious Developments</p>
<p class="fl">The Babylonian conquest of Judea and the destruction of the Solomonic temple in 586 <span class="era">BC</span> produced dramatic social and religious changes in Jewish life. The cessation of the temple cult struck a serious blow at the heart of the Israelite religion, since the Jerusalem temple alone was the legitimate and divinely appointed place for discharging much of the ritual requirement of the Mosaic law, chiefly the sacrificial cult. Even the three annual pilgrimage festivals, Succoth (Tabernacles), Pesach (Passover), and Shavuoth (Weeks) could no longer be observed by pious Jews who had remained in Judea after 586 <span class="era">BC</span>. When after 538 <span class="era">BC</span> many exiles chose to return to Judea, many others elected to remain in their new homeland. For the latter, the temple cult, even when reinstituted in 516 <span class="era">BC</span>, could no longer play a significant role in their religious lives.</p>
<p>During the exilic and early postexilic period, the peculiar Jewish institution of the synagogue (a Greek word meaning “gathering place”) began to evolve. The synagogue became such a popular and useful institution for Jewish communities outside Palestine that in the centuries after the dedication of the second temple they sprang up throughout Palestine, many in Jerusalem itself. By the end of the second temple period, the synagogue had come to play three important functions in Jewish life: it served as a house of prayer, a house of study, and a place of assembly. First-century <span class="era">AD</span> synagogue worship is illustrated in <a href="?bref=Luke.4.16-30">Luke 4:16-30</a> and <a href="?bref=Acts.13.13-42">Acts 13:13-42</a>. The focus of the service was a reading of a selection from the Torah (Law of Moses), then one from the Haphtorah (Prophets). These readings were followed by a homily based on Scripture. Other elements in first-century <span class="era">AD</span> synagogue worship included the recitation of the Shema (“Hear, O Israel”), a combination of biblical passages including <a href="?bref=Deut.6.4-9">Deuteronomy 6:4-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.11.13-21">11:13-21</a> and <a href="?bref=Num.15.37-41">Numbers 15:37-41</a>, and the Shemoneh Esreh (Eighteen Benedictions) called the Amidah (“standing”) because it was recited while standing upright. Jews also wore fringes on their garments in obedience to <a href="?bref=Num.15.38-39">Numbers 15:38-39</a> (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.5">Mt 23:5</a>), and phylacteries on their foreheads and left arms. Phylacteries are little boxes containing the portions of Scripture recited in Shema; they were used in literal fulfillment of the command in <a href="?bref=Deut.6.8">Deuteronomy 6:8</a>. Archaeologists have discovered first-century phylacteries in the ruins of Masada.</p>
<p>Outside of Palestine, Mesopotamia became the second most important center of Judaism. The Babylonian Jewish community was known as the Golah (“captivity”), and its titular head was called the Resh Galuta or Exilarch (both terms mean “leader of the captivity”). By the end of the exilic period, the descendants of the ancient original captives had forgotten Hebrew and had adopted Aramaic, the international language of the ancient Near East and sister language to Hebrew, as their first language. Even in Palestine, Aramaic was the primary language spoken. Thus, when portions of Scripture were read in synagogue services in Hebrew, most of those present were unable to understand what was read. This problem was solved by providing a methurgeman (translator) who would translate orally short sections of Scripture. Eventually these targums (“translations”) were reduced to writing, beginning in the second century <span class="era">AD</span>.</p>
<p>By the first century <span class="era">AD</span>, it had been estimated that there were from four to seven million Jews in the Greco-Roman world, perhaps three to four times the population of Palestine. Jews in lands outside of Palestine came to be known collectively as the Diaspora (“scattering”). After the Greeks dominated the Mediterranean world through Alexander and his successors, Greek became the common language throughout this region. Just as Mesopotamian Jews spoke Aramaic in place of Hebrew, so Jews in the Greco-Roman world came to speak Greek. By the middle of the third century <span class="era">BC</span>, Hellenistic Jews began to translate the Hebrew Scriptures into Greek. This translation, called the Septuagint (a term meaning “seventy,” based on a legend that it was translated simultaneously by seventy Jewish scholars), contained a more extensive canon of Scripture than that recognized by Palestinian Judaism. This reflects the more liberal attitudes of Hellenistic Jews.</p>
<p>During the second century <span class="era">BC</span>, most of the major sects within Palestinian Judaism came into being. The Hasidim (“pious”) were members of a religious association that aided the Hasmoneans in the revolt against the Seleucids (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.2.42">1 Macc 2:42</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.7.13">7:13</a>) but later opposed them when they claimed rights to the priesthood. Both the Pharisees and Essenes may have their origin in this religious sect. The Sadducees were perhaps connected with Zadok, a high priest appointed by David. Zadok’s descendants were regarded as the only legitimate priestly line; they were devoted above the Levites in <a href="?bref=Ezek.40.1-48.35">Ezekiel 40–48</a>. The Sadducees were a wealthy, aristocratic class that monopolized the high priesthood. They did not believe in angels, spirits, life after death, or the resurrection (<a href="?bref=Acts.23.8">Acts 23:8</a>), nor did they accept the validity of the oral law as developed by the Pharisees. They left no writings and disappeared with the destruction of the temple in <span class="era">AD</span> 70.</p>
<p>The Pharisees (“separated ones”) first appear in our sources toward the end of the second century <span class="era">BC</span> and were involved primarily in political affairs. They represented the common people against the tyrannical Hasmonean ruler Alexander Janneus (103–76 <span class="era">BC</span>), who had hundreds of Pharisees executed in reprisal. By the first century <span class="era">AD</span>, the Pharisees seem wholly concerned with religious matters and were noted for the scrupulous observance of the Mosaic law as traditionally interpreted. On grounds of ritual purity, they separated themselves from other Jews who were not as scrupulous and who might contaminate them. Pharisees went about in groups called Haberim (“associates”) in which they were insulated from those who were lax religiously. In their zeal to remain faithful to the Mosaic law, the Pharisees developed an oral law (later erroneously attributed to Moses) that served as a fence around the Torah. This oral law was an interpretation and expansion of the 613 commands in the Mosaic law; it was finally compiled and reduced to written form as the Mishnah (“teaching”) in the late second century <span class="era">AD</span>. Paul (<a href="?bref=Acts.22.3">Acts 22:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.23.6">23:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.26.5">26:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.3.5">Phil 3:5</a>) and many other early Christians were converts from Pharisaism (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.5">Acts 15:5</a>). Pharisaic Judaism survived the destruction of Jerusalem in <span class="era">AD</span> 70 to form the rabbinic Judaism that dominated Jewish religious life from the second century <span class="era">AD</span> to modern times.</p>
<p>The Essenes were another religious sect within Judaism that had its origins in the second century <span class="era">BC</span>. Like the Pharisees, the Essenes were concerned principally with maintaining ritual purity in obedience to the law of Moses. The Essenes lived and worked in Jewish society; they tried to influence people by the simple, altruistic life they followed. Some Essenes also lived in their own communities, to which they returned each night after work. There were numerous religious factions within Judaism, and one such group, which may only have had vague connections with the Essenes, established a community on the western shore of the Dead Sea. This group regarded itself as the true Israel and in the wilderness prepared for the final visitation of God by keeping themselves pure from all defilement. Many documents written by members of this sect were discovered in caves near the Dead Sea where they had been hidden just before the Romans destroyed the settlement. These documents, the Dead Sea Scrolls, have provided detailed information about this religious sect and its beliefs.</p>
<p>The Zealots were another Jewish sect, who may be related to the Sicarii (“dagger men”). This group of political activists flourished from <span class="era">AD</span> 6 to 66. Regarding God alone as their sovereign, they attempted to overthrow the Romans and those who collaborated with them by violent means, including assassination. They helped to foment the Jewish revolt of <span class="era">AD</span> 66–73 and perished with Jerusalem in <span class="era">AD</span> 70.</p>
<p>Social class and status in first-century <span class="era">AD</span> Palestine were determined in accordance with the rules of ritual purity. The upper class comprised members of the religious establishment, such as the Sadducees, scribes, Pharisees, and Jerusalem priests. The Sanhedrin was a deliberative body whose membership was drawn from these groups. For all practical purposes there was no middle class. The lower class consisted primarily of the Am Ha Arez (“people of the land”)—Jews who were ignorant of the law through lack of education and who did not scrupulously observe those commandments with which they were familiar. The generally hostile attitude of the Pharisees toward the Am Ha Arez is expressed in <a href="?bref=John.7.49">John 7:49</a>: “But this crowd, who do not know the law, are accursed” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). There was yet another social class in first-century Palestine, which can be designated as “untouchables.” This group was composed of Samaritans, tax collectors, prostitutes, shepherds, lepers, Gentiles, and perhaps worst of all, Jews who became as Gentiles (e.g., the prodigal son of <a href="?bref=Luke.15.11-32">Lk 15:11-32</a>). The rules of ritual purity as generally observed prevented any form of social contact between the upper class and the untouchables, and made contacts with the Am Ha Arez highly undesirable. Against this background, the horror of the Pharisees over Jesus’ association with tax collectors and sinners is throughly understandable (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.15-17">Mk 2:15-17</a>).</p>
<p>A further consequence of this religious criterion for determining social class and status was an uneasy tension between Jerusalem and the rural areas of Palestine, particularly Galilee, during the last two centuries of the second temple period. Those in Jerusalem regarded Galilee as a place where ignorance of the Torah was the rule (<a href="?bref=John.1.46">Jn 1:46</a>). Jerusalem was primarily a religious center, whose major industry was the temple cult. The total population of Jerusalem in the first century <span class="era">AD</span> has been estimated at 25,000 to 40,000. Most of these were either artisans and craftsmen devoted to building and adorning the temple (still incomplete before it was destroyed; see <a href="?bref=John.2.20">Jn 2:20</a>) or priests and Levites involved in the many ritual activities of the temple. Though Jews were expected to travel to Jerusalem for each of the three annual pilgrimage festivals, this requirement proved difficult for rural Palestinian farmers.</p>
<p>Further, the tithe demanded by Mosaic command was only on the produce of the land, not upon wages or bartered goods. The rural farmers, therefore, bore the brunt of this taxation and quite naturally resented the privileged position of urban artisans, merchants, and priests who were not obliged to tithe. The temptation not to tithe the produce of the land was very great, and many farmers succumbed to it. Their untithed produce was not kosher, and thus to be avoided by those, like the Pharisees, who were religiously scrupulous. In addition to the first and second tithes demanded of farmers (the second tithe had to be spent in the vicinity of Jerusalem), it has been estimated that Roman tax levies amounted to 10 to 15 percent of an individual’s income. Religious taxes, together with Roman taxes, added up to a crushing tax burden of from 25 to 30 percent. The fact that the Jews finally revolted against their Roman oppressors in <span class="era">AD</span> 66 is not difficult to comprehend. Throughout the first century <span class="era">AD</span>, in fact, minor revolts in Palestine occurred with predictable frequency. Many of these occurred during the three annual pilgrimage festivals in Jerusalem, when the normal population of 25,000 to 40,000 swelled to 500,000 or more. These festivals provided ideal opportunities for uprisings, and the Romans were particularly alert for such eventualities. Jesus was executed during one such Passover festival because he was suspected of being a political revolutionary (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.26">Mk 15:26</a>).</p>
<p>The second temple period provided the setting for the rise and fall of apocalypticism within Judaism. Apocalypticism (from a Greek word meaning “revelation”) was a kind of eschatology (“account of final events”) that assumed that ideal conditions could not be restored on earth unless God first intervened climactically to destroy evil (particularly foreign oppressors) and vindicate the righteous (Israel). Apocalyptic visionaries composed many documents, called apocalypses, in which they attempted to read the signs of the times and predict the coming of the visitation of God. Since there was a widespread consciousness that the era of prophecy was over, these apocalyptists wrote not under their own names but under the names of ancient Israelite worthies, such as Moses, Abraham, Enoch, and Ezra. Among the more significant expectations of Jewish apocalypticism were (1) the coming of a Messiah; (2) the coming of a great period of tribulation, sometimes called the messianic woes; (3) the resurrection of the just; (4) the judgment of the wicked and the reward of the righteous. Apocalyptic beliefs probably provided the motivation for most—if not all—of the Jewish revolts against the Romans.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="JewsPrayingAndReadingScripturesBeforeTheWailingWall"/>
<p>Some portions of the Hebrew Scriptures were still in the process of composition at the beginning of the second temple period. The last three prophetic books—Haggai, Zechariah, and Malachi—were written from the end of the sixth century to the mid fifth century <span class="era">BC</span>. Later rabbis expressed the opinion that the Spirit of God had been taken from Israel when these prophets ceased their labors. The Chronicler ends his work by referring to the decree of Cyrus (538 <span class="era">BC</span>), and both Ezra-Nehemiah and Esther appear to have been written in the fifth century <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>The second temple period witnessed not only the completion of those writings that were later regarded as inspired and authoritative in Judaism but also the full recognition of all 24 sacred books. Prior to the destruction of Jerusalem in 586 <span class="era">BC</span>, the Mosaic law had not been observed with any consistency (according to <a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.1-20">2 Kgs 22</a> it had been mislaid for an unknown period of time), nor had the classical prophets always received appropriate recognition. But after 586 <span class="era">BC</span> the Torah occupied a position of unquestioned sanctity in the lives and thoughts of the Jewish people, replacing in many respects the temple cult even before its final dissolution in <span class="era">AD</span> 70.</p>
<p>The Jewish Scriptures are divided into three sections, designated by Jews with the acrostic “Tanak”: (1) Torah (“Law” or “Revelation”), (2) Nebi’im (“Prophets”), and (3) Kethubim (“Writings”). It is generally claimed that while the Law and Prophets enjoyed canonical status prior to the second century <span class="era">BC</span>, the Writings were finally declared canonical at the rabbinic council of Jamnia (c. <span class="era">AD</span> 90), though the historicity of this is disputed. The rabbis are thought to have discussed whether certain biblical books should continue to be part of Scripture. In reality, the Jewish canon of Scripture was fully defined from traditional usage by the first century <span class="era">BC</span>. The Law consisted of five books: Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy. The Prophets consisted of two sections, the Former Prophets (Joshua, Judges, Samuel, and Kings) and the Latter Prophets (Isaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, and the 12 Minor Prophets). The Writings included Chronicles, Ezra-Nehemiah, Esther, Job, Psalms, Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, Song of Songs, Lamentations, Ruth, and Daniel. The total number of books in this canon is 24, identical with the Protestant canon of 39 books, since Samuel, Kings, Chronicles, Ezra-Nehemiah, and the 12 are each counted as only one book. The Alexandrian canon of Hellenistic Judaism was more extensive, and the extra books (called Apocrypha by Protestants) are all found in the Roman Catholic OT canon of 46 books.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheTalmudicPeriod">The Talmudic Period (<span class="era">AD</span> 73–425)</p>
<p class="h3">Historical Survey</p>
<p class="fl">According to Jewish legend, when the Romans were about to conquer Jerusalem in the revolt of <span class="era">AD</span> 66–73, a prominent Pharisee, Rabbi Johanan ben Zakkai, feigned death and his disciples were permitted to carry him out of the besieged city in a coffin. The more likely scenario is that he received permission from the Romans to move his school from Jerusalem to Jamnia, on the coast of Palestine. The temple cult and the priestly system had disappeared, and rabbinic academies such as that of Rabbi Johanan set themselves to the enormous task of reconstructing Judaism. The older Sanhedrin was reinstituted as the Beth Din (“Court of Law”), and Gamaliel II, a grandson of Hillel, who had presided over the old Sanhedrin, became its leader with the title Nasi (“prince”), or Patriarch. The patriarchate continued until <span class="era">AD</span> 425, when Emperor Theodosius II abolished the office upon the death of the last patriarch, Gamaliel VI. In Mesopotamia, Babylonian Judaism experienced a renaissance that lasted until the end of the fifth century <span class="era">AD</span>. This period was called the Age of the Gaonim (“excellencies”) after the heads of the two great rabbinic academies at Sura and Pumpeditha. It was there that the great Babylonian Talmud was compiled by the fifth century <span class="era">AD</span>.</p>
<p>In <span class="era">AD</span> 115 various Jewish communities throughout the eastern Mediterranean, including Egypt, Cyprus, and Cyrene, revolted against the Roman emperor Trajan. Without exception these revolts were all put down by Roman legions. Finally, when the emperor Hadrian was on the brink of founding the new city of Aelia Capitolina on the site of old Jerusalem, the Jews again revolted in <span class="era">AD</span> 132, led by a self-proclaimed messiah, Simeon Bar Koziba, who was called Bar-Kochba (“Son of a Star”) by his followers as an allusion to the messianic passage in <a href="?bref=Num.24.17">Numbers 24:17</a>. Bar-Kochba was aided by the famous rabbinic scholar Akiba. This revolt, though initially successful, was put down by the Romans under Julius Severus in 135. Shortly thereafter, Hadrian issued a decree banning all Jews from the new Aelia Capitolina.</p>
<p class="h3">Social and Religious Developments</p>
<p class="fl">During this period, the result of generations of rabbinical scholarship bore fruit with the compilation of the Babylonian and Jerusalem Talmuds. The rabbinic sages consciously saw themselves as the heirs of the ancient Israelite prophets, who in turn were the heirs of the Mosaic law. They distinguished consciously between their own legal interpretations of the Mosaic law (which they called Halakah, or “walking,” i.e., a guide for life), and the commands in the Torah itself (called Mitvah, or “commandment”). The oral law, developed through generations of rabbinic discussion, was finally compiled and written down through the efforts of the patriarch Judah ha-Nasi (c. <span class="era">AD</span> 135–220) during the last quarter of the second century <span class="era">AD</span> and became known as the Mishnah (“teaching”). This is a topical arrangement of rabbinic discussions on such subjects as the Sabbath, firstfruits, sacrifices, and women. The Mishnah became the basis for further rabbinic discussion in both Palestine and Babylonia. The decisions of sages who flourished after the writing of the Mishnah were compiled about <span class="era">AD</span> 450 in Palestine and about 500 in Babylonia. This second stage beyond the Mishnah was called the Gemara (meaning either “completion” or “repetition”). The Mishnah and the Babylonian Gemara make up the Babylonian Talmud, while the same Mishnah with the Jerusalem or Palestinian Gemara comprises the Jerusalem Talmud. Yet another type of rabbinic literature is the Midrashim (“interpretations”), which either follow the order of a particular biblical book or consist of homilies on particular biblical texts. The Targums, paraphrastic translations of Scripture into the Aramaic language, finally came to be written down beginning in the late second century <span class="era">AD</span>.</p>
<p>After the destruction of the temple, rabbinic Judaism concentrated on the religious significance of the Torah and elevated scholarship to the central role that it still plays in Judaism. Rabbinic Judaism gradually exerted its influence upon diaspora Judaism under the initial leadership of Rabbi Johanan until a kind of rabbinic orthodoxy emerged during the second century. Christianity was one of the major ideological foes of rabbinic Judaism. In order to purge Jewish Christians from their midst, the rabbis introduced an additional benediction to the eighteen benedictions customarily recited at synagogue services. This 19th benediction was a curse upon the <span class="ital">minim</span> (Christians and other heretics), which Jewish Christians who attended synagogue services found impossible to recite. The line was firmly drawn between Judaism and Christianity by this device, which was employed late in the first century.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DeadSeaScrolls_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dead Sea Scrolls</a>; <a href="?item=Essenes_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Essenes</a>; <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=FirstJewishRevolt_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">First Jewish Revolt</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=Jew_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jew</a>; <a href="?item=JudahTribeof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judah, Tribe of</a>; <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>; <a href="?item=Pharisees_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Pharisees</a>; <a href="?item=PhiloJudaeus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Philo, Judaeus</a>; <a href="?item=PostexilicPeriod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Postexilic Period</a>; <a href="?item=Sanhedrin_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sanhedrin</a>; <a href="?item=Talmud_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Talmud</a>; <a href="?item=Torah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Torah</a>; <a href="?item=Tradition_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tradition</a>; <a href="?item=TraditionOral_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tradition, Oral</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>