<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Zealot">
  <title>Zealot</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ZEALOT</p>
<p class="fl">Term used for the second Simon among the Twelve to distinguish him from Simon Peter (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.15">Lk 6:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.13">Acts 1:13</a>). Matthew (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.4">Mt 10:4</a>) and Mark (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.18">Mk 3:18</a>) use “Cananaean”—Greek and Aramaic equivalents for “zealous defender, enthusiast, one eager to acquire, fanatic” (from root words meaning “burn with zeal, or jealousy; desire eagerly”; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.14">Ex 34:14</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Macc.4.2">2 Macc 4:2</a>). In this general sense, Christ showed zeal for God’s house. Some were “zealots” for spiritual gifts, good works, goodness, and the law, as Paul was for the tradition of the fathers and for God (<a href="?bref=John.2.17">Jn 2:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.21.20">Acts 21:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.22.3">22:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.12">1 Cor 14:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Gal.1.14">Gal 1:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.2.14">Ti 2:14</a>). So, Simon was distinguished from Peter and the others by his religious zeal.</p>
<p>By the time Luke wrote, the title “Zealot” had become attached especially to a militant, anti-Roman, revolutionary faction, equally religious and political in motivation. This party may have been founded in <span class="era">AD</span> 6, following the death of Herod the Great, by Judas the Galilean and Zadduk the Pharisee. The movement was rooted in Maccabean resistance to foreign rule and infiltration (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.2.15-28">1 Macc 2:15-28</a>). Zealot opposition to Roman rule was rooted in zeal for the Torah and for God the only King. The Zealot regarded himself as an agent of divine judgment and redemption, resolutely and fearlessly contending against idolatry, apostasy, and collaboration. The Zealots thought that the Messiah would become their leader.</p>
<p>As hostility between Rome and Judea sharpened, the religious motivation was channeled by nationalist feeling into a “holy war.” Whereas the Maccabees had been forced to take arms in self-defense, the Zealots became increasingly militaristic. Josephus (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 18.1.1-6; <span class="ital">War</span> 4.3.9), with some prejudice, calls them brigands and robbers. Their Latin name was <span class="ital">sicarii,</span> assassins, but supporters would call them patriotic guerrillas. They reached preeminence in the revolt against Rome (<span class="era">AD</span> 66–70). Their last refuge and stronghold, at Masada, was overcome in <span class="era">AD</span> 73, when the surviving 960 committed suicide.</p>
<p>Simon probably was, or had been, a member of this movement’s earlier phase, around <span class="era">AD</span> 30. It is less probable that Judas Iscariot (possibly Sicarius) and the “sons of thunder” (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.17">Mk 3:17</a>) were. Judas the Galilean (<a href="?bref=Acts.5.37-38">Acts 5:37-38</a>), and even Paul (<a href="?bref=Acts.21.38">21:38</a>), were considered Zealots.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=FirstJewishRevolt_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">First Jewish Revolt</a>; <a href="?item=Judaism_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judaism</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>