<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Zerah">
  <title>Zerah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ZERAH</p>
<p class="list">1. One of the chiefs of the Edomites (<a href="?bref=Gen.36.17">Gn 36:17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.37">1 Chr 1:37</a>), listed as the son of Reuel, Esau’s son by his wife Basemath, and likely the ancestor of Jobab, who later assumed the position of king of the Edomites (<a href="?bref=Gen.36.13,33">Gn 36:13, 33</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. One of the twin sons of Judah by his daughter-in-law Tamar (<a href="?bref=Gen.38.30">Gn 38:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.46.12">46:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.1.3">Mt 1:3</a>). Although Zerah thrust out his hand first, he retracted it, allowing his brother, Perez, to be born first. The descendants of Zerah (the Zerahites) became one of the most influential clans of Judah (<a href="?bref=Num.26.20">Nm 26:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.7.1,18">Jos 7:1, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.22.20">22:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.4-6">1 Chr 2:4-6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.6">9:6</a>). Because Ethan and Heman are listed as sons of Zerah in <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.6">1 Chronicles 2:6</a>, the Ezrahites mentioned in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.31">1 Kings 4:31</a> and the titles to <a href="?bref=Ps.88.1-18">Psalms 88</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.89.1-52">89</a> are also considered to be Zerahites. However, Ethan and Heman are listed as Levites in <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.17">1 Chronicles 15:17</a>, thus making it more likely that the Ezrahites were a Levite clan.</p>
<p class="list">3. One of the sons of Simeon from whom the Zerahite clan descended (<a href="?bref=Num.26.13">Nm 26:13</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.4.24">1 Chr 4:24</a>); alternately called Zohar in <a href="?bref=Gen.46.10">Genesis 46:10</a> and <a href="?bref=Exod.6.15">Exodus 6:15</a>.</p>
<p class="list">4. One of the sons of Iddo, from the Gershonite branch of Levi’s tribe (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.21">1 Chr 6:21</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. One of the ancestors of Asaph from Levi’s tribe, listed as the son of Adaiah and the father of Ethni (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.41">1 Chr 6:41</a>). Several believe him to be the same individual as #4 above.</p>
<p class="list">6. Commander of the Ethiopians (Cushites) who fought against Asa, king of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.14.9">2 Chr 14:9</a>). It is difficult to identify this individual or the historical event with any certainty. The most common identification has been with Usarkon II of Egypt. The account of the battle agrees with the chronology of Usarkon’s reign in Egypt, as do the number and nationalities of the troops involved in the conflict.</p>
  </body>
</item>