<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="IntercessionofChrist">
  <title>Intercession of Christ*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">INTERCESSION OF CHRIST*</p>
<p class="fl">Theological term for Christ’s activity of petitioning God the Father to save, help, and sustain people on earth.</p>
<p>The Hebrew word meaning “to make intercession” is from a root meaning “to strike”; hence it means “to assail or encounter with a request.” That word is used prophetically of the ministry of the “servant of the Lord”: “He bore the sin of many, and made intercession for the transgressors” (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.12">Is 53:12</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The principal Greek verb meant in secular usage to “meet,” “approach,” or “make an appeal.” In intertestamental literature that word was employed in the sense of personally petitioning an official to gain a favor (e.g., <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Macc.4.8">2 Macc 4:8</a>). The noun form of the word is translated in the NT both as “intercession” (<a href="?bref=1Tim.2.1">1 Tm 2:1</a>) and as “prayer” (<a href="?bref=1Tim.4.5">4:5</a>).</p>
<p>Theologians generally see intercession as the second phase of Christ’s “high priestly work,” after he first made satisfaction for sin through his suffering and death on the cross (<a href="?bref=1Tim.2.5-6">1 Tm 2:5-6</a>). In the OT one of the priest’s functions was to petition God on the people’s behalf. In particular, on the annual Day of Atonement the high priest carried the blood of the sin offering into the Holy of Holies, sanctified the sacred place by means of incense, and sprinkled the sacrificial blood on and about the “mercy seat” (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.11-19">Lv 16:11-19</a>). Correspondingly, after Christ offered himself on the cross as the sacrifice for sins, he ascended to the Father and entered the heavenly sanctuary where he now represents his people (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.25">Heb 7:25</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="ChristsIntercessiononEarth">Christ’s Intercession on Earth</p>
<p class="fl">Before his life of intercession in heaven, Jesus Christ exercised such a ministry on earth, consistent with his own teaching that the disciples should always pray and not get discouraged (<a href="?bref=Luke.18.1">Lk 18:1</a>). Scripture often points to Jesus in prayer. For example, Jesus interceded at the grave of his friend Lazarus (<a href="?bref=John.11.41-42">Jn 11:41-42</a>). Jesus prayed all night on a mountain before selecting the 12 apostles (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.12-13">Lk 6:12-13</a>). After warning his disciple Peter that Satan had designs on him, Jesus said to Peter, “I have prayed for you that your faith may not fail” (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.32">Lk 22:32</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Jesus’ first words on the cross were a prayer for those who had persecuted him (<a href="?bref=Luke.23.34">23:34</a>).</p>
<p>The “high priestly prayer” recorded in <a href="?bref=John.17.1-26">John 17</a> provides the most complete account in Scripture of an intercessory prayer by Jesus. The ground, or basis, of his impassioned petition was his intimate relationship with his heavenly Father (<a href="?bref=John.17.5,8">Jn 17:5, 8</a>). The objects of his prayer were (1) himself, that he might glorify the Father and complete the work he had been sent to accomplish (<a href="?bref=John.17.1-5">Jn 17:1-5</a>); (2) his disciples, who were chosen to spread the gospel after his departure (vv <a href="?bref=John.17.8-9">8-9</a>); and (3) the entire family of believers (v <a href="?bref=John.17.20">20</a>). The goals of his intercession included (1) the unity of God’s people (vv <a href="?bref=John.17.11,21">11, 21</a>), (2) their joy in spite of hardships and discouragement (v <a href="?bref=John.17.13">13</a>), (3) their preservation from evil (v <a href="?bref=John.17.15">15</a>), (4) their sanctification by the Word of God (v <a href="?bref=John.17.17">17</a>), and (5) their eternal fellowship with Christ (v <a href="?bref=John.17.24">24</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="ChristsIntercessioninHeaven">Christ’s Intercession in Heaven</p>
<p class="fl">Christ’s intercession for his people, begun on earth, is continued in heaven. The Epistle to the Hebrews depicts Christ as a priest, placing considerable emphasis on his continuing ministry of intercession. Christ’s heavenly intercession is a sequel to his earthly sacrifice accomplished “once for all” (<a href="?bref=Heb.10.10-18">Heb 10:10-18</a>). Jesus himself said, “Every one who acknowledges me before men, I also will acknowledge before my Father who is in heaven” (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.32">Mt 10:32</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). His continuing intercession is recognized in such NT phrases as “through Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.8">Rom 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.16.27">16:27</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.5">1 Pt 2:5</a>), “through him” (<a href="?bref=Col.3.17">Col 3:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.13.15">Heb 13:15</a>), and “in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ” (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.20">Eph 5:20</a>).</p>
<p>The doctrine of Christ’s heavenly intercession is explicitly affirmed in four NT texts. The apostle Paul spoke of Christ “at the right hand of God, who indeed intercedes for us” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.34">Rom 8:34</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The writer of Hebrews affirmed that Christ “is able for all time to save those who draw near to God through him, since he always lives to make intercession for them” (<a href="?bref=Heb.7.25">Heb 7:25</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Further, Christ has entered “into heaven itself, now to appear in the presence of God on our behalf” (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.24">9:24</a>). The apostle John also described that ministry: “If any one does sin, we have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.1">1 Jn 2:1</a>). The Greek word for “advocate” meant a legal counselor who appeared before a magistrate to plead a client’s cause. John thus pictured the ascended Lord as appearing before God on behalf of his people, presenting his own obedience and suffering as the ground for the believer’s acquittal.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheWayIntercessionWorks">The Way Intercession Works</p>
<p class="fl">Christ’s heavenly intercession has both a static aspect (his redemptive work has been completed) and a dynamic aspect (he continues to care for God’s people). Thus Christ’s intercession is seen as including (1) his presence with the Father as the ground of each believer’s justification (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.24">Heb 9:24</a>); (2) his thwarting of Satan’s accusations against each believer (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.33">Rom 8:33</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.12.10">Rv 12:10</a>); (3) his claim for each believer’s right of access to the divine presence (<a href="?bref=Heb.4.14-16">Heb 4:14-16</a>); and (4) his mediation of the prayers of each believer. The heavenly Father’s response is to impart the full range of spiritual blessings on believers. In the words of the Puritan John Owen (1616–83), “The intercession of Christ . . . is his continual appearance for us in the presence of God, representing the efficacy of his oblation, accompanied with tender care, love and desires for the welfare, supply, deliverance and salvation of the church.”</p>
<p>Those for whom Christ intercedes in heaven are described in Scripture both broadly and narrowly. Christ is said to pray for all people everywhere (<a href="?bref=Isa.53.12">Is 53:12</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.26.28">Mt 26:28</a>). More specifically, and perhaps more profoundly, he prays for his own redeemed community, the church (<a href="?bref=John.14.16">Jn 14:16</a>; <a href="?bref=John.17.9,20">17:9, 20</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.15-16">Heb 4:15-16</a>). Nevertheless, Christ’s prayers are also centered on the specific needs of individual believers (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.31-32">Lk 22:31-32</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.2.1">1 Jn 2:1</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>