<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Maaseiah">
  <title>Maaseiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MAASEIAH</p>
<p class="list"> 1. One of the singers appointed by the Levites to accompany David when he brought the ark from Obed-edom’s house to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=1Chr.15.18-20">1 Chr 15:18-20</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Commander who agreed to assist Jehoiada the priest in crowning Joash king (<a href="?bref=2Chr.23.1">2 Chr 23:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Officer who served King Uzziah by assisting in the organization of the king’s army (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.11">2 Chr 26:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Son of Judah’s royal house who was slain when Pekah the king of Israel invaded Judah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.28.7">2 Chr 28:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Ruler in Jerusalem whom Josiah appointed to assist in repairing the temple (<a href="?bref=2Chr.34.8">2 Chr 34:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6–8. Three priests who obeyed Ezra’s exhortation to divorce their foreign wives during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.18-22">Ezr 10:18-22</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Pahath-moab’s son (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.30">Ezr 10:30</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Father of Azariah, a repairman of the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.23">Neh 3:23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Ezra’s attendant when he read the law to the people (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.4">Neh 8:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. Levite who, with others, helped the people to understand the law Ezra read (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.7">Neh 8:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">13. Leader who set his seal on Ezra’s covenant under Nehemiah’s leadership (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.25">Neh 10:25</a>).</p>
<p class="list">14. Judahite leader and the son of Baruch, who lived in Jerusalem with those chosen by lot to inherit the rebuilt city (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.5">Neh 11:5</a>). He is sometimes identified with the Asaiah mentioned in <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.5">1 Chronicles 9:5</a>.</p>
<p class="list">15. Ithiel’s son from Benjamin’s tribe who was chosen to live in Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.7">Neh 11:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">16. Priestly trumpeter at the dedication of the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.41">Neh 12:41</a>).</p>
<p class="list">17. Priestly singer at the dedication of the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.42">Neh 12:42</a>).</p>
<p class="list">18. Father of Zephaniah the priest. Zephaniah, with Pashhur, was sent to Jeremiah by King Zedekiah to inquire of the Lord concerning the future of Nebuchadnezzar’s war against Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Jer.21.1-2">Jer 21:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.29.25">29:25</a>) and to request that Jeremiah pray for Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Jer.37.3">37:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list">19. Father of Zedekiah the false prophet, an opponent of Jeremiah’s prophecy about Jerusalem’s fall under Nebuchadnezzar’s siege (<a href="?bref=Jer.29.21">Jer 29:21</a>).</p>
<p class="list">20. KJV form of Mahseiah, Baruch’s forefather, in <a href="?bref=Jer.32.12">Jeremiah 32:12</a> and <a href="?bref=Jer.51.59">51:59</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Mahseiah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mahseiah</a>.</p>
<p class="list">21. Keeper of the threshold during Jehoiakim’s reign (<a href="?bref=Jer.35.4">Jer 35:4</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>