<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Magi">
  <title>Magi*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MAGI*</p>
<p class="fl">“Wise men” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>) appearing in <a href="?bref=Matt.2.1-12">Matthew 2:1-12</a> who, following a star, came to Jerusalem and then to Bethlehem in order to pay homage to the newborn “king of the Jews.” Matthew’s account forms a significant introduction to his Gospel by drawing attention to the true identity of Jesus as King and by foreshadowing the homage paid by the Gentiles to Jesus throughout that Gospel.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheMagiintheAncientWorld">The Magi in the Ancient World</p>
<p class="fl">Extrabiblical evidence offers various clues that shed light on the place of origin and positions held by the magi of <a href="?bref=Matt.2.1-23">Matthew 2</a>. The historian Herodotus mentioned magi as a priestly caste of Media, or Persia, and, as the religion in Persia at the time was Zoroastrinism, Herodotus’s magi were probably Zoroastrian priests. Herodotus, together with Plutarch and Strabo, suggested that magi were partly responsible for ritual and cultic life (supervising sacrifices and prayers) and partly responsible as royal advisers to the courts of the East. Believing the affairs of history were reflected in the movements of the stars and other phenomena, Herodotus said, the rulers of the East commonly utilized the magi’s knowledge of astrology and dream interpretation to determine affairs of state. The magi were, therefore, concerned with what the movement of the stars (as signs and portents) might signify for the future affairs of history. Such an interest could account not only for the magi’s interest in the star in Matthew, but also their conclusion, shared with Herod, that the star’s appearance signified the birth of a new ruler of great importance (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.2">2:2</a>). Several centuries before Christ, a similar correlation was noted between a stellar phenomenon and the birth of Alexander the Great.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IdentityinMatthewsGospel">Identity in Matthew’s Gospel</p>
<p class="fl">Matthew’s infancy narrative contains little information concerning the identity of the magi. Matthew states only that the magi were “from the East” (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.1-2">2:1-2</a>), an ambiguous point of origin that left room for many subsequent hypotheses. Some church fathers proposed Arabia on the basis of where the gifts (gold, frankincense, and myrrh, <a href="?bref=Matt.2.11">2:11</a>) were likely to have originated. Others suggested Chaldea or Media/Persia because Persia had a caste of priests (magi), which would fit the description in Matthew.</p>
<p class="h2" id="SignificanceinMatthewsGospel">Significance in Matthew’s Gospel</p>
<p class="fl">The visit of the magi plays a significant role in introducing Matthew’s Gospel. From the beginning it reveals the true identity of the infant as the long-expected and prophesied royal Messiah of Israel. This is brought out first in the appearance of the “star,” which carried clear messianic connotations: “a star shall come forth out of Jacob, a scepter shall arise out of Israel” (<a href="?bref=Num.24.17">Nm 24:17</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Isa.60.3">Is 60:3</a>). Second, the interchange between the magi, Herod, and the chief priests and scribes (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.2-6">Mt 2:2-6</a>) reveals that Jesus is the fulfillment of the messianic prophecy of <a href="?bref=Mic.5.2">Micah 5:2</a>, the ruler of Israel coming from the small village of Bethlehem. Third, the offering of the gifts (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.11">Mt 2:11</a>) may also echo the possible messianic promises of <a href="?bref=Ps.68.29">Psalms 68:29</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.72.10">72:10</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to confirming that Jesus is the long-awaited Messiah, the account of the magi’s visit, as part of the introduction to Matthew’s Gospel, introduces several prominent themes that reappear in subsequent chapters. First, the account establishes that Jesus’ messiahship has bearing not only on the Jews but even on the gentile world (symbolized in the “wise men from the East”). A second theme, which surfaces later, is the surprising Gentile’s faith, a faith that is lacking among Jesus’ own people. Even as the foreign magi honor the infant Messiah, Herod and possibly the chief priests and scribes of the people plot the baby’s death (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.3-6,16">Mt 2:3-6, 16</a>). So also elsewhere in the Gospel, Gentiles exhibit faith in Jesus, which often contrasts markedly with the faithlessness of the Jews (see <a href="?bref=Matt.8.5-13">8:5-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.15.21-28">15:21-28</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.27.19,54">27:19, 54</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="TheMysteriousMagi"/>
  </body>
</item>