<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Malchijah">
  <title>Malchijah*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MALCHIJAH* </p>
<p class="list">1. Gershon’s descendant, appointed by David, along with the rest of his family, to serve as a temple musician (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.40">1 Chr 6:40</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span> “Malchiah”).</p>
<p class="list">2. Priest who served in the time of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.12">1 Chr 9:12</a>). His descendants were among those who returned to Jerusalem with Zerubbabel (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.12">Neh 11:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">3. Priest in David’s reign (<a href="?bref=1Chr.24.9">1 Chr 24:9</a>); perhaps the same as #2 above.</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Parosh’s son, who obeyed Ezra’s exhortation to divorce his pagan wife after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.25">Ezr 10:25</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span> “Malchiah”).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. KJV rendering of Hashabiah, another of Parosh’s sons, in <a href="?bref=Ezra.10.25">Ezra 10:25</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Hashabiah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hashabiah #9</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Harim’s son, who obeyed Ezra’s exhortation to divorce his pagan wife after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.31">Ezr 10:31</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span> “Malchiah”). He repaired part of the Jerusalem wall under Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.11">Neh 3:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Recab’s son and the ruler of Beth-hakkerem. Under Nehemiah’s direction, he repaired the Dung Gate of the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.14">Neh 3:14</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Goldsmith who worked under Nehemiah’s direction to help repair the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.31">Neh 3:31</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. One who stood to Ezra’s left during the public reading of the law (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.4">Neh 8:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Priest who signed Ezra’s covenant of faithfulness to God with Nehemiah and others after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.3">Neh 10:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Participant in the dedication of the rebuilt Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.42">Neh 12:42</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. Royal prince who owned a cistern in which the prophet Jeremiah was imprisoned (<a href="?bref=Jer.38.6">Jer 38:6</a>). Malchijah’s son Pashhur (<a href="?bref=Jer.21.1">21:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.38.1">38:1</a>) was one of those who, after hearing the harsh prophecies of Jeremiah, appealed to King Zedekiah to put Jeremiah to death. The princes attempted to do so by throwing him into Malchijah’s cistern.</p>
  </body>
</item>