<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ManassehPerson">
  <title>Manasseh (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MANASSEH (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="list">1. Firstborn son of Joseph and his Egyptian wife, Asenath (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.50-51">Gn 41:50-51</a>). Manasseh, along with Ephraim his brother, visited their grandfather Jacob on his deathbed. Jacob announced that Manasseh and Ephraim were to be considered his own, not Joseph’s sons (<a href="?bref=Gen.48.5-6">Gn 48:5-6</a>), and that Manasseh, the firstborn, would have descendants not quite as great as those of Ephraim (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.48.13-20">13-20</a>). This explains why Ephraim and Manasseh (in that order) provided their names for two of the 12 tribes of Israel but Joseph did not, at least in most listings (cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.7.6">Rv 7:6</a>). Manasseh also founded the Manassite family (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.43">Dt 4:43</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.33">2 Kgs 10:33</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ManassehTribeof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Manasseh, Tribe of</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. KJV translation for Moses in <a href="?bref=Judg.18.30">Judges 18:30</a>. In Hebrew the two names differ by only one letter. Apparently an early scribe was offended that this verse connected Moses’ grandson with idolatry, so he changed the name to Manasseh to preserve Moses’ reputation. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Moses_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Moses</a>.</p>
<p class="list">3. Thirteenth king of Judah (697–642 <span class="era">BC</span>) and Jesus’ ancestor (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.10">Mt 1:10</a>); notorious for his long and wicked reign, described in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.1-26">2 Kings 21:1-26</a> and <a href="?bref=2Chr.33.1-20">2 Chronicles 33:1-20</a>. His father was the godly king Hezekiah, and his mother was Hephzibah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.1">2 Kgs 21:1</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">At the age of 12 he became co-ruler with his father. In 686 <span class="era">BC</span> his father died and he became sole monarch at only 23. His 55-year reign (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.1">2 Kgs 21:1</a>) is dated from the beginning of his co-regency, so he ruled 11 years as co-regent and 44 years as sole king—longer than any other king in Judah or in Israel. Regrettably, he was the most wicked of all the Judean kings, even resorting to a series of murders, presumably to stay in power (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.16">21:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.4">24:4</a>). In addition to murder, among his sins listed in <a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.2-9">2 Kings 21:2-9</a> are rebuilding the high places for pagan worship; encouraging Baal, sun, moon, and star worship; and burning his son as a child sacrifice (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.6">21:6</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.10">23:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.7.31">Jer 7:31</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><a href="?bref=2Chr.33.11-16">Second Chronicles 33:11-16</a> indicates that he was taken as a prisoner of war to Babylon, that he genuinely repented there, that God restored him as king, and that he tried to abolish his former pagan practices and to restore proper worship of God alone. Skepticism about this account is not warranted, even though unparalleled in 2 Kings. Surviving Assyrian records twice mention Manasseh, saying that he faithfully provided men to transport timber from Lebanon to Nineveh for the Assyrian king Esar-haddon (681–669 <span class="era">BC</span>) and that he paid tribute to King Ashurbanipal (669–627 <span class="era">BC</span>) after an Assyrian military campaign in Egypt in 667 <span class="era">BC</span>. Though Pharaoh Neco’s similar captivity and release is mentioned, Manasseh’s is not.</p>
<p class="list-text">When Manasseh died in 642 <span class="era">BC</span>, at the age of 67, he was buried in his own garden (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.21.18">2 Kgs 21:18</a>), rather than with highly regarded kings like Jehoiada and Hezekiah (<a href="?bref=2Chr.24.16">2 Chr 24:16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.32.33">32:33</a>). His son Amon reverted to his father’s wicked practices, but reigned only two years (642–640 <span class="era">BC</span>) before being assassinated. It was his godly grandson Josiah (640–609 <span class="era">BC</span>) who led the people back to the true worship of Yahweh (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.4-14">2 Kgs 23:4-14</a>). But even his reforms could not avert the judgment promised on account of Manasseh’s sins (vv <a href="?bref=2Kgs.23.26-27">26-27</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PrayerofManasseh_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prayer of Manasseh</a>.</p>
<p class="list">4. Pahath-moab’s son, who obeyed Ezra’s exhortation to divorce his pagan wife after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.30">Ezr 10:30</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Hashum’s son, who obeyed Ezra’s exhortation to divorce his pagan wife after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.33">Ezr 10:33</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>