<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ManassehTribeof">
  <title>Manasseh, Tribe of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MANASSEH, Tribe of</p>
<p class="fl">Geographically, the largest of the 12 tribes of Israel, and unique in having two territories, a half-tribe in each. Isolated from each other by the Jordan River valley, they developed separately. The half-tribe west of the Jordan was more important, both in OT and NT times, because it was the main tribe of the northern kingdom of Israel (931–722 <span class="era">BC</span>) and one of the main ancestral stocks of the Samaritans.</p>
<p class="h2" id="EarlyHistory">Early History</p>
<p class="h3">Its Roots</p>
<p class="fl">Its families traced their origins back to Joseph’s elder son Manasseh, to Manasseh’s son Makir or grandson Gilead, or to later descendants such as Zelophehad and Jair. A fair harmony can be constructed from the biblical genealogical data in <a href="?bref=Gen.48.5-6">Gn 48:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.28-34">Nm 26:28-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.17.1-3">Jos 17:1-3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.2.21-23">1 Chr 2:21-23</a>; and <a href="?bref=1Chr.7.14-19">7:14-19</a>, a text corrupted by several copyists’ errors. The mention of Asriel in <a href="?bref=1Chr.7.14">1 Chronicles 7:14</a> seems to be a copyist’s mistake; otherwise, the accounts are capable of being reconciled, even if each list preserved different data and none is complete in itself.</p>
<p class="h3">Its Size</p>
<p class="fl">One year after the exodus, Manasseh had the smallest army, according to Moses’ first census (<a href="?bref=Num.1.34-35">Nm 1:34-35</a>). On the eve of the conquest of Canaan, after wandering 38 years in the Sinai wilderness and then conquering Transjordan, it had the sixth largest fighting force, according to a second census (<a href="?bref=Num.26.28-34">Nm 26:28-34</a>)—52,700 men.</p>
<p class="h3">Its First Settlements</p>
<p class="fl">The soldiers of the eastern half-tribe of Manasseh settled their families in Gilead, which they captured under Moses’ leadership from the Amorite king Og (<a href="?bref=Num.21.32-35">Nm 21:32-35</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.32.39-42">32:39-42</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.3.1-15">Dt 3:1-15</a>). Then, under Joshua, they crossed the Jordan to help the other tribes conquer Canaan (<a href="?bref=Num.32.1-32">Nm 32:1-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.1.12-18">Jos 1:12-18</a>). Subsequently, the western half-tribe received its allotment and began to settle in the central hill country (<a href="?bref=Josh.16.1-9">Jos 16:1-9</a>; ch <a href="?bref=Josh.17.1-18">17</a>). After the remaining tribes received their shares of land, the army from the eastern half-tribe returned home (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.1-9">22:1-9</a>). En route to their families in Gilead, they helped to build an altar by the Jordan River. This act was intended to preserve national unity, but it nearly started a civil war (vv <a href="?bref=Josh.22.10-34">10-34</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheEasternHalf-Tribe">The Eastern Half-Tribe</p>
<p class="h3">Its Territory</p>
<p class="fl">Moses allotted the eastern half-tribe nearly 3,000 square miles (7,770 square kilometers) of territory in three geographical regions (northern Gilead, Bashan, and Mt Hermon), but it succeeded in controlling only about 800 square miles (2,072 square kilometers)—the half of Gilead north of the Jabbok River (and south of the Yarmuk River)—despite successful initial conquests (<a href="?bref=Num.32.39-42">Nm 32:39-42</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.3.12-15">Dt 3:12-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.13.8-13">Jos 13:8-13</a>) and gradual northern expansion much later (<a href="?bref=1Chr.5.23">1 Chr 5:23</a>).</p>
<p>The territory occupied was mostly a high plateau with a mountainous center. It was watered well by rains in winter and by a heavy dew in summer. Olive trees, grapevines, and wheat thrived, and goats and sheep could find adequate pasture on the eastern slopes, which merged gradually into the desert to the east.</p>
<p class="h3">People and Places</p>
<p class="fl">Prominent citizens of the eastern half-tribe included the “judges” Jair and Jephthah (<a href="?bref=Judg.10.3-5">Jgs 10:3-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.11.6-12">11:6-12</a>) and David’s benefactor Barzillai (<a href="?bref=2Sam.19.31-39">2 Sm 19:31-39</a>). Principal cities were Jabeth-gilead and Ramoth-gilead, a city of refuge and a Levitical city, respectively (originally in Gad—<a href="?bref=Josh.20.8">Jos 20:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.21.38">21:38</a>).</p>
<p>The eastern territory was usually called simply “the half-tribe of Manasseh,” until David (c. 1000–961 <span class="era">BC</span>) made it an administrative district (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.21">1 Chr 27:21</a>). Solomon (970–930 <span class="era">BC</span>) divided and incorporated it into two new districts (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.13-14">1 Kgs 4:13-14</a>). Under Jeroboam I (930–909 <span class="era">BC</span>), it joined, on equal terms, with eight other tribes and with the western half-tribe, to form a confederacy of ten tribes—the northern kingdom of Israel—in 930 <span class="era">BC</span>. Syria and Assyria both held eastern Manasseh temporarily, in the ninth and eighth centuries <span class="era">BC</span> (cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.10.32-33">2 Kgs 10:32-33</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.7">13:7</a> with <a href="?bref=2Kgs.14.25">14:25</a>; and <a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.29">2 Kgs 15:29</a> with <a href="?bref=2Chr.34.6-7">2 Chr 34:6-7</a>). King Tiglath-pileser III (745–727 <span class="era">BC</span>) of Assyria invaded the area, conquered it, deported its people, and scattered them throughout his empire (<a href="?bref=1Chr.5.26">1 Chr 5:26</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Kgs.15.29">2 Kgs 15:29</a>) about ten years before the rest of the northern kingdom fell to the Assyrians in 722 <span class="era">BC</span>. Most of the western Manassites who were left behind intermarried with the foreigners, began to worship pagan gods, and became ancestors of the Samaritans (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.24-41">2 Kgs 17:24-41</a>). Subsequently, the region was known as Gilead. By NT times the region was partly in the Decapolis and partly in Perea.</p>
  </body>
</item>