<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Manger">
  <title>Manger</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MANGER</p>
<p class="fl">Feeding trough for domesticated animals. The Greek term for manger is found only four times in the NT. Three of these instances are in the Nativity narrative of Luke and are translated with the English word manger (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.7,12,16">Lk 2:7, 12, 16</a>). The fourth occurrence, also in Luke’s Gospel, is translated “manger” in the <span class="sc">rsv</span> and <span class="sc">neb</span>, but “stall” in <a href="?bref=Luke.13.15">13:15</a> in the <span class="sc">kjv</span>, <span class="sc">niv</span>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>.</p>
<p>The most common OT equivalent is the Hebrew term translated “crib” or “stall” in <a href="?bref=Job.39.9">Job 39:9</a>, <a href="?bref=Pr.14.4">Proverbs 14:4</a>, and <a href="?bref=Isa.1.3">Isaiah 1:3</a>. The context of these passages favors the use of the Greek word for manger. In the Septuagint, however, three other Hebrew words are also translated by this same Greek term. They are the Hebrew terms for “a stall,” that is, an enclosure for animals (<a href="?bref=2Chr.32.28">2 Chr 32:28</a>); “a mash” or “fodder” (<a href="?bref=Job.6.5">Jb 6:5</a>); and “pens” or “stalls” (<a href="?bref=Hab.3.17">Hb 3:17</a>).</p>
<p>Through a study of modern Middle Eastern customs and biblical archaeology, two possible locations of the stable and manger area have been determined. In the home of a poor family, the stable was generally a room adjacent to and slightly lower than the living quarters. The stone manger was either located against one of the wooden walls of the stable or carved from a natural outcropping of rock. The other possible location of the stable was in a cave near the house or in the limestone foundation beneath the living quarters of the house. An example of the first of these was found at the ancient site of Megiddo. At Lachish a cave (c. 1200 <span class="era">BC</span>), which seems to have been used as a stable, was discovered beneath the remains of a building.</p>
<p>Traditionally, the manger area in which Jesus was born was a cave stable; it is over such a cave that the present Church of the Nativity was erected. However, the evidence recorded in Luke’s Gospel could as easily refer to an area adjacent to a house. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Life and Teachings of</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>