<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Mari">
  <title>Mari*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MARI*</p>
<p class="fl">Influential city-state, located in eastern Syria, which became important in the early second millennium <span class="era">BC</span>. It seems to have been settled by Semitic nomads, who adopted the values of city dwellers and progressed so far as to adapt cuneiform to their own Akkadian language.</p>
<p>The importance of this cosmopolitan city, which was an outpost of Sumerian civilization, is highlighted by the fact that it became the capital of an empire extending over a great part of northern Mesopotamia, about 22 miles (35.4 kilometers) along the Euphrates River.</p>
<p>Archaeological excavations at Mari yielded a monumental discovery: archives containing over 20,000 documents. These records virtually rewrite the history of western Asia. In addition to the tablets, a well-preserved palace was also unearthed. Original mural paintings were still intact, as were some kitchen and bath installations. These artifacts and tablets shed a great deal of light on life during the period from 1810 to 1760 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p>As one viewed Mari from a distance, a great defensive wall was seen that encircled the city, protecting it from invading forces. One prominent structure rose portentously above the town, probably to an approximate height of 150 feet (45.6 meters). This was the ziggurat, a temple tower built in a lofty pyramidal structure with successive stages. One ascended its heights by means of outside staircases, which led to the shrine at the top. There were smaller temples at its base.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="MariTabletSideFrontAndBack"/>
<p>Not far away, the royal palace commanded about six acres (2.4 hectares) of land. The palace was constructed of extremely thick walls made of brick covered with clay, rising to a height of 16 feet (4.9 meters). An elaborate drainage system was also discovered that effectively carried away rainwater through its bitumen-lined clay pipes, some 30 feet (9.1 meters) underground. The palace at Mari contained nearly 300 rooms. It was not only the royal residence but also the center of business, diplomatic services, and military leadership. It even had room to store merchants’ goods and military equipment, such as battering rams and siege towers. The royal court enjoyed such foods as fish, meat, four varieties of bread, cucumbers, peas, beans, garlic, dates, grapes, and figs. Beverages were beer and wine. The religious observances involved sacrifices and temple prostitution, which was common in the ancient Near East.</p>
<p>The clay tablets of the archives reveal a great deal about the everyday life of the people. Some of the records are bilingual, some literary, but most deal with a period between Jahdun-Lim of Hana, the founder of Mari, to the decline under Zimri-Liom, his son. The recovered information at Mari reveals that the king held court every day, listening to officials and ambassadors presenting affairs of state. He also was called upon to settle certain serious legal disputes. The state religion demanded the daily participation of the king, who visited the temples, officiated at rituals, sacrificed animals, reported to the gods, and attended religious feasts, and who was sometimes considered divine. The king also was responsible for regulating the calendar, which necessitated an extra month every three years.</p>
<p>The commercial and economic records indicate that there were metalworkers, weavers, fullers, gem cutters, jewelers, painters, perfume makers, boatmen, carpenters, leather workers, fishermen, potters, and masons. Payment for services rendered was largely made in goods, though sometimes in gold or silver. Such commodity payments were corn, wool, clothing, wine, or oil.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Inscriptions_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Inscriptions</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>