<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MarkGospelof">
  <title>Mark, Gospel of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MARK, Gospel of</p>
<p class="fl">Second book of the NT, probably written by John Mark of Jerusalem sometime between <span class="era">AD</span> 60 and 68.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#AuthorDateProvenance">Author, Date, Provenance</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Distinctives">Distinctives</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Structure">Structure</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#OccasionPurposeTheology">Occasion, Purpose, Theology</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="AuthorDateProvenance">Author, Date, Provenance</p>
<p class="fl">Our most ancient testimony about who wrote the second Gospel comes from Papias (c. 60–130), author of several expositions of Jesus’ teachings, in which he reports various traditions from “the Elder John” (possibly to be identified with the apostle John, although this is by no means certain). At one point Papias states, “The Elder used to say this also: Mark became Peter’s interpreter and wrote down accurately, though not in order, all that [Peter] remembered concerning the things both said and done by the Lord.” (This quotation was preserved by the fourth-century writer Eusebius of Caesarea in his <span class="ital">Ecclesiastical History</span> 3.39.15.) One need not doubt the basic reliability of this statement. Mark—almost surely to be identified with the John Mark of <a href="?bref=Acts.12.12">Acts 12:12</a> (see also <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.13">1 Pt 5:13</a>)—was a disciple of Peter, and the second Gospel owes its existence, at least in part, to the apostle’s reminiscences. It does not follow, however, that one has adequately characterized Mark’s work if that is all one says. For instance, Papias’s qualification, “though not in order,” indicates that Mark did not intend to write a chronological biography. Furthermore, Papias goes on to comment (according to one interpretation of his ambiguous words) that Mark (or Peter?) adapted the material to the teaching situation and that therefore Mark is absolved from any (implied) charges of inaccuracy. It appears that from the earliest times Christians appealed to the purposes and circumstances of Mark’s writing in order to account for difficulties in harmonizing the material found in the various Gospels.</p>
<p>Other statements from Christian writers in the second, third, and fourth centuries seem dependent on Papias’s testimony, but some additional data they provide may possess independent value. For example, a fairly early document (date uncertain) known as the Anti-Marcionite Prologue asserts that Mark wrote his Gospel somewhere in Italy after Peter’s death (in the mid-60s), and this testimony is considered reliable by many scholars. Still, the possibility that Mark composed his work before Peter’s martyrdom cannot be ruled out completely.</p>
<p>Papias says nothing specific about <span class="ital">when</span> the Gospel was written. A small minority of scholars date Mark shortly after <span class="era">AD</span> 70. Another minority suggest a date in the 40s or 50s on the basis of a papyrus fragment discovered in Qumran called 7Q5. (According to José O’Callaghan, the fragment, which has been dated about <span class="era">AD</span> 50–68, should be identified as <a href="?bref=Mark.6.52-53">Mark 6:52-53</a>.) This fragment contains only 20 letters on one side, making the Markan reconstruction very uncertain. Few scholars are convinced that the text is Mark; some think it is part of 1 Enoch or Zechariah. An impressive majority of scholars date Mark in the 60s, with conservatives usually preferring the early years of the decade. Why this preference? If the theory of Markan priority is accepted, then clearly Mark was written before Luke; and since Luke is normally dated by conservatives about <span class="era">AD</span> 62, Mark can be no later than <span class="era">AD</span> 60 or 61. This line of argument, though strong, is not decisive. In the first place, Luke cannot be dated with complete certainty. Second, the view that Matthew and Luke used Mark (the working assumption of most scholars) is only a hypothesis, and one that is vigorously opposed by some writers. Third, a tradition going back to the second century (see above) asserts that Mark wrote his Gospel <span class="ital">after</span> Peter’s death, no earlier than <span class="era">AD</span> 64. Fourth, one persuasive view regarding the occasion of this Gospel assumes that the Neronian persecution (<span class="era">AD</span> 64) had begun. (According to a different view of the occasion, Mark was written after the beginning of the Jewish revolt in <span class="era">AD</span> 66.) Therefore, while a date in the early 60s remains possible, it does not require committal.</p>
<p>With regard to the authorship of the second Gospel, there seems to be no compelling reason to deny Papias’s report that Mark (no doubt the John Mark of <a href="?bref=Acts.12.12">Acts 12:12</a>) took down Peter’s reminiscences and that these became the basis of his work. Some scholars argue that the Gospel contains geographical inaccuracies (e.g., we have no evidence of a region called Dalmanutha, <a href="?bref=Mark.8.10">Mk 8:10</a>) and that a native of Jerusalem such as Mark would have been more reliable in his information. However, the topographical problems in Mark, though real, need not be interpreted as inaccuracies (present ignorance of a place named Dalmanutha is hardly conclusive proof that it did not exist). Furthermore, in other respects (e.g., <a href="?bref=Mark.14.54,66">14:54, 66</a>) the Gospel reveals an impressive knowledge of local details. Many writers also point out bits of information that support a Petrine background, such as the healing of Peter’s mother-in-law (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.30-31">1:30-31</a>). In short, the internal evidence, while falling short of proof, does not at all undermine the tradition preserved by Papias. A generation ago, the trustworthiness of Papias’s testimony was almost universally accepted. This situation has changed somewhat, but even those scholars who adopt a skeptical attitude toward this tradition concede that it <span class="ital">may</span> be true.</p>
<p>As attention turns to the provenance of the Gospel, the task becomes more difficult. Tradition going back to the second century asserts what may be already implied by Papias—namely, that Mark wrote his Gospel in Rome. Although some scholars have suggested other possibilities, such as Galilee and Antioch, these have not proved satisfactory. Mark did spend some time in Rome, and some characteristics in the Gospel (such as Latinisms in the Greek and the explanation of Jewish customs, as in <a href="?bref=Mark.7.3-4">7:3-4</a>), while proving nothing, are certainly consonant with a Roman origin. Furthermore, one persuasive view of the occasion that gave rise to the Gospel assumes a background of persecution in Rome.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Distinctives">Distinctives</p>
<p class="fl">A number of characteristics of Mark set it apart from the other Gospels. For example, a word usually translated “immediately” occurs more than 40 times in Mark and only a dozen times in the rest of the NT. While this feature could be interpreted as a simple “mannerism,” consonant with Mark’s unpretentious, colloquial style, it certainly adds to the rapid flow of his narrative, which, dwelling more on Jesus’ activity than on his discourses (in contrast to Matthew and Luke), shifts from scene to scene with hardly a pause. Since the Gospel is also quite brief (Luke is nearly twice as long), one may wonder whether the author intended for it to be read at a sitting; even if read aloud, this would take only about one and a half hours. At any rate, there can be little doubt that the work conveys a sense of urgency.</p>
<p>Other characteristics, however, prove more significant. Someone unfamiliar with the story of Jesus who happened to read Mark for the first time would no doubt be taken aback by its rather abrupt beginning. After a brief clause that stands as a sort of title (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.1">1:1</a>), Mark moves on to describe in brief the ministry of John the Baptist. Then he introduces Jesus as coming from Nazareth without telling us anything whatever of his earlier life. Furthermore, over one-third of the book (including the so-called Passion narrative) is devoted to Jesus’ last week. These and other factors lend to the work a note of mystery, accentuated by the fact that at various points Mark calls attention to the fear or amazement gripping those who came in contact with Jesus (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.12">2:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.41">4:41</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.5.15,33,42">5:15, 33, 42</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.51">6:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.9.6">9:6</a>; and several other passages, especially the strange words of <a href="?bref=Mark.10.32">10:32</a>). In addition, if one assumes that the Gospel originally ended with <a href="?bref=Mark.16.8">16:8</a>, Mark wished to leave his readers with the same sense of awe that the disciples experienced at Jesus’ resurrection.</p>
<p>But how does one account for this fear and amazement? Mark’s clear answer is that Jesus, though truly a man, is also divine. While Mark’s Gospel exhibits the humanity of Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.41">1:41</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.5">3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.8.12">8:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.14">10:14</a>), his chief emphasis is on the Lord’s deity. Indeed, Mark introduces his book by referring to Jesus as “the Son of God” (a phrase omitted in some manuscripts, however), a position that is recognized both by the demons (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.11">3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.5.7">5:7</a>) and by God himself (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.7">9:7</a>). What may well be the true climax of the Gospel occurs at <a href="?bref=Mark.15.39">15:39</a>, where Mark writes that a Gentile, a Roman centurion, upon hearing Jesus’ death cry, exclaimed, “Truly this man was the Son of God!”</p>
<p class="h2" id="Structure">Structure</p>
<p class="fl">The author organized his Gospel according to a simple plan. The first eight chapters summarize the nature of Christ’s public ministry by alternating stories that show his growing popularity with stories that stress the disapproval of the Jewish leaders. This first half of the book, while indicating some of the tensions created by Jesus’ coming, gives the basic impression of success and general optimism. A significant shift then strikes the reader toward the end of chapter <a href="?bref=Mark.8.1-38">8</a>, particularly beginning with verse <a href="?bref=Mark.8.31">31</a>. At Caesarea Philippi, Peter has just confessed that Jesus is the Messiah, and now for the first time Jesus reveals that as Messiah he must die. The disciples become perplexed and discouraged and their pessimism mounts as this thought is brought home to them repeatedly (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.9,31">9:9, 31</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.32-34">10:32-34</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.17-25">14:17-25</a>). In the end they desert their master (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.50">14:50</a>).</p>
<p>Interestingly, this pessimistic note is anticipated in the earlier part of the Gospel at three points: <a href="?bref=Mark.3.6">3:6</a> (Jesus’ enemies plot his death); <a href="?bref=Mark.6.6">6:6</a> (faithlessness in Nazareth); and <a href="?bref=Mark.8.21">8:21</a> (lack of understanding in the disciples). Some scholars suggest that Mark used these three verses to indicate the first three divisions of his book. In addition, other scholars note that two healings of blind men (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.22-26">8:22-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.10.46-52">10:46-52</a>) seem to provide the opening and the conclusion of a section that emphasizes the spiritual blindness of the disciples. One more structural clue is <a href="?bref=Mark.14.1">14:1</a>, which clearly marks out the final section of the Gospel.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="MarkInCodexVaticanus"/>
<p class="h2" id="OccasionPurposeTheology">Occasion, Purpose, Theology</p>
<p class="fl">A few scholars think that Mark may have been combating a heretical sect that stressed the miracles of Jesus and viewed him purely as a divine wonder-worker. Although this view has not gained acceptance as originally formulated, a number of writers do see the Gospel as a theological corrective. Ralph Martin, who links Mark very closely with Paul, suggests that the evangelist is opposing some heretical groups who have distorted Paul’s message by placing exclusive stress on Christ as a <span class="ital">heavenly</span> figure (cf. the views that Paul himself opposes in Colossians). Mark responds to these aberrations by emphasizing, in Martin’s words, “the paradox of Jesus’ earthly life in which suffering and vindication form a two-beat rhythm.” Even if one decides that this reconstruction, too, is rather speculative, one may nevertheless retain certain elements in it as valid.</p>
<p>Other scholars, such as H. Kee, place emphasis on the apocalyptic background of Mark. Kee and others tie this element to the Jewish revolt of <span class="era">AD</span> 66, but commitment to this particular historical connection is unnecessary to appreciate the great significance of <a href="?bref=Mark.13.1-37">Mark 13</a> (Jesus’ apocalyptic discourse) for those original readers of the Gospel who may have been undergoing persecution.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most satisfactory reconstruction links this Gospel to the Neronian persecution in the mid-60s. Mark, for example, is the only Gospel that records that Jesus, after being driven to the wilderness, found himself in the company of wild animals (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.13">1:13</a>). This detail, according to William Lane, “was filled with special significance for those called to enter the arena where they stood helpless in the presence of wild beasts.” This interpretation, while not without difficulties, has the advantage of accounting for most of the available data. First, it is compatible with the strong tradition that assigns the origin of Mark’s work to Rome. Second, Mark speaks distinctly to those suffering persecution by introducing them quickly to John’s imprisonment and several other details. Third, related to this is Mark’s emphasis on discipleship. Christians facing persecution must have been tempted to relax the standards (<a href="?bref=Mark.4.17-19">4:17-19</a>). Fourth, given this general situation, one can hardly doubt the significance of our Lord’s apocalyptic message in chapter <a href="?bref=Mark.13.1-37">13</a>, intended to encourage the disciples in the midst of their trials by reminding them of the glory to follow. Finally, Mark’s clear concern for the Gentile mission fits in with the needs of pagan Rome. The suffering Christians cannot afford to forget the unbelieving society in which they live. In the light of this particular responsibility, Mark assures his readers of what even the Roman centurion began to recognize—surely Jesus <span class="ital">is</span> the Son of God (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.39">15:39</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="fl">The development of Mark’s narrative can be presented in six major divisions within a twofold structure:</p>
<p class="list-0">Introduction (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.1-13">1:1-13</a>)</p>
<p class="list-0">Part I: Popularity and Opposition (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.14-8.21">1:14–8:21</a>)</p>
<p class="list-1">1. Jesus’ authority and the Pharisees’ enmity (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.14-3.6">1:14–3:6</a>)</p>
<p class="list-1">2. The people’s response (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.7-6.6">3:7–6:6a</a>)</p>
<p class="list-1">3. The disciples’ misunderstanding (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.6b-8.21">6:6b–8:21</a>)</p>
<p class="list-0">Part II: Darkness and Death (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.22-15.47">8:22–15:47</a>)</p>
<p class="list-1">4. The Messiah’s mission and the disciples’ blind-ness (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.22-10.52">8:22–10:52</a>)</p>
<p class="list-1">5. Final ministry (<a href="?bref=Mark.11.1-13.37">11:1–13:37</a>)</p>
<p class="list-1">6. The Passion narrative (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.1-15.47">14:1–15:47</a>)</p>
<p class="list-1">Conclusion (<a href="?bref=Mark.16.1-8">16:1-8</a>)</p>
<p class="sp">Although one can hardly claim that this outline corresponds exactly to the author’s original plan (Mark may not have consciously worked out a detailed outline), the sixfold division provides a useful starting point for an interpretive summary of the contents.</p>
<p class="h3">Jesus’ Authority and the Pharisees’ Enmity (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.14-3.6">1:14–3:6</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Immediately after the introductory portion (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.1-13">1:1-13</a>), which describes John the Baptist’s ministry as well as Jesus’ baptism and temptation, Mark opens the body of the work with a summary statement (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.1.14-15">14-15</a>). In these two verses he seems to suggest that Jesus’ public ministry, characterized by the proclamation that God’s kingdom is about to be inaugurated, was occasioned by John’s imprisonment. This is followed by the call of the first disciples (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.1.16-20">16-20</a>) and then by a complex of stories (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.1.21-38">21-38</a>), all of which report incidents that took place in Capernaum, apparently within a 24-hour period: synagogue instruction followed by the healing of a demoniac; the healing of Peter’s mother-in-law; numerous other healings in the evening; prayer in a lonely place. The statement that Jesus proceeded to expand his ministry throughout the province of Galilee (v <a href="?bref=Mark.1.39">39</a>) is followed by the story of a leper’s cure (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.1.40-45">40-45</a>). Next are found a very important group of incidents (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.1-3.6">2:1–3:6</a>), all of them focusing on Jesus’ conflicts with Jewish leaders: the healing and forgiveness of a paralytic; the call of Levi, whose dinner (attended by Jesus as well as by the hated tax gatherers) occasioned some disputes, particularly on the issue of fasting; and two significant stories regarding proper behavior on the Sabbath.</p>
<p class="h3">The People’s Response (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.7-6.6">3:7–6:6a</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Mark opens this second section as he opened the first: a summary statement (Jesus’ healings by the lake—<a href="?bref=Mark.3.7-12">3:7-12</a>) followed by the official appointment of 12 apostles (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.3.13-19">13-19</a>). Then follows a section that focuses on the kinds of charges brought against Jesus by his own family and by the scribes (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.3.20-22">20-22</a>), leading to a response touching on Satan, on blasphemy against the Holy Spirit, and on what constitutes true membership in his family (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.3.23-35">23-35</a>). Most of chapter <a href="?bref=Mark.4.1-41">4</a> is devoted to Jesus’ parables of the kingdom—the sower, the seed growing secretly, the mustard seed—and includes statements on the nature and purpose of his teachings (<a href="?bref=Mark.4.10-12,21-25,33-34">4:10-12, 21-25, 33-34</a>). In the evening Jesus and his disciples set out to cross the Sea of Galilee, leading to the stilling of the storm (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.4.35-41">35-41</a>), the healing of the Gerasene demoniac on the other side of the lake (<a href="?bref=Mark.5.1-20">5:1-20</a>), and, on their return to Capernaum, the healing of a hemorrhaging woman and the raising of Jairus’s daughter (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.5.21-43">21-43</a>). The section concludes with Jesus’ visit to his hometown, Nazareth, and the rejection he suffered there (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.1-6">6:1-6a</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Disciples’ Misunderstanding (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.6b-8.21">6:6b–8:21</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The third section begins with two introductory passages: the sending out of the 12 (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.6b-13">6:6b-13</a>) and the story of John the Baptist’s death (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.6.14-29">14-29</a>). When the disciples return, Jesus determines to seek some rest, but the crowds follow them; Jesus then teaches and feeds the 5,000 (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.6.30-44">30-44</a>) and, after crossing the lake (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.6.45-52">45-52</a>, which includes Jesus’ walk over the water), he performs numerous cures in and around Gennesaret (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.6.53-56">53-56</a>). Then follows a controversy with the Pharisees regarding the hand-washing ritual (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.1-8">7:1-8</a>), and this incident leads to Christ’s assertion of the authority of God’s word over human tradition (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.7.9-13">9-13</a>) and to some general instructions on true purity (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.7.14-23">14-23</a>). The next several stories describe Jesus’ withdrawal from Galilee, first to Tyre, where a gentile woman’s daughter is healed (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.7.24-30">24-30</a>), then to the Decapolis, where he cures a deaf-mute (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.7.31-37">31-37</a>) and feeds a crowd of four thousand (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.1-10">8:1-10</a>). The demand of the Pharisees for a sign (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.8.11-12">11-12</a>) leads to Jesus’ warning against the “leaven” of the Pharisees, a statement misunderstood by the disciples (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.8.13-21">13-21</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Messiah’s Mission and the Disciples’ Blindness (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.22-10.52">8:22–10:52</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Still away from Galilee, but now in the nearby town of Bethsaida, Jesus heals a blind man (<a href="?bref=Mark.8.22-26">8:22-26</a>). He then leads his disciples north toward Caesarea Philippi, which sets the stage for Peter’s confession (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.8.27-30">27-30</a>). This recognition on the part of the disciples (of whom Peter is in effect a representative) leads Jesus to prophesy his death, but Peter’s refusal to accept the prophecy calls forth a rebuke and instruction on discipleship (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.8.31-38">31-38</a>). The failure of the disciples to understand the necessity of Christ’s death provides the background for the Transfiguration (<a href="?bref=Mark.9.1-8">9:1-8</a>), which assures Peter, John, and James that God’s kingdom will indeed come (note v <a href="?bref=Mark.9.1">1</a>); further, the Father himself enjoins them to believe Jesus’ prophecy (v <a href="?bref=Mark.9.7">7</a>). After some words about the resurrection and about the coming of Elijah (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.9.9-13">9-13</a>), Mark relates the healing of a demoniac boy (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.9.14-29">14-29</a>). Back in Galilee, a second prophecy of Jesus’ death (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.9.30-32">30-32</a>) is followed, sadly, by a trivial discussion among the disciples as to who is the greatest (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.9.33-37">33-37</a>). Appropriately, one finds some further instructions concerning discipleship (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.9.38-50">38-50</a>). Mark next writes that Jesus left Galilee for the last time and began his journey toward the south. During this journey, Jesus delivered teachings on divorce and on the spiritual privileges of children (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.1-16">10:1-16</a>), then met the rich young ruler (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.10.17-22">17-22</a>), an incident that leads to further words on discipleship (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.10.23-31">23-31</a>). A third prophecy of Jesus’ death (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.10.32-34">32-34</a>) is again followed by selfish behavior on the part of the disciples, in this case an ambitious request from James and John (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.10.35-40">35-40</a>). The incident produces indignation among the rest of the disciples, thus necessitating another rebuke from their master, who himself came to serve and to die (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.10.41-45">41-45</a>). The section ends as it began—by reporting the cure of a blind man, Bartimaeus of Jericho in this story (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.10.46-52">46-52</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Final Ministry (<a href="?bref=Mark.11.1-13.37">11:1–13:37</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This section seems naturally to divide into three balanced subsections. The first one (<a href="?bref=Mark.11.1-26">11:1-26</a>) includes three events: the Triumphal Entry, the withering of the fig tree, and the cleansing of the temple. The second subsection (<a href="?bref=Mark.11.27-12.44">11:27–12:44</a>) is particularly important, for here is found Jesus’ final series of controversies with the Jewish leaders. The topics covered are the source of Jesus’ authority (<a href="?bref=Mark.11.27-33">11:27-33</a>), the parable of the wicked husbandmen (<a href="?bref=Mark.12.1-12">12:1-12</a>), the legitimacy of Caesar’s tax (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.12.13-17">13-17</a>), the Sadducees’ denial of resurrection (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.12.18-27">18-27</a>), the chief commandment (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.12.28-34">28-34</a>), and the question regarding David’s son (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.12.35-37">35-37</a>). This subsection ends with a warning against the scribes and with the story of the widow’s mite (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.12.38-44">38-44</a>). The third subsection (ch <a href="?bref=Mark.13.1-37">13</a>) is devoted completely to the Olivet discourse, with its prophecies of destruction, calamities, persecutions, deceivers, and final vindication. The discourse ends with various admonitions to keep alert.</p>
<p class="h3">The Passion Narrative (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.1-15.47">14:1–15:47</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This final section, which is introduced by a report of the priests’ plot (<a href="?bref=Mark.14.1-2">14:1-2</a>), may be divided into two subsections. The first one relates the events leading up to Jesus’ trial (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.14.3-52">3-52</a>). They include the anointing of Jesus (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.14.3-9">3-9</a>), Judas’s betrayal (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.14.10-11">10-11</a>), the incidents connected with the Last Supper (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.14.12-31">12-31</a>), the scene at Gethsemane (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.14.32-42">32-42</a>), and the arrest (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.14.43-52">43-52</a>). The second subsection relates Jesus’ trial before the Jews (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.14.53-65">53-65</a>), Peter’s denials (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.14.66-72">66-72</a>), the trial before Pilate (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.1-15">15:1-15</a>), the crucifixion (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.15.16-41">16-41</a>), and the burial (vv <a href="?bref=Mark.15.42-47">42-47</a>).</p>
<p>The Gospel concludes somewhat mysteriously, but no less triumphantly, with the news that Jesus has risen from the dead (<a href="?bref=Mark.16.1-8">16:1-8</a>). The earliest surviving Greek manuscripts, usually regarded as the most reliable, end at verse <a href="?bref=Mark.16.8">8</a>; the majority of manuscripts, however, include an additional 12 verses that report Jesus’ appearances to his disciples.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=JesusChristTeachingsof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Jesus Christ, Life and Teachings of</a>; <a href="?item=MarkJohn_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mark, John</a>; <a href="?item=MatthewGospelof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Matthew, Gospel of</a>; <a href="?item=LukeGospelof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Luke, Gospel of</a>; <a href="?item=SynopticGospels_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Synoptic Gospels</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>