<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MarriageMarriageCustoms">
  <title>Marriage, Marriage Customs</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MARRIAGE, MARRIAGE CUSTOMS</p>
<p class="fl">The joining together of male and female in matrimony, as practiced by various cultures.</p>
<p>The idea of marriage was ordained by God in his instruction to Adam that a man should leave his father and mother, and that he and his wife should be as one flesh (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Gn 2:24</a>). </p>
<p>Several forms of marriage are referred to in the OT, the earliest of which seems to be based on a matrilineal principle. Although there appears to be some evidence for this in the middle Bronze Age and in the early monarchy, it is difficult to be certain about the matter, despite the importance in Egypt, and perhaps elsewhere, of the role of the mother in determining descent.</p>
<p>Generally, the bride left her parents when she married and went to live with her husband’s clan, as Rebekah did (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.58-59">Gn 24:58-59</a>). The phrase “to marry a wife” is from a root meaning to “become master” (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.13">Dt 21:13</a>), and the wife frequently treated her husband as, and referred to him as, master.</p>
<p>Hebrew genealogical lists indicate that descent was reckoned through the male line (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.10">Gn 5:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.36.9-43">36:9-43</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.1.1-15">Nm 1:1-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Ruth.4.18-22">Ru 4:18-22</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.1-9">1 Chr 1:1-9</a>). The important right of naming a child, indicating power and authority over that child, was exercised almost equally between father and mother in biblical references (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.4.1,25-26">Gn 4:1, 25-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.5.29">5:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.35.18">35:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.1.20">1 Sm 1:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.4.21">4:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.8.3">Is 8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.1.4-9">Hos 1:4-9</a>). Sons were frequently named after their fathers and were identified with them.</p>
<p>The father was the authority figure in the home in a patriarchal society. His wife and children were regarded as his possessions in somewhat the same way as his fields and livestock (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.17">Ex 20:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.21">Dt 5:21</a>). He had the right to sell his daughters (<a href="?bref=Exod.21.7">Ex 21:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.5.5">Neh 5:5</a>), and even had the power of life and death over his children.</p>
<p>The ease with which a man could terminate a marriage by divorcing his wife also shows the measure of his authority in the family (<a href="?bref=Deut.24.1-4">Dt 24:1-4</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Deut.22.13-21">22:13-21</a>).</p>
<p>A levirate marriage was instituted to preserve a family name and inheritance. When a man died, the responsibility for maintaining his widow and any children that she might have fell upon her husband’s closest male relative. The order of responsibility is set out in <a href="?bref=Deut.25.5-10">Deuteronomy 25:5-10</a>. Normally, the brother of the deceased husband living with the clan was expected to enter into a levirate marriage with the widow. If she was childless, the firstborn of the new marriage was regarded as a child of the deceased. Levirate marriage was also known to the Canaanites, Assyrians, and Hittites.</p>
<p>The most familiar levirate situation in the OT, although not conforming strictly to the law of <a href="?bref=Deut.25.1-19">Deuteronomy 25</a>, is described in the book of Ruth. It was essential for Ruth to find some close male relative to marry her so that the family name and property could be preserved. The closest male relative declined the responsibility, feeling that it was a double imposition, first, to have to purchase the land and support Ruth, and second, to know that the first son would be regarded as her dead husband’s child, bearing his name and inheriting the land. Boaz agreed to undertake the responsibility (<a href="?bref=Ruth.2.20-4.10">Ru 2:20–4:10</a>).</p>
<p>Despite numerous examples of polygamy cited in the OT, there is no doubt that the vast majority of the Israelites were monogamous. There are no examples given of large polygamous marriages in the families of commoners.</p>
<p>The original instruction to Adam was that a “man . . . cleaves to his wife” (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Gn 2:24</a>). Hebrew laws generally imply that a marriage with one wife is the most acceptable form of marriage (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.17">Ex 20:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.21.5">21:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.18.8,16-20">Lv 18:8, 16-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.20.10">20:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.5.12">Nm 5:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.5.21">Dt 5:21</a>). Although this seems to have become the norm by the time of the monarchy, a king such as Solomon did not follow Hebrew traditions in this matter. In the postexilic period marriages were predominantly monogamous, although they were being terminated increasingly by divorce. In the NT period monogamy seems to have been the rule, although persons such as Herod the Great were polygamous. Christ taught that marriage should last the lifetime of the partners, and if a man divorced his wife and married another woman during his previous spouse’s lifetime, he committed adultery (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.31-32">Mt 5:31-32</a>).</p>
<p>Marriage generally took place with those who were close to the immediate family circle, and it was imperative, therefore, that limits on acceptable consanguinity should be imposed. In patriarchal times a man could marry his half sister on his father’s side (<a href="?bref=Gen.20.12">Gn 20:12</a>), and this continued to be the case even under David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.13.13">2 Sm 13:13</a>), although it was specifically forbidden in <a href="?bref=Lev.20.17">Leviticus 20:17</a>. As there is some contradiction between the marriage laws of Deuteronomy and those in the Law of Holiness (<a href="?bref=Deut.25.5">Dt 25:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.18.16">Lv 18:16</a>), it is possible that there was some modification of the stricter Levitical regulations. Marriages between cousins, such as Isaac with Rebekah, and Jacob with Rachel and Leah, were common. When a close relative was interested in marriage, it was almost impossible to refuse (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Tb.6.13">Tb 6:13</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Tb.7.11-12">7:11-12</a>). Moses was the offspring of a marriage between nephew and aunt (<a href="?bref=Exod.6.20">Ex 6:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.26.59">Nm 26:59</a>), which would have been forbidden in <a href="?bref=Lev.18.12-13">Leviticus 18:12-13</a> and <a href="?bref=Lev.20.19">20:19</a>, as would Jacob’s marriage with two sisters at the same time (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.30">Gn 29:30</a>).</p>
<p>When the Israelites settled in Canaan, many of them married Canaanite women, much to the consternation of those who desired to maintain the purity of the Hebrew religion (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.4">1 Kgs 11:4</a>). Such intermarriage was prohibited under Mosaic law (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.15-16">Ex 34:15-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.7.3-4">Dt 7:3-4</a>), although many Israelites ignored these regulations and continued to indulge in mixed marriages. If a woman was captured in war and was prepared to abandon her native country, an exception could be made (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.10-14">Dt 21:10-14</a>). By contrast, Samson married a Philistine woman who remained with her own people, but who received conjugal visits from her husband periodically (<a href="?bref=Judg.14.8-15.2">Jgs 14:8–15:2</a>).</p>
<p>The danger of intermarriage affecting the purity of Hebrew religion was considered so great that in the postexilic period wholesale divorce was ordered where Jews had married foreign wives (<a href="?bref=Ezra.9.2">Ezr 9:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.10.3,16-17">10:3, 16-17</a>). The intent was that the national religion should remain pure, even though homes and families were destroyed. Even in NT times, Paul denounced marriage with non-Christians (<a href="?bref=2Cor.6.14-15">2 Cor 6:14-15</a>).</p>
<p>It is difficult to estimate at what age young people married. A boy was considered to be a man by his early teens, and late in Jewish tradition this transition was celebrated by the bar mitzvah, which generally occurred when the boy was 13.</p>
<p>Normally the young man’s parents chose the bride. The resulting discussion about the marriage occurred between the groom’s parents and the bride’s parents, and often neither of the young people was consulted. It was not essential for the eldest in the family to be married first (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.26">Gn 29:26</a>). When Abraham decided that Isaac should be married, a servant was sent to choose a bride from among Abraham’s relatives in Mesopotamia. The servant made contact with the bride’s brother and mother (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.33-53">24:33-53</a>), and it was only afterward that Rebekah was asked to give her consent (vv <a href="?bref=Gen.24.57-58">57-58</a>). Her father was possibly incapacitated; otherwise, it would have been unlikely that her consent would have been asked at all.</p>
<p>One of the reasons why the average young man would not have been able to afford more than one wife was the practice of the bride-price, which had to be paid to the bride’s father. It was possible to substitute service for the bride-price (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.15-30">Gn 29:15-30</a>), or the completion of an appointed task (<a href="?bref=1Sam.18.25-27">1 Sm 18:25-27</a>). A specific sum is mentioned for the bride-price in the case of a virgin who had been raped and who had to be purchased by her seducer. The price was set at 50 shekels, but this was considered to be a punishment; it is probable that the normal amount was between 10 and 320 shekels (<a href="?bref=Lev.27.4-5">Lv 27:4-5</a>).</p>
<p>At the time of the second temple, a virgin bride was considered to be worth 50 shekels, and a widow or divorced woman about half that sum. During this period, a virgin bride was normally married in midweek so that, if her husband found her not to be a virgin, he could bring proof to the court the following day, which would still be in advance of the Sabbath. A widow or a divorced woman normally married on the equivalent of a Thursday, giving her a full day with her husband before the Sabbath.</p>
<p>Marriage was a covenant or alliance between two families. It thus united them, and by extending the kinship, the overall size of the group was increased. This was important in a society where responsibilities for relatives, however distant, were accepted unhesitatingly. The covenant concept also could have political overtones, as with the marriage between Solomon and the Egyptian princess (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.1">1 Kgs 11:1</a>) or Ahab of Israel and Jezebel of Tyre (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.16.31">16:31</a>).</p>
<p>The sealing of the covenant included the transfer of gifts, which would establish the wealth and status of the donor and of the bride (<a href="?bref=Gen.34.12">Gn 34:12</a>). In the ancient Near East, the giving of a gift was thought to include a part of the donor, so that the giver was actually offering a portion of himself. The gift that sealed the covenant also established the donor’s authority over the bride.</p>
<p>The next stage in the marriage procedure was the betrothal. First mentioned in <a href="?bref=Exod.22.16">Exodus 22:16</a>, the term is used several times in Deuteronomy (<a href="?bref=Deut.20.7">Dt 20:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.22.23-24">22:23-24</a>). The betrothal had the legal status of a marriage (<a href="?bref=Deut.28.30">Dt 28:30</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.3.14">2 Sm 3:14</a>), and anyone violating a betrothed virgin would be stoned, according to the law of Deuteronomy, for violating his neighbor’s “wife” (<a href="?bref=Deut.22.23-24">Dt 22:23-24</a>). The meaning of a betrothal involved taking possession, in a manner similar to that of receiving tribute. Nevertheless, there remained a distinction between betrothing a woman and taking her as a wife (<a href="?bref=Deut.20.7">20:7</a>). During the period of betrothal, the prospective groom was exempt from military service. It was assumed that the betrothal was a formal part of a permanent relationship (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.18">Mt 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.1.27">Lk 1:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.2.5">2:5</a>).</p>
<p>A man who was to marry another’s daughter was already regarded as a son-in-law at the time of betrothal (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.14">Gn 19:14</a>). Mary, as Joseph’s betrothed, was actually considered his wife, although he did not have intercourse with her until after the birth of Jesus.</p>
<p>The first biblical record of a wedding being celebrated by a feast is in the story of Jacob (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.22">Gn 29:22</a>). There was no actual marriage contract recorded until its mention in the book of Tobit (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Tb.7.12">Tb 7:12</a>). This contract was not considered valid until the couple had cohabited for a week (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.27">Gn 29:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.14.12,18">Jgs 14:12, 18</a>). When Samson left his bride before the end of the seven-day period, the bride’s parents considered the marriage void and gave her to another man (<a href="?bref=Judg.14.20">Jgs 14:20</a>).</p>
<p>The wedding was an occasion of great family rejoicing. The special clothing of the bride and groom (<a href="?bref=Isa.61.10">Is 61:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.9-13">Ez 16:9-13</a>) included for the bride a fine dress often adorned with jewels (<a href="?bref=Ps.45.14-15">Ps 45:14-15</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.61.10">Is 61:10</a>) and other ornaments, while the bridegroom had fine clothing and wore a diadem (<a href="?bref=Song.3.11">Sg 3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.61.10">Is 61:10</a>). The bride wore a veil (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.65">Gn 24:65</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.3">Sg 4:3</a>), which was removed in the bridal chamber. This would account for Rebekah’s need to veil herself in the presence of Isaac, her fiancé (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.65">Gn 24:65</a>), and also for the ease with which Laban was able to replace Rachel with Leah on Jacob’s wedding night (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.23-25">29:23-25</a>).</p>
<p>Symbolic ceremonies may sometimes have been included as part of the betrothal or wedding ceremonies, such as Ruth’s request that Boaz spread his skirt over her to indicate that he was taking her to wife (<a href="?bref=Ruth.3.9">Ru 3:9</a>). Another ritual may have been the ceremonial removal of the bride’s girdle by the groom in the nuptial chamber, which was a room or tent specially prepared for the newly married couple. The marriage was normally consummated on the first night (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.23">Gn 29:23</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Tb.8.1">Tb 8:1</a>), and the stained linen would be retained as evidence of the bride’s virginity.</p>
<p>In a contrast to the elaborate procession and feasting of the marriage, divorce was simple. A man could divorce his wife if he found fault with her in any particular matter, and this right was not abolished until the 11th century <span class="era">AD</span>. Divorce was discouraged, however, and gradually the procedure became more complex, being hedged about with a number of deterrents.</p>
<p>As the laws regarding divorce became more complex, so the procedure became increasingly expensive. At a later time a lawyer, or sometimes a rabbi, would give advice, especially on such matters as the return of property rightly belonging to the bride or her family.</p>
<p>If a bride was found to have committed adultery, the husband was thought to be entitled to a divorce. This was also the case if he even suspected her of infidelity. He could also divorce his wife if he felt that she had violated normal morality, had become apostate, or had been less than efficient in the management of her household. If a woman refused her husband his conjugal rights for a period of at least one year, she could be divorced. Other grounds for divorcing a wife included insulting behavior to a husband or his relatives, contracting an incurable disease, or refusing to accompany her husband when he moved the domicile to a new area.</p>
<p>In general, the status of the wife was low. Despite the fact that she gave advice, managed the household, educated the young children, and worked alongside her husband when necessary, he was still her master, and her role was to obey. She was little more than a servant, although better than a slave, for she could not be sold even though she could be divorced.</p>
<p>In the frequent figurative uses of marriage in the OT, the Hebrew people and God are referred to in terms of bride and bridegroom (<a href="?bref=Isa.62.4-5">Is 62:4-5</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.2.2">Jer 2:2</a>). The desolation that is about to overtake Judah is contrasted by Jeremiah with the celebration of a wedding feast (<a href="?bref=Jer.7.34">Jer 7:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.16.9">16:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.25.10">25:10</a>). Figurative forms are used again in Hosea, where God rejects the relationship with his wife, Israel (<a href="?bref=Hos.2.2">Hos 2:2</a>), but is prepared to accept her again if she resumes her faithful practices (vv <a href="?bref=Hos.2.19-20">19-20</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT, John the Baptist compares his sense of joy with that of a friend of the groom at a wedding (<a href="?bref=John.3.29">Jn 3:29</a>), while Jesus himself made reference to the wedding preparations in the parable of the wise and foolish virgins (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.1-12">Mt 25:1-12</a>). In the story of the marriage feast (<a href="?bref=Matt.22.1-14">22:1-14</a>) Christ mentions quite incidentally the fact that wedding robes were provided for the guests at such ceremonies. The theme of the Christian church as the bride of Christ occurs in such books as 2 Corinthians, Ephesians, and Revelation.</p>
<p class="h2" id="JesusTeachingsonMarriageandAdultery">Jesus’ Teachings on Marriage and Adultery</p>
<p class="fl">In the realm of civil law there are changes of emphasis in Jesus’ teaching over against the OT. For example, the OT did not regard infidelity by a husband as adultery against his wife. When challenged by the Jews, Jesus said that originally God had made one wife for a man; therefore, there should be no divorce (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.2-9">Mk 10:2-9</a>). Further, he stated if a man does divorce his wife and marry again, he “commits adultery against her” (v <a href="?bref=Mark.10.11">11</a>). Thus, Jesus made man and woman equal as regards adultery. An unfaithful husband is just as adulterous as an unfaithful wife. This revolutionary teaching struck the disciples as severe (see <a href="?bref=Matt.19.10">Mt 19:10</a>), but it illustrates what Jesus meant when he said their righteousness must be greater than that of the Jewish leaders (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.20">5:20</a>).</p>
<p>There is a slight difference in Matthew’s account of Jesus’ teaching, which has led some scholars to argue that Jesus was not quite as strict as the above summary suggests. According to <a href="?bref=Matt.19.9">Matthew 19:9</a>, a wife’s “unchastity” (probably some sexual misconduct) allows an aggrieved husband to divorce her and marry again. If this remark concluded the passage, this interpretation would be the simplest. However, from the context it is more likely that Jesus allowed innocent spouses to separate from their wives but not to remarry. This explains why the disciples were so shocked and why Jesus went on to speak about some who refuse to marry for the sake of the kingdom of heaven (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.12">Mt 19:12</a>). This was also the way the church interpreted the passage for the first five centuries. They allowed Christians to separate but not to remarry (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.7.11">1 Cor 7:11</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Adultery_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Adultery</a>; <a href="?item=CivilLawandJustice_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Civil Law and Justice</a>; <a href="?item=ConcubinageConcubines_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Concubinage, Concubines</a>; <a href="?item=Divorce_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Divorce</a>; <a href="?item=FamilyLifeandRelations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Family Life and Relations</a>; <a href="?item=SexSexuality_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sex, Sexuality</a>; <a href="?item=Virgin_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Virgin</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>