<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MatthewPerson">
  <title>Matthew (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MATTHEW (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Son of Alphaeus; a tax collector by occupation; chosen by Jesus to be one of the 12 apostles; credited with the authorship of the Gospel of Matthew.</p>
<p>Matthew is listed in each of the four rosters of the 12 (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.3">Mt 10:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.3.18">Mk 3:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.15">Lk 6:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.1.13">Acts 1:13</a>). Aside from these lists, Matthew is mentioned only in the account of his calling (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.9">Mt 9:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.2.13-14">Mk 2:13-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.27">Lk 5:27</a>). Before his apostolic call, the Gospels refer to Matthew as Levi (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.14">Mk 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.27">Lk 5:27</a>; compare <a href="?bref=Matt.9.9">Mt 9:9</a>). The identity of Levi as Matthew is beyond all doubt. It is improbable that Matthew was the brother of James the Less whose father was also named Alphaeus (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.3">Mt 10:3</a>), since this fact would have been mentioned in the record of Scripture, as it is in the cases of Peter and Andrew and the sons of Zebedee.</p>
<p>Matthew served King Herod Antipas in Capernaum of Galilee, collecting tariffs on goods passing on the road from Damascus to the Mediterranean Sea. To function in this capacity Matthew would have been an educated man, acquainted with the Greek language as well as the native Aramaic, thus qualifying him to write the Gospel of Matthew. As a tax collector, Matthew may have been a man of wealth, but this occupation also caused him to be despised by the Jews and to be considered among the lowest of people. The Pharisees consistently spoke of tax collectors in the same breath with sinners (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.19">Mt 11:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.2.16">Mk 2:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.34">Lk 7:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.15.1">15:1</a>).</p>
<p>Matthew was called while he was working at his tax booth. Jesus passed by on the road and said to him, “Follow me” (<a href="?bref=Mark.2.14">Mk 2:14</a>). Matthew left everything and did so (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.28">Lk 5:28</a>). Immediately he gave Jesus a great banquet at his house, and a large crowd of his fellow tax collectors and others were there to enjoy it. It was at this feast that the Pharisees and their scribes made the well-known complaint “Why do you eat and drink with tax collectors and sinners?” (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.30">Lk 5:30</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span> mg).</p>
<p>It is not certain when Matthew was called, but it is probable that the first six disciples were present on that day, since the Pharisees complained to Christ’s disciples during Matthew’s feast. Unlike the first men Jesus called, Matthew was not originally a follower of John the Baptist.</p>
  </body>
</item>