<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Mephibosheth">
  <title>Mephibosheth</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MEPHIBOSHETH</p>
<p class="list">1. Son of Jonathan, David’s friend. The original form of the name was undoubtedly Merib-baal (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.34">1 Chr 8:34</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.40">9:40</a>), but when the word <span class="hebrew">baal</span> became predominantly associated with the chief male deity of the Canaanite fertility cult, it was replaced, in some instances, by the Hebrew word <span class="hebrew">bosheth</span> (meaning “shame”). As the grandson of Saul, Mephibosheth was born into a situation of privilege, which changed dramatically when the Philistines attacked. Saul, Jonathan, and two of his brothers were killed in the battle on Mt Gilboa (<a href="?bref=1Sam.31.1-6">1 Sm 31:1-6</a>). When news of the catastrophe reached the Israelite palace at Jezreel, the five-year-old Mephibosheth was snatched up by his nurse. In a panicked scramble for safety, she fell, dropping Mephibosheth, whose legs or ankles were broken. The lack of adequate medical attention meant that he became completely crippled (<a href="?bref=2Sam.4.4">2 Sm 4:4</a>). Eventually, he found refuge at Lo-debar in Transjordan, with Makir, who later on befriended David himself (<a href="?bref=2Sam.9.4">9:4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.17.27">17:27</a>). Mephibosheth’s uncle, Ishbosheth (Saul’s only surviving son), who had been made Israel’s puppet king (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.8-10">2:8-10</a>) was murdered (ch <a href="?bref=2Sam.4.1-12">4</a>). Mephibosheth, although apparently next in succession, appears not to have been considered. When David was established on the throne of a now united kingdom and wished to show kindness to any surviving members of Jonathan’s family, he was informed of Mephibosheth’s existence by Ziba, once an influential steward in Saul’s palace (<a href="?bref=2Sam.9.1-13">9:1-13</a>). Summoned to Jerusalem, Mephibosheth was naturally apprehensive, probably fearing that David might want to eliminate all possible rivals (see <a href="?bref=2Sam.19.28">19:28</a>). But David’s generous nature showed itself in restoring to Mephibosheth all of Saul’s original land, with Ziba and his family continuing to manage the estate, and in granting the cripple a permanent place at the royal table.</p>
<p class="list-text">When Absalom’s rebellion broke out, Ziba met the fleeing David and supplied him with welcome provisions, taking the opportunity to curry favor at the expense of his master. Mephibosheth, he suggested, even entertained hopes of gaining the kingdom for himself. David, in the stress of the crisis, was taken in by this unlikely story and promised Ziba all Mephibosheth’s property (<a href="?bref=2Sam.16.1-4">2 Sm 16:1-4</a>). The civil war over, Mephibosheth himself came to David with clear evidence of his grief at the latter’s exile and therefore of Ziba’s duplicity. But David, not willing to alienate Ziba and probably grateful for his earlier gift, compromised, dividing the land between the two. Mephibosheth’s genuine joy at the king’s restoration was such that the loss of his land was of no account in comparison (<a href="?bref=2Sam.19.24-30">19:24-30</a>). Later, when seven descendants of Saul were slain to appease the Gibeonites, David’s continuing remembrance of Jonathan resulted in Mephibosheth’s being spared (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.7">21:7</a>). Mephibosheth’s son, Mica (<a href="?bref=2Sam.9.12">9:12</a>), became the head of a considerably large family (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.35">1 Chr 8:35</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.41">9:41</a>).</p>
<p class="list">2. Son of Rizpah, Saul’s concubine. Unlike his better-known namesake, he was one of Saul’s seven descendants who had to be hung in order to appease the Gibeonites, whose ancient treaty with Israel had been violated by Saul, causing a three-year famine (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.8">2 Sm 21:8</a>; see <a href="?bref=Josh.9.3-27">Jos 9:3-27</a>). In the sequel (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.10-14">2 Sm 21:10-14</a>), Rizpah’s untiring vigil over the corpses prompted David to give them a decent burial, together with the remains of Saul and Jonathan, in the family sepulcher.</p>
  </body>
</item>