<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MercySeat">
  <title>Mercy Seat*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MERCY SEAT*</p>
<p class="fl">Gold slab placed on top of the ark of the covenant with cherubim attached to it on either end, termed the “mercy seat” in many English versions of the Bible (cf. <a href="?bref=Exod.25.17-22">Ex 25:17-22</a>). The Hebrew word for which “mercy seat” is the translation is technically best rendered as “propitiatory,” a term denoting the removal of wrath by the offering of a gift. The significance of this designation is found in the ceremony performed on the Day of Atonement, held once a year, when blood was sprinkled on the mercy seat to make atonement for the sins of the people of Israel (<a href="?bref=Lev.16.1-34">Lv 16</a>). Because of the importance of this covering on the ark and the ceremony associated with it, the Holy of Holies in which the ark was housed in the temple is termed the “room for the mercy seat” in <a href="?bref=1Chr.28.11">1 Chronicles 28:11</a> (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). The term “mercy seat” came into English use from Luther’s German rendering of the Hebrew term, which is difficult to translate appropriately from the Hebrew (cf. <span class="sc">niv</span> “atonement cover” and <span class="sc">nlt</span> “Ark’s cover”).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TheMercySeatALidOrCoverOnTheArkOfTheCovenant"/>
<p>The mercy seat measured two and a half cubits (45 inches, or 114.3 centimeters) by one and a half cubits (27 inches, 68.6 centimeters). The cherubim on each end were also made of gold and faced each other with their wings spread upward over the ark. It was in this space above the ark that the Lord’s presence with his people was localized in a special sense, and from which the Lord made his commandments known to Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.22">Ex 25:22</a>; cf. also <a href="?bref=Lev.16.2">Lv 16:2</a>). Because of the close association of the Lord’s presence with the space above the ark, he is said to be enthroned between the cherubim (<a href="?bref=1Sam.4.4">1 Sm 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.6.2">2 Sm 6:2</a>). The ark itself contained the tables of stone inscribed with the Ten Commandments that summarized the covenantal obligations of the Israelites to their divine King. When the children of Israel fell short of their covenant obligations by sinning against God and breaking his commands, the blood of the sacrifice sprinkled on the mercy seat made atonement for their sin and reconciled them with God.</p>
<p>The propitiatory or mercy seat points forward to Jesus, who is termed by Paul (<a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">Rom 3:25</a>) the “means of propitiation” through faith in his blood for all who have sinned and fallen short of the glory of God. Here in <a href="?bref=Rom.3.25">Romans 3:25</a> the Greek term translated “propitiation” is the same Greek word consistently used in the Septuagint and in <a href="?bref=Heb.9.5">Hebrews 9:5</a> to translate the Hebrew word for mercy seat in the OT.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ArkoftheCovenant_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ark of the Covenant</a>; <a href="?item=Propitiation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Propitiation</a>; <a href="?item=Tabernacle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tabernacle</a>; <a href="?item=Temple_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Temple</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>