<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Mercy">
  <title>Mercy</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MERCY</p>
<p class="fl">A divine quality by which God faithfully keeps his promises and maintains his covenant relationship with his chosen people despite their unworthiness and unfaithfulness (<a href="?bref=Deut.30.1-6">Dt 30:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.14.1">Is 14:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.39.25-29">Ez 39:25-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.9.15-16,23">Rom 9:15-16, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.11.32">11:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.2.4">Eph 2:4</a>).</p>
<p>The biblical meaning of mercy is exceedingly rich and complex, as evidenced by the fact that several Hebrew and Greek words were used to express the concept. Consequently, there are many synonyms employed in translation to express the dimensions of meaning involved, such as “kindness,” “lovingkindness,” “goodness,” “grace,” “favor,” “pity,” “compassion,” and “steadfast love.” Prominent in the concept of mercy is the compassionate disposition to forgive offenders or adversaries and to help or spare them in their sorry plight.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TheologicalSignificance">Theological Significance</p>
<p class="fl">At the heart of the concept of mercy is the love of God, which is freely manifested in his gracious saving acts on behalf of those to whom he has pledged himself in covenant relationship. In the OT it was his chosen people Israel whom he elected to be his own and to whom he showed mercy (<a href="?bref=Exod.33.19">Ex 33:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.54.10">Is 54:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.63.9">63:9</a>). God persistently puts up with his disobedient and wayward people and continuously seeks them out to draw them back to himself. The psalmist describes God as a father who pities his children who revere and trust him (<a href="?bref=Ps.103.13">Ps 103:13</a>). Hosea pictures God as a loving father who looks down from heaven with a yearning heart of compassion upon his rebellious and wayward people (<a href="?bref=Hos.11.1-12">Hos 11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Jer.31.20">Jer 31:20</a>). He also regards Israel as an unfaithful and adulterous wife whom God loves as a faithful husband in spite of her apostate and sinful condition (<a href="?bref=Hos.1.1-3.5">Hos 1–3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.54.4-8">Is 54:4-8</a>). Isaiah depicts God as a mother who has compassion on the son of her womb (<a href="?bref=Isa.49.15">Is 49:15</a>). These pictures reveal God’s mercy in rich and different ways. Other dimensions include forgiveness and restoration to favor (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.13.23">2 Kgs 13:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.54.8">Is 54:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.18-32">Jl 2:18-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.7.18-20">Mi 7:18-20</a>), and deliverance from distress and perils (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.19-21">Neh 9:19-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.40.11-17">Pss 40:11-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.69.16-36">69:16-36</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.79.8-9">79:8-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.49.10">Is 49:10</a>).</p>
<p>Because of what Israel as a covenant nation had learned about the steadfast love and faithfulness of God, devout Jews instinctively lifted their voices in petition for divine mercy and forgiveness in times of need, eloquently expressed in the penitential psalms (<a href="?bref=Ps.6.1-10">Pss 6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.32.1-11">32</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.38.1-22">38</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.51.1-19">51</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.102.1-28">102</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.130.1-8">130</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.143.1-12">143</a>), as well as other OT passages (<a href="?bref=Exod.34.6">Ex 34:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.17">Neh 9:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.57.1-11">Pss 57</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.79.1-13">79</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.86.1-17">86</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.123.1-4">123</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.33.1-6">Is 33:1-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.9.3-19">Dn 9:3-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.2.13">Jl 2:13</a>). It is the remembrance of God’s mercy that gives the repentant person the hope and assurance of divine favor and of reconciliation with the offended Lord.</p>
<p>In the NT a very descriptive Greek word is used for Jesus’ mercy toward the needy (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.36">Mt 9:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.14.14">14:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.20.34">20:34</a>). It expresses his pity and compassion by means of an intense verb literally translated “to be moved in one’s bowels.” The Hebrews regarded the bowels as the center of the affections, especially that of the most tender kindness. Jesus was described as being deeply moved in his inner feeling of benevolence toward the needy and spontaneously acting to relieve their suffering—to heal (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.34">Mt 20:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.41">Mk 1:41</a>), to raise the dead (<a href="?bref=Luke.7.13">Lk 7:13</a>), and to feed the hungry (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.32">Mt 15:32</a>).</p>
<p>The OT concept of God’s mercy expressed in his faithfulness to the covenant people is found also in the NT (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.50,54,72,78">Lk 1:50, 54, 72, 78</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.2.4">Eph 2:4</a>; <a href="?bref=1Tim.1.2">1 Tm 1:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.3">1 Pt 1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.10">2:10</a>). The most characteristic use of mercy in the NT is that of God’s provision of salvation for mankind in Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.30-32">Rom 11:30-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.2.4">Eph 2:4</a>). God is “the Father of mercies” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.1.3">2 Cor 1:3</a>), which he bestows on those who believe in his Son. It is because he is “so rich in mercy” that he saved those who are spiritually dead and doomed by their sins (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.4-6">Eph 2:4-6</a>). It is out of God’s mercy that one is forgiven and granted eternal life (<a href="?bref=1Tim.1.13-16">1 Tm 1:13-16</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="PeoplesResponsibilitytoShowMercytoOthers">People’s Responsibility to Show Mercy to Others</p>
<p class="fl">Because God has freely extended his mercy irrespective of worthiness or faithfulness, people are to respond by showing mercy to others, even though they do not deserve it or seek it. Indeed, people are commanded to be merciful, especially to the poor, the needy, widows, and orphans (<a href="?bref=Pr.14.31">Prv 14:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.19.17">19:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.6.8">Mi 6:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.7.9-10">Zec 7:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.12">Col 3:12</a>). God regards mercy more than the ritual sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.13">Mt 9:13</a>). God’s mercy in Christ actually puts people under obligation to act toward others as God himself has acted toward them. The Lord made mercy a foundation for his teaching (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.7">Mt 5:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.9.13">9:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.12.7">12:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.23.23">23:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.6.36">Lk 6:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.10.37">10:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.3.17">Jas 3:17</a>). His coming was anticipated and announced in the context of the mercy that would characterize his mission (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.50,54,72,78">Lk 1:50, 54, 72, 78</a>).</p>
<p>Members of the Christian church are to show compassion and practical concern for each other. They are to give aid and relief, love and comfort to one another, as Christ freely gave to them in their need. The apostle James teaches the essential nature of such good works as being of the very essence of genuine faith (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.14-26">Jas 2:14-26</a>). It was the mercy that the good Samaritan had toward the man who was beaten and robbed that was singled out by the Lord for special commendation (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.36-37">Lk 10:36-37</a>). To be full of mercy is a distinguishing virtue of the citizens of the kingdom of heaven (<a href="?bref=Matt.5.7">Mt 5:7</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=GodBeingandAttributesof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">God, Being and Attributes of</a>; <a href="?item=Grace_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Grace</a>; <a href="?item=Love_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Love</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>