<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Meshullam">
  <title>Meshullam</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MESHULLAM</p>
<p class="list"> 1. Forefather of Shaphan, the royal secretary to King Josiah of Judah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.22.3">2 Kgs 22:3</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Zerubbabel’s son and a descendant of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.19">1 Chr 3:19</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Gadite leader registered during the reigns of Jotham, king of Judah (950–932 <span class="era">BC</span>), and Jeroboam II, king of Israel (993–953 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.5.13">1 Chr 5:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Benjamite and a descendant of Elpaal (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.17">1 Chr 8:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Benjamite and the father of Sallu, a resident in Jerusalem during the postexilic period (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.7">1 Chr 9:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.11.7">Neh 11:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Benjamite and the son of Shephatiah, who resided in Jerusalem during the postexilic period (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.8">1 Chr 9:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Priest, the son of Zadok and the father of Hilkiah, whose descendants served in Jerusalem’s sanctuary during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.11">1 Chr 9:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.11.11">Neh 11:11</a>). He is probably identical with Shallum in <a href="?bref=1Chr.6.12-13">1 Chronicles 6:12-13</a>.</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Priest, the son of Meshillemith and a forefather of Adaiah. Adaiah served in Jerusalem’s sanctuary during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.12">1 Chr 9:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Kohathite Levite who was appointed to oversee the repair of the temple during King Josiah’s reign (<a href="?bref=2Chr.34.12">2 Chr 34:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. One of the Jewish leaders whom Ezra sent to Iddo at Casiphia to gather Levites and temple servants for the caravan of Jews returning to Palestine from Babylonia (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.16">Ezr 8:16</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. One who opposed Ezra’s suggestion that the sons of Israel should divorce the foreign women they had married since returning to Palestine from exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.15">Ezr 10:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. Bani’s son, who was encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.29">Ezr 10:29</a>).</p>
<p class="list">13. Berekiah’s son, who rebuilt a section of the Jerusalem wall during the days of Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.4,30">Neh 3:4, 30</a>). His daughter married Jehohanan, the son of Tobiah the Ammonite (<a href="?bref=Neh.6.18">6:18</a>).</p>
<p class="list">14. Besodeiah’s son, who with Joiada repaired the Old Gate in the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.6">Neh 3:6</a>).</p>
<p class="list">15. One of the men who stood to Ezra’s left when Ezra read the law to the people (<a href="?bref=Neh.8.4">Neh 8:4</a>).</p>
<p class="list">16. One of the priests who set his seal on the covenant of Ezra (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.7">Neh 10:7</a>).</p>
<p class="list">17. One of the leaders of Israel who set his seal on the covenant of Ezra (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.20">Neh 10:20</a>).</p>
<p class="list">18. Head of Ezra’s priestly family during the days of Joiakim, the high priest, in postexilic Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.13">Neh 12:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">19. Head of Ginnethon’s priestly family during the days of Joiakim (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.16">Neh 12:16</a>).</p>
<p class="list">20. One of the gatekeepers during the days of the high priest Joiakim (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.25">Neh 12:25</a>); perhaps identifiable with Shallum in <a href="?bref=1Chr.9.17">1 Chronicles 9:17</a>.</p>
<p class="list">21. One of the princes of Judah who participated in the dedication of the Jerusalem wall during the postexilic era (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.33">Neh 12:33</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>