<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Michal">
  <title>Michal</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MICHAL</p>
<p class="fl">Younger daughter of Saul (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.49">1 Sm 14:49</a>). She fell in love with David after his defeat of Goliath (<a href="?bref=1Sam.18.20">18:20</a>). Saul, jealous of David, offered his first daughter, Merab, to David, but the recent victor graciously declined. When Michal’s love became known to Saul, he renewed his offer of a wife, providing David produce evidence of having killed 100 Philistines—a condition Saul felt would surely lead to David’s death.</p>
<p>David met Saul’s condition in double measure and married Michal. Saul’s jealousy was only fanned, and he plotted to have David murdered. Michal heard of the plot and assisted in her husband’s escape (<a href="?bref=1Sam.19.8-17">1 Sm 19:8-17</a>). During David’s exile, Saul gave Michal to Palti (<a href="?bref=1Sam.25.44">25:44</a>).</p>
<p>Following Saul’s death, Abner negotiated with David, part of the agreement being the return of Michal to David’s household. This was done despite Palti’s remorse (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.12-16">2 Sm 3:12-16</a>). But youthful ardor had apparently suffered strain. When David returned with the ark to Jerusalem, dancing before it, Michal voiced her harsh criticism. David’s reply was equally severe. Michal would remain childless as punishment for her candidness. (The <span class="sc">kjv</span>, using inferior manuscripts, reports Michal as the mother of five sons in <a href="?bref=2Sam.21.8">2 Samuel 21:8</a>. Adriel, however, was the husband of Merab—a correction reflected in modern versions.)</p>
<p>David’s overwhelming popularity should not overshadow the courage and passion displayed by Michal. She let her love be known when women hardly took the initiative in courtship, saved David’s life at the risk of her own, was emotionally victimized by her forced marriage and separation from Palti, and voiced her critical convictions against the tide of public opinion.</p>
  </body>
</item>