<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="MineralsandMetals">
  <title>Minerals* and Metals</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MINERALS* AND METALS</p>
<p class="fl">A “mineral” is a naturally occurring substance, normally an ore that must be mined and treated before the metal can be extracted. A “metal” is a chemical element such as iron or copper, which is free from contamination by other materials. Metals in a pure form generally do not occur in nature, though there are exceptions.</p>
<p>In Palestine, mining and smelting are ancient arts, practiced long before the Israelites arrived. The quarrying of suitable stones, such as flint, for toolmaking goes back to the Stone Age; the quarrying of stone for building is also an ancient craft. In particular, metals, native gold, copper, and meteoric iron were known and used in the Middle East before 4000 <span class="era">BC</span>. From 4000 to 3000 <span class="era">BC</span>, native silver became known as well as copper and lead ores. The art of smelting was discovered probably almost by accident, resulting in the production of alloys like bronze. Then the reduction of oxidized iron was discovered. From 3000 to 2000 <span class="era">BC</span>, important advances were made. Copper sulfides and tin oxides were reduced to metal, and metallic tin and copper became important items of trade.</p>
<p>In the years 2000 to 1000 <span class="era">BC</span>, bellows came into use for furnaces, and iron was reduced from its ores and forged. The art of making brass from copper and zinc was discovered about 1500 <span class="era">BC</span> but did not become significant till somewhat later. Bronze, known for many centuries, was made sometimes with a high tin content to form speculum for mirrors. By this time the Israelites were settled in the land and the kingdom was established. From 1000 <span class="era">BC</span> to the start of the Christian era, the production of metals, especially iron, greatly expanded. A form of steel was made and used for weapons and tools.</p>
<p>By the time of David and Solomon, the Israelites had learned many skills in the preparation and working of metals. Under David, Edom, with its rich copper and iron deposits, was conquered (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.13-14">2 Sm 8:13-14</a>) and there was a lot of activity in the casting of metals in the Jordan Valley (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.13-14,45-46">1 Kgs 7:13-14, 45-46</a>). In this activity Solomon had the assistance of Hiram, a Phoenician artisan. Israelite tradition associated the origins of metallurgy with Tubal-cain (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.22">Gn 4:22</a>), who is said to have forged all kinds of tools out of bronze and iron. <a href="?bref=Deut.8.9">Deuteronomy 8:9</a> refers to the presence of iron and copper in the land to which Israel was going.</p>
<p>While the Israelites eventually undertook their own metalworking processes, it is evident from <a href="?bref=1Sam.13.19-22">1 Samuel 13:19-22</a> that on at least one occasion, in the days of Philistine domination, they were obliged to have their agricultural tools made by their enemies. Similarly, the manufacture of cult vessels for Solomon’s temple was supervised by Phoenician artisans (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.7.13-50">1 Kgs 7:13-50</a>).</p>
<p>Minerals, metals, and precious stones were also important items of trade. Israel was never a land rich in these commodities and was obliged to import a wide variety of them. The visit of the queen of Sheba was partly diplomatic and partly for trade (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.2,10-11">1 Kgs 10:2, 10-11</a>).</p>
<p>Metals and precious stones featured also among the booty carried off by invaders, notably—but not only—by the Egyptians and Assyrians. These items were in constant demand as they were needed for agriculture and making weapons of war, and for the manufacture of jewelry and items of personal adornment.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Minerals">Minerals</p>
<p class="fl">A mineral is an inorganic substance with a definite chemical composition and structure, sometimes occurring alone or sometimes combined with others. “Ore” refers to any mineral or mineral aggregate containing chemical compounds of metals in sufficient quantity and grade to make the extraction of the metal commercially profitable. The essential element, the metal, occurs in nature as a chemical compound, such as a sulfide, an oxide, a carbonate, or some other compound, though the sulfides and oxides are the most common. Minerals exhibit a variety of properties, such as color, luster, crystal form, cleavage, fracture, hardness, and density, which help in their identification and exercise control on the commercial and industrial uses of the particular mineral.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Metals">Metals</p>
<p class="fl">A metal in its pure form is a chemically pure element with its own fixed physical properties, such as density, tensile strength, crystalline structure, melting point, ductility, conductivity, and the like. Metals form alloys with other metals, but this process destroys their purity. In both the ancient world and the modern world the alloy is extremely important.</p>
<p>In order to obtain a pure metal, the ore in which the metal is contained must be smelted—a process known as metallurgy. In ancient Israel pure metals were widely used—among them were gold, silver, iron, and lead. Yet alloys such as bronze and brass were even more widely used.</p>
<p class="h3">Metallurgy and Metal Extraction</p>
<p class="fl">The method of producing hard wrought iron was discovered by the Hittites of Asia Minor about 1300 <span class="era">BC</span>, and was taken up by the Philistines (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.19-20">1 Sm 13:19-20</a>). At first, the iron obtained from simple furnaces was drawn off and hammered to drive out slag (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.20">Dt 4:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.51">1 Kgs 8:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.11.4">Jer 11:4</a>). Later, the addition of carbon produced an early form of steel.</p>
<p>The lead sulfide ore is heated with lime in a flow of air. A slag with rock particles forms. The air is then cut off and the temperature is raised. Finally, the lead flows free.</p>
<p>The OT refers to the mining of silver (<a href="?bref=Job.28.1">Jb 28:1</a>), the refining of the metal (<a href="?bref=Zech.13.9">Zec 13:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Mal.3.3">Mal 3:3</a>), the melting of scrap metals or jeweler’s remnants (<a href="?bref=Ezek.22.20-22">Ez 22:20-22</a>), and of multiple refinings in a crucible (<a href="?bref=Pr.17.3">Prv 17:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.27.21">27:21</a>) to produce refined silver (<a href="?bref=1Chr.29.4">1 Chr 29:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.12.6">Ps 12:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.10.20">Prv 10:20</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Specific Metals</p>
<p class="fl">Although several OT passages suggest that the science of metallurgy was known in biblical times, comparatively little archaeological evidence is available. The processing plants were small and were used for the treatment of copper and iron. The archaeological record is far from complete, but the general impression is that metallic ores were comparatively rare in Palestine; imports must have been considerable. However, numerous molds for casting agricultural and military tools have come to light in excavations. Evidently, some refined metal was available locally, but perhaps most of it was imported. The metal was then heated and poured into the appropriate earthenware or pottery mold.</p>
<p>There are many references to metals in the Bible, but especially to gold, silver, iron, and lead. While copper was widely used, it was normally in the form of its alloys, bronze and brass. There are comparatively few references to tin as such, though it was used in manufacturing bronze. Similarly zinc, though used in the manufacture of brass, is not mentioned in the Bible.</p>
<p>Gold is referred to hundreds of times in the OT and NT, more frequently than any other metal. It is often mentioned together with silver, and in the majority of cases silver is mentioned first, reflecting a time when gold was less valued.</p>
<p>Gold was used in the manufacture of ornaments for personal use (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.53">Gn 24:53</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.41.42">41:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.3.22">Ex 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.11.2">11:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.12.35">12:35</a>). Gold was important in worship both in Israel and among the non-Israelites. References to pagan gods occur in several passages (<a href="?bref=Exod.20.23">Ex 20:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.32.2-4">32:2-4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.115.4">Ps 115:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.2.20">Is 2:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.30.22">30:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.31.7">31:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.40.19">40:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.46.6">46:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.8.4">Hos 8:4</a>). It seems that the gold was melted down and later engraved so that the replicas could be called both molten images (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.24">Ex 32:24</a>) and graven images. The tabernacle and the temple used a great deal of gold. The wooden ark was covered inside and outside with gold (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.11">25:11</a>). Other timber pieces were overlaid with gold (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.11">25:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.20-22,30">1 Kgs 6:20-22, 30</a>).</p>
<p>The vessels and utensils used in the tabernacle and temple were made of “pure gold”: the cherubim (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.18">Ex 25:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.37.7">37:7</a>), the mercy seat (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.17">25:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.37.6">37:6</a>), the candlestick (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.31">Ex 25:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.4.2">Zec 4:2</a>), various vessels (<a href="?bref=Exod.25.38">Ex 25:38</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.13">2 Kgs 24:13</a>), chains to carry the ephod (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.14">Ex 28:14</a>), and the bells on the high priest’s robe. The high priest’s crown, ephod, and breastplate were also of gold (<a href="?bref=Exod.39.2-30">39:2-30</a>). The offerings collected for the manufacture of such articles in the wilderness include golden dishes weighing 120 shekels (<a href="?bref=Num.7.86">Nm 7:86</a>). The more lavishly adorned temple apparently used more gold than the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.20-28">1 Kgs 6:20-28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.29.2-7">1 Chr 29:2-7</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.3.4-4.22">2 Chr 3:4–4:22</a>). The number of specific references to gold in the tabernacle and temple is far too great to mention all of them here. The large amount of gold used in the temple was attractive to invaders, who would strip the temple of its gold and carry it off as booty (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.26">1 Kgs 14:26</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.8">2 Kgs 16:8</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.14">18:14</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.24.13">24:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.15">25:15</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.12.9">2 Chr 12:9</a>).</p>
<p>Gold had commercial value. It was imported in Solomon’s day, and up to 666 talents were brought to Israel annually (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.14">1 Kgs 10:14</a>). Hiram of Tyre gave Solomon 120 talents of gold (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.14">9:14</a>), possibly as a loan. Certainly Solomon used a lot of gold in the temple (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.16-17">10:16-17</a>). Gold was useful, too, for buying off an enemy (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.16.8">2 Kgs 16:8</a>) or simply as tribute (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.14">18:14</a>). Evidence of this comes also from the Assyrian annals, where the tribute taken from various lands often included gold.</p>
<p>The possession of gold was not in itself an evil thing, but preoccupation with its accumulation was condemned (<a href="?bref=Job.28.15-17">Jb 28:15-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.3.14">Prv 3:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.8.10,19">8:10, 19</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.16.16">16:16</a>). The possession of wisdom and the knowledge of God was of greater value than the possession of much gold (<a href="?bref=Ps.19.10">Pss 19:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.119.72,127">119:72, 127</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.20.15">Prv 20:15</a>). Job rejected trust in gold (<a href="?bref=Job.31.24">Jb 31:24</a>). Gold would not save a man in the day of judgment (<a href="?bref=Zeph.1.18">Zep 1:18</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT gold was regarded as perishable (<a href="?bref=Jas.5.3">Jas 5:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.1.18">1 Pt 1:18</a>) and as an unnecessary burden to carry (<a href="?bref=Matt.10.9">Mt 10:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.3.6">Acts 3:6</a>). The wearing of a gold ring was certainly no measure of a man’s worth (<a href="?bref=Jas.2.2">Jas 2:2</a>); indeed, both Paul and Peter forbade it (<a href="?bref=1Tim.2.9">1 Tm 2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.3">1 Pt 3:3</a>).</p>
<p>The use of gold in itself was no measure of piety. The elders of <a href="?bref=Rev.4.4">Revelation 4:4</a> wore golden crowns, but the great harlot was “bedecked with gold” (<a href="?bref=Rev.17.4">Rv 17:4</a>), as was the harlot city Babylon (<a href="?bref=Rev.18.16">18:16</a>). By contrast, there are some positive statements in the NT about the value of gold (<a href="?bref=Rev.3.18">3:18</a>). The wise men brought gold to the infant Jesus as a symbol of his kingly character (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.11">Mt 2:11</a>), and the Holy City, the new Jerusalem, was a city of gold, clear as glass (<a href="?bref=Rev.21.18">Rv 21:18</a>).</p>
<p>In the OT, silver is mentioned in several connections. Being a precious metal, once considered more precious than gold, it was regularly used in commerce for the payments of debts. Small pieces of silver were weighed into a balance against a standard weight. Abraham bought the cave at Machpelah as a burial place for Sarah for 400 shekels of silver and weighed out the “money” according to the weight’s current value with the merchant (<a href="?bref=Gen.23.15-16">Gn 23:15-16</a>). Joseph’s brothers received 20 pieces of silver in payment for Joseph (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.28">37:28</a>), and Benjamin was given a money gift by Joseph in pieces of silver (<a href="?bref=Gen.45.22">45:22</a>).</p>
<p>There are other examples of payment in silver for commodities or services (<a href="?bref=Gen.20.16">Gn 20:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.21.32">Ex 21:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.27.16">Lv 27:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.32">Jos 24:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.17.10">Jgs 17:10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.24.24">2 Sm 24:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.72">Neh 7:72</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.28.15">Jb 28:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.7.23">Is 7:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.46.6">46:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.2.6">Am 2:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.8.6">8:6</a>). Silver was a measure of a man’s wealth (<a href="?bref=Gen.13.2">Gn 13:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.24.35">24:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.25.3">Ex 25:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.22.18">Nm 22:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.7.25">Dt 7:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Zeph.1.18">Zep 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.8">Hg 2:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.11">Zec 6:11</a>). An unusual comment in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.21">1 Kings 10:21</a> notes that in Solomon’s day “it was not considered as anything,” apparently because it was so plentiful. It was regularly taken as booty (<a href="?bref=Josh.6.19">Jos 6:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.7.21">7:21</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.18">1 Kgs 15:18</a>). Sometimes the drinking cup of an important man was made of silver (<a href="?bref=Gen.44.2">Gn 44:2</a>). Sometimes, too, a royal crown was made of gold and silver (<a href="?bref=Zech.6.11">Zec 6:11</a>). It was important in the manufacture of personal ornaments (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.53">Gn 24:53</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.3.22">Ex 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.12.35">12:35</a>), and one example is given of ornaments of gold studded with silver (<a href="?bref=Song.1.11">Sg 1:11</a>).</p>
<p>The process of refining silver was used as a metaphor for the trying of people’s hearts (<a href="?bref=Ps.66.10">Ps 66:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.48.10">Is 48:10</a>), and the tarnishing and deterioration of silver was a picture of the disintegration of one’s character (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.22">Is 1:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.30">Jer 6:30</a>). God’s Word is pictured as “pure” silver refined and purified in a furnace. Despite silver’s great value, wisdom excels it (<a href="?bref=Job.28.15">Job 28:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.3.14">Prv 3:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.8.19">8:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.10.20">10:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.16.16">16:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.22.1">22:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.25.11">25:11</a>).</p>
<p>Native copper is mentioned in <a href="?bref=Deut.8.9">Deuteronomy 8:9</a>, though the reference may be to one of its ores. More commonly, biblical references are to brass, the alloy of copper and zinc. However, the chemical analysis of copper-based tools and implements during the middle and late Bronze Ages (c. 2000–1200 <span class="era">BC</span>) shows that the material was bronze. References to brass in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> are therefore to bronze.</p>
<p>By NT times, copper in the form of alloys (bronze and brass) was widely used. Bronze coinage was well known and this may be the sense of <a href="?bref=Matt.10.9">Matthew 10:9</a>. The widow’s mite was a tiny bronze coin, the lepton. Bronze utensils and vessels were well known (<a href="?bref=Rev.9.20">Rv 9:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.18.12">18:12</a>). The reference to “sounding brass” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) in <a href="?bref=1Cor.13.1">1 Corinthians 13:1</a> may actually be to brass, which was a bright, shining alloy, and was used in musical instruments. In the vision of John in Revelation (<a href="?bref=Rev.1.15">Rv 1:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.2.18">2:18</a>), the Son of Man had feet of fine brass (<span class="sc">nlt</span> “bronze”).</p>
<p>The Iron Age began in Palestine about 1200 <span class="era">BC</span>, that is, in the days of the judges, though native iron had been known in Egypt in the predynastic period. Archaeological evidence suggests that the smelting of iron ore was discovered by the Hittites about 1400 <span class="era">BC</span>. The Philistines seem to have introduced iron to Palestine about 1300 <span class="era">BC</span>. In the days of Moses an encounter with the Midianites produced much tribute, among which iron is mentioned (<a href="?bref=Num.31.22">Nm 31:22</a>). When Israel captured Jericho, the spoils included iron (<a href="?bref=Josh.6.24">Jos 6:24</a>). Manasseh’s half-tribe also took booty including iron (<a href="?bref=Josh.22.8">22:8</a>). In the days of the judges the Canaanites were equipped with chariots of iron (<a href="?bref=Josh.17.16-18">Jos 17:16-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.1.19">Jgs 1:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.4.3">4:3</a>).</p>
<p>These early references point to the arrival of iron at the start of the Iron Age. The Philistines enjoyed a local monopoly in its use (<a href="?bref=1Sam.13.19-21">1 Sm 13:19-21</a>), and their mighty warrior Goliath was armed with an iron spear (<a href="?bref=1Sam.17.7">17:7</a>). It was not long, however, before Israel learned the use of iron (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.31">2 Sm 12:31</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.23.7">23:7</a>). Evidently, by Solomon’s time, iron was widely used, because builders of the temple were forbidden to use iron tools (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.6.7">1 Kgs 6:7</a>). The false prophet Zedekiah in Ahab’s day used the horns of iron to thrust toward Syria as he spoke of their defeat (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.11">22:11</a>).</p>
<p>The prophet Isaiah in the eighth century <span class="era">BC</span> referred to iron (<a href="?bref=Isa.10.34">Is 10:34</a>), and Jeremiah later spoke of the metal in several places (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.18">Jer 1:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.28">6:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.11.4">11:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.15.12">15:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.17.1">17:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.28.13-14">28:13-14</a>). Ezekiel made use of an iron plate in one of his symbolic actions (<a href="?bref=Ezek.4.3">Ez 4:3</a>), referred to iron in his description of smelting (<a href="?bref=Ezek.22.18,20">22:18, 20</a>), and listed it as a commodity for trade (<a href="?bref=Ezek.27.12,19">27:12, 19</a>). The prophet Amos spoke of threshing instruments of iron (<a href="?bref=Amos.1.3">Am 1:3</a>). Micah used iron as a symbol for military might (<a href="?bref=Mic.4.13">Mi 4:13</a>). The book of Daniel makes several references to it (<a href="?bref=Dan.2.33-35,40-45">Dn 2:33-35, 40-45</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.4.15,23">4:15, 23</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.7.7,19">7:7, 19</a>).</p>
<p>By Roman times, iron weapons were the regular implements of war. Gates of iron were used to close prisons (<a href="?bref=Acts.12.10">Acts 12:10</a>), and in a symbolic usage powerful rulers were said to rule with a rod of iron (<a href="?bref=Rev.2.27">Rv 2:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.9.9">9:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.12.5">12:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.15">19:15</a>). The term “iron” was used also in some metaphorical expressions. The smelting of iron was a symbol of testing and suffering (<a href="?bref=Deut.4.20">Dt 4:20</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.51">1 Kgs 8:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.11.4">Jer 11:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.22.18">Ez 22:18</a>), a pillar of iron was symbolic of strength (<a href="?bref=Jer.1.18">Jer 1:18</a>), and an iron rod of harsh rule (<a href="?bref=Ps.2.9">Ps 2:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.2.27">Rv 2:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.12.5">12:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.19.15">19:15</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Coppersmith_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Coppersmith</a>; <a href="?item=Goldsmith_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Goldsmith</a>; <a href="?item=Ironsmith_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ironsmith</a>; <a href="?item=MasonMasonry_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mason, Masonry</a>; <a href="?item=Silversmith_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Silversmith</a>; <a href="?item=StonesPrecious_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Stones, Precious</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>