<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Mizpah">
  <title>Mizpah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MIZPAH</p>
<p class="fl">Name meaning “watchtower” in Hebrew (alternately spelled Mizpeh) used to designate a number of different locations mentioned in the OT and Apocrypha.</p>
<p class="list-space">1. Place in Gilead where Jacob and Laban made a covenant (<a href="?bref=Gen.31.49">Gn 31:49</a>) and set up a heap of stones to mark the borders between their territories.</p>
<p class="list">2. Place referred to as “the land of Mizpah” (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.3">Jos 11:3</a>) or the “valley of Mizpah” (<a href="?bref=Josh.11.8">Jos 11:8</a>) near Mt Hermon and inhabited by the Hivites.</p>
<p class="list">3. Town in Judah near Lachish referred to in <a href="?bref=Josh.15.38">Joshua 15:38</a>.</p>
<p class="list">4. Place in the tribal area of Benjamin (<a href="?bref=Josh.18.26">Jos 18:26</a>). It was here that the Israelites gathered to war against the tribe of Benjamin (<a href="?bref=Judg.20.1">Jgs 20:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.21.1">21:1</a>) after the men of Gibeah had abused and killed the concubine of a visiting Levite. It was here that Samuel called all Israel together to pray for victory over the Philistines (<a href="?bref=1Sam.7.5-8">1 Sm 7:5-8</a>). Later, Samuel called for an assembly at Mizpah to publicly designate Saul as king and to instruct the people and king in the ways of the kingdom (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.17-25">10:17-25</a>). In the time of Asa, Mizpah was a fortified town on the border between Israel and Judah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.15.22">1 Kgs 15:22</a>). After the fall of Jerusalem in 586 <span class="era">BC</span> to the Babylonians, Mizpah became the residence of Gedaliah the governor (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.23-24">2 Kgs 25:23-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.40.10">Jer 40:10</a>), who was murdered there by Ishmael of the “royal seed” (<a href="?bref=Jer.41.3">Jer 41:3</a>). Two days later Ishmael murdered a company of pilgrims who were going to Jerusalem to bring their offerings at the ruined temple, and he cast their bodies into a cistern that had been constructed centuries earlier by Asa.</p>
<p class="list-text">In the intertestamental period Mizpah continued to be an important religious center. Judas Maccabeus called the people together at Mizpah “because Israel formerly had a place of prayer in Mizpah” (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.3.46">1 Macc 3:46</a>).</p>
<p class="list">5. Home of Jephthah, from which he led the Israelites in battle against the Ammonites, and to which he returned to carry out his vow (<a href="?bref=Judg.10.1-11.40">Jgs 10–11</a>). This is possibly the same place as the Ramath-mizpeh of <a href="?bref=Josh.13.26">Joshua 13:26</a> and is thought by many to be identified with Khirbat Jal’ad just south of the Jabbok.</p>
<p class="list">6. Town in Moab to which David fled from Saul (<a href="?bref=1Sam.22.3">1 Sm 22:3</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>