<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Music">
  <title>Music</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">MUSIC</p>
<p class="fl">A natural human expression that probably began with speech-singing and developed into songs, which were then accompanied by instruments. Music as we know it has become quite complex, a luxury and entertainment; music in antiquity, however, was a functional expression of daily life, work, and worship.</p>
<p>The phrase “sing to the Lord,” common to the OT (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.21">Ex 15:21</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.16.9">1 Chr 16:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.68.32">Pss 68:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.96.1-2">96:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.42.10">Is 42:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.20.13">Jer 20:13</a>), was not unique to the Jewish nation. All religions draw on the natural human impulse to sing. The injunction “sing to the Lord” was a signal for the people to pour out their praise in song.</p>
<p>The Bible, however, is limited in its treatment of music in ancient Israel. Since there was no written musical notation, the primary record of songs sung by the Hebrews is the collection of texts, particularly the psalms, and a few enigmatic musical instructions. The biblical writers were writing a history not of their culture but of their relationship with God; hence, their comments about music are not critical. Also, the biblical documents cover a long span of history and are grouped according to category rather than in chronological order, thus making it difficult to order the development of musical style with precision. Finally, there is the problem of understanding the biblical descriptions of music and its performance. Only in this century have scholars been able to interpret the information provided in the Bible in terms of Eastern music systems.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#MusicintheOldTestament">Music in the Old Testament</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#MusicinthePsalms">Music in the Psalms</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#MusicintheNewTestament">Music in the New Testament</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="MusicintheOldTestament">Music in the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">The first musician mentioned in the Bible is “Jubal, the first musician—the inventor of the harp and flute” (<a href="?bref=Gen.4.21">Gn 4:21</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). The importance of this description of a musician so early in history lies in the equality Jubal is given with his brothers Jabal, the herdsman, and Tubal-cain, the smith. Music making is recognized among the earliest professions of nomadic peoples. The name Jubal is believed to be a derivative from the Hebrew word for “ram.” The ram’s horn <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">shophar</span><span class="ital">)</span> was an early instrument of the Jewish people and was significant in signaling important events.</p>
<p>For the most part, the music described in early biblical history was of a functional nature. Music gained special significance as it became an important part of temple worship. Many of the descriptions of music making in ancient Israel, before David’s time, are quite utilitarian. There are accounts of music at times of farewell (<a href="?bref=Gen.31.27">Gn 31:27</a>), at times of rejoicing and feasting (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.17-18">Ex 32:17-18</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.12">Is 5:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.24.8-9">24:8-9</a>), at military victories (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.27-28">2 Chr 20:27-28</a>), and for work (<a href="?bref=Num.21.17">Nm 21:17</a>, the song of the well diggers; <a href="?bref=Isa.16.10">Is 16:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.48.33">Jer 48:33</a>). Most of this music was probably rather crude and primitive in nature, especially the music associated with military advances, which was meant to terrify the enemy (<a href="?bref=Judg.7.17-20">Jgs 7:17-20</a>). The music and dancing that greeted Moses as he descended from the mountain was described as if it sounded like “war in the camp” (<a href="?bref=Exod.32.17-18">Ex 32:17-18</a>).</p>
<p>In the early history of the Jewish people, women played an important part in the performance of music. The image of women dancing and singing for joy accompanied by percussion instruments is repeated several times: Miriam led the women in a hymn of thanksgiving after the deliverance from the Red Sea (<a href="?bref=Exod.15.1-27">Ex 15</a>); Jephthah’s daughter welcomed her father in his victory (<a href="?bref=Judg.11.34">Jgs 11:34</a>); Deborah joined with Barak in singing a song of victory (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.1-31">Jgs 5</a>); and women hailed David after his defeat of the Philistines (<a href="?bref=1Sam.18.6-7">1 Sm 18:6-7</a>). There is little mention of women as musicians following the establishment of the temple in Jerusalem, but there are a few allusions to the fact that women did participate in singing and dancing. The account of the return from exile in Babylon includes both male and female singers (<a href="?bref=Neh.7.67">Neh 7:67</a>), confirming that women still took part in musical performance.</p>
<p>As Jerusalem became the religious center of the Hebrew people (950–850 <span class="era">BC</span>), the role of the professional musician became more important. The women’s songs became insignificant compared to the pomp and ceremony associated with the temple and the royal court. While the Levitical singers took most of the musical responsibility at the temple, the development of antiphonal singing allowed the people to join in on responses in the singing of psalms.</p>
<p class="h3">Musical Style and Use</p>
<p class="fl">The Jewish people seem to have been especially musical. Of course, they were influenced by other ancient cultures, but there is evidence that they were in demand as musicians by other peoples. According to an Assyrian document, King Hezekiah gave as tribute to King Sennacherib many male and female Jewish musicians. The Babylonians demanded that the captive Jews sing to them and entertain them (cf. <a href="?bref=Ps.137.3">Ps 137:3</a>).</p>
<p>Since the OT’s purpose was to narrate the relationship between the Jewish nation and God, most of the references to music deal with its function in worship. However, evidence reveals that there was also a large body of secular musical literature. There may have been guilds of poets and singers early in Jewish history. The kinds of songs recorded in the early part of the OT represent a folklike poetry. The song of thanksgiving to the Lord by Moses and the people of Israel after their escape at the Red Sea is a stirring national song. Many descriptions of the biblical writers reflect the spirit of bardic song. This would be logical, as these stories were meant to be passed on. Marching songs (<a href="?bref=2Chr.20.27-28">2 Chr 20:27-28</a>), and songs of triumph (<a href="?bref=Judg.5.1-31">Jgs 5</a>) also indicate a secular body of music.</p>
<p class="h3">Music in Worship</p>
<p class="fl">The singers and musicians for the temple worship were chosen from the tribe of Levi. King David assembled the Levites for a census, and out of the total of 38,000 men over the age of 30, 4,000 were chosen as musicians. These 4,000 were subsequently given specific jobs. “David and the chiefs of the service also set apart for the service certain of the sons of Asaph, and of Heman, and of Jeduthun, who should prophesy with lyres, with harps, and with cymbals. . . . The number of them along with their brethren, who were trained in singing to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, all who were skilful, was two hundred and eighty-eight” (<a href="?bref=1Chr.25.1,7">1 Chr 25:1, 7</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The singers were further divided into 24 groups of 12 singers, who rotated in participating in the weekday, Sabbath, and high holy day services.</p>
<p>According to a later source, there were minimum and maximum numbers of singers and instrumentalists required at each service. The minimum number of singers was twelve, the maximum was unlimited. There had to be in attendance at least two harps but no more than six, at least two flutes but no more than twelve, a minimum of two trumpets with no maximum, and a minimum of nine lyres with no maximum. There was only one player with a pair of cymbals.</p>
<p>A singer was admitted to the Levitical choir at the age of thirty following a five-year apprenticeship (<a href="?bref=1Chr.23.3">1 Chr 23:3</a>). Five years is a relatively short time considering the amount of material these singers had to memorize (for there was no notation) and the liturgical ritual they had to master; it is speculated that they actually were in training from childhood. The Levites lived in villages outside the city wall and may have been actively involved in the musical education of their children (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.29">Neh 12:29</a>). The Levites performed other duties connected with the sacred service, but the singers were excused from all other duties because they were on duty day and night (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.33">1 Chr 9:33</a>). Their skills were an important part of the temple worship, and they were able to devote their entire life to the development of their musical ability. A singer served in the choir for 20 years, from age 30 to 50, and the music was of a high quality due to strict discipline and continuous practice and performance.</p>
<p>From the beginning of Jewish formal worship connected with the tabernacle, music and sound was important. In <a href="?bref=Exod.28.34-35">Exodus 28:34-35</a> the descriptions of Aaron’s robe include bells attached to the lower hem that sounded as he entered the Holy Place. The first liturgical music mentioned in the OT is found in <a href="?bref=2Sam.6.1-23">2 Samuel 6</a> in the descriptions of the transfer of the ark: David and the Israelites sang, played instruments, and danced to the glory of the Lord. This music bore little resemblance to the stately ceremony described later in Solomon’s temple. In <a href="?bref=2Chr.7.6">2 Chronicles 7:6</a>, David is given recognition for inventing the musical instruments used in the temple. In the postexilic era Levitical singers are mentioned as the descendants of Asaph, the “singing master” appointed by David (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.41">Ezr 2:41</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.44">Neh 7:44</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.11.22-23">11:22-23</a>). From passages such as these, we have a definite indication that liturgical music and organization stemmed from David’s time.</p>
<p>The ceremonies in the Jewish temple were organized around the sacrifice. Singing formed an integral part of the sacrificial service and was necessary to validate the sacrificial action. There were special musical settings for each sacrifice; thus the daily burnt, expiatory, and laudatory offerings and libations had individual liturgies. Particular psalms became associated with certain sacrifices as well as with certain days of the week. The psalm of the day was intoned as the high priest started to pour out the drink offering. The psalm was divided into three sections, each signaled by the blowing of the trumpets, on which signal the people would prostrate themselves. This is the only time the trumpets were used together with the other instruments in orchestral fashion on solemn occasions (<a href="?bref=2Chr.5.12-13">2 Chr 5:12-13</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="MusicinthePsalms">Music in the Psalms</p>
<p class="h3">Musical Psalm Titles</p>
<p class="fl">The collection of 150 lyric poems known as the book of Psalms contains the most information on music making in ancient Israel. The Psalter contains not only religious songs but also songs that have their roots in secular or popular songs, such as work songs, love songs, and wedding songs. The majority are songs of praise, thanksgiving, prayer, and repentance. There are also historic odes that relate great national events—for example, <a href="?bref=Ps.30.1-12">Psalm 30</a>, “a song at the dedication of the temple,” and <a href="?bref=Ps.137.1-9">Psalm 137</a>, which portrays the sufferings of the Jews in captivity.</p>
<p>The psalms were an important part of all the services of the temple; the Psalter became the liturgical hymnal of the Israelites. Worship included an appointed psalm for each day of the week. On the first day of the week, <a href="?bref=Ps.24.1-10">Psalm 24</a> was sung in remembrance of the first day of creation, <a href="?bref=Ps.48.1-14">Psalm 48</a> was sung on the second day, <a href="?bref=Ps.82.1-8">Psalm 82</a> on the third, <a href="?bref=Ps.94.1-23">Psalm 94</a> on the fourth, <a href="?bref=Ps.81.1-16">Psalm 81</a> on the fifth, <a href="?bref=Ps.93.1-5">Psalm 93</a> on the sixth, and <a href="?bref=Ps.92.1-15">Psalm 92</a> on the Sabbath. After the sacrificial offerings, <a href="?bref=Ps.105.1-5">Psalm 105:1-5</a> was sung at the morning service and <a href="?bref=Ps.96.1-13">Psalm 96</a> at the evening service. The Hallel psalms (<a href="?bref=Ps.113.1-118.29">Pss 113–118</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.120.1-136.26">120–136</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.146.1-148.14">146–148</a>) were sung during the offering of the paschal lamb at the Passover feast.</p>
<p>While most of the liturgical music was performed by Levites, texts of the psalms suggest that there was also congregational participation. The forms of music found both in synagogal and ecclesiastical chant had their source in the forms of the poetic text of the psalms. The simplest is the plain psalmody sung by one person (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.3.1-5.12">Pss 3–5</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.46.1-11">46</a>). In responsorial psalmody the soloist is answered by the choir (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.67.1-2">Ps 67:1-2</a>; the soloist sang verse <a href="?bref=Ps.67.1">1</a> and the choir answered with verse <a href="?bref=Ps.67.2">2</a>). Antiphonal psalmody involves two groups singing alternately (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.103.20-22">Ps 103:20-22</a>). The congregation would chant a refrain such as appears in <a href="?bref=Ps.80.1-19">Psalm 80</a>: “Restore us, O God; let thy face shine, that we may be saved!” recurs throughout the psalm (<span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p>Even though the synagogue had no altar for sacrifice, psalm singing retained an important place. After the Romans destroyed the temple, the worship heritage of the Jews could have been lost if the customs, including musical customs, had not become an integral part of synagogue worship.</p>
<p>The most enigmatic part of the psalms is the headings that are not part of the poetic text. The first question is whether these should even be considered as superscripts. Greek, Latin, Hebrew, and other ancient languages were written in such a way that the text ran together without any break between chapters or paragraphs. This means that the verses, and even the division of the psalms themselves, were partially determined by copyists, chiefly the Masoretes. There is some question as to which psalms the extrapoetic texts actually belong with; they may actually be subscripts instead of superscripts. Sumerian and Babylonian poetry had information such as the name of the author, the musical instrument used for accompaniment, the tune, the purpose, and such listed at the end of the poem. Hence, some of the headings may actually be endings.</p>
<p>The indications at the beginning of a psalm fall into three categories. They are either musical terms giving direction for the actual performance, musical cues designating the tune to which the psalm would be sung, or comments indicating the function of the psalm. These terms have been interpreted in various ways.</p>
<p>Originally, these headings may have been marginal notes for the choir leaders. Realizing that these terms were not related to the psalm text proper, early biblical scribes may not have been overly careful with their placement in the text, which may explain some of the discrepancies among the early manuscripts—why certain words are left out in some and why terms assigned to only a few psalms may originally have been indicated on more of them.</p>
<p>All but 50 of the psalms contain a proper name in the heading. These names possibly indicate the author; other commentators, interpreting the preposition appearing before the names to mean “for,” think the names are a dedication. Thus the title would be “A Psalm for David,” not “A Psalm of David.” This may be the case with the names of Asaph, Heman, Ethan, and especially the sons of Korah, where it would make better sense for the psalm to be written for rather than by the family. Seventy-three psalms have David’s name in the heading, hence the common reference to the Psalter as the Psalms of David. Twelve include the name of Asaph, eleven the children of Korah, two Solomon, and one each contains Moses, Heman, and Ethan.</p>
<p class="h3">Musical Terms in the Psalm Titles</p>
<p class="fl">Numerous musical terms are included in the superscriptions to cue the kind of instrumental accompaniment, mood, and style of performance for the psalm.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Alamoth</span> is one of the most controversial terms found in the psalm headings. It appears at the beginning of <a href="?bref=Ps.46.1-11">Psalm 46</a> and also in <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.20">1 Chronicles 15:20</a>. One meaning for the Hebrew word is “maiden,” and musicologists interpret this as an instruction that the psalm should be sung in the range of the female singing voice. The reference in Chronicles is to harps in the range of women’s voices. This interpretation does not seem to fit <a href="?bref=Ps.46.1-11">Psalm 46</a>, but if we look at the preceding psalm and read the term as a subscript, it becomes logical. <a href="?bref=Ps.45.1-17">Psalm 45</a> is a song of love, actually a nuptial ode; it would be natural for women to sing the second half (vv <a href="?bref=Ps.45.10-17">10-17</a>). While there is little mention of women singing in the temple, there is speculation that young boys in training may have sung along with the Levitical singers. Also this may be a case where the term appears only once in the modern text but may have been used more often in the original. Another possible meaning for <span class="hebrew">Alamoth</span> is “flutes,” perhaps describing the kind of musical accompaniment for the performance of the psalm.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Gittith</span> is a term found in the superscriptions of <a href="?bref=Ps.8.1-9">Psalms 8</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.81.1-16">81</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ps.84.1-12">84</a>. It may be a musical cue, indicating a mood for the performance of these psalms, but a more common explanation is that it is a collective term for the stringed instruments that would have accompanied them.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Mahalath</span> has been left in its original Hebrew form by early translators and is found in the headings of <a href="?bref=Ps.53.1-6">Psalms 53</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.88.1-18">88</a>. It may have roots in the Hebrew <span class="hebrew">mahaleh</span> “sickness” or <span class="hebrew">mahot</span> “dance,” though neither of these words can be related to the psalm texts. Another explanation is a musical one. <span class="hebrew">Mahalath</span> may come from the word <span class="hebrew">halal</span> meaning “to pierce,” implying that the psalm was to be accompanied with pipes.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Maskil</span> (<span class="sc">kjv</span> “Maschil”) appears in the headings of 13 psalms (<a href="?bref=Ps.32.1-11">Pss 32</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.42.1-11">42</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.44.1-45.17">44–45</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.52.1-55.23">52–55</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.74.1-23">74</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.78.1-72">78</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.88.1-89.52">88–89</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.142.1-7">142</a>). The term is probably derived from the verb <span class="hebrew">sakal</span><span class="ital">,</span> “to have insight or comprehension,” but there is no agreement among commentators. By looking at the psalms themselves, their didactic nature and the structure of stanzas and refrains, musicologists conclude the term represents a song of praise, possibly sung by a soloist with participation by the choir.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Menazzeah</span> appears in the heading of 55 psalms. It appears 52 times in the first three books of Psalms (<a href="?bref=Ps.1.1-89.52">Pss 1–89</a>), not at all in book four (<a href="?bref=Ps.90.1-106.48">Pss 90–106</a>), and 3 times in book five (<a href="?bref=Ps.107.1-150.6">Pss 107–150</a>). The most common modern translations are “to the Choirmaster” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>), “to the choir director” (<span class="sc">nasb</span>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>), “to the director of music” (<span class="sc">niv</span>), “to the chief Musician” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>, <span class="sc">nkjv</span>). The word is derived from the Hebrew verb <span class="hebrew">nazzah</span><span class="ital">,</span> appearing in <a href="?bref=1Chr.23.4">1 Chronicles 23:4</a> and <a href="?bref=Ezra.3.8-9">Ezra 3:8-9</a> in the sense of “administering.” In <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.21">1 Chronicles 15:21</a> the word is found in relation to leading or directing song in the temple. <span class="hebrew">Menazzeah</span> relates to the choirmaster and represents the singer chosen to lead the music who probably was involved in rehearsing and instructing. It is now assumed that <span class="hebrew">menazzeah</span> indicates the psalm was to be sung partially or entirely by a soloist. This is evidenced by the change in some texts from “I” where the soloist sang, to “we” where the choir or congregation sang. <a href="?bref=Ps.5.1-12">Psalm 5</a> is an example of a text divided for solo and choral singing: verses 1-3 solo; verses 4-6 choral; verses 7-8 solo; verses 9-10 choral; and verses 11-12 end the psalm with the combined soloist and choir.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Miktam</span> (<span class="sc">kjv</span> “Michtam”) is another term that has no clear musical meaning, due mainly to the fact that its etymology is unknown. It occurs in <a href="?bref=Ps.16.1-11">Psalms 16</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.56.1-60.12">56–60</a>, all of which have a character of lamentation or supplication. In a musical sense, it probably meant that a certain well-known tune was to be selected as the melody of the psalm.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Mizmor</span> (Hebrew, meaning a song sung to instrumental accompaniment) is found nowhere else in the Bible; it is included in the superscriptions of 57 psalms. It probably indicated a song accompanied by melodic instruments as opposed to a dance song accompanied by rhythmic instruments.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Neginah</span> appears in the superscriptions of <a href="?bref=Ps.4.1-8">Psalms 4</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.6.1-10">6</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.54.1-55.23">54–55</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.61.1-8">61</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.67.1-7">67</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ps.76.1-12">76</a>. The term <span class="hebrew">neginah</span> and its plural <span class="hebrew">neginoth</span> are found in <a href="?bref=Ps.77.7">Psalm 77:7</a>, <a href="?bref=Lam.5.14">Lamentations 5:14</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.38.20">Isaiah 38:20</a>, and <a href="?bref=Hab.3.19">Habakkuk 3:19</a>. <span class="hebrew">Neginah</span><span class="ital">,</span> from the Hebrew root <span class="hebrew">naggen</span><span class="ital">,</span> “to touch the strings,” instructs that stringed instruments accompany the singing.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Nehiloth</span> is found only in the introduction to <a href="?bref=Ps.5.1-12">Psalm 5</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>). The origin of the word is problematic. It could come from the verb <span class="hebrew">nahal</span><span class="ital">,</span> “to possess or inherit,” or more feasibly from <span class="hebrew">halal</span><span class="ital">,</span> meaning “to pierce.” The latter implies the idea of a pierced instrument (the flute or pipe) to be used for accompaniment.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Sheminith</span> appears in <a href="?bref=Ps.6.1-10">Psalms 6</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.12.1-8">12</a> and also in <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.21">1 Chronicles 15:21</a>. The Hebrew word means literally “over the eighth.” Some scholars feel it had something to do with an octave, but the Hebrew musical language probably did not include a musical unit divided into eight parts. Other scholars interpret <span class="hebrew">sheminith</span> as meaning an eight-stringed instrument. A more logical interpretation comes from examining its use in 1 Chronicles. In <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.20">15:20</a> the instructions are for musicians to play the harps according to <span class="hebrew">alamoth</span> and in verse <a href="?bref=1Chr.15.21">21</a> to play the lyres according to <span class="hebrew">sheminith</span><span class="ital">.</span> Here the terms <span class="hebrew">alamoth</span> and <span class="hebrew">sheminith</span> seem to be used in opposition. If <span class="hebrew">alamoth</span> implies a register of the female voice, then <span class="hebrew">sheminith</span> would imply a lower register. Thus, it may have been an instruction to use a lower pitched instrument for accompaniment.</p>
<p class="h3">Psalm Varieties in the Titles</p>
<p class="fl">Some of the notes in the psalm headings are indications of the type or variety of psalm.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Hazkir</span> is found in the headings of <a href="?bref=Ps.38.1-22">Psalms 38</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.70.1-5">70</a>. According to the Targum, this is an indication that the psalm was sung at the sacrificial rite called <span class="hebrew">askara</span> and is translated “for a memorial offering.”</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Lammed</span> appears in the superscription of <a href="?bref=Ps.60.1-12">Psalm 60</a> in the phrase <span class="hebrew">le-lammed</span><span class="ital">,</span> translated “to teach.” According to tradition, this was a psalm, though undoubtedly not the only one, taught to young people as part of their education. This is another example of a term that may have been omitted from other psalms in later versions of the Psalter.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Shiggaion</span> is in the heading of <a href="?bref=Ps.7.1-17">Psalm 7</a> and also in <a href="?bref=Hab.3.1">Habakkuk 3:1</a>. The word probably comes from the Hebrew verb <span class="hebrew">shagah</span><span class="ital">,</span> “to wander,” but may also be connected with the Assyrian liturgical term <span class="hebrew">shigu</span><span class="ital">,</span> which represented a plaintive song in several stanzas. Biblical scholars have assumed <span class="hebrew">shiggaion</span><span class="ital">,</span> plural <span class="hebrew">shigionoth</span><span class="ital">,</span> was a lament or penitential song.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Shir</span> is the simplest word for “song” and was probably used in the headings at an early stage of the Psalter; it is usually found with <span class="hebrew">mizmor</span> (13 times). Fifteen psalms have this heading. It was probably the term for a specific type of praise song, usually performed by the choir.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Shir Hamaalot</span> and <span class="hebrew">Shir Lamaalot</span> occur in the headings of <a href="?bref=Ps.120.1-134.3">Psalms 120–134</a>, which are often referred to as the Psalms of Ascent (<span class="sc">kjv</span> “Psalms of Degrees”). Most explanations offered relate to the fact that the temple was situated on high ground. Often these 15 psalms are associated with the 15 steps leading from the Court of the Women to the Court of the Israelites. But most contemporary scholars believe the idea of “going up” referred to the pilgrims’ journey to Jerusalem to worship at the temple. These psalms are short, with popular appeal, making them appropriate for singing during the journey.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Shir Hanukkat Habayit</span> is found only in the heading of <a href="?bref=Ps.30.1-12">Psalm 30</a>. This phrase tells that the psalm was to be used for the dedication or rededication of the house of God.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Shir-yedidot</span> appears only in <a href="?bref=Ps.45.1-17">Psalm 45</a>. It refers to a love song that was probably sung at wedding ceremonies.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Tefillah</span> is a common term for “prayer” and appears in the headings of <a href="?bref=Ps.17.1-15">Psalms 17</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.86.1-17">86</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.90.1-17">90</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.102.1-28">102</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ps.142.1-7">142</a>, and also in <a href="?bref=Hab.3.1">Habakkuk 3:1</a>. The word probably refers to a specific form of poetic prayer.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Selah</span> is one of the most frequently used, but most enigmatic, terms found in the book of Psalms. It occurs in 39 psalms, appearing a total of 71 times in the Psalter—67 times within the text and 4 times at the end of a psalm. It is most frequent in the first three books. In the first book <span class="hebrew">selah</span> appears in 9 psalms; in the second book, 17 psalms; in the third book, 11 psalms. In the fourth book it is not found at all and in the fifth book in only two psalms. Thirty-one of these psalms also include the term <span class="hebrew">menazzeah</span> in their superscriptions, which implies that they were sung by a soloist and choir. Most commonly, <span class="hebrew">selah</span> is interpreted as a signal for a break in the singing and possibly for an instrumental interlude. It never appears at the beginning of a psalm but only in the middle of the text or at the end. The regularity of its appearance within a psalm is not consistent, and in only a few instances do these divisions break the psalm into equal sections. Because of the random placement of the term, some scholars believe that, like the headings, <span class="hebrew">selah</span> was not always carefully copied into the text. It may have been a note appearing only in the texts of the musicians, which would explain this inconsistency. An explanation of <span class="hebrew">selah</span> is found in the Talmudic tradition: “Ben Azra clashed the cymbal and the Levites broke forth into singing. When they reached a break in the singing they blew upon the trumpets and the people prostrated themselves; at every break there was a blowing of the trumpet and at every blowing of the trumpet a prostration. This was the rite of the daily whole offering in the service of the House of our God.” <span class="hebrew">Selah</span><span class="ital">,</span> then, would be an instruction for the musicians that the singing was to cease and the instrumentalists were to play.</p>
<p>The term <span class="hebrew">higgaion selah</span> appears once, in <a href="?bref=Ps.9.16">Psalm 9:16</a>. The word <span class="hebrew">higgaiaon</span> comes from the root <span class="hebrew">hagah</span><span class="ital">,</span> “to murmur, to growl, to produce a low sound.” This may have been an instruction for the interlude to be more subdued than a normal <span class="hebrew">selah</span><span class="ital">.</span></p>
<p class="h3">Ancient Melodies in the Titles</p>
<p class="fl">Many psalms contain headings that are not direct musical references but are cue words to suggest well-known tunes. They probably refer either to names or the first words of popular secular songs <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">makams</span><span class="ital">)</span> whose melodic patterns were used in singing the psalm. Many biblical scholars have tried to find hidden meaning in these headings, but most musicologists believe these are simply references or introductions to melodies.</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Aijeleth Shahar</span><span class="ital">,</span> in <a href="?bref=Ps.22.1-31">Psalm 22</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>), is translated “according to The Hind of the Dawn” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>), and “To the tune of ‘The Doe of the Morning’ ” (<span class="sc">niv</span>), “To the tune ‘Doe of the Dawn’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Al-taschith</span><span class="ital">,</span> in <a href="?bref=Ps.57.1-59.17">Psalms 57–59</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.75.1-10">75</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>), is translated “To the tune ‘Do Not Destroy!’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Jonath-elem-rechokim</span><span class="ital">,</span> in <a href="?bref=Ps.56.1-13">Psalm 56</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>), is translated “according to The Dove on Far-off Terebinths” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>), and “To the tune ‘Dove on Distant Oaks’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Mahalath Leannoth</span><span class="ital">,</span> in <a href="?bref=Ps.88.1-18">Psalm 88</a>, is translated “To the tune ‘The Suffering of Affliction’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Muthlabben</span><span class="ital">,</span> in <a href="?bref=Ps.9.1-20">Psalm 9</a>, is translated “To the tune ‘Death of the Son’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Shoshannim</span><span class="ital">,</span> in <a href="?bref=Ps.45.1-17">Psalms 45</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.69.1-36">69</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>), is translated “To the tune ‘Lilies’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Shoshannim-Eduth</span><span class="ital">,</span> in <a href="?bref=Ps.80.1-19">Psalm 80</a> (<span class="sc">kjv</span>), is translated “To the tune ‘Lilies of the Covenant’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p><span class="hebrew">Shushan-eduth</span><span class="ital">,</span> in <a href="?bref=Ps.60.1-12">Psalm 60</a>, is translated “To the tune ‘Lily of the Testimony’ ” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>These melody types appear only in the first three books of the Psalter, and this may imply that these popular <span class="hebrew">makams</span> had fallen into disuse by the time the final books of the Psalter were written. Other <span class="hebrew">makam</span>-types had probably become popular, and the authors, realizing the relatively short life of a popular tune, did not include them in the headings of the Psalms but left the choice up to the performer.</p>
<p class="h2" id="MusicintheNewTestament">Music in the New Testament</p>
<p class="h3">First-Century Influences</p>
<p class="h4">The Synagogue</p>
<p class="fl">By the time of Christ, the synagogue had become the chief place of worship for the Jewish people. It began as a place for study of the law but gradually became the center of worship for Jews unable to attend the temple. The liturgical service of the temple could not be duplicated in the synagogue as there was no sacrificial rite, and the music could not be exactly reproduced as there were no trained Levitical singers. Scholars do not agree about the amount of continuity between the music of the temple and the music of the synagogue, but there is evidence that certain musical practices did remain constant between the two places of worship.</p>
<p>Information on the customs and rituals of the synagogue come from Talmudic writings. The musical elements of worship in the synagogue were the chanting of Scripture, psalmody, and spiritual songs. The choral singing of the temple was replaced by a single cantor. The cantor was a layman who, according to tradition, had to have the following qualifications: “He had to be well educated, gifted with a sweet voice, of humble personality, recognized by the community, conversant with Scripture and all the prayers; he must not be a rich man, for his prayers should come from his heart.” His most important job was the cantillation of the Law and the Prophets. A series of accents and punctuations, forerunners of actual musical notation, were indications for the cantor in the musical interpretation of the Scripture.</p>
<p>Psalm singing was gradually transplanted from the temple to the synagogue, which in turn influenced the early Christian church. Gregorian psalm tones have their roots in Hebrew psalmody.</p>
<p class="h4">Greek and Roman Cultures</p>
<p class="fl">While both the temple and the synagogue were familiar to the early Christians (<a href="?bref=Acts.2.46-47">Acts 2:46-47</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.3.1">3:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.5.42">5:42</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.20">9:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.4">18:4</a>; etc.), the Greek and Roman cultures also played a major part in shaping the young church. Hellenistic influences by the time of Christ had long been felt in the Middle East, and while it was strongly opposed by some Jewish leaders, the Greek arts had permeated Jewish culture. Greek philosophers considered music a cathartic force that could lead humans into metaphysical knowledge. This understanding led to the belief that music had a moral substance that could influence people to either good or evil. If this philosophy had totally encompassed Judeo-Christian thought, certainly Paul would have encouraged the use of music in the spread of the gospel. However, Paul’s omission of this theory implies that the Judeo-Christian world at that time had rejected the Greek ideal, at least in part.</p>
<p>While the Jewish rabbis considered music an art form for the praise of God, and while the Greek philosophers thought of it as a powerful moral force in creation, the Romans considered music mainly as entertainment. The music of the Roman games was neither religious nor philosophic and, from the accounts of witnesses, it was not technically exceptional. In the Roman Empire musicians were given a lower status and looked on as mere entertainers. One reason the early church did not include instrumental music in their worship was in reaction to the debased secular use of instruments by the Romans.</p>
<p class="h3">In the New Testament Writings</p>
<p class="fl">One of the few mentions of instruments in the NT is the use of flutes at a wake (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.23">Mt 9:23</a>). As in the OT, music is associated with feasting and merrymaking (e.g., the return of the prodigal son, <a href="?bref=Luke.15.25">Lk 15:25</a>). Five passages mention music metaphorically (<a href="?bref=Matt.6.2">Mt 6:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.11.17">11:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.7.32">Lk 7:32</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.13.1">1 Cor 13:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.7-8">14:7-8</a>). The most well known of these is Paul’s celebration of love in <a href="?bref=1Cor.13.1-13">1 Corinthians 13</a>. The denunciation of the gong and cymbals must be understood in light of the attitude of the early Christians toward the music of the Pharisees. Here the signal instruments of the temple were used to represent pompous display of religious pietism.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientChristianHymn"/>
<p>Most references to music are found in the eschatological visions and prophetic passages scattered throughout the NT—most frequently in the book of Revelation (also <a href="?bref=Matt.24.31">Mt 24:31</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.15.52">1 Cor 15:52</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.16">1 Thes 4:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.12.19">Heb 12:19</a>). Many of these descriptions have a direct association with musical references in the OT (e.g., the use of harps and trumpets and the singing of the Hallelujah). But the value of many of the passages in Revelation comes from their literary style. These doxological and psalmlike passages were probably spontaneous “spiritual songs” composed by the young church (e.g., <a href="?bref=Rev.5.9-10">Rv 5:9-10</a>).</p>
<p>The passages that mention religious or liturgical music are often more conceptual than literal. Two parallel passages describing the Last Supper (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.30">Mt 26:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.14.26">Mk 14:26</a>) mention that Christ and his disciples sang a hymn. This is the only direct account of Jesus singing, but it is probable that when he read in the synagogue he did so in the accepted vocal style (<a href="?bref=Luke.4.16-20">Lk 4:16-20</a>). There is much controversy surrounding the actual events at the Last Supper, but we can assume that the hymn sung was a traditional Jewish hymn, probably associated with the Passover.</p>
<p>From the account in <a href="?bref=Acts.16.25">Acts 16:25</a> we know that Paul and Silas sang hymns while in jail. Paul gives instruction for music making in <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.15,26">1 Corinthians 14:15, 26</a> in terms of a balance between rationalism and emotion. And, as with all the gifts of the Spirit, Paul asks that singing be done for edification.</p>
<p>In two similar passages (<a href="?bref=Eph.5.19">Eph 5:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.16">Col 3:16</a>) Paul groups together three musical terms—psalms, hymns, and spiritual songs. The singing of psalms was an obvious carryover from the synagogue, and we can assume that the early Christian psalm singing followed the Jewish style. The term for “hymns” probably refers to poetic texts, possibly modeled after the psalms, but in praise of Christ. “Spiritual songs” may refer to a spontaneous, ecstatic form of musical prayer, possibly wordless (perhaps related to glossolalia), in a style that was popular in mystical Judaism. These outbursts of song were probably melismatic (sung on one tone) and are perhaps the forerunners of the later Alleluia chant.</p>
<p class="h3">Hymnody in the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">It can be assumed that the early Christians composed hymns in praise of Christ. Logically, most of the hymns found in the NT are based on Hebrew poetic psalm forms, but there is Greek and Latin influence also. The hymns from the Gospel of Luke have become well-known canticles adopted by the church: the Magnificat (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.46-55">Lk 1:46-55</a>), the Benedictus (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.68-79">1:68-79</a>), the Gloria (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.14">2:14</a>) and the Nunc Dimittis (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.29-32">2:29-32</a>). While patterned after the psalms of the OT, these hymns are full of confidence in the salvation of Christ and in his imminent return. Other Christological hymns found in the NT include the prologue to the Gospel of John, <a href="?bref=Eph.2.14-16">Ephesians 2:14-16</a>, <a href="?bref=Phil.2.6-11">Philippians 2:6-11</a>, <a href="?bref=Col.1.15-20">Colossians 1:15-20</a>, <a href="?bref=1Tim.3.16">1 Timothy 3:16</a>, <a href="?bref=Heb.1.3">Hebrews 1:3</a>, and <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.18-22">1 Peter 3:18-22</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>