<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="ThessaloniansSecondLettertothe">
  <title>Thessalonians, Second Letter to the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">THESSALONIANS, Second Letter to the</p>
<p class="fl">Paul’s second epistle to the church at Thessalonica.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Authors">Author(s)</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Purpose">Purpose</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Authors">Author(s)</p>
<p class="fl">This letter, like 1 Thessalonians, begins with the names of Paul, Silvanus, and Timothy, and like that letter often retains the plural pronouns “we” and “us” but also has the singular “I” (e.g., <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.5">2 Thes 2:5</a>). The end of the letter reads: “Now here is my greeting, which I write with my own hand—<span class="sc">Paul</span>. I do this at the end of all my letters to prove that they really are from me” (<a href="?bref=2Thes.3.17">3:17</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Some scholars have questioned Paul’s authorship, mostly because of the difference between the teaching about the future in this letter and that in 1 Thessalonians. In the light of the words of <a href="?bref=2Thes.3.17">2 Thessalonians 3:17</a>, the first letter would have to be seen as a blatant forgery. And this is not the case. The early church did not question Paul’s authorship of both.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DateOriginandDestination">Date, Origin, and Destination</p>
<p class="fl">In the first verse, exactly as in 1 Thessalonians, the letter is addressed “to the church of the Thessalonians.” Unlike 1 Thessalonians, this letter provides us with no other personal details of the movements of Paul and his coworkers. Thus, there is no direct evidence of the date and place of the letter.</p>
<p>Just as the difference between the teaching of this epistle from that of 1 Thessalonians has led some to question its Pauline authorship, so it has led others to a variety of explanations for its date and destination. These include:</p>
<p class="list-space">1. It was written much later than 1 Thessalonians. This is improbable because both Silas and Timothy were still with Paul.</p>
<p class="list">2. It was written earlier than 1 Thessalonians. In <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.15">2:15</a>, however, there is a reference to a letter written previously to Thessalonica, and the early church from the second century certainly called this 2 Thessalonians.</p>
<p class="list">3. It was written to Jewish Christians in Thessalonica, while 1 Thessalonians was written to gentile Christians. This, however, is most unlikely, as the apostle who had such concern for the unity of all Christians in one place (e.g., <a href="?bref=1Cor.1.1-3.23">1 Cor 1–3</a>) and especially for the unity of Jewish and gentile Christians (see <a href="?bref=Eph.2.11-22">Eph 2:11-22</a>) could hardly have done such a thing.</p>
<p class="list">4. It was written to Christians in a different place (Berea or Philippi), and then came to be in the hands of the Thessalonian Christians. There is no evidence to support the idea that the letter was sent anywhere but to Thessalonica.</p>
<p class="sp">When this epistle was written, Paul had the same coworkers with him as when he wrote 1 Thessalonians (<a href="?bref=2Thes.1.1">2 Thes 1:1</a>). This indicates that probably a short time after writing 1 Thessalonians, Paul heard of further problems being faced by the Christians in Thessalonica, and in his concern for them, he wrote this second letter.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Purpose">Purpose</p>
<p class="fl">There were three main concerns in the mind of the apostle Paul as he wrote this letter.</p>
<p>As in all his letters, he wanted to encourage his readers to stand firm in their faith (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.15">2:15</a>). He could thank God for his work in their lives (<a href="?bref=2Thes.1.3">1:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.13">2:13</a>), made evident by their faith, love, and steadfastness in the face of persecutions (<a href="?bref=2Thes.1.4">1:4</a>). Paul assured them of the righting of wrongs in the ultimate judgment of God. Their task was to glorify the name of Jesus by their lives; then at his coming he would be glorified in his faithful people (vv <a href="?bref=2Thes.1.5-12">5-12</a>).</p>
<p>There was false teaching, even purportedly from Paul, that the Day of the Lord had already come (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.2">2:2</a>). The apostle rejected this teaching by saying that certain things must take place prior to the Second Coming. There must be a still greater manifestation of evil in the person of one called “the man of lawlessness” or “the son of perdition.” This one will reject all true worship, show signs and wonders, and proclaim himself to be God. At present there is a restraining influence. The time will come, however, when the lawless one will be revealed. Then the Lord himself will come and “the lawless one” will be conquered and destroyed. This teaching (vv <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.1-12">1-12</a>) is similar to that in the Gospels about the Antichrist or antichrists, claiming to be Christ, deceiving people by signs and wonders (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.5,23-26">Mt 24:5, 23-26</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.5-6,20-23">Mk 13:5-6, 20-23</a>). In 1 Thessalonians, Paul emphasized that the time of the Lord’s coming is unknown, and believers must be ready for him at any time. Here, in opposition to the idea that the Lord had already come, Paul spoke of those things that must take place before the Lord’s coming. Both of these aspects were also presented by Jesus when he taught about the future (<a href="?bref=Matt.24.1-51">Mt 24</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.13.1-37">Mk 13</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.21.1-38">Lk 21</a>).</p>
<p>Finally, the problem of laziness in the Christian community (referred to in <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.11">1 Thes 4:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.5.14">5:14</a>) remained, and probably had increased. Paul had to refer again to the example that he and his coworkers had given to them—they had worked with their own hands to earn a living instead of depending on those to whom they brought the gospel. Paul had a simple dictum that he applied: “If any one will not work, let him not eat” (<a href="?bref=2Thes.3.10">2 Thess 3:10</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Thanksgiving for Their Christian Lives (<a href="?bref=2Thes.1.3-4">1:3-4</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Paul praised God for the Thessalonians’ growing faith, increasing love, and endurance of persecution.</p>
<p class="h3">A Reversal of Persecutors and Persecuted (<a href="?bref=2Thes.1.5-10">1:5-10</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">At that time the Thessalonian Christians were having to suffer, but their persecutors would have to face the just judgment of God at the coming of the Lord Jesus “with his mighty angels.” Those who reject the knowledge of God and the salvation offered in the gospel must “suffer the punishment of eternal destruction.” His people will experience that glory of his coming and will realize that they have not believed or suffered in vain.</p>
<p class="h3">Prayer That the Lord Jesus Will Be Glorified (<a href="?bref=2Thes.1.11-12">1:11-12</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This is Paul’s prayer for the Thessalonian Christians—a life worthy of their calling, the fulfilling of their resolves, and by the grace of God, that the name of Christ would be glorified in them.</p>
<p class="h3">Events That Must Precede Christ’s Second Coming (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.1-12">2:1-12</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In this section, Paul deals with the false teaching that the Day of the Lord had already come. Before this event, there must be the revealing of “the man of lawlessness,” otherwise called the Antichrist (though it may be noted that the NT also speaks of “antichrists” and “the spirit of antichrist”—<a href="?bref=1Jn.2.18">1 Jn 2:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Jn.4.3">4:3</a>). Paul said, “That day will not come until there is a great rebellion against God and the man of lawlessness is revealed” (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.3">2 Thes 2:3</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>At the present time, the mystery of lawlessness is restrained (vv <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.6-7">6-7</a>). But in the future—just prior to the Lord’s coming—the restraint will be taken away. In other words, all hell will break loose. Christians must be prepared for a supreme manifestation of evil “with pretended signs and wonders” (v <a href="?bref=2Thes.2.9">9</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) by which many will be deceived. The coming of Christ will mean the overthrow of evil and the judgment of those who oppose the truth and take pleasure in unrighteousness.</p>
<p class="h3">Renewed Thanksgiving, Encouragement, and Prayer (<a href="?bref=2Thes.2.13-3.5">2:13–3:5</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Subsequent to the discussion of the power of evil in people’s lives, Paul gives thanks for the work of the Spirit of God in the lives of the Thessalonian Christians. He encourages them to continue in all that the apostle has taught them, when present with them or by letter. Paul’s prayer is that God, as the great Giver of comfort and hope, will establish them in every good work and word. He also expresses his need of their prayers, that God may continue to prosper the word he preaches and deliver him from evil men. His Christian readers, for their part, can be assured of God’s faithfulness. Paul’s prayer for them is that, as they continue in the things in which they have been taught, they will be directed to the love of God and the endurance that comes from Christ.</p>
<p class="h3">Warning against Disorderliness and Idleness (<a href="?bref=2Thes.3.6-15">3:6-15</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Another of Paul’s special purposes in writing was to stress that there is no place for idleness in the lives of Christians. He had taught this and exemplified this in his own life. Christian people are “to do their work in quietness,” “earn their own living,” and “not be weary in well-doing” (vv <a href="?bref=2Thes.3.12-13">12-13</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). There should be no associating with those who reject this teaching, but they should be admonished as brothers, not treated as enemies.</p>
<p class="h3">Conclusion (<a href="?bref=2Thes.3.16-18">3:16-18</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">With a prayer for grace and peace and with his own personal signature, Paul concludes the letter. When he speaks of writing with his own hand in verse <a href="?bref=2Thes.3.17">17</a>, it probably means that up to that point Paul had dictated his letter to someone else (cf. <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.21">1 Cor 16:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.4.18">Col 4:18</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Eschatology_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eschatology</a>; <a href="?item=PaultheApostle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paul, The Apostle</a>; <a href="?item=SecondComingofChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Second Coming of Christ</a>; <a href="?item=ThessaloniansFirstLettertothe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Thessalonians, First Letter to the</a>; <a href="?item=Thessalonica_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Thessalonica</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>