<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TimothySecondLetterto">
  <title>Timothy, Second Letter to</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">TIMOTHY, Second Letter to</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PlaceandDateofWriting">Place and Date of Writing</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Background">Background</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">Many of those who deny the Pauline authorship of the Pastoral Epistles recognize that 2 Timothy contains some true Pauline fragments in the numerous personal references in the letter. But the evidence in favor of the Pauline authorship is much stronger than the evidence against it. (See the discussion on authorship of the Pastoral Letters under “<a href="?item=TimothyFirstLetterto_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Timothy, First Letter to</a>.”)</p>
<p class="h2" id="PlaceandDateofWriting">Place and Date of Writing</p>
<p class="fl">Paul was in prison when he wrote this letter to Timothy; <a href="?bref=2Tim.1.15-18">2 Timothy 1:15-18</a> tells specifically of his being in Rome and how Onesiphorus was faithful to him when others from the province of Asia had deserted him. <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.9">Second Timothy 2:9</a> again refers to his being in jail for preaching the gospel. Toward the end of the letter, starting at <a href="?bref=2Tim.4.6">4:6</a>, Paul relates his experience in prison—and that he has no hope for release. Second Timothy is a type of last will and testament of the apostle. Early, trustworthy tradition reports that Paul was martyred in Rome under Nero. Rome, then, was the place from which 2 Timothy was written.</p>
<p>The letter was written to Timothy in Ephesus, as is made plain throughout the letter.</p>
<p>As to the year in which it was written, two dates are possible. The year 64 <span class="era">AD</span> was the date of the great fire in Rome. Nero tried to shift responsibility for the fire to the Christians. Possibly Paul was martyred at that time. Nero himself died in <span class="era">AD</span> 67, so that would be the latest date that could be assigned. The letter was written between <span class="era">AD</span> 64 and 67, with some preference being given to the earlier date.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Background">Background</p>
<p class="fl">Since the time of the writing of 1 Timothy, Paul made further travels and then came to Rome for his second imprisonment. See this section under “<a href="?item=TimothyFirstLetterto_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Timothy, First Letter to</a>.”</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Salutation (<a href="?bref=2Tim.1.1-2">1:1-2</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">As was customary in ancient letters, the writer puts his name first. Then he gives a fuller identification of himself as an apostle, one belonging to Jesus Christ, and one commissioned to tell the whole world about the eternal life that God has made available through faith in Jesus Christ. Paul hereby indicates his authority and also gives a brief summary of the essence of the true Christian faith.</p>
<p>The person to whom the letter is written is “Timothy, my beloved child.” Then follows a triple blessing, “Grace, mercy, and peace” from God the Father and his Son, Jesus Christ. As in all his letters, Paul changes the rather colorless Greek salutation, “greetings,” to one of the greatest theological concepts, “grace,” and adds the Greek translation of the regular Hebrew salutation, “peace.” Then he adds here the great word, “mercy,” as he did in 1 Timothy.</p>
<p class="h3">Exhortations to Timothy to Be a Good Minister (<a href="?bref=2Tim.1.3-2.13">1:3–2:13</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Paul begins this section by telling Timothy how often he offered prayers of thanksgiving to God on his behalf, to the God of his fathers, to the God whom it was his chief purpose in life to please. Paul greatly desired to see Timothy, especially as he remembered their tearful parting.</p>
<p>Paul reminded Timothy of his great trust in the Lord, a trust that was passed on to him by two godly women: his mother, Eunice, and his grandmother, Lois. <a href="?bref=Acts.16.1-3">Acts 16:1-3</a> states that Timothy’s mother was a believing Jewess, and his father was a Greek, or Gentile. He had not allowed his son to be circumcised in infancy. But the believing mother had passed on her faith to her son. When Paul decided to take him along as an assistant on his second missionary journey, he had him circumcised so that he could work more effectively with the Jews. Thus, Timothy had a great heritage from Lois, Eunice, and Paul himself.</p>
<p>“Hence I remind you to rekindle the gift of God that is within you through the laying on of my hands” (<a href="?bref=2Tim.1.6">2 Tm 1:6</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). <a href="?bref=1Tim.4.14">First Timothy 4:14</a> adds this: “when the council of elders laid their hands upon you.” This seems very much like there had been a formal service of ordination, when Timothy was set apart as a minister of the gospel by the laying on of hands accompanied by prayer. Timothy should have never forgotten that solemn moment, and the memory should have kept his life filled with strength and boldness. He was truly a man of God, a man filled with the Spirit of God, and a man not afraid to do his Christian work. Timothy might suffer for his faith, but he could be encouraged as he remembered the sufferings and imprisonment of his spiritual father, Paul. God would give Timothy strength to endure suffering, as he had done for Paul.</p>
<p>Then Paul reminded Timothy of how God had saved him and Paul, and how he had chosen them from all eternity to tell others of God’s saving love through Jesus Christ, who came in time to work out that salvation, by breaking the power of death and showing the way to eternal life. Paul knew, of course, what he believed, but more importantly he knew whom he believed, or trusted—Jesus Christ. And in spite of the many uncertainties that must have been in Paul’s mind, he could be absolutely sure of Christ. Paul was also sure that Christ would be able to guard what had been entrusted to him—guard it until the day Paul and Jesus saw each other. Paul was confident of that, and he wanted Timothy to have a similar assurance.</p>
<p>So Paul urged Timothy to hold fast to the pattern of truth Paul had taught him—that body of Christian doctrine, especially as it pertained to Jesus Christ and the faith and love in Christ. He should guard this gift carefully, with the help of the Holy Spirit.</p>
<p>Paul then shared with Timothy his great sorrow that all the Christians of the Roman province of Asia, of which Ephesus was the chief city, had deserted him. Paul mentions two of the deserters by name, Phygelus and Hermogenes. Evidently Timothy knew who they were. In striking contrast, Paul mentioned the good man Onesiphorus (also at <a href="?bref=2Tim.4.19">4:19</a>), who had been such a wonderful and faithful helper of Paul, both in Ephesus and in Rome.</p>
<p>Paul again urged Timothy to be strong in the strength that Christ has given him (<a href="?bref=2Tim.2.1">2:1</a>). Timothy should pass on the Christian truths to others and train them to pass them on to still others. Paul was probably thinking especially of the elders and deacons (cf. 1 Timothy). Paul used three effective illustrations to encourage Timothy to give his best in his Christian service. He was to fight and suffer as a good soldier, play the game well as a good athlete, and work hard as a good farmer. The rewards will come to all three if they perform their tasks well. All three illustrations had been used by Jesus, and they were used by other NT writers.</p>
<p>In the midst of his exhortations, Paul provided a fine summary of true Christology in <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.8-10">2:8-10</a>. Jesus was truly man and truly God. It is heretical to deny either the full humanity or the full deity of Christ, even though no human mind can full understand the mystery of the Incarnation. And this divine-human being died and then rose again from the dead.</p>
<p class="h3">Warnings against Heresy (<a href="?bref=2Tim.2.14-4.5">2:14–4:5</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">This section begins with the affirmation “Remind everyone of these things, and command them in God’s name to stop fighting over words. Such arguments are useless, and they can ruin those who hear them” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). There are heretical beliefs that should be definitely condemned, but Christians are warned against arguing among themselves about insignificant matters. Christians can become angry with other Christians and spend time fighting one another rather than fighting Satan.</p>
<p>Timothy was to strive to make himself a good servant, meriting the approval of his Master, knowing well the truths of his word. In that way, he could combat the false teachings of the heretics. Two of the heretics are mentioned by name, Hymenaeus and Philetus. Philetus is named only here in the NT. Hymenaeus, though, was mentioned also in <a href="?bref=1Tim.1.20">1 Timothy 1:20</a>, along with another heretic, Alexander; these two had been given over to Satan, or excommunicated, by Paul at that time. Their heresy was that they taught that the resurrection of believers had already happened (<a href="?bref=2Tim.2.18">2 Tm 2:18</a>). This heresy undermines the Christian hope of the final resurrection, which brings all believers into eternity. The heretics were denying the reality of that and redefining it as something that had already happened.</p>
<p>In various ways Paul urged Timothy to prove himself a true servant of God, one who is known by God and one who lives by the truths of God’s word. He should avoid the evil thoughts that so often come to young men, and also the temptation to quarrel. Rather, he should be gentle, patient, and humble, seeking to help his people avoid the traps of Satan.</p>
<p><a href="?bref=2Tim.3.1-9">Second Timothy 3:1-9</a> gives Paul’s strongest condemnation of the heretics in the church. They attend church but they do not believe the Christian truths. They do not live Christian lives themselves, and they strive to get others to follow their beliefs and practices; Paul likened the heretics of his day to the Egyptian magicians in <a href="?bref=Exod.7.1-25">Exodus 7</a> (who were given the names Jannes and Jambres by Jewish tradition). The heretics in Timothy’s day would fail in their attacks against the truth, just as Jannes and Jambres had failed in their attacks against God and his spokesman Moses.</p>
<p>Paul contrasted his own life and beliefs with those of the heretics. He had been persecuted by heretics himself even on his first missionary journey, but he had continued to preach the truth and had brought many to accept Christ. Timothy should follow Paul’s example.</p>
<p>The supreme way to overcome heresy is the diligent study of the Word of God. “All Scripture is inspired by God and is useful to teach us what is true and to make us realize what is wrong in our lives. It straightens us out and teaches us to do what is right. It is God’s way of preparing us in every way, fully equipped for every good thing God wants us to do” (<a href="?bref=2Tim.3.16-17">3:16-17</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>Paul gave Timothy a solemn charge to preach that Word faithfully and diligently. Many would not be willing to listen to the truths of the Bible, but Timothy should try to correct and rebuke them, even though it may bring persecution upon himself.</p>
<p class="h3">Paul’s Faith and Hope (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.6-18">4:6-18</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Paul had been writing these important injunctions to Timothy because he knew that he had very little time left here on earth: “As for me, my life has already been poured out as an offering to God. The time of my death is near” (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.6">4:6</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). He can look back with satisfaction upon a life of true faith and service. So he can look forward in all confidence to his crown of victory in eternity. This kind of faith enabled Paul to face his death bravely, and it will do the same for all believing Christians for whom the Second Coming is a blessed hope.</p>
<p>Paul urged Timothy to come and be with him in Rome. Luke was the only one of his friends still with him. Paul told Timothy about other friends who had been with him but who had left. One, Demas, had proved to be a failure. Crescens, Titus, and Tychicus had left for other places. Paul asked Timothy to bring his coat, which he had left at Troas with Carpus, and also his books, especially those written on parchment (probably some copies of Scripture, both Old Testament and New). Paul warned Timothy against the evil man, Alexander the coppersmith (see <a href="?bref=1Tim.1.20">1 Tm 1:20</a>).</p>
<p>At Paul’s first trial, all of his friends had left him. But God had been with him and saved him. Paul had even had an opportunity of proclaiming the gospel for all the world to hear.</p>
<p class="h3">Concluding Greetings (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.19-22">4:19-22</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Paul sent his greetings to a number of his friends in Ephesus. And he sent greetings to Timothy from some of the Roman Christians whom he evidently knew. He urged Timothy to try to come to him before winter, when traveling would be difficult or impossible. He then concluded with a short benediction: “The Lord be with your spirit.”</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PaultheApostle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paul, The Apostle</a>; <a href="?item=TimothyFirstLetterto_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Timothy, First Letter to</a>; <a href="?item=TitusLetterto_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Titus, Letter to</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>