<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="TitusLetterto">
  <title>Titus, Letter to</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">TITUS, Letter to</p>
<p class="fl">Paul’s epistle to his coworker, Titus.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#Author">Author</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Recipient">Recipient</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Date">Date</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#PurposeandTeaching">Purpose and Teaching</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="Author">Author</p>
<p class="fl">Though this letter begins with the name and greeting of Paul (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.1-3">Ti 1:1-3</a>), Paul’s authorship has been questioned by modern scholars on the grounds of its language and style, the church situation it presents, and the way that it sets forth Christian teaching. But Pauline authorship has been stoutly defended by eminent scholars and careful students who have argued that there is no reason for supposing that this epistle was written by someone else using Paul’s name, after the apostle himself had died. The differences in this epistle and Paul’s other letters are explained previously in the section on “Author” in the article “Timothy, First Letter to.”</p>
<p class="h2" id="Recipient">Recipient</p>
<p class="fl">Titus appears to have been one of Paul’s most trusted and valuable coworkers. Paul speaks of him (<a href="?bref=2Cor.8.23">2 Cor 8:23</a>) as “my partner and coworker.” According to <a href="?bref=Titus.1.4">Titus 1:4</a>, he owed his conversion to Paul. It is clear from <a href="?bref=Gal.2.1-4">Galatians 2:1-4</a> that he was a Gentile, as his was a test case whether gentile Christians should be compelled to be circumcised. At that time Titus was with Paul and Barnabas in Jerusalem. Much later, at the time of Paul’s third missionary journey, he had two delicate missions to carry out for Paul in Corinth: the first pertained to the strained relationship between the apostle and the Corinthian Christians; the second related to the gentile collection for the Jerusalem church (<a href="?bref=2Cor.2.12-13">2 Cor 2:12-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.7.5-16">7:5-16</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.8.1-24">8:1-24</a>). If <a href="?bref=2Tim.4.9-18">2 Timothy 4:9-18</a> was written at the end of Paul’s life, then Titus went to Dalmatia after the time of this letter.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Date">Date</p>
<p class="fl">To date this letter with precision is difficult. Titus was left by the apostle in Crete to continue his work (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.5">Ti 1:5</a>). Paul was in Crete briefly on his voyage to Rome (<a href="?bref=Acts.27.7-13">Acts 27:7-13</a>), but that could not have been the occasion referred to. In <a href="?bref=Titus.3.12">3:12</a> Titus is called to come to Nicopolis (probably the Nicopolis in Epirus in Greece), as Paul had decided to winter there. Many have favored the view that after Paul’s first imprisonment in Rome (<a href="?bref=Acts.28.16-31">Acts 28:16-31</a>) he was released, carried out further ministry in various places (including Spain, Crete, and Greece), and then was arrested, imprisoned a second time, and finally put to death. Those who do not accept Pauline authorship of Titus, date this letter, like 1 and 2 Timothy, in the generation that followed Paul’s death.</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="TitusServestheChurchesinCrete"/>
<p class="h2" id="PurposeandTeaching">Purpose and Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">Although this letter is addressed to an individual colleague of the apostle, it has a minimum of personal references and exhortations. The growing and developing churches in Crete were Paul’s main concern. They were being bothered by false teachings that appear to have had Jewish elements, ascetic emphases, and a great deal of speculative discussion (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.10,14-15">Ti 1:10, 14-15</a>: <a href="?bref=Titus.3.9">3:9</a>). In short, it seems that they were dealing with an early Jewish form of Gnosticism. Its advocates promoted this teaching “for base gain” (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.11">1:11</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Titus and those whom he would appoint as elders were called upon to refute the wrong teaching and to provide the believers with healthy teaching (v <a href="?bref=Titus.1.9">9</a>). Though this healthy teaching is not specified, it must have pertained to the saving grace of God in Christ, the renewing work of the Holy Spirit, and the future coming of the Lord Jesus (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.11-13">2:11-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.3.4-7">3:4-7</a>). In this letter there is constant emphasis on the lifestyle that bears out the truth of the gospel—with application to different groups in the Christian community: older men and women, young women, young men, and slaves.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">Salutation (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.1-4">1:1-4</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Greetings come from Paul—whose apostleship is described as a stewardship of the gospel that promotes faith and strengthens the knowledge of the truth, hope of eternal life, and godliness of living—to Titus, spoken of as “my true son in our common faith.”</p>
<p class="h3">Titus’s Work in Crete (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.5-9">1:5-9</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Titus was left behind in Crete to continue Paul’s work and to appoint elders in every church (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.14.23">Acts 14:23</a>). These elders are also called bishops (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.20.17,28">20:17, 28</a>)—that is, those with oversight of the church. The necessary qualities of life for these positions are described (cf. <a href="?bref=1Tim.3.2-7">1 Tm 3:2-7</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Dealing with False Teachings (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.10-16">1:10-16</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">The closing words of the previous section speak about the responsibility of elders “to encourage others with right teaching and show those who oppose it where they are wrong” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>). The opposers were upsetting people, indeed “whole families,” by teaching what was not true. These false teachers were described by Paul in terms disparaging of Cretans, and as people whose lives do not demonstrate the knowledge of God that they professed to have.</p>
<p class="h3">Promoting Right Teaching (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.1-10">2:1-10</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">Titus had a particular responsibility to “promote the kind of living that reflects right teaching.” He was charged to exhort the older men to exercise self-control (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.2">2:2</a>), and he was supposed to teach the older women to live godly lives (v <a href="?bref=Titus.2.3">3</a>). In turn, these women were supposed to train the younger women to live pure and loving lives in their homes so that no one will malign the word of God (vv <a href="?bref=Titus.2.4-5">4-5</a>). Younger men were to show self-control (v <a href="?bref=Titus.2.6">6</a>), and Titus himself was to be an example in word and life so that the opponents would have nothing bad to say about the Christians (vv <a href="?bref=Titus.2.7-8">7-8</a>). Finally, in this section slaves are taught to submit to their masters, to give good and honest service with the motivation that “then they will make the teaching about God our Savior attractive in every way” (v <a href="?bref=Titus.2.10">10</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p class="h3">God’s Grace (<a href="?bref=Titus.2.11-15">2:11-15</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">What has been said leads now to a great statement of the purpose of the revelation of the grace of God in Jesus Christ: to bring salvation to all people, who will make a complete break with godless and sensual living so that they may live upright lives with the constant expectancy of the coming again of “our great God and Savior Jesus Christ.” Their lives will show them to be a people who are God’s very own, always eager to do what is right.</p>
<p class="h3">Doing What Is Good (<a href="?bref=Titus.3.1-8">3:1-8</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In this section, Paul encourages Titus to tell the Christians at Crete that it is their duty to submit to rulers (cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.13.1-7">Rom 13:1-7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.2.13-17">1 Pt 2:13-17</a>) and to be available in the community for honest work. Again, the quality of lifestyle is emphasized—in particular, courtesy and the desire for peace in relationships with others. This lifestyle comes from spiritual transformation. The means of that transformation is the saving work of Christ—not merited, but entirely of his mercy. He has brought cleansing from sin, “rebirth and renewal by the Holy Spirit.”</p>
<p class="h3">Paul’s Final Remarks and Greetings (<a href="?bref=Titus.3.9-15">3:9-15</a>)</p>
<p class="fl">In this final section, Paul encourages Titus to avoid those who like to debate about religion for the sake of debating. And he tells Titus how to deal with those who cause divisions.</p>
<p>Following this, Paul tells Titus that he will send him Artemas (not mentioned otherwise in the NT) or Tychicus. Then he encourages Titus to take care of Apollos and Zenas if they pass by Crete. Titus himself is supposed to come to Paul in Nicopolis before winter.</p>
<p>The epistle closes with a final exhortation to “good deeds” and to a spiritually fruitful life.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PaultheApostle_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Paul, The Apostle</a>; <a href="?item=TimothyFirstLetterto_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Timothy, First Letter to</a>; <a href="?item=TimothySecondLetterto_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Timothy, Second Letter to</a>; <a href="?item=TitusPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Titus (Person) #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>