<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Travel">
  <title>Travel</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">TRAVEL</p>
<p class="fl">In biblical times travelers found roads bad and often impassable. Sea voyages were made in comparatively small ships, usually by military and commercial personnel, and hardly ever for simple tourist traffic. With little reason to travel, ordinary citizens tended to remain in fairly limited areas. From time to time, there were group migrations, and sometimes people traveled for religious festivals or fled from war or famine.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TravelOnTheAppianWay"/>
<p class="h2" id="TravelinOldTestamentTimes">Travel in Old Testament Times</p>
<p class="fl">Several accounts depict the people of Israel moving over restricted areas to graze their flocks. Joseph’s brothers took their flocks from the south of the land up to Shechem and then to Dothan (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.12-17">Gn 37:12-17</a>), but this was a mere 60 miles (96.5 kilometers). David traveled around Palestine and even went to Moab (<a href="?bref=1Sam.22.3">1 Sm 22:3</a>). The Danites moved from their home southwest of Jerusalem to the north, just south of the Lebanon Mountains (<a href="?bref=Judg.18.1-31">Jgs 18</a>).</p>
<p>Examples of travel for pasturage, migration, and protection could be multiplied. Such travelers would normally walk, though the ass was used both for riding and as a pack animal. The ox was employed for transporting heavy loads and sometimes for people (<a href="?bref=Gen.46.5">Gn 46:5</a>). Later the camel came into general use (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.2">1 Kgs 10:2</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.8.9">2 Kgs 8:9</a>). Little is known of resting places for travelers in OT times. There are only a few references to a “lodging place” (<span class="hebrew">malon</span>) in OT narratives (<a href="?bref=Gen.42.27">Gn 42:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.43.21">43:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.4.24">Ex 4:24</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="TravelinNewTestamentTimes">Travel in New Testament Times</p>
<p class="fl">The Roman world knew a great deal of travel: to fulfill religious obligations at festival time, for trade, for government administration, for military purposes. Not the least among first-century travelers were the early Christian missionaries.</p>
<p>The advent of Roman peace and authority and the construction of well-made stone roads made travel relatively safe and quick. The modes of travel improved over that known in OT times. Long distances were traveled within the Roman Empire over good roads and in comparative safety. There were some hazards, however, notably in sea travel, from wind, storms, and pirates (<a href="?bref=Acts.15.39">Acts 15:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.18-22">18:18-22</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.15.24-25">Rom 15:24-25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.25-26">2 Cor 11:25-26</a>). Paul’s sea journey to Rome, for example, was perilous (<a href="?bref=Acts.27.1-28.14">Acts 27:1–28:14</a>).</p>
<p>The NT mentions a number of journeys on foot. Mary journeyed from Galilee to Judea to visit Elizabeth (<a href="?bref=Luke.1.39-40,56">Lk 1:39-40, 56</a>). The baby Jesus was born in Bethlehem during the census (<a href="?bref=Luke.2.1-7">2:1-7</a>); Jesus was brought to Jerusalem to comply with the Jewish purification law (v <a href="?bref=Luke.2.22">22</a>). Thus three trips were made from Nazareth to Jerusalem, a distance of about 70 miles (112.6 kilometers), from the time of Jesus’ conception to Mary’s purification. The annual Passover visit was made by Joseph and Mary (vv <a href="?bref=Luke.2.41-51">41-51</a>). Other journeys are mentioned (<a href="?bref=John.2.13">Jn 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=John.5.1">5:1</a>; <a href="?bref=John.7.1-10">7:1-10</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.1">12:1</a>). Jesus himself walked to Jericho from Galilee (<a href="?bref=Mark.1.1-11">Mk 1:1-11</a>) and also to the region of Tyre and Sidon (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.24">7:24</a>). He was in Samaria more than once (<a href="?bref=Luke.17.11">Lk 17:11</a>; <a href="?bref=John.4.4">Jn 4:4</a>). His last journey to Jerusalem was via Jericho and up through the hills to Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Mark.10.1,46">Mk 10:1, 46</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.11.1">11:1</a>). His last journey after the resurrection was to Emmaus (<a href="?bref=Luke.24.13-35">Lk 24:13-35</a>).</p>
<p>Paul traveled by sea on each of his missionary journeys (<a href="?bref=Acts.13.1-14">Acts 13:1-14</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.15.41-18.22">15:41–18:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.18.23-21.17">18:23–21:17</a>), generally accompanied by friends. He also made many journeys on foot in Palestine, Asia Minor, and the Greek peninsula. But not all travel was on foot in NT times. The ass, used for carrying loads, often carried people. Jesus once rode from Bethphage to Jerusalem, a short but highly symbolic journey (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.2-7">Mt 21:2-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.11.1-11">Mk 11:1-11</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.12-15">Jn 12:12-15</a>). When Joseph traveled with his pregnant wife, Mary, to Bethlehem for the census at the time of Jesus’ birth, Mary probably rode on an ass. The Ethiopian eunuch was riding in a chariot after worshiping at Jerusalem and was joined by Philip traveling on foot (<a href="?bref=Acts.8.26-38">Acts 8:26-38</a>). Roman soldiers both marched and made wide use of horses. When Paul was brought to Caesarea from Jerusalem, mounts were prepared for him (<a href="?bref=Acts.23.23-24">23:23-24</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="RoadsandSeaLanes">Roads and Sea Lanes</p>
<p class="fl">The roads of biblical times figured prominently in the geography, topography, and history of Palestine—a land that served as a bridge between Egypt and centers of civilization and trade in the Middle East. Many of the roads were strategically important, both commercially and militarily. Some roads gained significance as pilgrim routes to facilitate travel to religious centers like Jerusalem. Roads in biblical times were of three main types: long-distance international roads, medium-distance intraregional roads, and a variety of roads inside each region or state.</p>
<p class="h3">Great International Roads</p>
<p class="fl">These linked the Mediterranean coast to the northern Tigris Valley and southern Mesopotamia. Some linked Mesopotamia to Asia Minor, while others led south to Egypt, either along the coast or east of the Jordan River and the Dead Sea and across the Sinai Peninsula. There were trade routes between Anatolia and Assyria early in the second millennium <span class="era">BC</span>. Apparently the military campaign referred to in <a href="?bref=Gen.14.1-24">Genesis 14</a> aimed to secure the great trade route, the King’s Highway, from northern Mesopotamia to Egypt. Military invaders and travelers from Babylonia, Assyria, and Persia would head across the hinterlands of Syria toward the coast before turning south into Palestine and Egypt. The advent of European powers, Greece and Rome, into the Middle East opened up another vast network of international roads for the peoples of the East. Until Roman times, these roads were not surfaced with stone but were cleared pathways. They were very rough, ungraded, and in wet weather, impassable in many places. But they were evidently well defined by “waymarks” and “guideposts” (<a href="?bref=Jer.31.21">Jer 31:21</a>). With the coming of the Romans, important roads were built with deep foundations and with large blocks of flat stone at the surface. The remains of these roads are still seen in many places in the Middle East and in Europe. Distance markers or milestones were regularly placed along the roads.</p>
<p class="h3">International North-South Roads in Palestine</p>
<p class="fl">The roads that linked countries to the north with Egypt passed through Palestine, a natural land bridge. There were three major roads. The coastal road began in Damascus and passed via Hazor across the plain of Esdraelon, through the Megiddo Pass, down the coast past Gaza and into Egypt. This was probably “the way of the sea” (<a href="?bref=Isa.9.1">Is 9:1</a>). The Sinai road led from Egypt into the southern Negev and then to Kadesh-barnea, Beersheba, Hebron, Jerusalem, Shechem, Acco, Tyre, and Sidon. The Red Sea road entered the Palestine area from the Gulf of Aqaba, where the ancient port of Elath and Solomon’s port of Ezion-geber stood (<a href="?bref=Num.33.35">Nm 33:35</a>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.8.17">2 Chr 8:17</a>). From there it led through the mountainous areas of Transjordan, crossing the deep wadis and then north through the Hauran region to Damascus. This was the road taken by caravans from southern Arabia to Damascus, the ancient King’s Highway (<a href="?bref=Num.20.17">Nm 20:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.21.22">21:22</a>).</p>
<p>There were other north-south roads of lesser importance. One coastal road led from Joppa via Caesarea and Dor to Acco, where it linked with the Sinai road. Evidently it was not very significant until Roman times, when the port of Caesarea was built. The marshes in the plain of Sharon posed many problems. The plain of Esdraelon was also marshy and interrupted the roads north in bad seasons. A raised road across the swampy sections was eventually constructed. Another road led north from Hazor, branching off the main trunk road to Damascus. The Jordan Valley road skirted the southwestern part of Galilee and led down the Jordan Valley to Jericho.</p>
<p class="h3">East-West Roads</p>
<p class="fl">Several important roads ran east-west, intersecting the larger roads leading north. One such road led from Gaza to Beersheba and then down the Arabah, with an offshoot to Petra. Another led from Ashkelon, via Gath, to Hebron and on to En-gedi on the Dead Sea. Another road led from Joppa east up the valley of Aijalon (<a href="?bref=Josh.10.6-14">Jos 10:6-14</a>) to Bethel and on to Jericho. One well-used road led from Joppa to Shechem, across the Jordan at Adam (<a href="?bref=Josh.3.16">3:16</a>) and into Gilead in Transjordan. Other roads led from Acco eastward to Galilee and also up the coast to Tyre and Sidon. There were, indeed, numerous east-west roads that provided contact between various parts of Palestine. In Roman times, when the speedy movement of armies was essential, some of the old roads were greatly improved and new ones built.</p>
<p class="h3">Sea Lanes</p>
<p class="fl">The people of Israel, unlike the Phoenicians, seldom used the sea lanes. When Solomon planned to send ships down the Red Sea to Ophir (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.9.26-28">1 Kgs 9:26-28</a>), he used Phoenician seamen. Jehoshaphat planned a similar expedition, but his ships were wrecked (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.48-49">22:48-49</a>). Coastal traffic in OT times was in the hands of Philistines and Phoenicians. There were several ports along the Mediterranean Sea coast, such as Gaza, Joppa, Dor, and Acco, but none was very good. There were also sea lanes linking the Mediterranean coast with Egypt and distant Tarshish (probably Spain). The other coastal water was the Gulf of Aqaba with its two ports—Ezion-geber for Transjordan, and Elath for west of the Jordan. Solomon’s fleet used Ezion-geber as its home port.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientShipOfTheLargestSize"/>
<p>In NT times things changed considerably. The Middle East produced commodities used by peoples farther west, especially the Romans. Alexandria in Egypt and Antioch in Syria handled both cargo and travelers. Smaller ports like those in Palestine and many others around the coast of Asia Minor provided a haven for ships. One ingenious scheme to avoid a 200-mile (321.8-kilometer) journey around the Greek peninsula was to drag small boats across the five-mile- (8-kilometer-) wide isthmus at Corinth. Even the largest ship in NT times was in danger from wind and storm at sea (<a href="?bref=Acts.27.1-44">Acts 27</a>), so sea travel was undertaken preferably when the risk of storms was minimal, roughly from November to March. There was a lot of sea traffic in the Mediterranean Sea at appropriate seasons, largely for trade. Grain ships crossed regularly from Rome to Egypt and to the east.</p>
<p>Ships were driven by sail power supplemented as necessary by oars operated by slaves. Some indication of the size of ships comes from the discovery of ancient wrecks and from Latin and Greek literature. An old dry dock 130 feet (39.6 meters) long found near Athens was once used for Greek war vessels, which were smaller than the cargo vessels. The Roman writer Lucian refers to an Alexandrian grain ship 180 feet (54.9 meters) long, suggesting a capacity of about 1,200 tons (1,088.6 metric tons). Paul’s ship carried 276 persons (<a href="?bref=Acts.27.37">Acts 27:37</a>). Modern underwater archaeology is providing valuable information about these ancient ships.</p>
<p class="h3">Reasons for Travel</p>
<p class="fl">The most important reason for travel in NT times was for trade and commerce, which involved far more than merely transporting goods. There were agents, supervisors, insurers of cargo, bankers, and a whole range of people involved in the acquisition and safe delivery of the cargo.</p>
<p>Military travel was considerable. A wide variety of tasks had to be undertaken in the way of reconnaissance, procuring of supplies, forward arrangements for the bivouacking of troops, and the transport of both troops and equipment.</p>
<p>Some travelers were tradespeople changing their place of employment, like Aquila and Priscilla (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.2-3">Acts 18:2-3</a>). Aquila had traveled from Pontus on the Black Sea to Rome and then, in a time of persecution, he had fled to Corinth with his wife. Many others traveled for similar reasons.</p>
<p>People on religious pilgrimage traveled by land or sea. Jews from many lands journeyed to Jerusalem for the annual Passover festivities (cf. <a href="?bref=Acts.2.5-11">Acts 2:5-11</a>). Non-Jews went to religious centers at Ephesus, Athens, and Eleusis, where there were important temples. Many minor temples also attracted pilgrims. The construction of new temples and a variety of government administration buildings brought craftsmen from afar. Often the materials used in construction had to be transported to the site. Some people made trips for health reasons to temples famed for healing miracles or to enjoy the benefits of hot springs like those at Capernaum or Tiberias. Athletes traveled to centers for important contests like the Olympic games, and crowds of people flocked to witness the spectacle. Some travelers were students or teachers going to great centers of learning—the universities of those times. Yet others traveled as official emissaries bearing important government and commercial documents. Despite all this activity, vast numbers of ordinary citizens hardly ever traveled more than a few miles from their homes.</p>
  </body>
</item>