<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hades">
  <title>Hades*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HADES*</p>
<p class="fl">Abode of the dead. In Greek mythology Hades was originally the god of the underworld (also named Pluto), a brother of Zeus. He was the abductor of Persephone and thus the cause of winter. His realm, which was called by his name (and also called Tartarus), was the dark land where the dead existed. Odysseus entered that realm and fed the ghosts with blood to get directions back home (Homer’s <span class="ital">Odyssey</span> 4.834). Originally the Greeks thought of hades as simply the grave—a shadowy, ghostlike existence that happened to all who died, good and evil alike. Gradually they and the Romans came to see it as a place of reward and punishment, an elaborately organized and guarded realm where the good were rewarded in the Elysian Fields and the evil were punished (so described by the Roman poet Virgil, 70–19 <span class="era">BC</span>).</p>
<p>“Hades” became important to the Jews as the typical term used by the translators of the Septuagint to render the Hebrew name “Sheol” into Greek. This was a very suitable translation for the Hebrew term, for both words can signify the physical grave or death (<a href="?bref=Gen.37.35">Gn 37:35</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.5.5">Prv 5:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.7.27">7:27</a>), and both originally referred to a dark underworld (<a href="?bref=Job.10.21-22">Jb 10:21-22</a>) where existence was at best shadowy (<a href="?bref=Job.38.17">Jb 38:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.14.9">Is 14:9</a>). Sheol is described as under the ocean (<a href="?bref=Job.26.5-6">Jb 26:5-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jon.2.2-3">Jon 2:2-3</a>) and as having bars and gates (<a href="?bref=Job.17.16">Jb 17:16</a>). All people go there whether they are good or evil (<a href="?bref=Ps.89.48">Ps 89:48</a>). In the earlier literature there is no hope of release from Sheol/hades. C. S. Lewis describes this concept well in <span class="ital">The Silver Chair:</span> “Many sink down, and few return to the sunlit lands.” Of course, all these descriptions are in poetic literature; how literally the Hebrews (or the Greeks, for that matter) took their descriptions of hades/Sheol is hard to say. They may have simply used the older picture-language of Greek poetry to describe that for which prose words were inadequate.</p>
<p>Jew and Greek alike came in contact with Persia—the Jews at the time the postexilic writers were composing their books (e.g., Malachi, Daniel, and some psalms), and the Greeks somewhat later (they fought the Persians 520–479 <span class="era">BC</span> and conquered them 334–330 <span class="era">BC</span>). Whether because of Persian influence on these groups or not, during this period, the idea of reward and punishment after death developed, and Sheol/hades changed from a shadow land to a differentiated place of reward and punishment for both Greeks (and Romans) and Jews. Josephus records that the Pharisees believed in reward and punishment at death (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 18.1.3), and a similar idea appears in 1 Enoch 22. In these and many other cases in Jewish literature, hades stands for the one place of the dead, which has two or more compartments. In other Jewish literature, hades is the place of torment for the wicked, while the righteous enter paradise (Pss of Sol 14; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.2.1">Wisd of Sol 2:1</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.3.1">3:1</a>). Thus, by the beginning of the NT period, hades has three meanings: (1) death, (2) the place of all the dead, and (3) the place of the wicked dead only. Context determines which meaning an author intends in a given passage.</p>
<p>All these meanings appear in the NT. In <a href="?bref=Matt.11.23">Matthew 11:23</a> and <a href="?bref=Luke.10.15">Luke 10:15</a>, Jesus speaks of Capernaum’s descending to hades (<span class="sc">nlt</span> mg). Most likely he simply means that the city will “die” or be destroyed. “Hades” means “death” in this context, as “heaven” means “exaltation.” <a href="?bref=Rev.6.8">Revelation 6:8</a> also exemplifies this: Death comes on a horse, and hades (a symbol of death) comes close behind. This personification of hades probably comes from the OT, where hades/Sheol is viewed as a monster that devours people (<a href="?bref=Pr.1.12">Prv 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.27.20">27:20</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.30.16">30:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.14">Is 5:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.28.15,18">28:15, 18</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.2.5">Hb 2:5</a>).</p>
<p><a href="?bref=Matt.16.18">Matthew 16:18</a> is a more difficult use of hades. The church will be built upon a rock and the gates of hades will not prevail against it. Here the place of the dead (complete with gates and bars) is a symbol for death: Christians may in fact be killed, but death (the gates of hades) will no more hold them than it held Christ. He who burst out of hades will bring his people out as well. This is also the meaning of <a href="?bref=Acts.2.27">Acts 2:27</a> (quoting <a href="?bref=Ps.16.10">Ps 16:10</a>): Christ did not stay dead; his life did not remain in hades; unlike David, he rose from the dead. It is uncertain in either of these cases whether hades is simply a symbol for death or whether it means that Christ and the Christian actually went to a place of the dead called hades; probably the former is intended. Whatever the case, since Christ did rise, he has conquered death and hades. He appears in <a href="?bref=Rev.1.18">Revelation 1:18</a> as the one holding the keys (the control) to both.</p>
<p>Two NT passages refer to hades as the place where the dead exist: <a href="?bref=Rev.20.13-14">Revelation 20:13-14</a> and <a href="?bref=Luke.16.23">Luke 16:23</a>. In <a href="?bref=Rev.20.1-15">Revelation 20</a> hades is emptied of all who are in it (either all dead or the wicked dead, depending on one’s eschatology)—the resurrection is complete. When the wicked are judged and cast into the lake of fire (Gehenna), hades is also thrown in. <a href="?bref=Luke.16.23">Luke 16:23</a>, however, clearly refers to hades as the place of the wicked dead. There the rich man is tormented in a flame, while the poor man, Lazarus, goes to paradise (Abraham’s bosom).</p>
<p>Hades, then, means three things in the NT, as it did in Jewish literature: (1) Death and its power is the most frequent meaning, especially in metaphorical uses. (2) It also means the place of the dead in general, when a writer wants to lump all the dead together. (3) It means, finally, the place where the wicked dead are tormented before the final judgment. This is its narrowest meaning, occurring only once in the NT (<a href="?bref=Luke.16.23">Lk 16:23</a>). The Bible does not dwell on this torment—Dante’s picture in <span class="ital">The Inferno</span> draws on later speculation and Greco-Roman conceptions of hades more than on the Bible.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DeadPlaceofthe_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Dead, Place of the</a>; <a href="?item=Gehenna_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Gehenna</a>; <a href="?item=Hell_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hell</a>; <a href="?item=Sheol_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sheol</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>