<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HaggaiBookof">
  <title>Haggai, Book of</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HAGGAI, Book of</p>
<p class="fl">Tenth of the 12 short prophetic books at the end of the OT.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#AuthorandDate">Author and Date</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Purpose">Purpose</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Teaching">Teaching</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#Content">Content</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="AuthorandDate">Author and Date</p>
<p class="fl">Haggai was among the Jewish colonists at Jerusalem in the year 520 <span class="era">BC</span> when his prophetic words were recorded (<a href="?bref=Ezra.5.1-2">Ezr 5:1-2</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezra.6.14">6:14</a>). The four messages the Lord gave to Haggai were to be directed to specific individuals. The first was to Zerubbabel the governor and Joshua the high priest (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1">Hg 1:1</a>). The second was to Zerubbabel, Joshua, and the remnant of the people (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.2">2:2</a>). The third was a word to the priests (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.11">11</a>). The final message was limited to Zerubbabel (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.21">21</a>).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Purpose">Purpose</p>
<p class="fl">The key phrase of Haggai’s prophecies is “Consider your ways” or “Consider” (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.5,7">1:5, 7</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.15,18">2:15, 18</a>). The purpose of God’s messages to the Judean leadership and people, therefore, was to awaken them to their spiritual responsibilities. Two different classes of Judeans had to be turned from their indifference. The true believers needed to be reminded that God was merciful. The situation could be remedied, even though they thought the sins committed by their fathers were unforgivable. The hypocrites among the Judeans had only sought the promised blessings. They had only exchanged one form of idolatry for another. When the blessings did not materialize, they were disappointed.</p>
<p>The unifying message was that today gives no key to what God will do tomorrow. God’s fulfillment of his promises cannot be judged by appearances. Haggai’s message was twofold: reproof and encouragement. The colonists needed to be chastised for their indifference and consoled in the midst of their troubles.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Teaching">Teaching</p>
<p class="fl">Haggai is a practical book, dealing with the believer’s service to God. Procrastination and indifference have been debilitating sins among God’s people throughout all ages. Concern and a sense of urgency are always pleasing to God (<a href="?bref=Rom.13.11-14">Rom 13:11-14</a>).</p>
<p>The presence of God is the primary motivation for boldness and the means of banishing discouragement (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.19-20">Mt 28:19-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Eph.3.8-21">Eph 3:8-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.13.5-6">Heb 13:5-6</a>).</p>
<p>Separation from contaminating influences and sin is demanded of all believers (<a href="?bref=2Cor.6.14-7.1">2 Cor 6:14–7:1</a>). Without this quality of life, the believer cannot expect to be found fit for God’s service (<a href="?bref=2Tim.2.19-26">2 Tm 2:19-26</a>). The disobedient child of God can expect removal of blessing and chastisement from God (<a href="?bref=Heb.12.3-13">Heb 12:3-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Jas.4.1-3">Jas 4:1-3</a>).</p>
<p>The message concerning God’s judgment of sin and the establishment of the messianic kingdom is a message of hope to the NT believer as well as the Jews of Haggai’s day (<a href="?bref=Rom.15.4-13">Rom 15:4-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.3.10-18">2 Pt 3:10-18</a>).</p>
<p>The key phrase of Haggai (“consider your ways”) has echoes in <a href="?bref=1Cor.11.28">1 Corinthians 11:28</a> and <a href="?bref=2Cor.13.5">2 Corinthians 13:5</a>, as do his writings about the effects of sin and the blessings of God (<a href="?bref=Jude.1.1-25">Jude 1:1-25</a>).</p>
<p>The God of Haggai is given the title “Lord of hosts” (“<span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Almighty”) 14 times in the book. This title is characteristic of the postexilic prophetic books, Haggai, Zechariah, and Malachi, where it is found more than 80 times. It teaches that God is all-powerful and is Master of all spirit beings in heaven and all created beings on the earth.</p>
<p>Haggai also testifies to the God-breathed quality of the Word of God and its divine authority. Over and over the prophet announces ways that God has spoken to him and is the author of these messages (at least 25 times in the space of 28 verses).</p>
<p class="h2" id="Content">Content</p>
<p class="h3">First Message</p>
<p class="fl">The first message Haggai was to deliver to the Judeans was given to him “on the first day of the month” (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1">Hg 1:1</a>). Upon the first day of each month, the Jews were to bring special offerings to the sanctuary (<a href="?bref=Num.28.11-15">Nm 28:11-15</a>). God chose this special time to reveal the sin of the people with regard to the unfinished sanctuary.</p>
<p>The leaders of the Judeans were singled out for the first message from the Lord (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1">Hg 1:1</a>). Zerubbabel was the civil leader or governor, and Joshua was the spiritual leader or high priest. Together, they were responsible for the activity (or inactivity) of God’s people.</p>
<p>The word of the Lord revealed the procrastination of the people (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.2">1:2</a>). God’s temple had not been completed because his people had determined for themselves that “the time is not come.” The energies and finances of God’s people had been channeled selfishly into their own homes (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.4">4</a>).</p>
<p>“Now” (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.5">1:5</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) focused the attention of the Jews upon the present requirement of God in the light of their sinful indifference. They were to give attention to their own condition spiritually and materially: “Consider how you have fared.” This key phrase of Haggai’s prophecies is literally “Set your heart on your ways” or “Lay your ways to your heart.” Self-examination would reveal that their procrastination had robbed them of more than just 16 years.</p>
<p>Verse <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.6">6</a> reveals the poverty in which the Jews were living as a result of God’s chastisement for their sin. The blessings of God had been withdrawn in accord with his covenant (see <a href="?bref=Deut.28.15-29.1">Dt 28:15–29:1</a>).</p>
<p>Following another exhortation to “consider” their ways (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.7">Hg 1:7</a>), the Lord revealed the remedy for the Jews’ cursed condition: “rebuild my house” (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.8">8</a>). The disobedience with regard to the completion of the temple was the reason for their poverty (vv <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.9-11">9-11</a>).</p>
<p>The response of the leaders and the people was encouraging. The resumption of the construction of the temple was a definite manifestation of belief in the word of God (<a href="?bref=Hagg.1.12">1:12</a>). Immediate obedience also testified to the acceptance of the ministry of Haggai, who was “the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>’s messenger” delivering “the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>’s message” (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.13">13</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Second Message</p>
<p class="fl">Approximately one month later Haggai was summoned again by the Lord (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.1">2:1</a>). The second message continued the note of encouragement with which the first message closed. Perhaps the builders had begun to feel the pressures of their service. Perhaps the old doubts and discouragements had plagued their faith again. The adversaries had reappeared to hinder them (<a href="?bref=Ezra.5.3-6.12">Ezr 5:3–6:12</a>). Haggai’s second message was similar to Ezra’s claim that “the eye of their God was upon the elders of the Jews” (<a href="?bref=Ezra.5.5">Ezr 5:5</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The Lord not only sees his servants’ needs but also sends relief and encouragement.</p>
<p>The day of this second message was the last day of the Feast of Tabernacles (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.33-43">Lv 23:33-43</a>). Perhaps this reminder of God’s glorious presence with their ancestors in the wilderness made their present situation all the more discouraging. Therefore, the Lord spoke to all the people rather than just to their leaders (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.2">Hg 2:2</a>). Was there any survivor of the preexilic days who had personally beheld the glory of God as it resided in the Solomonic temple (cf. <a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.1-11">1 Kgs 8:1-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.9.1-11.23">Ez 9:1–11:23</a>)? Was the present temple “as nothing” in comparison (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.3">Hg 2:3</a>)? The Babylonian Talmud listed five things that were absent in the new temple that had been present in the Solomonic temple: (1) the ark of the covenant, (2) the sacred fire, (3) the shekinah glory, (4) the Holy Spirit, and (5) the Urim and Thummim.</p>
<p>Again, “now” calls attention to God’s remedy. Three times the command “take courage” is proclaimed (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.4">2:4</a>). Each time the command is given, one of the recipients of God’s message is addressed (cf. v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.2">2</a>). The concluding command was “work.” The reason for the strength and the activity was God’s presence. The Holy Spirit might seem to be absent from the temple, but he would remain among the people “according to the word” of God (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.5">5</a>).</p>
<p>To encourage the workers further, God revealed the future glory of his house (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.6-9">2:6-9</a>). That glory would come to pass after a time of judgment (vv <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.6-7">6-7a</a>), when the treasures of all nations come in (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.7">7b</a>). The exact meaning of this verse has been variously interpreted. The views center around two different translations: “the desire of all nations shall come” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>) and “and the treasures of all the nations will come to this Temple” (<span class="sc">nlt</span>).</p>
<p>The arguments for the messianic interpretation based on the first translation may be summarized as follows: (1) The vast majority of both Christian and Jewish interpreters took this phrase as a reference to the Messiah. (2) The abstract noun “desire” may have the concrete concept of the one who is desirable. (3) Though the verb in the Hebrew is plural, it is grammatically possible for the agreement of subject and predicate to be based upon the second noun (“nations”) in a genitive relationship. (4) The time element is suitable since God has just judged the nations and the hour of Christ’s coming would be at hand. (5) An alternate translation is available that meets the grammatical difficulties but retains the messianic import: “They [the nations] have come to the desire of all the nations.”</p>
<p>In spite of the weight of the arguments for this first view, it seems better to accept the second translation and corresponding view. The arguments are as follows: (1) The vast majority of early Christian and Jewish interpreters base their view on the Latin Vulgate translation (c. <span class="era">AD</span> 400), while the second translation is in agreement with an older version, the Greek Septuagint (c. 300 <span class="era">BC</span>). (2) The singular “desire” may be taken as a collective noun referring to “features” or “wealth.” (3) The principle of Hebrew grammar that allows the noun “nations” to be the one with which the verb agrees is a rare occurrence in poetic books for such constructions as this. It is unlikely that such phraseology would be used without Haggai’s declaring the exact meaning in the immediate context. (4) The immediate context does solve the difficulty by the plain declaration that the silver and the gold belong to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.8">2:8</a>). (5) The kingdom context of these verses accords well with such parallel passages as <a href="?bref=Isa.60.5,11">Isaiah 60:5, 11</a> and <a href="?bref=Rev.21.24">Revelation 21:24</a>.</p>
<p>The conclusion to this message of encouragement is that the future glory of the temple (cf. <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.3">Hg 2:3</a>) will be greater than in the days of the Solomonic temple (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.9">9</a>), because the shekinah glory will return (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.7">Hg 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.43.1-5">Ez 43:1-5</a>) and the building will have great beauty (cf. <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.8">Hg 2:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.60.13,17">Is 60:13, 17</a>). God will also grant peace (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.9">Hg 2:9</a>) in his kingdom at the time of this future glorious temple (see <a href="?bref=Isa.9.6-7">Is 9:6-7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.66.12">66:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.6.13">Zec 6:13</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Third Message</p>
<p class="fl">About two months later Haggai received a third message from God (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.10">Hg 2:10</a>). This time exhortation would be the theme, and the message was directed to the priests alone (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.11">11</a>). Haggai used questions concerning the law of Moses to instruct the priests in the polluting character of sin. Something clean or holy cannot transfer its sanctity to something else (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.12">12</a>). But that which is unholy <span class="ital">can</span> transfer <span class="ital">its</span> character to something clean, defiling it (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.13">Hg 2:13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Lev.22.4-6">Lv 22:4-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.19.11">Nm 19:11</a>).</p>
<p>The application of this principle to the Judeans was clear: the offerings they brought during their years of disobedience were unacceptable to God because of Judah’s uncleanness (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.14">Hg 2:14</a>).</p>
<p>By reviving the memory of past disobedience and chastisement, God was exhorting the Jews to constantly “consider” (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.15,18">2:15, 18</a>) the consequences of disobedience. Such consideration should prevent future spiritual indifference. The conclusion of the message was a reminder of the blessing of God upon the obedient (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.19">19</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Fourth Message</p>
<p class="fl">On the same day Haggai received another message from God (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.20">2:20</a>). This message was to be directed toward Zerubbabel (v <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.21">21</a>), who was to be encouraged by the permanency of his inherited Davidic office (cf. <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.1">Hg 1:1</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.7.4-17">2 Sm 7:4-17</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.3.1,5,10,17-20">1 Chr 3:1, 5, 10, 17-20</a>). The gentile nations would be judged and the kingdoms of the world overthrown (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.6-7,21-22">Hg 2:6-7, 21-22</a>). This would be but the preparation for God’s rule (cf. <a href="?bref=Rev.11.15-18">Rv 11:15-18</a>).</p>
<p>The promise to Zerubbabel in <a href="?bref=Hagg.2.23">Haggai 2:23</a> was God’s means of confirming that his promises to David were still operative even after the 70-year Babylonian captivity and the 16-year stagnation among the Judeans who had returned to Jerusalem. Zerubbabel was appointed “as a signet ring” by God. A signet was a personal cylinder or ring seal and a sign of the authenticity of their signature. Kings used them for identifying their decrees (<a href="?bref=Esth.3.10">Est 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.8.8-10">8:8-10</a>) and for confirming the authority of their deputies (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.42">Gn 41:42</a>). God’s appointment of Zerubbabel “as a signet ring,” therefore, meant that Zerubbabel would be God’s seal of authority on the continuation of the Davidic line from which the Messiah should come and reign (cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.1.12">Mt 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.27">Lk 3:27</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=HaggaiPerson_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Haggai (Person)</a>; <a href="?item=IsraelHistoryof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Israel, History of</a>; <a href="?item=PostexilicPeriod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Postexilic Period</a>; <a href="?item=Prophecy_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophecy</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetProphetess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophet, Prophetess</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>