<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hallelujah">
  <title>Hallelujah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HALLELUJAH</p>
<p class="fl">Important Christian acclamation used extensively in the church’s worship and liturgy from early times. “Hallelujah” is a transliteration into Greek, and thence into English, of two Hebrew words that mean “Praise the Lord.” This combination of the two Hebrew words forms the characteristic call to praise. Jews living in the Dispersion in pre-Christian times were already using the transliteration in their synagogue worship. “Hallelujah,” according to ancient Hebrew tradition, is to be written as one word, except in <a href="?bref=Ps.135.3">Psalm 135:3</a>. It occurs nowhere in the OT but in the Psalter, where it occurs 23 times, and for the first time in <a href="?bref=Ps.104.35">Psalm 104:35</a>. Each of <a href="?bref=Ps.111.1-10">Psalms 111</a> to 113 begins with “Hallelujah”; each of <a href="?bref=Ps.115.1-18">Psalms 115</a> to 117 ends with the word; and each of <a href="?bref=Ps.146.1-10">Psalms 146</a> to 150 begins and ends with it.</p>
<p>In the Septuagint version of <a href="?bref=Ps.113.1-118.29">Psalms 113–118</a>, all the individual psalms are headed “Allelujah.” Through the Vulgate, this form of the word “Hallelujah” has come into use in the church. Like another famous Hebrew liturgical term, “Amen,” “Hallelujah” has passed from the OT to the NT, and thence to the Christian church. But in the <span class="sc">kjv</span> and <span class="sc">erv</span> the phrase is rendered “Praise ye the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,” and similarly, in the <span class="sc">rsv</span> and <span class="sc">nlt</span>, it is rendered “Praise the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.”</p>
<p>In Hebrew liturgical usage the Hallel, or Hymn of Praise, <a href="?bref=Ps.113.1-118.29">Psalms 113–118</a>, is sung at the three great religious festivals of Passover, Pentecost, and Tabernacles. At the domestic celebration of Passover, <a href="?bref=Ps.113.1-9">Psalms 113</a> and <a href="?bref=Ps.114.1-8">114</a> are sung before the meal and <a href="?bref=Ps.115.1-118.29">Psalms 115–118</a> are sung after it. <a href="?bref=Matt.26.30">Matthew 26:30</a> and <a href="?bref=Mark.14.26">Mark 14:26</a> refer to the singing of <a href="?bref=Ps.115.1-118.29">115–118</a> as the “hymn” sung by the Lord and his disciples after their celebration of the Passover and before they left the upper room.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="CalligraphyByTimothyRBotts"/>
<p>“Hallelujah” does not appear anywhere in the NT except in <a href="?bref=Rev.19.1-6">Revelation 19:1-6</a>. There it is a chant of the saints in heaven. It was taken over into the liturgy and hymnody of the church at an early date. It became the characteristic expression of joy and was therefore sung especially at Eastertide, as is witnessed by Augustine. The choice by the Christian church of <a href="?bref=Ps.113.1-9">Psalms 113</a>, <a href="?bref=Ps.114.1-8">114</a>, and <a href="?bref=Ps.118.1-29">118</a> from the Hebrew Hallel as the psalms to be sung on Easter day marks the liturgical connection of Easter with Passover.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Hallel_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hallel</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>