<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hamath">
  <title>Hamath</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HAMATH</p>
<p class="list">1. City and district located about 125 miles (201 kilometers) north of Damascus (Syria), on the Orontes River. The early residents apparently were of the Hamitic race from the descendants of Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.18">Gn 10:18</a>), but later inhabitants were Semitic. It was to be the northern boundary of the nation of Israel, described as the “entrance of Hamath” (<a href="?bref=Num.34.7-8">Nm 34:7-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.13.5">Jos 13:5</a>; Hebrew, <span class="hebrew">Lebo Hamath</span>), but actually it was such only in the early monarchy and under Jeroboam II (793–753 <span class="era">BC</span>). The location is uncertain but was between the Lebanon and Anti-Lebanon Mountains. Some scholars have thought of it as an actual place-name, Lebo-hamath, and have identified it with modern Lebweh on the Orontes. Others have located it elsewhere in Syria.</p>
<p class="list-text">Hamath was established during the Neolithic period and destroyed about 1750 <span class="era">BC</span>, perhaps by the Hyksos. It was later rebuilt and conquered by Thutmose III (1502–1448 <span class="era">BC</span>), and while Egypt controlled Syria, Hamath prospered. Several Hittite inscriptions have been discovered that disclose that Hamath had become the capital of a small Hittite kingdom prior to 900 <span class="era">BC</span>.</p>
<p class="list-text">When David fought Hadadezer, king of Zobah, and defeated him, then Toi, king of Hamath, sent his son to congratulate David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.9-10">2 Sm 8:9-10</a>). Since Solomon built store-cities in the region of Hamath (<a href="?bref=2Chr.8.4">2 Chr 8:4</a>), it has been suggested that Hamath had become a tributary kingdom to Israel. During the reign of Ahab of Israel, the Assyrian royal inscriptions state that Irhulini, king of Hamath, allied with Damascus, Israel, and the 12 kings of the coast to resist the advances of Shalmaneser III (860–825 <span class="era">BC</span>). The league halted Shalmaneser, although he continued to harass Syria, and about 846 <span class="era">BC</span> he conquered the Syrian league, when Hamath became subject to Assyria. In 730 <span class="era">BC</span> Eni-Ilus, then king of Hamath, paid tribute to Tiglath-pileser III. About 720 <span class="era">BC</span> Sargon II colonized Hamath with 4,300 Assyrians and moved many people from different areas of his kingdom, including Hamath, to Samaria (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.24">2 Kgs 17:24</a>). Israelites also were apparently colonized in Hamath (<a href="?bref=Isa.11.11">Is 11:11</a>). Other OT references to the Assyrian conquest of Hamath include <a href="?bref=2Kgs.18.34">2 Kings 18:34</a>, <a href="?bref=2Kgs.19.13">19:13</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.10.9">Isaiah 10:9</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.36.19">36:19</a>, <a href="?bref=Isa.37.13">37:13</a>, and <a href="?bref=Amos.6.2">Amos 6:2</a>. Later the city seems to have been subject to Damascus (<a href="?bref=Jer.49.23">Jer 49:23</a>). Some of the prophets predicted that Israel would eventually extend its boundaries once again to Hamath (<a href="?bref=Ezek.47.16-17">Ez 47:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.48.1">48:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Zech.9.2">Zec 9:2</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">During the Maccabean period, Jonathan Maccabeus and his army met the army of Demetrius at Hamath (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Macc.12.25">1 Macc 12:25</a>). According to Josephus, Antiochus Epiphanes changed its name to Epiphania (<span class="ital">Antiquities</span> 1.4.2), the name by which it was known to the Greeks and Romans.</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=HamathEntranceof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hamath, Entrance of</a>.</p>
<p class="list">2. Hamath-zobah is mentioned in <a href="?bref=2Chr.8.3">2 Chronicles 8:3</a> as a town conquered by Solomon. Some have suggested that it was the same city as the Hamath above, while others suggest that it was a different town in the district of Zobah.</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=HamathZobah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hamath-zobah</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>