<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HamPerson">
  <title>Ham (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HAM (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Second son of Noah (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.32">Gn 5:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.6.10">6:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.7.13">7:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.9.18,22">9:18, 22</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.10.1,6,20">10:1, 6, 20</a>). Ham had four sons whose names were Cush, Mizraim (Hebrew for Egypt), Put, and Canaan (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.6">Gn 10:6</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.1.8">1 Chr 1:8</a>). Ham, then, is seen as the ancestor of the Egyptians (though a mixed race apparently occurs later), as well as of peoples in Africa, Arabia, and Canaan.</p>
<p>After the Flood, Noah began cultivating vineyards, and on one occasion exposed himself while drunk (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.20-24">Gn 9:20-24</a>). Ham saw his father lying naked and related the incident to Shem and Japheth, who covered Noah up discreetly. When Noah awoke and learned what “his youngest son” (seen by some as Ham) had done, he cursed Ham’s son Canaan, saying his brothers (Cush, Mizraim, and Put) and Shem and Japheth would rule over him. But if Ham is the one referred to in <a href="?bref=Gen.9.24">9:24</a> as offending Noah, why should the curse fall on his son Canaan? The most likely answer is that Ham is not being referred to in verse <a href="?bref=Gen.9.24">24</a>. The expression is “his youngest son” (the “younger” of the <span class="sc">kjv</span> is hardly possible in Hebrew), whereas Ham is repeatedly seen as the second of the brothers, not the youngest (<a href="?bref=Gen.5.32">5:32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.6.10">6:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.7.13">7:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.9.18">9:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.10.1">10:1</a>), the explicit order of the sons indicating age. Instead, “his youngest son” refers to Canaan, and to some base deed not being recorded, on whom the curse falls. “Son” used for “grandson” is common Semitic material, and it seems to have been used here in this way since Canaan is the “youngest” of the (grand)sons. The curse, then, as the text clearly says, is on Canaan rather than Ham. Canaan (and his posterity) is to be subjugated by Japheth and Shem with the Canaanites, finally disappearing by NT times.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Nations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Nations</a>; <a href="?item=Noah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Noah #1</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>