<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hananiah">
  <title>Hananiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HANANIAH</p>
<p class="list"> 1. Zerubbabel’s son and a descendant of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.3.19,21">1 Chr 3:19, 21</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Benjamite and the son of Shashak (<a href="?bref=1Chr.8.24">1 Chr 8:24</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Heman’s son and the leader of the 16th of 24 divisions of musicians trained for service in the house of the Lord (<a href="?bref=1Chr.25.4,23">1 Chr 25:4, 23</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. One of the commanders of King Uzziah’s army (<a href="?bref=2Chr.26.11">2 Chr 26:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Bebai’s son, who returned with the exiles from Babylon and was later encouraged by Ezra to divorce his foreign wife (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.28">Ezr 10:28</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Perfumer who helped Nehemiah rebuild the Jerusalem wall (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.8">Neh 3:8</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Shelemiah’s son, who with Hanun repaired a section of the Jerusalem wall during the days of Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.30">Neh 3:30</a>). He is perhaps identical with #6 above.</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Commander of the citadel of Jerusalem who was assigned by Nehemiah to rule the city jointly with Hanani, Nehemiah’s brother. Hananiah, described as a faithful and God-fearing man, was appointed the task of seeing that the city walls and gates were regularly guarded (<a href="?bref=Neh.7.2-3">Neh 7:2-3</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 9. One of the leaders of the people who set his seal on the covenant of Ezra (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.23">Neh 10:23</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Head of the priestly family of Jeremiah during the days of Joiakim, the high priest, in postexilic Jerusalem (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.12">Neh 12:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. One of the priests who blew a trumpet at the dedication of the Jerusalem wall during the days of Nehemiah (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.41">Neh 12:41</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. Gibeonite and the son of Azzur. Hananiah prophesied during the fourth year of King Zedekiah of Judah’s reign (597–586 <span class="era">BC</span>). He openly declared in the temple that in two years the Lord would break the yoke of Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon (605–562 <span class="era">BC</span>), from the neck of Judah and return its exiles and sacred possessions to Palestine. Told by the Lord that Hananiah’s prophecy was false, Jeremiah reproached Hananiah for lying and foretold his imminent death. Hananiah died two months later (<a href="?bref=Jer.28.1-17">Jer 28</a>).</p>
<p class="list">13. Father of Zedekiah, an official of King Jehoiakim of Judah (609–598 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=Jer.36.12">Jer 36:12</a>).</p>
<p class="list">14. Grandfather of Irijah, the captain of the guards, who arrested Jeremiah at Jerusalem’s Gate of Benjamin for apparently deserting to the Babylonians (<a href="?bref=Jer.37.13">Jer 37:13</a>).</p>
<p class="list">15. One of the three Jewish friends of Daniel exiled in Babylon. He was assigned the Babylonian name Shadrach (<a href="?bref=Dan.1.6-19">Dn 1:6-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Dan.2.17">2:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text"><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=ShadrachMeshachandAbednego_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>