<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HardnessofHeart">
  <title>Hardness of Heart*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HARDNESS OF HEART*</p>
<p class="fl">A phrase signifying spiritual obstinacy.</p>
<p>The first references to the hardening of the heart exemplify the fundamental features of this doctrine in Scripture. The number of times it is referred to is surprising; there are at least 20 references to the hardening of Pharaoh’s heart in the OT alone, as well as Paul’s exposition of its significance in <a href="?bref=Rom.9.17-24">Romans 9:17-24</a>.</p>
<p>The first reference is <a href="?bref=Exod.4.21">Exodus 4:21</a>, where God promises Moses that he will harden Pharaoh’s heart that he might not allow the Israelites to go. This promise is repeated (see <a href="?bref=Exod.7.3">Ex 7:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.14.4,17">14:4, 17</a>) and rapidly comes to pass (<a href="?bref=Exod.7.13-14">7:13-14</a>), as revelation and miracle follow one another before the eyes of Pharaoh, followed by the actual occurrence of the events God warned about, including all the judgments of the 10 plagues.</p>
<p>No doubt is left in the mind of the reader, either in the exodus account itself or later, that Pharaoh’s obstinacy was an act of divine judgment on God’s part for his own external ends and purposes (<a href="?bref=Exod.9.16">Ex 9:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.11.20">Jos 11:20</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.9.17-18">Rom 9:17-18</a>). Nevertheless, it is also stated that Pharaoh hardened his own heart (<a href="?bref=Exod.8.15,32">Ex 8:15, 32</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.9.34">9:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.13.15">13:15</a>), showing that the hardening process is a deliberate product of personal rebellion against revealed truth. This is a crucial aspect of the scriptural presentation of the matter; judicial hardening of the heart is not only an act of God upon the sinner’s nature but also a willful turning from the truth. The sinner is therefore responsible to God for his hardness of heart.</p>
<p>The process of judicial hardening is described by Paul in <a href="?bref=Rom.1.18-32">Romans 1:18-32</a>. All humans have an innate God-consciousness from which they deliberately turn away. They change the truth into a lie and suppress what truth they have. As a result, hardness of heart takes over. Paul’s expression for this is that “their foolish heart was darkened” because “God gave them up” to the results of their own sin. The results are both intellectual (“God gave them over to a reprobate mind”) and moral, as well as social or cultural. Paul uses the term “hardness of heart” in <a href="?bref=Rom.2.5">Romans 2:5</a> to describe the general result. It is important to note that it is not against God’s wrath or against the results of sin that the wicked are in revolt but against “truth” and against their own conscience (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.14-16">2:14-16</a>).</p>
<p>God often warns his people not to harden their hearts, for Scripture associates hardening with unbelief (<a href="?bref=Deut.15.7">Dt 15:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.3.8,15">Heb 3:8, 15</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.7">4:7</a>). Jesus was grieved at the callousness of his hearers’ hearts (<a href="?bref=Mark.3.5">Mk 3:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.16.14">16:14</a>). He referred to allowances God had made to the Jews concerning divorce because of the hardness of their hearts (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.8">Mt 19:8</a>).</p>
<p>On at least two occasions in the Gospels, judicial blindness is ascribed directly to God, and its purpose stated (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.13-15">Mt 13:13-15</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.39-41">Jn 12:39-41</a>). Hardness of heart is therefore an aspect of the development of the fallen character, manifesting the root of rebellion (<a href="?bref=Ps.95.8">Ps 95:8</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.40">Jn 12:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.3.8,15">Heb 3:8, 15</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.4.7">4:7</a>). Throughout Scripture, Jewish apostasy is so described (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.17.14">2 Kgs 17:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.9.16-17">Neh 9:16-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.3.8">Heb 3:8</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Blindness_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Blindness</a>; <a href="?item=Judgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judgment</a>; <a href="?item=Regeneration_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Regeneration</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>