<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hashabiah">
  <title>Hashabiah</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HASHABIAH</p>
<p class="list"> 1. Ancestor of Ethan, a Levite and descendant of Merari. Ethan was a musician in the temple during the reign of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.6.45">1 Chr 6:45</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 2. Ancestor of a group of Levites who helped rebuild the temple after the Babylonian exile (<a href="?bref=1Chr.9.14">1 Chr 9:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.11.15">Neh 11:15</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 3. Jeduthun’s son, a Levite and musician in the temple during the time of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.25.3,19">1 Chr 25:3, 19</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 4. Head of a group of Hebronites who was given the position of overseer of Israel west of the Jordan. He was in charge of both political and religious activities (<a href="?bref=1Chr.26.30">1 Chr 26:30</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 5. Kemuel’s son, a Levite and head of a household during the reign of David (<a href="?bref=1Chr.27.17">1 Chr 27:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 6. Chief of the Levites who participated in the Passover kept by King Josiah in the kingdom of Judah (640–609 <span class="era">BC</span>; <a href="?bref=2Chr.35.9">2 Chr 35:9</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 7. Merarite Levite who returned to Jerusalem from Babylon with Ezra (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.19">Ezr 8:19</a>).</p>
<p class="list"> 8. Priest who returned to Jerusalem from Babylon with Ezra (<a href="?bref=Ezra.8.24">Ezr 8:24</a>); perhaps the same person as #7 above.</p>
<p class="list"> 9. Parosh’s son, who obeyed Ezra’s exhortation to divorce his pagan wife after the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezra.10.25">Ezr 10:25</a>); possibly the same as Asibias (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=1Esd.9.26">1 Esd 9:26</a>).</p>
<p class="list">10. Ruler over half the district of Keilah (a city of Judah in the Shephelah district of Libnah-mareshah) who participated in rebuilding the Jerusalem wall for his district after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.17">Neh 3:17</a>).</p>
<p class="list">11. Levite who signed Ezra’s covenant of faithfulness to God (<a href="?bref=Neh.10.11">Neh 10:11</a>).</p>
<p class="list">12. Ancestor of Uzzi, an overseer of Levites in Jerusalem after the exile (<a href="?bref=Neh.11.22">Neh 11:22</a>).</p>
<p class="list">13. Priest and head of a household in Palestine after the exile during the time of the high priest Joiakim (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.21">Neh 12:21</a>).</p>
<p class="list">14. Chief of the Levites and a temple musician after the exile during the time of Joiakim the high priest (<a href="?bref=Neh.12.24">Neh 12:24</a>); perhaps the same person as #11 above.</p>
  </body>
</item>