<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="HebronPlace">
  <title>Hebron (Place)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HEBRON (P<span class="lc">lace</span>)</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="HebronBurialSiteForThePatriarchs"/>
<p class="list">1. City of antiquity still standing today. It was built on the southern end of the highlands that run north to south through the length of Palestine. In patriarchal times it was known as Kiriath-arba (<a href="?bref=Gen.23.2">Gn 23:2</a>) and stood on the hill known as El Arbain. The modern city straddles both ridges of the mountain range.</p>
<p class="list-text">Hebron is situated 25 miles (40 kilometers) southwest of Jerusalem and less than two miles (3.2 kilometers) from Mamre, where Abraham spent much of his life. It is 3,000 feet (914 meters) above sea level and marks the southern end of the Judean highlands. From this elevation the land slopes down rapidly to the east, but gradually to the west and south. The soil is relatively fertile, and a variety of fruits (apples, plums, figs, pomegranates, apricots), nuts, and vegetables are grown easily. To the south is the Negev, where the grazing land is excellent. A large number of springs and wells dot the landscape and assure residents of an abundance of water.</p>
<p class="list-text">In OT times Hebron included Mamre, the place where Abraham built an altar to the Lord after parting from Lot (<a href="?bref=Gen.13.18">Gn 13:18</a>). It was here, too, that he learned of the capture of his nephew Lot (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.12-16">14:12-16</a>); and here that, years later, he entertained three angels and was told of the judgment soon to fall on Sodom and Gomorrah (ch <a href="?bref=Gen.18.1-33">18</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">Sarah died in Hebron, and Abraham purchased the cave of Machpelah from Ephron the Hittite (<a href="?bref=Gen.23.8-9,17">Gn 23:8-9, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.25.9-10">25:9-10</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.49.29-32">49:29-32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.50.12-13">50:12-13</a>) in which to bury her. This cave is now within the walls of the modern city, and the famous mosque of Haram el-Khalil was built over it.</p>
<p class="list-text">At the time of the exodus of the Israelites from Egypt, spies were sent into the land. They began in the south and traversed the central highlands of Palestine from Kadesh-barnea through Hebron to Rehob (<a href="?bref=Num.13.17-21">Nm 13:17-21</a>). On their return they brought back evidence of the productivity of the land (vv <a href="?bref=Num.13.23-24">23-24</a>). From <a href="?bref=Num.13.33">Numbers 13:33</a> we know that giants (“sons of Anak”) lived in Hebron. The sight of these men filled ten of the spies with fear. Only Caleb and Joshua proved equal to the occasion. Because of their faith, they were promised a possession in the land, and Caleb was given Hebron (<a href="?bref=Josh.14.9,13">Jos 14:9, 13</a>). The unfaithful spies died in a plague in the presence of the Lord (<a href="?bref=Num.14.36-37">Nm 14:36-37</a>).</p>
<p class="list-text">During the period of the judges, Hebron is mentioned in connection with Samson. When trapped inside the city of Gaza, he carried off the gates and left them at Hebron (<a href="?bref=Judg.16.3">Jgs 16:3</a>). Following the death of Saul, the first king of Israel, David was crowned king of the tribes of Judah and Benjamin in Hebron (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.1">2 Sm 2:1</a>). He made this city his capital, for it was more centrally located than Benjamin, and its position at the southern end of the mountain range removed it as far as possible from the 10 northern tribes that followed Ishbosheth, the son of Saul. It was far enough from the Philistines to the west and the Amalekites to the south to avoid notice, and it was also easily defensible. Hebron also lay at the junction of several important trade routes, and this ensured its prominence. Later, however, when David was made king over all Israel, he moved his capital to Jerusalem—an act that must have displeased the people of Hebron.</p>
<p class="list-text">When Absalom wished to obtain support for his claim to the throne, he initiated his revolt from Hebron (<a href="?bref=2Sam.15.7-12">2 Sm 15:7-12</a>). Following the death of Solomon, David’s son, the kingdom was divided. Rehoboam, fearing an attack by the Egyptians on his southern border, fortified Hebron (<a href="?bref=2Chr.11.1-12">2 Chr 11:1-12</a>). From this time onward the city disappears from the OT record.</p>
<p class="list">2. KJV translation of the town of Ebron, in <a href="?bref=Josh.19.28">Joshua 19:28</a>. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Ebron_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ebron</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>