<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Herodias">
  <title>Herodias</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HERODIAS</p>
<p class="fl">Daughter of Aristobulus, the son of Herod the Great, and Berenice. Born between 9 and 7 <span class="era">BC</span>, her older brother was Herod Agrippa I. In 6 <span class="era">BC</span>, while still in her infancy, she was betrothed by her grandfather, Herod the Great, to his son by Mariamne II named Herod Philip. Herodias was the mother of Salome, born between <span class="era">AD</span> 15 and 19.</p>
<p>Herodias and Herod Philip lived on the seacoast of Judea, possibly at Azotus or Caesarea. In <span class="era">AD</span> 29 Herod Antipas visited Herodias’s (his niece) residence on his way to Rome. They were attracted to each other and Herodias agreed to marry him provided he would divorce his present wife, the daughter of Aretas IV, the Nebatean king of Petra. Herodias, being a Hasmonean, did not want to share the house with an Arab—longtime foes of the Hasmonean dynasty. When Aretas’s daughter got word of this plot, she secretly escaped to her father, and Herodias and Antipas were married. This incident was the beginning of hostilities between Antipas and Aretas, which eventually led to Aretas’s war against and defeat of Antipas in <span class="era">AD</span> 36.</p>
<p>John the Baptist openly denounced this marriage (<a href="?bref=Matt.14.3-12">Mt 14:3-12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.6.17-29">Mk 6:17-29</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.3.19-20">Lk 3:19-20</a>) because Jewish law forbade marriage with one’s brother’s wife (<a href="?bref=Lev.18.16">Lv 18:16</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.20.21">20:21</a>), except in order to raise children for a deceased childless brother by a levirate marriage (<a href="?bref=Deut.25.5">Dt 25:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.19">Mk 12:19</a>). In this case the brother, Herod Philip, was still alive and had a child, Salome. The bold denunciation by John the Baptist led to Antipas’s imprisoning him around <span class="era">AD</span> 30 or 31. Herodias wanted more than this. She arranged, possibly at Herod Antipas’s birthday, to have her daughter dance before him and his magistrates. In appreciation, Herod Antipas promised Salome up to half of his kingdom. At her mother’s bidding, she asked for John the Baptist’s head on a platter.</p>
<p>Herodias last appears in history involved in an intrigue between her brother, Agrippa I, who had been designated king by the emperor Caligula, and her husband Antipas, who had long wanted such a title. Antipas, at his wife’s insistence, went to Rome to plead his case, but he lost and was banished. Herodias, however, did remain faithful and followed him into exile, even though Caligula would not have punished her because she was Agrippa’s sister.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=HerodHerodianFamily_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Herod, Herodian Family</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>