<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Hospitality">
  <title>Hospitality</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">HOSPITALITY</p>
<p class="fl">Biblical concept often used with the terms “guest,” “stranger,” and “sojourner.” It is useful to limit the meaning of “hospitality” to benevolence done to those outside one’s normal circle of friends, as is implied in the literal meaning of the Greek word meaning “love of strangers.” Although the concept is thoroughly endorsed in the Bible, it is clearly found in nonbiblical cultures as well, especially among the nomadic peoples, where definite obligations to provide food, shelter, and protection are recognized.</p>
<p>The normal exercise of hospitality in the OT can be seen in the examples of Abraham and the three visitors (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.2-8,16">Gn 18:2-8, 16</a>), Laban’s reception of Abraham’s servant (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.15-61">24:15-61</a>), and Manoah’s treatment of the angel (<a href="?bref=Judg.13.15">Jgs 13:15</a>). But there are also cases in which the host felt compelled to take extreme steps to protect his guest, even to the harm of his own family (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.1-8">Gn 19:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.19.14-24">Jgs 19:14-24</a>). The hospitality of the Shunammite family is also noteworthy, although Elisha was no stranger to them (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.10">2 Kgs 4:10</a>).</p>
<p>According to the NT, Jesus relied on the general practice of hospitality in sending out the disciples (<a href="?bref=Luke.10.7">Lk 10:7</a>), as well as in his own travels. As the gospel was spread by traveling missionaries, Christians were commended for entertaining them in their homes (<a href="?bref=Heb.13.2">Heb 13:2</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.4.9">1 Pt 4:9</a>; <a href="?bref=3Jn.1.5-8">3 Jn 1:5-8</a>). Church leaders must not exempt themselves from this ministry (<a href="?bref=1Tim.3.2">1 Tm 3:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Titus.1.8">Ti 1:8</a>); to do so is grounds for judgment (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.43-46">Mt 25:43-46</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Foreigner_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Foreigner</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>