<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="KadeshKadeshBarnea">
  <title>Kadesh, Kadesh-Barnea</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">KADESH, KADESH-BARNEA</p>
<p class="fl">Home of the wandering Israelites for nearly 38 years. In the vast area of the Sinai there are two main oases: in the south is Wadi Feiran, near the mountain of Moses (Mt Sinai or Horeb); in the north is Kadesh, or Kadesh-barnea. The former was the place where the law was given; the latter, the main campsite of the 12 tribes during their exodus from Egypt (<a href="?bref=Deut.1.46">Dt 1:46</a>).</p>
<p>Kadesh-barnea (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.7">Gn 14:7</a>, “En-mishpat”) was raided by Chedorlaomer, king of Elam, during the time of Abraham. In this area Hagar was driven from the tent of Sarah, her mistress (<a href="?bref=Gen.16.14">16:14</a>), and here Miriam died and was buried (<a href="?bref=Num.20.1">Nm 20:1</a>). The great contention over water took place here, giving rise to the name Meribah or Meribath-kadesh (<a href="?bref=Num.20.2-24">Nm 20:2-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.32.51">Dt 32:51</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.47.19">Ez 47:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.48.28">48:28</a>). This was also the scene of Korah’s rebellion against the leadership of Moses and Aaron (<a href="?bref=Num.16.1-17.13">Nm 16–17</a>). This area would long remain in the memory of the Israelite tribes as the place of their unbelief following the report of the 10 spies and a delay of 38 years before their occupancy of the Promised Land (<a href="?bref=Ps.95.8-11">Ps 95:8-11</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.3.7-19">Heb 3:7-19</a>).</p>
<p>Because of the water, pasture, and agricultural lands, plus its proximity to Canaan, the Israelites found this area the best spot in which to spend most of their time prior to entering the Promised Land.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Meribah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Meribah #2</a>; <a href="?item=WildernessWanderings_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wilderness Wanderings</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>