<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Kindness">
  <title>Kindness</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">KINDNESS</p>
<p class="fl">State of being that includes the attributes of loving affection, sympathy, friendliness, patience, pleasantness, gentleness, and goodness. Kindness is a quality shown in the way a person speaks and acts. It is more volitional than emotional.</p>
<p>The Bible is filled with illustrations of kindness. Joseph wanted Pharaoh’s butler to show kindness by remembering him to Pharaoh (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.14">Gn 40:14</a>). Rahab requested kind treatment from Israel for her protection of the two spies who had come into her home (<a href="?bref=Josh.2.12">Jos 2:12</a>). Before he attacked Amalek, Saul asked the Kenites to leave the Amalekite territory, not wanting to kill them along with the Amalekites because of the kindness they had shown Israel when Israel came up from Egypt (<a href="?bref=1Sam.15.6">1 Sm 15:6</a>). David commended the men of Jabesh-gilead for the kindness they had shown Saul in giving his body a decent burial (<a href="?bref=2Sam.2.5">2 Sm 2:5</a>). Jonathan requested “unfailing kindness” of David so that he would not be killed (<a href="?bref=1Sam.20.14-15">1 Sm 20:14-15</a>). David extended this kindness to Jonathan’s son by granting him the right to eat at the king’s table (<a href="?bref=2Sam.9.1-7">2 Sm 9:1-7</a>).</p>
<p>It is the worst kind of ingratitude to return evil for kindness. Abimelech wanted Abraham to swear that he would return kindness for kindness to his offspring (<a href="?bref=Gen.21.23">Gn 21:23</a>). Abner showed kindness to Ishbosheth by not delivering him over to David, while Ishbosheth, in return, charged Abner with guilt regarding Saul’s concubine, Rizpah (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.8">2 Sm 3:8</a>). Hanun received David’s kind act of sending condolences on his father’s death by humiliating David’s messengers, thereby bringing on war between the two nations (<a href="?bref=2Sam.10.2-19">10:2-19</a>). Absalom rebuked Hushai, David’s friend, for supposedly leaving David’s side when he needed him. Absalom asked Hushai if that was the way he was repaying David’s friendship (<a href="?bref=2Sam.16.17">2 Sm 16:17</a>; see also <a href="?bref=2Chr.24.22">2 Chr 24:22</a>).</p>
<p>God’s actions provide the outstanding illustrations of kindness in the Bible. The Levites praised God because he had proved to be a God of forgiveness, graciousness, compassion, and abundant lovingkindness (<a href="?bref=Neh.9.17-31">Neh 9:17-31</a>). To highlight God’s virtue even more, they declared his kindness against the backdrop of Israel’s unfaithfulness. God did not forsake his people, even though they forsook him for a golden calf. He gave them his Spirit to instruct them. He gave them manna to eat and water to drink for 40 years in the wilderness. He gave them Canaan, a land in which to dwell.</p>
<p>The high point of God’s kindness was his provision of salvation for sinners, not on the basis of their works but on the basis of his mercy (<a href="?bref=Titus.3.4">Ti 3:4</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Eph.2.7">Eph 2:7</a>). Because of God’s great kindness toward them, in giving both physical and spiritual blessings, Christians are exhorted, as God’s elect, to put on hearts of compassion, kindness, humility, gentleness, and patience; that is, to show kindness to others in return for God’s kindness (<a href="?bref=Col.3.12">Col 3:12</a>). The apostle Peter commanded Christians to add to their faith, along with other excellences, the excellence of brotherly kindness (<a href="?bref=2Pet.1.7">2 Pt 1:7</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>).</p>
  </body>
</item>