<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="KissKissofPeace">
  <title>Kiss, Kiss of Peace*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">KISS, KISS OF PEACE*</p>
<p class="fl">Common salutation symbolizing love and fellowship. In the Bible, kissing is referred to in a wide variety of contexts. In addition to its ordinary expression among relatives (<a href="?bref=Gen.29.11">Gn 29:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.33.4">33:4</a>), its sensual aspect is noted (<a href="?bref=Pr.7.6-13">Prv 7:6-13</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.1.2">Sg 1:2</a>). It is well attested as an act of homage (<a href="?bref=1Sam.10.1">1 Sm 10:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Job.31.27">Jb 31:27</a>), although such expressions may be heinous in God’s sight (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.18">1 Kgs 19:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.13.2">Hos 13:2</a>). Hypocrisy, even betrayal, may accompany a kiss (<a href="?bref=Matt.26.48-49">Mt 26:48-49</a>).</p>
<p>Five NT texts refer to a “holy kiss,” called later in church liturgy a “kiss of peace” (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.16">Rom 16:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.20">1 Cor 16:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Cor.13.12">2 Cor 13:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.5.26">1 Thes 5:26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.14">1 Pt 5:14</a>). Peter speaks of a “kiss of love” and mentions peace in conjunction with it. Although the practice is neither described nor limited by Scripture, the kiss was evidently exchanged between Christians as a pledge of brotherly friendship and fidelity (<a href="?bref=1Thes.5.25-27">1 Thes 5:25-27</a>).</p>
<p>In the generations following the apostolic era, the kiss of peace came to occupy an established place in liturgical worship. In the latter part of the second century, Justin Martyr spoke of the exchange of kisses throughout the congregation following the conclusion of prayer. Eventually, the church placed the ceremony immediately prior to Holy Communion. Later on, the actual kiss was largely replaced by a simple bow. Other variant forms of the practice are still observed in various churches.</p>
  </body>
</item>