<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Kneeling">
  <title>Kneeling</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">KNEELING</p>
<p class="fl">Position often denoting worship, respect, or submission. A strong knee symbolically implied a man with strength of faith and purpose, and thus bowing the knee indicated submission to a superior. The knee was bowed before a king, a ruler, a governor, or God. <a href="?bref=Gen.41.43">Genesis 41:43</a> describes the people who were kneeling before Pharaoh and Joseph. Kneeling in reverence before the Lord was common (<a href="?bref=Isa.45.23">Is 45:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Rom.14.11">Rom 14:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Phil.2.10">Phil 2:10</a>). In a time of famine, when the Israelites turned away from the Lord, those who remained faithful were described as “all the knees that have not bowed to Baal” (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.18">1 Kgs 19:18</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>; see <a href="?bref=Rom.11.4">Rom 11:4</a>).</p>
<p>As firm knees represented strength, so smiting those knees represented the destruction of power (<a href="?bref=Deut.28.35">Dt 28:35</a>). Isaiah pleaded with the Lord for the strengthening of weak knees (<a href="?bref=Isa.35.3">Is 35:3</a>). References to weak or feeble knees were generally used to show a lack of firmness of faith (<a href="?bref=Job.4.4">Jb 4:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Heb.12.12">Heb 12:12</a>) but could sometimes refer to failing health (<a href="?bref=Ps.109.24">Ps 109:24</a>). Ezekiel referred to those who had knees “as weak as water” (<a href="?bref=Ezek.7.17">Ez 7:17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.21.7">21:7</a>).</p>
<p>Kneeling before the Lord was a posture representing worship (<a href="?bref=Ps.95.6">Ps 95:6</a>) and also prayer (<a href="?bref=Dan.6.10">Dn 6:10</a>). Christ himself knelt to pray in the garden of Gethsemane (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.41">Lk 22:41</a>), and Peter, Paul, and Stephen all did the same (<a href="?bref=Acts.7.60">Acts 7:60</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.9.40">9:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.20.36">20:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.21.5">21:5</a>). Solomon knelt in prayer and supplication before the Lord (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.54">1 Kgs 8:54</a>), and even on one occasion had a scaffold built so that he could climb up and be seen by the whole congregation of Israel kneeling before the Lord (<a href="?bref=2Chr.6.13">2 Chr 6:13</a>).</p>
<p>Some knelt in penitence, as Ezra did at the evening sacrifice (<a href="?bref=Ezra.9.5">Ezr 9:5</a>) and as Peter did when begging the Lord’s forgiveness for his lack of faith and trust (<a href="?bref=Luke.5.8">Lk 5:8</a>). Those who were beseeching the prophet Elijah knelt before him as God’s representative (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.1.13">2 Kgs 1:13</a>), and many came kneeling and begging the Lord for healing (<a href="?bref=Matt.17.14">Mt 17:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.40">Mk 1:40</a>). Daniel knelt in wonder and awe before an angel (<a href="?bref=Dan.10.10">Dn 10:10</a>), and a sign of Belshazzar’s fear was that his “knees knocked together” (<a href="?bref=Dan.5.6">Dn 5:6</a>). In the NT a regal and patient Christ is subjected to the taunting and mockery of the soldiers who knelt before him and sarcastically cried, “Hail, King of the Jews” (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.29">Mt 27:29</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.15.19">Mk 15:19</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>