<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="VinesVineyard">
  <title>Vines, Vineyard</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">VINES, VINEYARD</p>
<p class="fl">Plants cultivated for the production of grapes, raisins, and wine. The grapevine is mentioned frequently in Scripture both in a literal and a figurative sense. Probably originating in the Ararat region (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.20">Gn 9:20</a>), the vine was also cultivated in ancient Egypt, where tomb murals depict the wine-making process. The Canaanites provided wine for Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.14.18">14:18</a>), and Moses described the vineyards in the Promised Land (<a href="?bref=Deut.6.11">Dt 6:11</a>). Excellent grapes from the valleys and plains (<a href="?bref=Num.13.20,24">Nm 13:20, 24</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.14.5">Jgs 14:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.15.5">15:5</a>) provided fruit and wine to enhance the bland diet of the Hebrews. Wine was traded extensively in the late monarchy (cf. <a href="?bref=Ezek.27.18">Ez 27:18</a>), as well as in the Greek and Roman periods. For the Hebrews, an ideal picture of life was a sedentary one in which a man could remain peacefully in one place, cultivating his plot of land, and sitting under his vine (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.25">1 Kgs 4:25</a>).</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="TheGrapevine"/>
<p>The typical vineyard was surrounded by a protective hedge or fence, and at harvesttime a watchtower was manned to guard the crop from thieves (<a href="?bref=Job.24.18">Jb 24:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.1.8">Is 1:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.1">Mk 12:1</a>). The vines were planted in rows within the enclosed area, and as the plants grew, the tendrils were trained along supports to raise the fruit-bearing branches off the ground (<a href="?bref=Ezek.17.6">Ez 17:6</a>). The vines were pruned and tended by vinedressers (<a href="?bref=Lev.25.3">Lv 25:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.61.5">Is 61:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.3.10">Jl 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=John.15.2">Jn 15:2</a>). At harvesttime the mature fruit was picked and taken to the winepresses (<a href="?bref=Hos.9.2">Hos 9:2</a>). A festive atmosphere accompanied the treading of the grapes (<a href="?bref=Isa.16.10">Is 16:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.25.30">Jer 25:30</a>), and the fermenting juice was collected in new goatskin bags (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.17">Mt 9:17</a>) or large pottery jars.</p>
<p>People working in the grape harvest were exempted from military service, which attests to its importance. Taxes and debts were often discharged by payments of wine, and the law provided for the poor to glean in the vineyards as in the wheat fields (<a href="?bref=Lev.19.9-10">Lv 19:9-10</a>). Nonproductive vines were used for producing charcoal (<a href="?bref=Ezek.15.4">Ez 15:4</a>; <a href="?bref=John.15.6">Jn 15:6</a>).</p>
<p>Christ frequently used the vineyard as a background for his parables (<a href="?bref=Matt.20.1-16">Mt 20:1-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.21.28-43">21:28-43</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.12.1-11">Mk 12:1-11</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.13.6-9">Lk 13:6-9</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.20.9-18">20:9-18</a>). Wine-making methods were commonly known and understood, so that an allegory of placing new wine in old wineskins (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.17">Mt 9:17</a>) was immediately familiar and significant. In a symbolic sense, Christ described himself as the true vine (<a href="?bref=John.15.1-11">Jn 15:1-11</a>), and his blood became the sacramental wine of communion.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Agriculture_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Agriculture</a>; <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants (Vine)</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>