<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Virgin">
  <title>Virgin</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">VIRGIN</p>
<p class="fl">Word used only of women and (metaphorically) of places, nations, and the church. Literally, it describes a woman who has reached physical maturity but has not experienced sexual intercourse. Mary, mother of Jesus, is an obvious example (<a href="?bref=Matt.1.18-25">Mt 1:18-25</a>).</p>
<p>The OT puts a high value on premarital virginity. One of Rebekah’s qualities that made her a suitable bride for Isaac was her virginity (<a href="?bref=Gen.24.16">Gn 24:16</a>). The law prescribed that priests, as men whose lives should conform most closely to God’s standards, must marry only virgins (<a href="?bref=Lev.21.7,13-14">Lv 21:7, 13-14</a>).</p>
<p>Undoubtedly this reflects the whole Bible’s teaching on marriage, with its ideal of exclusive faithfulness. The NT expresses that ideal by its ban on premarital intercourse (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.13,18">1 Cor 6:13, 18</a>), and by its use of “virgin” language to describe Christians who remain faithful to their Lord (<a href="?bref=Rev.14.4">Rv 14:4</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=2Cor.11.2">2 Cor 11:2</a>).</p>
<p>Negatively, the OT highlights the same principle in the penalties it lays down for the loss of a woman’s virginity. If the man is morally responsible, he must either marry her or compensate her father (<a href="?bref=Exod.22.16-17">Ex 22:16-17</a>). If the woman herself is to blame, the punishment is death (<a href="?bref=Deut.22.20-21">Dt 22:20-21</a>). The OT says little, however, to commend lifelong virginity. Jeremiah was told not to marry, only to reinforce God’s warning of coming judgment (<a href="?bref=Jer.16.2">Jer 16:2</a>). From the woman’s point of view, it was a tragedy to remain an unmarried virgin and therefore childless for life (cf. <a href="?bref=Judg.11.37">Jgs 11:37</a>).</p>
<p>The NT echoes the value of marriage but brings out more clearly the advantages of a commitment to virginity for Christian men as well as women. Celibacy for some is God’s gift, declared Paul, because it has positive gains for Christian service (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.7,25-38">1 Cor 7:7, 25-38</a>). Jesus commended those who “make themselves eunuchs” for the kingdom of heaven’s sake (<a href="?bref=Matt.19.12">Mt 19:12</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=FamilyLifeandRelations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Family Life and Relations</a>; <a href="?item=MarriageMarriageCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Marriage, Marriage Customs</a>; <a href="?item=SexSexuality_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sex, Sexuality</a>; <a href="?item=VirginBirthofJesus_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Virgin Birth of Jesus</a>; <a href="?item=Woman_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Woman</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>