<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="VowVows">
  <title>Vow, Vows</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">VOW, VOWS</p>
<p class="fl">Serious promises or pledges made to God. The making of vows to God is a religious practice frequently mentioned in Scripture. Most references to vows are found in the OT, especially in the Psalms, but there are a few in the NT.</p>
<p>Unlike tithing, sacrifices and offerings, Sabbath keeping, and circumcision, vow making was not something commanded by the Mosaic law. For example, <a href="?bref=Ps.50.14">Psalm 50:14</a> says, “Offer to God a sacrifice of thanksgiving, and pay your vows to the Most High” (<span class="sc">rsv</span>). The command is to “pay,” that is, to keep or fulfill a pledge that has already been made. No order is given to make such promises in the first place. The practice is accepted and regulated but not demanded.</p>
<p>The purpose of a vow is to win a desired favor from the Lord, to express gratitude to him for some deliverance or benefit, or simply to prove absolute devotion to him by way of certain abstinences. Dedication of oneself and separation to the Lord were the primary features of the Nazirite vow. Samson, Samuel, and John the Baptist are the most familiar examples of those who took this type of vow. <a href="?bref=Num.6.1-8">Numbers 6:1-8</a> prescribes the conditions of this commitment, and verses <a href="?bref=Num.6.13-21">13-21</a> tell how release from the vow may be obtained. Women, as well as men, might take this vow of separation (v <a href="?bref=Num.6.2">2</a>), which could be of limited duration. The Recabite clan pledged themselves to an ascetic and nomadic life. They constitute a compelling illustration of loyalty to the God of Israel (<a href="?bref=Jer.35.1-19">Jer 35</a>).</p>
<p>Frequently, however, vows were taken as a type of bargain with God. At Bethel, Jacob promised God worship and the tithe if he would protect him and supply his needs (<a href="?bref=Gen.28.20-22">Gn 28:20-22</a>). Hannah pledged that if God would give her a son, she would return him to God (<a href="?bref=1Sam.1.11,27-28">1 Sm 1:11, 27-28</a>). In the Psalms, payment of vows is often associated with thanksgiving for deliverance from danger or affliction (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ps.22.24-25">Pss 22:24-25</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.56.12-13">56:12-13</a>). </p>
<p>Most important is that once a vow is made, the obligation is serious. To refrain from making any vow is no sin (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.22">Dt 23:22</a>), but once declared, the vow must be kept (<a href="?bref=Deut.23.21-23">Dt 23:21-23</a>; see also <a href="?bref=Num.30.2">Nm 30:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Eccl.5.4-6">Eccl 5:4-6</a>).</p>
<p>The term “vow” occurs just twice in the NT, both times in association with the apostle Paul (<a href="?bref=Acts.18.18">Acts 18:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Acts.21.23-24">21:23-24</a>). But the same principle is involved in the case of the word “Corban” (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.11-13">Mk 7:11-13</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Matt.15.5-6">Mt 15:5-6</a>). In these two passages Jesus severely rebuked those who made a vow that served as a clever escape from meeting obligations to care for aged parents. A monetary figure was involved in such a “gift” or “offering.” But Jesus declared that God did not want a gift designed to deprive someone.</p>
<p>In the case of Paul, he may have entered into his vows for the very purpose of averting objections that either antagonistic Jews or Jewish-Christian believers had to his removing the yoke of Mosaic regulations from the shoulders of gentile believers. Paul was in Jerusalem under the keen surveillance of Jewish authorities. He made it a point to join with four other Jewish believers in the payment of vows in the temple. This action, however, was misconstrued by his enemies, who charged that he was bringing Gentiles into the holy temple.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Covenant_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Covenant</a>; <a href="?item=Oath_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Oath</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>