<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Earthquake">
  <title>Earthquake</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EARTHQUAKE</p>
<p class="fl">Shaking or trembling of the earth originated by volcanic or tectonic activity. Earthquakes occur frequently in Palestine due mostly to the volcanic nature of the regions around the Dead Sea and the Sea of Galilee. The primary centers of earthquakes in Palestine are upper Galilee, the Samaritan country near Shechem, and the western edge of the Judean Mountains near Lydda.</p>
<p>The Hebrew word for “earthquake” indicates a great noise or a tremendous roaring, suggesting that the Israelites were impressed with the rumbling connected with earthquakes.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="ReportsOfAncientEarthquakes"/>
<p>Instances of earthquakes are (1) at Mt Sinai, in connection with God’s giving the law to Moses (<a href="?bref=Exod.19.18">Ex 19:18</a>); (2) during the wilderness wandering of the Israelites, when Korah and his followers rebelled against Moses and were destroyed as punishment for their rebellion (<a href="?bref=Num.16.31-33">Nm 16:31-33</a>); (3) among the Philistines on the occasion when Jonathan and his armor bearer fought a garrison of Philistines (<a href="?bref=1Sam.14.15">1 Sm 14:15</a>); (4) after Elijah killed the prophets of Baal and, fleeing Jezebel’s wrath, sat under a juniper tree feeling sorry for himself (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.19.7-9,11">1 Kgs 19:7-9, 11</a>); (5) in the reign of King Uzziah (<a href="?bref=Amos.1.1">Am 1:1</a>); (6) at the death of Jesus on Calvary (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.51-54">Mt 27:51-54</a>); (7) at the resurrection of Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.28.2">Mt 28:2</a>); and (8) at Philippi while Paul and Silas were in jail (<a href="?bref=Acts.16.26">Acts 16:26</a>). Earthquakes are also mentioned as one of the phenomena in connection with the “Day of the Lord” (<a href="?bref=Zech.14.4-5">Zec 14:4-5</a>) and the consummation of this age (<a href="?bref=Rev.6.12-24">Rv 6:12-24</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.11.19">11:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.16.18">16:18</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>