<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EblaTablets">
  <title>Ebla Tablets*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EBLA TABLETS*</p>
<p class="fl">Tablets, dating c. 2220–2240 <span class="era">BC</span>, discovered in the ancient Syrian city-state of Ebla, now identified with the site of Tell Mardikh.</p>
<p>Ebla was a commercial center, manufacturing items of textiles, wood, ceramics, gold, silver, and other metals. A large number of the clay tablets unearthed are economic documents, recording transactions with many other cities, stretching from Asia Minor to Egypt and from Cyprus to Iran (Persia). Thousands of cities are named in these documents. Included are many familiar biblical names, such as Hazor, Megiddo, Dor, Joppa, Gaza, and Uru-salim (Jerusalem, or possibly “city of Salem”). In one text we also see Sodom, Gomorrah, and Zoar. Zoar is described as “in the territory of Bela” (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.14.2">Gn 14:2</a>). According to the biblical account, Sodom and Gomorrah were destroyed in the days of Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.24-29">Gn 19:24-29</a>); hence, the details recorded in <a href="?bref=Gen.14.1-24">Genesis 14</a> and <a href="?bref=Gen.19.1-38">19</a> could not have been reconstructed at a later date unless there was a living tradition recording the events.</p>
<p>Many personal names appear in the tablets from Tell Mardikh that have biblical equivalents, e.g., Abram <span class="ital">(ab-ra-mu),</span> Israel <span class="ital">(ish-ra-ilu),</span> Saul <span class="ital">(sha-u-lu),</span> and David <span class="ital">(da-u-du).</span> To some, this fact raises questions, while others find it to be a confirmation of the biblical record. For example, it might be asked how the name “Israel” could be found four or more centuries before God gave the name to Jacob. The Bible does not suggest that the name was new. Names in those days were often composed of the name of a deity plus a verbal form (e.g., Isaiah = “Yah is salvation”). It is entirely conceivable that parents named their children <span class="ital">ish-ra-ilu,</span> “El [God] has prevailed,” before the days of Jacob. What was new in the biblical experience was the personal encounter with God and the blessing that it brought on Jacob.</p>
<p>A number of the names from Ebla seem to appear in two forms, one compounded with <span class="ital">-ilu</span> (El), the other with <span class="ital">-ya</span> (Yah). Thus the names <span class="ital">mi-ka-ya</span> (Micaiah, Micah) and <span class="ital">mi-ka-il</span> (Michael) are reported by Pettinato, along with other theophoric (God-bearing) names. The appearance of the ending <span class="ital">-ya,</span> if it has been properly interpreted as a divine name (Yah, the Lord), raises an important question. According to <a href="?bref=Exod.6.3">Exodus 6:3</a>, God told Moses that he appeared to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob as El Shaddai, “but by my name Yahweh I did not make myself known to them.” This seems to say that the name Yahweh was not known prior to the revelation to Moses at Sinai. On the other hand, the name Yahweh is found many times in Genesis, not only in narrative portions (where a later author or editor might have inserted a name, such as was done with certain place-names), but also in oaths taken in the name of Yahweh and in quotations that imply that the name of Yahweh was actually in use. This problem has long been recognized, and biblical scholars have divided into two groups: those who held that the name was <span class="ital">not</span> known prior to the time of Moses, and those who held that the name <span class="ital">was</span> known but that it took on a new meaning in the light of the Sinai-exodus event. If the interpretation of the Eblean materials proves to be correct—namely, that <span class="ital">-ya</span> is a divine-name element in personal names—then we shall have to conclude that the name Yah(weh) was known in patriarchal times but that its true significance, that Yahweh is the ever-living and life-giving God, only began to be fully revealed in his deliverance of his people from Egyptian bondage.</p>
<p>The Eblean materials have certainly opened a new door to a rich storehouse of knowledge. It will be many years before all the implications of this discovery are fully realized. But certain facts are already clear, and among these is this very important truth: the patriarchal stories in <a href="?bref=Gen.11.1-35.29">Genesis 11–35</a> can no longer be ascribed to authors of the eighth or seventh centuries <span class="era">BC</span>. To assume that such an author could have included hundreds of names of places and persons, items of trade, and the many details that are found in these chapters, and then to suggest that it is mere coincidence that has brought to light the same names, places, trade relationships, and countless other details through modern archaeological discoveries, is simply unreasonable. Ebla has delivered the coup de grâce to such theories.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Inscriptions_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Inscriptions</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="DoTheEblaTabletsProveTheBible"/>
  </body>
</item>