<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EphodGarment">
  <title>Ephod (Garment)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EPHOD (Garment)</p>
<p class="fl">Upper garment worn during religious services associated with the tabernacle or temple. “Ephod” generally referred to the ornamented vest that the high priest wore over a blue robe (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.31">Ex 28:31</a>). Included with the ephod were the Urim and Thummim, the sacred lots. Sometimes “ephod” meant the complete dress of the high priest (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.28">1 Sm 2:28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.23.6,9">23:6, 9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.30.7">30:7</a>) or similar garments worn by lesser priests.</p>
<p>Made of dyed material and fine linen, the garment was embroidered in blue, purple, scarlet, and gold. At the upper end were attached two shoulder straps, each having an onyx stone inscribed with the names of Israel’s 12 tribes. The breastplate, also containing the tribal names, was bound to the ephod by an elaborate series of cords and chains (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.22-29">Ex 28:22-29</a>).</p>
<p>Jewish writers suggest various appearances for the ephod: (1) apronlike, covering the body from the chest to the heels; (2) enveloping the body only from the waist down, the upper body being covered by the breastplate; or (3) sleeved and jacketlike, with the middle of the breast uncovered so the breastplate could be inserted easily.</p>
<p>Prior to the Babylonian exile, the ephod served as a means of revelation from God, especially concerning military operations. Abiathar the priest brought the ephod into David’s camp on one occasion for consulting the Lord (<a href="?bref=1Sam.23.6-9">1 Sm 23:6-9</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.30.7">30:7</a>). It is uncertain whether the priest donned or held the ephod whole, seeking counsel from the Lord by means of the Urim and Thummim.</p>
<p>During the period of the judges, the ephod was often misused, as by Gideon (<a href="?bref=Judg.8.27">Jgs 8:27</a>), Micah (<a href="?bref=Judg.17.5">17:5</a>), and Jonathan, grandson of Moses (<a href="?bref=Judg.18.30">18:30</a>; cf. vv 14, 17, 20). Either the garment itself or an image that represented God, on which the garment was placed, was worshiped as the people sought revelation in a manner condemned by God. Household idols (teraphim) were also associated with this ungodly practice (<a href="?bref=Judg.17.5">17:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Hos.3.4">Hos 3:4</a>).</p>
<p>Besides the high priest, other priests wore an ephod for certain religious services (<a href="?bref=1Sam.22.18">1 Sm 22:18</a>), and even Samuel (<a href="?bref=1Sam.2.18">2:18</a>) and David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.6.14">2 Sm 6:14</a>) wore one. By the postexilic period, and perhaps as early as Solomon, the ephod was no longer consulted (<a href="?bref=Ezra.2.63">Ezr 2:63</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.7.65">Neh 7:65</a>). There was no need for ephod or Urim revelation once there was the more complete revelation of the prophetic ministry promised by Moses (<a href="?bref=Deut.18.15-22">Dt 18:15-22</a>). However, the high priest continued to wear this vestment until the destruction of Jerusalem in <span class="era">AD</span> 70.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=PriestsandLevites_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Priests and Levites</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>