<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Eschatology">
  <title>Eschatology*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">ESCHATOLOGY*</p>
<p class="fl">Branch of theology concerned with the study of the last things, or end times, whether in relation to the individual or the world.</p>
<p class="h2" id="TopicsofEschatology">Topics of Eschatology</p>
<p class="h3">Death</p>
<p class="fl">The Bible teaches that all humans will die (<a href="?bref=Heb.9.27">Heb 9:27</a>). The only exceptions will be those who are still alive when Christ returns (<a href="?bref=1Thes.4.17">1 Thes 4:17</a>). Physical death, or the “first death,” is the separation of the soul from the body. Because of the presence of sin in the world, everyone must die (<a href="?bref=Rom.5.12">Rom 5:12</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Intermediate State</p>
<p class="fl">This refers to the condition of the person between the time of death and the resurrection. The traditional orthodox view is that believers experience a state of conscious bliss in the presence of the Lord, while unbelievers are tormented by separation from the presence of God. This, however, is a relatively incomplete state when compared with the final destiny of each. Some groups, such as Seventh-Day Adventists, have held a belief in a type of “soul sleep,” or unconsciousness, between death and resurrection. Still others, notably Roman Catholics, believe in a place of purging in preparation for the future life.</p>
<p class="h3">The Second Coming</p>
<p class="fl">Scripture teaches that at the end of time Christ will return in a personal, bodily form (<a href="?bref=Acts.1.11">Acts 1:11</a>). No one knows exactly when this will occur, and it will consequently catch some by surprise, coming as a thief in the night (<a href="?bref=Luke.12.39-40">Lk 12:39-40</a>). Although the time is not known, the fact that it will occur is very definite. Many of Jesus’ parables (especially in <a href="?bref=Matt.24.1-25.46">Mt 24–25</a>) refer to this fact and to the appropriateness of alert, faithful, and intensive activity.</p>
<p class="h3">The Resurrection</p>
<p class="fl">All who have died will come to life. This will be a bodily resurrection, a resumption of the bodily existence of each person. For believers, this will take place in connection with the second coming of Christ and will involve the transformation of the body of this present flesh into a new, perfected body (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.35-56">1 Cor 15:35-56</a>). The Bible also indicates a resurrection of unbelievers, unto eternal death (<a href="?bref=John.5.28-29">Jn 5:28-29</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">The Judgment</p>
<p class="fl">There will be a time of judgment in which the Lord will determine the spiritual condition of all who have lived, based on their relationship to him. On these grounds some will be sent off to everlasting reward and others to eternal punishment. Some theologians distinguish between the times when believers and unbelievers will be judged. Some see as many as seven different judgments occurring.</p>
<p class="h3">The Final States</p>
<p class="fl">The Bible teaches the existence of heaven, a place of eternal joy, where Christians are in the presence of God. The Bible also speaks of hell (specifically Gehenna, or the lake of fire), a state of anguished separation of unbelievers from the presence of God. These are fixed states, determined by decisions made within this life.</p>
<p class="h3">The Millennium</p>
<p class="fl">Many Christians believe there will be an earthly reign of Jesus Christ, called the Millennium, immediately preceding the final judgment. This belief is based on <a href="?bref=Rev.20.4-7">Revelation 20:4-7</a>. Those who hold that Christ will return personally to inaugurate this period are called premillennialists. Others, who teach that the kingdom will be established through the progressive successful preaching of the gospel, are termed postmillennialists. Still others, called amillennialists, do not believe that there will be any earthly reign of Christ at all, interpreting the 1,000 years of <a href="?bref=Rev.20.1-15">Revelation 20</a> symbolically.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="WatchOut"/>
<p class="h3">The Great Tribulation</p>
<p class="fl">The Bible speaks of a time of great anguish or tribulation, which will come upon the earth, exceeding anything that has ever occurred before. Some, identifying this with the 70th week of <a href="?bref=Dan.9.24-27">Daniel 9:24-27</a>, believe it will be of seven years duration. Some believe the church will be present to experience this because the Lord will not return until the end of the period. These are termed posttribulationists. Others, known as pretribulationists, believe that the Lord’s second coming will be in two stages, or phases: (1) Christ will come for his church to take the believers away before the great Tribulation; (2) Christ will then make an open display of his glory before the whole world. Still others, known as midtribulationists, believe that the church will be present for the first half of the seven years but will be removed before the severe part of the Tribulation begins.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Apocalyptic_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Apocalyptic</a>; <a href="?item=DayoftheLord_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Day of the Lord</a>; <a href="?item=Death_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Death</a>; <a href="?item=EternalLife_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Eternal Life</a>; <a href="?item=Heaven_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Heaven</a>; <a href="?item=Hell_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Hell</a>; <a href="?item=IntermediateState_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Intermediate State</a>; <a href="?item=Judgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Judgment</a>; <a href="?item=LastDays_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Last Days</a>; <a href="?item=LastJudgment_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Last Judgment</a>; <a href="?item=Millennium_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Millennium</a>; <a href="?item=Resurrection_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Resurrection</a>; <a href="?item=SecondComingofChrist_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Second Coming of Christ</a>; <a href="?item=DanielBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Daniel, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=Tribulation_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Tribulation</a>; <a href="?item=WrathofGod_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Wrath of God</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>