<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EuphratesRiver">
  <title>Euphrates River</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EUPHRATES RIVER</p>
<p class="fl">Largest river in western Asia, formed by the union of two rivers in Asia Minor, the Kara-Su and the Murat-Suyu. Its source is in central Armenia. The river flows generally in a southeasterly direction for some 1,800 miles (2,896.2 kilometers) until it reaches the Persian Gulf. At Korna, about 100 miles (160.9 kilometers) from the gulf, it joins with the Tigris River. The Euphrates is shallow until it combines with the Tigris and can be navigated for about 1,200 miles (1,930.8 kilometers) by small boats only. After the union of the Tigris and Euphrates, ocean liners can proceed as far as Basra. Melting snows at the source cause the river to rise from about the middle of March until about June. Control and storage of water in flood canals during the overflow of the river made possible abundant harvests that sustained large populations in antiquity.</p>
<p>The Euphrates was one of four branches issuing from the river that watered the Garden of Eden (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.14">Gn 2:14</a>). In the promises made to Abraham, the northern boundary of the land of Israel was to be the upper division of the river (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.18">Gn 15:18</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.1.7">Dt 1:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.11.24">11:24</a>). These boundaries were approximately reached during the period of kings David and Solomon (<a href="?bref=2Sam.8.3">2 Sm 8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.10.16">10:16</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.24">1 Kgs 4:24</a>). The Euphrates is called “the river” (<a href="?bref=Num.22.5">Nm 22:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.11.24">Dt 11:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Josh.24.3,14">Jos 24:3, 14</a>) or “the great river” (<a href="?bref=Josh.1.4">Jos 1:4</a>). People living east of the Euphrates referred to Israel and its surrounding territories to the west as “beyond the river” (<a href="?bref=Ezra.4.10">Ezr 4:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Neh.2.7-9">Neh 2:7-9</a>). It was to this river that Jeremiah sent Seraiah with a book of prophecies relating to the destruction of Babylon. After reading them, Seraiah was told to throw the book into the Euphrates as a symbol of the way Babylon would sink to rise no more (<a href="?bref=Jer.51.63">Jer 51:63</a>).</p>
<p>Two NT references to the Euphrates appear in the book of Revelation (<a href="?bref=Rev.9.14">Rv 9:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.16.12">16:12</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BabylonBabylonia_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Babylon, Babylonia</a>; <a href="?item=Mesopotamia_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mesopotamia</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>