<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Exhortation">
  <title>Exhortation*</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EXHORTATION*</p>
<p class="fl">Translation of a Greek word literally meaning “a calling of someone alongside to help.” Its primary meaning in the NT is the urging of someone to do something—particularly some ethical course of action. In some contexts, the same Greek word may also include the idea of comforting and consoling. The given context will determine which meaning to use.</p>
<p>A passage that most clearly illustrates “exhortation” in the sense of inciting or spurring people on to action is <a href="?bref=Luke.3.7-18">Luke 3:7-18</a>. John the Baptist exhorts his Jewish hearers to bring forth fruits in keeping with repentance, to stop resting on descent from Abraham as protection from punishment for sin, and to share clothing and food. He exhorted tax gatherers to collect no more money than they had a right to take, and soldiers not to take money from anyone by force, not to accuse anyone falsely, and to be content with their wages.</p>
<p>The ability to exhort is said to be a spiritual gift that God has given to some in the church for the benefit of the whole (<a href="?bref=Rom.12.8">Rom 12:8</a>). In addition, exhortation is one of the results of a proper use of the gift of prophecy, as seen in <a href="?bref=1Cor.14.3,31">1 Corinthians 14:3, 31</a>. It was also one of the responsibilities that Paul commanded of Timothy: “Give attention to the public reading of Scripture, to exhortation and teaching” (<a href="?bref=1Tim.4.13">1 Tm 4:13</a>, <span class="sc">nasb</span>). The writer to the Hebrews also refers to an exhortation addressed to the readers lest they regard lightly the discipline of the Lord or “faint” when they are reproved (<a href="?bref=Heb.12.5">Heb 12:5</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>).</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=2Cor.1.3-7">2 Corinthians 1:3-7</a> the Greek word for exhortation is used in the sense of consolation or encouragement. The context is one in which serious suffering for Christ is evident. Paul said that God encourages us in our times of testing so that we may be able to do the same for those experiencing similar trials. <a href="?bref=Acts.15.31">Acts 15:31</a> refers to the encouragement and consolation that came to the church at Antioch when the decree of the Jerusalem Council was read in their hearing. They had been fearful that the Judaizers might have their way and that Christians would be required to become circumcised in order to be saved. Another clear illustration of this word meaning “comfort” is in <a href="?bref=1Thes.4.18">1 Thessalonians 4:18</a>, where Paul instructs the believers that those who die in Christ will not miss out on the blessings of the day of Christ; he then exhorts them to “comfort one another with these words.” <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=SpiritualGifts_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Spiritual Gifts</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>