<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="EzekielPerson">
  <title>Ezekiel (Person)</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">EZEKIEL (P<span class="lc">erson</span>)</p>
<p class="fl">Priest and prophet during Israel’s Babylonian exile. Ezekiel was a descendant of the influential priestly family of Zadok (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.3">Ez 1:3</a>). He was probably reared in Jerusalem and was familiar with the temple ritual; it is unknown whether he served as a priest there. All that is known of his personal life is obtained from the OT book of Ezekiel.</p>
<p>Ezekiel was married (<a href="?bref=Ezek.24.16-18">24:16-18</a>) and lived at Tel-abib in Babylonia (<a href="?bref=Ezek.3.15">3:15</a>), in his own house (<a href="?bref=Ezek.3.24">3:24</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.8.1">8:1</a>). Most of the Judean captives had settled by the Kebar Canal (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.3">1:3</a>), which went from Babylon by Nippur to Erech. The elders of Israel there sought out Ezekiel for counsel (<a href="?bref=Ezek.8.1">8:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.14.1">14:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.20.1">20:1</a>). In the fifth year of the exile, when Ezekiel was between 25 and 30 years old, he received God’s call to the prophetic office (<a href="?bref=Ezek.1.1-3.11">1:1–3:11</a>). His wife died suddenly during the exile, but he was forbidden to mourn for her in public (<a href="?bref=Ezek.24.16-18">24:16-18</a>). Her sudden death was meant to convey a striking and solemn warning of what would occur in the captives’ homeland (vv <a href="?bref=Ezek.24.15-27">15-27</a>).</p>
<p>The time of Ezekiel’s ministry was unusual in many ways. It was a period of great prophetic activity. With the prophets Jeremiah and Daniel, Ezekiel spoke to the nation’s needs at the time of the Babylonian captivity. It was an era of upheaval and uprooting for the southern kingdom of Judah, and a time of persistent apostasy, idolatry, and general disobedience to the Mosaic law. It was also a period of international conflict and shifting power balances throughout the Near East.</p>
<p>Ezekiel’s ministry seems to have extended from 592 <span class="era">BC</span> to at least the 27th year of the exile (<a href="?bref=Ezek.29.17">29:17</a>). It falls into two main periods. During the first period (592–587 <span class="era">BC</span>), his messages were repeated warnings—in prose discourse and symbolic acts—intended to lead the exiles to repentance and faith in God. During the second period (586–570 <span class="era">BC</span>), after Nebuchadnezzar’s destruction of Jerusalem and the temple, the prophet comforted the exiles and encouraged them to look to the future in hope (chs <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.1-48.35">33–48</a>). There were 13 years in which no prophetic utterances were delivered, namely 585 <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=Ezek.32.1,17">32:1, 17</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.33.21">33:21</a>) to 572 <span class="era">BC</span> (<a href="?bref=Ezek.40.1">40:1</a>). The prophet learned of the fall of Jerusalem while in Babylon (<a href="?bref=Ezek.33.21-22">33:21-22</a>).</p>
<p>The burden of Ezekiel’s message was that Judah was ripe for judgment. His preparation for speaking God’s message is given in the picture of his eating the written prophecies (<a href="?bref=Ezek.2.8-3.3">2:8–3:3</a>). At first the messages were not accepted, but later his prophecies were vindicated as they began to come true and as the nation was purged of its idolatry. Ezekiel has been called “the father of Judaism” because of his supposed influence on Israel’s later worship. His greatest contribution to postexilic Jewish worship consisted in establishing the basis of the synagogue. He stressed the teaching of personal immortality, resurrection, and the ritual law.</p>
<p>Ezekiel carried out his messages with vivid and dramatic acts of symbolism (e.g., <a href="?bref=Ezek.4.1-8">4:1-8</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.5.1-17">5:1-17</a>). His style has been characterized as heavy and repetitious, but it was designed with the themes of apostasy and subsequent judgment in view.</p>
<p>The place and circumstances of his death are unknown, and Ezekiel is not mentioned elsewhere in the OT.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=DiasporaoftheJews_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Diaspora of the Jews</a>; <a href="?item=EzekielBookof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Ezekiel, Book of</a>; <a href="?item=ProphetProphetess_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Prophet, Prophetess</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>