<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Famine">
  <title>Famine</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FAMINE</p>
<p class="fl">Prolonged and extreme lack of food. Famine, along with other disasters (such as war and disease), has always been part of the human experience. Sometimes there was enough rainfall, properly timed, but occasionally rainfall was too early or late or insufficient (<a href="?bref=Lev.26.19">Lv 26:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.4.7-8">Am 4:7-8</a>). The Hebrews and other people in the Near East viewed famine as judgment from God. Since God is the Creator and Sustainer, he has power over the natural world. He could use his created order as he chose; it was no accident when there was famine. Whether a famine occurred through lack of rainfall, hailstorms, or any other event, God was the agent.</p>
<p>The most prevalent cause of famine in the ancient world was lack of rain. Such famines occurred in the time of Abraham (<a href="?bref=Gen.12.10">Gn 12:10</a>) and Isaac (<a href="?bref=Gen.26.1">26:1</a>). Joseph was greatly concerned about overcoming the famines in Egypt (chs <a href="?bref=Gen.41.1-47.31">41–47</a>). The Nile River usually provided the Egyptians with enough water for their crops; a failure to receive adequate water supplies from upland regions meant famine for Egypt.</p>
<p>Besides lack of rainfall, famine could result from other causes, such as hail and thunderstorms (<a href="?bref=Exod.9.28">Ex 9:28</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.12.17">1 Sm 12:17</a>). Sieges on crops by locusts and other pests sometimes caused famine (<a href="?bref=Exod.10.15">Ex 10:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.4.9">Am 4:9</a>). Invasion by foreign armies also brought on famine (<a href="?bref=Deut.28.53">Dt 28:53</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.25">2 Kgs 6:25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.3">25:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Lam.4.9-10">Lam 4:9-10</a>). Disease often accompanied famine (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.8.37">1 Kgs 8:37</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.14.12">Jer 14:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.21.9">21:9</a>).</p>
<p>Famine brought changes to the lives of Naomi and Ruth (<a href="?bref=Ruth.1.1">Ru 1:1</a>). God raised Joseph to a position of power in famine conditions. Famine also affected the lives of King David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.1">2 Sm 21:1</a>), Elijah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.17.1-24">1 Kgs 17</a>), Elisha (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.38">2 Kgs 4:38</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.25">6:25</a>), and Zedekiah (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.25.2-3">25:2-3</a>).</p>
<p>Famine was used by God to warn (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.17.1">1 Kgs 17:1</a>), correct (<a href="?bref=2Sam.21.1">2 Sm 21:1</a>), and punish his people or the heathen (<a href="?bref=Jer.14.12,15">Jer 14:12, 15</a>). The famines predicted by Jesus and the writer of the book of Revelation were signs of judgment (<a href="?bref=Mark.13.8">Mk 13:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.18.8">Rv 18:8</a>).</p>
  </body>
</item>