<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Firstfruits">
  <title>Firstfruits</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FIRSTFRUITS</p>
<p class="fl">Firstborn child or animal or first parts of any crop that, in Hebrew thought, were considered as holy and therefore belonged to the Lord. The firstfruits, as a foretaste of more to come, were offered to God in thanksgiving for his goodness in providing them.</p>
<p>Firstfruit offerings could include produce either in its natural state or prepared or processed in some way, such as dough, bread, wine, olive oil, and wool. The firstborn son and the firstborn of the animals that one owned were to be treated as belonging to God. The firstborn children and the firstborn of the unclean animals were “redeemed” (paid for) with money by the offerer, and the firstborn of the cows, sheep, and goats were offered in sacrifice to God (<a href="?bref=Num.18.14-17">Nm 18:14-17</a>).</p>
<p>Firstfruits of any kind were reserved for those whom God designated, namely, the priests. At least three times “the first of the firstfruits” is mentioned in the OT. This may be a reference to the first ripened of the firstfruits, or it may refer to the choicest of them. These offerings were especially designated for the priests and could be eaten by any of them who was ritually clean (<a href="?bref=Num.18.12-13">Nm 18:12-13</a>). For other references to the firstfruits, see <a href="?bref=Exod.23.15-19">Exodus 23:15-19</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.34.22,26">34:22, 26</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.2.14">Leviticus 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.23.10-17">23:10-17</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.15.20-21">Numbers 15:20-21</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.28.26-31">28:26-31</a>; and <a href="?bref=Deut.26.1-11">Deuteronomy 26:1-11</a>.</p>
<p>The firstfruits were presented to God by bringing the offering to the priest at the tabernacle and, in later times, at the temple (<a href="?bref=Deut.26.2">Dt 26:2</a>). The priest took the offering, and on the first day of the week, with arms outstretched, waved it before the Lord. On the same day, the person presenting the firstfruits offered a male lamb as a burnt offering to the Lord, a grain offering of fine flour mixed with olive oil, and a drink offering of wine. Fifty days later another grain offering was to be made. Each family was to give two loaves of bread to the Lord as a special gift. These were also given with appropriate animal, grain, and drink offerings (<a href="?bref=Lev.23.9-22">Lv 23:9-22</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT the apostle Paul referred to Jesus Christ’s resurrection as the firstfruits of the resurrection of believers that will occur at Jesus’ return (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.20,23">1 Cor 15:20, 23</a>). The Holy Spirit, who indwells all believers (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.9">Rom 8:9</a>), is also said to be the firstfruits of the full redemption that is yet to come. “Firstfruits” is sometimes used of the first believers in a geographical area (<a href="?bref=Rom.16.5">Rom 16:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Cor.16.15">1 Cor 16:15</a>). They were a kind of promise of a spiritual harvest to follow in that particular locality.</p>
<p>Christian believers are said to be firstfruits, referring to their being a unique and sacred possession of God out of all he has created (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.18">Jas 1:18</a>). Similarly, in the book of Revelation the 144,000 are said to have been redeemed from humanity as firstfruits belonging to God and to the Lamb, Jesus Christ (<a href="?bref=Rev.14.4">Rv 14:4</a>).</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=FeastsandFestivalsofIsrael_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Feasts and Festivals of Israel</a>; <a href="?item=OfferingsandSacrifices_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Offerings and Sacrifices</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>