<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Flesh">
  <title>Flesh</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FLESH</p>
<p class="fl">The body; the physical being of humans; the human person and human existence; the carnal nature of humans.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheOldTestament">In the Old Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Term commonly used to designate the material stuff of the body, whether of people (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.19">Gn 40:19</a>) or of animals (<a href="?bref=Lev.6.27">Lv 6:27</a>). However, “flesh” is used in the OT with a variety of meanings. Sometimes it is used as equivalent for the whole body (<a href="?bref=Pr.14.30">Prv 14:30</a>), and the meaning is extended to designate the whole person (“my flesh also shall rest in hope,” <a href="?bref=Ps.16.9">Ps 16:9</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). This idea leads to the union of two different persons, man and wife as “one flesh” (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.24">Gn 2:24</a>), and a man can say of his relatives, “I am your bone and your flesh” (<a href="?bref=Judg.9.2">Jgs 9:2</a>). The idea of flesh as the whole person leads to the expression “all flesh,” denoting the totality of humankind, sometimes including also the animal world.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most distinctive use of “flesh” in the OT is found in those passages where it designates human weakness and frailty over against God. “My spirit shall not abide in man for ever, for he is flesh” (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.3">Gn 6:3</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). In <a href="?bref=Ps.78.39">Psalm 78:39</a>, God attributes sin to the fact that men are but flesh. In <a href="?bref=2Chr.32.8">2 Chronicles 32:8</a> the arm of flesh of the king of Assyria (i.e., his weakness) is contrasted with the all-powerful God. The one who puts trust in God need not fear what “flesh” can do (<a href="?bref=Ps.56.4">Ps 56:4</a>), but the one who puts trust in human flesh instead of in God is under a curse (<a href="?bref=Jer.17.5">Jer 17:5</a>). In <a href="?bref=Isa.31.3">Isaiah 31:3</a> flesh is contrasted with spirit, as weakness is with strength.</p>
<p>However, nowhere in the OT is flesh viewed as sinful. Flesh is conceived as being created by God of the dust of the earth (<a href="?bref=Gen.2.7">Gn 2:7</a>), and as God’s creation, it is good.</p>
<p class="h2" id="IntheNewTestament">In the New Testament</p>
<p class="fl">Paul ascribes many—often unique—definitions to the word “flesh” (Greek <span class="greek">sarx</span>).</p>
<p class="h3">Flesh as the Stuff of the Body</p>
<p class="fl">“Flesh” is frequently used to describe the tissues that constitute the body. There are different kinds of flesh—“of men,” “of animals,” “of birds,” “of fish” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.39">1 Cor 15:39</a>). Pain and suffering may be experienced in the flesh (<a href="?bref=2Cor.12.7">2 Cor 12:7</a>). Circumcision is done in the flesh (<a href="?bref=Rom.2.28">Rom 2:28</a>). While “flesh” in such references is not sinful, it is corruptible and cannot inherit the kingdom of God (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.50">1 Cor 15:50</a>). Jesus’ body was also a body of flesh (<a href="?bref=Col.1.22">Col 1:22</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Flesh as the Body Itself</p>
<p class="fl">By a natural transition, the part is used for the whole, and in many places “flesh” is synonymous with the body as a whole rather than designating the fleshy part of the body. Paul may thus speak either of being absent in the body (<a href="?bref=1Cor.5.3">1 Cor 5:3</a>) or in the flesh (<a href="?bref=Col.2.5">Col 2:5</a>). Paul can say that the life of Jesus may be manifested in our body or in our mortal flesh (<a href="?bref=2Cor.4.10-11">2 Cor 4:10-11</a>). “He who joins himself to a prostitute becomes one body with her. For, as it is written, ‘The two shall become one flesh’ ” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.16">1 Cor 6:16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>).</p>
<p class="h3">Flesh as Person with Reference to Origin</p>
<p class="fl">Following OT usage, “flesh” was used by Paul to refer not merely to the stuff of the body or to the body itself, but concretely to the person as constituted by flesh. In this usage the word may refer to the person’s human relationship, the physical origin and the natural ties that bind one to other humans. Paul speaks of his kinsmen “according to the flesh,” his fellow Jews (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.3">Rom 9:3</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>), and even uses “my flesh” (<a href="?bref=Rom.11.14">11:14</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>) as a synonym for these kinsmen. The “children of the flesh” (<a href="?bref=Rom.9.8">9:8</a>) are those born by natural generation in contrast to those born as a result of divine intervention. Christ was descended from David according to the flesh (<a href="?bref=Rom.1.3">1:3</a>). The phrase does not designate the source merely of his bodily life but of his entire human existence, including both his body and his human spirit.</p>
<p class="h3">Flesh as Human Existence</p>
<p class="fl">Another use of “flesh” simply designates human existence. As long as a person lives in the body, that one is “in the flesh.” Thus, Paul can speak of the life that he lives “in the flesh” as lived by faith in the Son of God (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.20">Gal 2:20</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). Referring to Jesus’ earthly ministry, Paul says that he abolished “in the flesh” the enmity between Jew and Gentile (<a href="?bref=Eph.2.15">Eph 2:15</a>). Peter has the same meaning when he speaks of Jesus having been put to death “in the flesh” (<a href="?bref=1Pet.3.18">1 Pt 3:18</a>). So also John: “Jesus Christ is come in the flesh” (<a href="?bref=1Jn.4.2">1 Jn 4:2</a>). This usage is reflected most notably in the Johannine saying “The Word became flesh and dwelt among us” (<a href="?bref=John.1.14">Jn 1:14</a>).</p>
<p class="h3">Flesh as Human Existence in Terms of Outward Presentation</p>
<p class="fl">“Flesh” also extends beyond humans in their bodily life to include other factors crucial to human existence. Thus, “confidence in the flesh” (<a href="?bref=Phil.3.3">Phil 3:3</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) does not mean confidence in the body but confidence in the whole complex of the outward realm of human existence. It includes Paul’s Jewish ancestry, his strict religious training, his zeal, and his prominence in Jewish religious circles. The phrase to “glory after the flesh” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.11.18">2 Cor 11:18</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>) is rendered “boast about their human achievements” in the <span class="sc">nlt</span>. A good showing “in the flesh” is practically synonymous with worldly prominence (<a href="?bref=Gal.6.11-14">Gal 6:11-14</a>). The Judaizers insisted upon circumcision to promote a sense of prideful attainment in the religious life so that they might have a ground of glorying. But these external distinctions and grounds for glorying no longer appealed to Paul, because the world had been crucified to him and he to the world.</p>
<p>“Flesh” is also used of outward relationships, as when describing the social ties existing between slave and master (<a href="?bref=Eph.6.5">Eph 6:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Col.3.22">Col 3:22</a>; <a href="?bref=Phlm.1.16">Phlm 1:16</a>). “In the flesh” also describes the realm of marital relationships, which entails certain troublesome problems (<a href="?bref=1Cor.7.28">1 Cor 7:28</a>).</p>
<p>This usage illuminates an otherwise difficult saying, “Henceforth know we no man after the flesh; yea, though we have known Christ after the flesh, yet now henceforth know we him no more” (<a href="?bref=2Cor.5.16">2 Cor 5:16</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). The <span class="sc">rsv</span> correctly renders the phrase “from a human point of view.” The verse does not mean that Paul had heard and seen Jesus in Jerusalem at some previous time and had gained some acquaintance with Christ “after the flesh.” “After the flesh” modifies the verb “to know,” not the noun “Christ.” Before his conversion, Paul knew all people “after the flesh”; that is, he judged them by worldly, human standards. To know Christ “after the flesh” means to look at him through merely human eyes. As a Jew, Paul had felt that Jesus was a deluded messianic pretender. According to the Jewish understanding, the Messiah was to reign over the earth as a Davidic king, save his people Israel, and punish the hated Gentiles. But Paul surrendered this false human view and came to know Christ as he really is—the incarnate Son of God, the Savior of all who believe. As a Christian, Paul no longer judged others according to the flesh.</p>
<p class="h3">Flesh as Fallen Humanity</p>
<p class="fl">When Paul says that “flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.50">1 Cor 15:50</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>), he does not mean that humans cannot inherit the kingdom of God but rather that human fallenness cannot; as the next clause shows, “neither does corruption inherit incorruption.” The weak, fallen, corruptible body cannot inherit the kingdom of God; there must be a change; the “corruptible must put on incorruption, and this mortal must put on immortality” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.15.53">1 Cor 15:53</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). This is not the salvation of the soul or spirit but the exchange of one kind of body for another that is suited to the final glorious kingdom of God.</p>
<p>When Peter confessed the messiahship of Jesus, Jesus replied, “Flesh and blood has not revealed this to you, but my Father who is in heaven” (<a href="?bref=Matt.16.17">Mt 16:17</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). The meaning of this verse is obvious. This knowledge of Jesus’ messiahship was not a human deduction; it could be achieved only by divine revelation.</p>
<p class="h3">Flesh as Sinful Humanity</p>
<p class="fl">There remains a group of ethical references that are distinctly Pauline. The most important feature of this usage is that man is seen not only as fallen and weak before God, but as fallen and sinful. Flesh is contrasted with human spirit regenerated by the divine Spirit, and without the aid of the Spirit, one cannot please God. The most vivid passage is the first part of <a href="?bref=Rom.8.1-39">Romans 8</a>, where Paul sharply contrasts those who are “in the flesh” with those who are “in the Spirit.” To be “in the Spirit” in this sense does not mean to be in a state of ecstasy but to be living one’s life in that spiritual realm that is controlled by the Spirit of God. Those who are “in the flesh,” that is, unregenerate, cannot please God. There are two contrasting and mutually exclusive realms: “in the flesh” and “in the Spirit.” To be “in the Spirit” means to be indwelt by God’s Holy Spirit, that is, to be a regenerate person.</p>
<p>In <a href="?bref=Rom.7.1-8.39">Romans 7–8</a> Paul makes it clear that the unregenerate person cannot please God by loving and serving him as God requires. Thus, the Law was unable to make mankind truly righteous, because the flesh is weak (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.2">8:2</a>). To live after the flesh is death; to live after the Spirit is life (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.6">8:6</a>). Elsewhere Paul says, “For I know that in me (that is, in my flesh,) dwelleth no good thing” (<a href="?bref=Rom.7.18">7:18</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). Flesh here cannot be the physical flesh, for the body of flesh is the temple of the Spirit (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.19">1 Cor 6:19</a>) and a member of Christ (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.15">6:15</a>) and is to be the means of glorifying God (<a href="?bref=1Cor.6.20">6:20</a>). Paul, therefore, means that in his unregenerate nature there dwells none of the goodness that God demands.</p>
<p>While Paul makes a sharp and absolute contrast between being “in the flesh” (unregenerate) and “in the Spirit” (regenerate), when one becomes regenerate and comes to be “in the Spirit,” that person is no longer in the flesh, but the flesh is still in him. In fact, there remains in the believer a struggle between the flesh and the Spirit. Writing to people who are “in the Spirit,” Paul says, “For the flesh lusteth [strives] against the Spirit, and the Spirit against the flesh: and these are contrary the one to the other: so that ye cannot do the things that ye would” (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.17">Gal 5:17</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). Because the Christian life is the battleground of these two opposing principles, it is impossible to be the perfect person that one would wish to be.</p>
<p>The same situation is reflected in <a href="?bref=1Cor.2.14-3.3">1 Corinthians 2:14–3:3</a> where Paul describes three classes of people: the “natural” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.2.14">2:14</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>); the “carnal,” that is, fleshly man (<a href="?bref=1Cor.3.1,3">3:1, 3</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>); and the “spiritual man” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.3.1">3:1</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). The “natural man” is unregenerate. Those who are “in the flesh” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.9">Rom 8:9</a>) have devoted the whole of their life to the human level and hence are unable to know the things of God. “Spiritual man” refers to those whose life is ruled by the Spirit of God, so that the fruits of the Spirit (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.22-23">Gal 5:22-23</a>) are evident in their life. Between these two there is a third class—those who are “fleshly” yet who are babes in Christ. Therefore, they must be “in the Spirit,” yet they do not walk “according to the Spirit.” Because they are “babes in Christ,” the Spirit of God dwells in them, yet the Holy Spirit is not allowed to have full control over them, and they are still walking “like men” (<a href="?bref=1Cor.3.3">1 Cor 3:3</a>), manifesting the works of the flesh in jealousy and strife.</p>
<p class="h3">Works of the Flesh</p>
<p class="fl">In <a href="?bref=Gal.5.19-23">Galatians 5:19-23</a> Paul contrasts the life in the flesh and the life in the Spirit: “Now the works of the flesh are manifest, which are these: adultery, fornication, uncleanness, lasciviousness, idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, strife, seditions, heresies, envyings, murders, drunkenness, revellings, and such like” (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.19-21">Gal 5:19-21</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). The important thing to note about this list is that while some of these are sins of bodily and sexual appetite, others are religious sins—idolatry, witchcraft—and several are sins “of the spirit,” that is, of the disposition—hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, strife. The words “seditions” and “heresies” refer not to theological heresies but to a factious, divisive spirit. This proves conclusively that for Paul the “flesh” is not synonymous with the body but includes the whole person, with all the inner attitudes and disposition.</p>
<p class="h3">Victory over the Flesh</p>
<p class="fl">While a struggle remains in the Christian between the Spirit and the flesh, Paul knows of a way of victory for the Spirit. The flesh of the body comes within the sphere of sanctification (<a href="?bref=1Thes.5.23">1 Thes 5:23</a>), but the flesh as the unregenerate human nature can only be put to death.</p>
<p>This is called the tension between the objective and the subjective. Because certain things have happened in Christ (objective), certain inevitable results should accrue (subjective). In Paul’s view, the flesh has already been put to death in the death of Christ. Those who belong to Christ have already crucified the flesh with its passions and desires (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.24">Gal 5:24</a>). Paul elsewhere says, “I have been crucified with Christ” (<a href="?bref=Gal.2.20">2:20</a>) and “our old self was crucified with him” (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.6">Rom 6:6</a>). Such references make it clear that “flesh” and the “self” are in some ways to be identified. This identity is further supported in the teaching about crucifixion, for Paul means the same thing by the crucifixion of the flesh that he means when he says, “How shall we, that are dead to sin, live any longer therein? We were baptized into his death. We are buried with him by baptism into death” (vv <a href="?bref=Rom.6.1-4">1-4</a>). It is I myself who have died with Christ.</p>
<p>This crucifixion and death of the flesh does not, however, work automatically. It is an event that must be appropriated by faith. This involves two aspects. First, believers are to recognize that the flesh has been crucified with Christ. “Reckon ye also yourselves to be dead indeed unto sin, but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord” (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.11">Rom 6:11</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). One cannot consider the self dead with Christ to sin unless that person has actually died and been crucified with Christ, but because this has already happened at the moment of saving faith, it can be put into daily practice. Those who have died with Christ are to “mortify [put to death] the deeds of the body” (<a href="?bref=Rom.8.13">8:13</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>). “Body” is here used as a vehicle for the works of the “flesh”—the sensual life of the unregenerate nature. Those who have been brought from death into life are to yield their members to God as instruments of righteousness (<a href="?bref=Rom.6.13">6:13</a>). One who has died with Christ is to “mortify” (<span class="sc">kjv</span>), that is, put to death what is earthly—fornication, uncleanness, covetousness (<a href="?bref=Col.3.5">Col 3:5</a>). Having already put off the old nature and put on the new, the believer is to put on compassion, kindness, lowliness and the like.</p>
<p>Victory over the flesh is sometimes described as walking in the Spirit. “Walk by the Spirit, and do not gratify the desires of the flesh” (<a href="?bref=Gal.5.16">Gal 5:16</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>; cf. <a href="?bref=Rom.8.4">Rom 8:4</a>). Walking in the Spirit means to live each moment under the control of the Holy Spirit.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Body_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Body</a>; <a href="?item=Sin_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Sin</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>