<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Floodthe">
  <title>Flood, the</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FLOOD, The</p>
<p class="fl">Rising and overflowing of water to cover the land, specifically the flood of Noah.</p>
<p class="h2" id="BiblicalAccount">Biblical Account</p>
<p class="fl">The narrative of Noah’s flood, found in <a href="?bref=Gen.6.1-9.29">Genesis 6–9</a>, is referred to frequently elsewhere in the Bible, in each case being mentioned as a historical event (<a href="?bref=Gen.10.1,32">Gn 10:1, 32</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.11.10">11:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.24.38-39">Mt 24:38-39</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.17.27">Lk 17:27</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.5">2 Pt 2:5</a>). According to the biblical account, God brought about the Flood because of human society’s increasing deterioration, which finally reached a point where “the wickedness of man was great in the earth” (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.5">Gn 6:5</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>). God determined to destroy the race and to begin again with a new people who would obey him (cf. <a href="?bref=Gen.1.26-28">Gn 1:26-28</a>). Of all the people on earth, only Noah, his sons, and their wives remained faithful to the Lord. They became God’s means of repopulating the earth following its watery destruction. After a period of 120 years’ preparation, during which Noah built a great ship and preached God’s coming judgment (<a href="?bref=Gen.6.3">Gn 6:3</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Heb.11.7">Heb 11:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.3.20">1 Pt 3:20</a>; <a href="?bref=2Pet.2.5">2 Pt 2:5</a>), the Flood came in the form of heavy rain, giving rise to subterranean waters (<a href="?bref=Gen.7.11">Gn 7:11</a>). Only the selected pairs of land animals brought aboard the vessel were saved from the onslaught. For more than a year the waters prevailed, until finally the waters receded and the earth was dry and habitable again (<a href="?bref=Gen.7.6-12,24">Gn 7:6-12, 24</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.8.3-6,10-14">8:3-6, 10-14</a>). When Noah and his family left the ark, they offered sacrifices to God in thanksgiving. God then promised that he would never again destroy the earth by a flood.</p>
<p class="h2" id="ExtentoftheFlood">Extent of the Flood</p>
<p class="fl">Scholars who view the flood account as history are divided as to its geographical extent. An objective reading of the story would seem to indicate that the whole earth was flooded, even to the height of the highest mountains (<a href="?bref=Gen.7.17-20">Gn 7:17-20</a>; <a href="?bref=Gen.8.4">8:4</a>). Some have argued that waters high enough to cover “all the high mountains under the whole heaven” (<a href="?bref=Gen.7.19">7:19</a>, <span class="sc">rsv</span>) would extend over the entire earth. Some advocates of a local flood respond that the narrative uses the language of appearance (that is, to Noah it <span class="ital">appeared</span> that all the earth was flooded). Thus a universal flood was unnecessary, for God wished to destroy only the human race, which at that time may have lived only in Mesopotamia. Others point out translation difficulties in the use of the word “earth.” In <a href="?bref=Gen.1.1">Genesis 1:1</a>, it is part of an ancient idiomatic expression denoting totality (“heaven and earth” means “cosmos”). Sometimes “earth” describes a person’s country (<a href="?bref=Gen.47.13">Gn 47:13</a>), the soil itself (<a href="?bref=Gen.23.15">23:15</a>), and so on. Thus, one should not necessarily assume that the use of the word in the Genesis flood story implies the complete inundation of the world.</p>
<p>Some advocates of a universal flood use the presence of marine fossils on the tops of the world’s highest mountains in support of their arguments. But others disagree, saying that since all the mountains originally emerged from the seas, they would be expected to preserve traces of their marine ancestry on their summits. One’s view on the matter must be determined in the final analysis on theological considerations as well as interpretive factors. <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=ScientificEvidenceForTheFlood_Textbox_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">“Scientific Evidence for the Flood?”</a>.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=GilgameshEpic_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Gilgamesh Epic</a>; <a href="?item=Noah_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Noah #1</a>.</p>
<include_items src="../Textboxes/Textboxes.xml" name="ScientificEvidenceForTheFlood"/>
  </body>
</item>