<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="FoodandFoodPreparation">
  <title>Food and Food Preparation</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FOOD AND FOOD PREPARATION</p>
<p class="fl">Substances required by the body to sustain life, and the methods of making them edible. Food consumed in Bible times included bread, milk products, fruit, meat, and fish. Food was also offered sacrificially or given as gifts. The availability of food was a perpetual concern because of the recurrent scarcity: droughts were frequent (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.38">2 Kgs 4:38</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.14.1,4-6">Jer 14:1, 4-6</a>; <a href="?bref=Hagg.1.11">Hg 1:11</a>), hailstorms wrought devastation among crops (<a href="?bref=Hagg.2.17">Hg 2:17</a>), farming was frequently interrupted by warfare with neighboring nations (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.6.25">2 Kgs 6:25</a>), and intermittent plagues of locusts ravaged large areas.</p>
<p>Food was more plentiful in Palestine (described as a “land flowing with milk and honey”) than in many other parts of the Near East. Shallow cultivation of the soil, however, made crops highly reliant on regular rainfall. Egyptian crops were far less susceptible to weather variations, because the Nile provided a dependable source of water.</p>
<p>Food shortages were considered warnings or punishment from God (<a href="?bref=Lam.4.9,11">Lam 4:9, 11</a>; <a href="?bref=Amos.4.6-9">Am 4:6-9</a>) to teach the Hebrews that life is more than food and that faith must continue despite scarcity, famine, or even death (<a href="?bref=Deut.8.3">Dt 8:3</a>; <a href="?bref=Hab.3.17-18">Hb 3:17-18</a>).</p>
<p>The staples of nomadic Hebrews were milk, curds, and cheese. As the people became more stationary, they grew grains and vegetables and planted orchards and vineyards. Grain would sometimes be grown for a season, and then after the harvest, the tribes would move their flocks to other pastures and find other arable land. Religious sacrifices and festivals were times not only of solemnity but also of rejoicing and great feasting. Victories were also celebrated with banquets and feasting on the food obtained from the camp of the vanquished enemy.</p>
<p class="h2-preview">Preview</p>
<p class="preview-list-first">• <a href="#DairyProducts">Dairy Products</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#GrainCrops">Grain Crops</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#AnimalProducts">Animal Products</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#InsectsandTheirFoodProducts">Insects and Their Food Products</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#VegetablesandSeasoning">Vegetables and Seasoning</a></p>
<p class="preview-list">• <a href="#FruitsNutsandWine">Fruits, Nuts, and Wine</a></p>
<p class="h2" id="DairyProducts">Dairy Products</p>
<p class="fl">Milk and its by-products formed a vital part of the Hebrew diet (see <a href="?bref=Judg.4.19">Jgs 4:19</a>). Goat’s milk was most frequently used, although milk from camels, cows, and sheep was also available (<a href="?bref=Gen.32.15">Gn 32:15</a>; <a href="?bref=Deut.32.14">Dt 32:14</a>; <a href="?bref=Pr.27.27">Prv 27:27</a>).</p>
<p>Since fresh milk could not be preserved in Palestine’s hot climate, it was processed into buttermilk, curds, and cheese. Milk was poured into goatskins, where it soured and thickened because of the nonsterile condition of the previously used skins and the movement as it was transported. That movement of the pouch (often made from a cow’s stomach, containing the enzyme rennin used in cheese making) produced curds. Curds are first mentioned in the Bible as part of the meal that Abraham provided for his extraordinary guests (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.8">Gn 18:8</a>).</p>
<p>The Hebrew word for curds <span class="ital">(</span><span class="hebrew">chena</span><span class="ital">)</span> is also translated “butter” (<a href="?bref=Job.10.10">Jb 10:10</a>). This butter would be similar in consistency to yogurt from which the water has been squeezed out. When pressed and rolled into small balls, it kept indefinitely, despite the climate. Thus, compressed curds were particularly valuable for journeys in arid regions where food was scarce.</p>
<p class="h2" id="GrainCrops">Grain Crops</p>
<p class="fl">The most frequently mentioned food in the Bible is bread. The term refers in a general sense to all foods but more particularly to food prepared from grain. In biblical times bread was prepared from several grains. Wheat, barley, and spelt were grown in Egypt (<a href="?bref=Exod.9.31-32">Ex 9:31-32</a>).</p>
<p>An Egyptian physician named Sinuhe, living in the mid-20th century <span class="era">BC</span>, recorded that bread was baked daily in Palestine and Syria, and it is probable that it was served with every meal. This bread was probably a wafer or flat cake made from barley or emmer (an inferior form of wheat), since these were the two grain crops that Sinuhe mentioned seeing. Wheat was the most expensive grain. Fine wheat flour was a luxury only the rich could afford (<a href="?bref=Gen.18.6">Gn 18:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.13,19">Ez 16:13, 19</a>). In later periods wheat became a valuable export crop that was shipped from Tyre to other ports in the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>Because barley could grow in less productive soil and was more tolerant of drought conditions, it became a popular grain crop in the ancient Near East. Barley could also be harvested several weeks earlier than wheat. Barley bread (<a href="?bref=Judg.7.13">Jgs 7:13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.42">2 Kgs 4:42</a>) and barley cakes (<a href="?bref=Ezek.4.12">Ez 4:12</a>) were eaten by the average laborer. Jesus miraculously multiplied a young boy’s five barley loaves and two fishes and fed five thousand (<a href="?bref=John.6.9-13">Jn 6:9-13</a>).</p>
<p>Millet, a cereal with a small grain head growing on a stalk less than two feet (.6 meter) high, and spelt, a type of wheat, were also used in times of need as a border around the edges of fields.</p>
<p>The most primitive way of processing grain was to rub the ears between the hands to separate the kernels, as Jesus and his disciples did (<a href="?bref=Luke.6.1">Lk 6:1</a>). To perform this act on the Sabbath (the day of rest) was considered the equivalent of reaping and was therefore forbidden.</p>
<p>Parching (roasting the grain lightly in a pan) was another simple method of preparation (<a href="?bref=Josh.5.11">Jos 5:11</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.17.17">1 Sm 17:17</a>). It formed a quick and easy meal for laborers or kings (<a href="?bref=Ruth.2.14">Ru 2:14</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.25.18">1 Sm 25:18</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.17.28">2 Sm 17:28</a>). Parched corn was ideal for taking on journeys.</p>
<p>Bread making was a strenuous task. Mortars, pestles, and simple mills with upper and lower stones were used for grinding flour in ancient Egypt around 2900 <span class="era">BC</span>. These primitive mills were normally placed on the ground, and one was compelled to kneel in order to do the backbreaking work. The resulting meal was coarse and filled with small pieces of husk.</p>
<p>When the flour had been prepared, water was added and the mixture was kneaded in a special trough. The dough could then be made immediately into cakes, pancakes, or unleavened bread (<a href="?bref=Gen.19.3">Gn 19:3</a>). These flat cakes or wafers were often baked on previously heated stones, on the inner walls of small conical ovens, or in larger communal ovens. Leaven was added to make a lighter dough. The leaven was normally a piece of dough left over from an earlier mixing and allowed to ferment before being used. The flour meal was also mixed with a porridge made of lentil beans in order to stretch the food supply.</p>
<p class="h2" id="AnimalProducts">Animal Products</p>
<p class="fl">The introduction of meat as part of the diet seems to have coincided with the time when Noah and his family left the ark (<a href="?bref=Gen.9.3">Gn 9:3</a>). After this time, however, the animals normally eaten for food were so valuable that only the wealthy could afford to slaughter them. So in biblical times the peasant had a simple, somewhat monotonous diet, while the rich feasted on meat, delicacies, and imported commodities. As a result, meat was a luxury item that the poor would rarely enjoy except on such occasions as the Passover celebration or sacrifices in which the worshiper ate part of the offering (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.8">Ex 12:8</a>). Although it was clearly uneconomic to slaughter an animal that produced such staples as milk, curds, and cheese, the rules of hospitality in the Near East dictated that an animal should be killed to entertain an honored guest (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.2-4">2 Sm 12:2-4</a>).</p>
<p>Domestic sheep, goats, and oxen provided the main source of meat, although venison was popular with the upper classes. When the blind Isaac was deceived by his son Jacob, the father was offered the luxury of both kid’s meat and wild game (<a href="?bref=Gen.27.3,9,19">Gn 27:3, 9, 19</a>). The ox kept in a stall or the fatted calf were reserved for occasions of great festivity (<a href="?bref=Matt.22.4">Mt 22:4</a>).</p>
<p>The use of meat for sacrifice was given definitive form in the provisions of Leviticus and Deuteronomy. The Law forbade anyone to slaughter an animal and its offspring on the same day (<a href="?bref=Lev.22.28">Lv 22:28</a>). Another prohibition, perhaps directed at pagan Canaanite sacrificial rituals, would not allow a kid to be stewed or poached in its mother’s milk (<a href="?bref=Deut.14.21">Dt 14:21</a>). Mosaic law was emphatic in prohibiting the consumption of blood in any form. Animal blood was considered the source of the animal’s life and was offered by priests as a sacrifice to God to atone for human sin (<a href="?bref=Lev.17.11">Lv 17:11</a>). In the Mosaic law, pigs, camels, badgers, and rabbits were considered unclean and were therefore forbidden for food, principally on hygienic grounds (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.4-8">11:4-8</a>).</p>
<p>In the ancient world, meat was usually boiled or stewed. Roasting an ox or a kid would usually occur only as part of a special feast or sacrificial ritual. Animals might also be roasted for members of the royal palace or for a king’s special guests.</p>
<p>Despite the fact that hunting was enjoyed by all who were able to participate, wild game provided only a minor part of the diet. Among the game found in Palestine and mentioned in the Bible are gazelle, roebuck, wild goat, and deer (<a href="?bref=Deut.14.5">Dt 14:5</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.23">1 Kgs 4:23</a>). It is probable that pheasants were available, and there were certainly turtledoves, pigeons, quails, and partridges, although the precise quantities of food that these birds provided is not certain (<a href="?bref=Gen.15.9">Gn 15:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.16.13">Ex 16:13</a>). Goose was the most popular dish in Egypt, and marsh ducks were also highly esteemed as game. After the Persian period, chickens were eaten (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=2Esd.1.30">2 Esd 1:30</a>), and eggs and omelettes were popular in Rome in early Christian times. The eggs mentioned in Deuteronomy are probably wild birds’ eggs (<a href="?bref=Deut.22.6-7">Dt 22:6-7</a>; cf. <a href="?bref=Isa.10.14">Is 10:14</a>).</p>
<p>Thirty varieties of fish were available in the Jordan, and an extensive fishing industry existed on the shores of the Sea of Galilee at the time of Christ. Supplies of fish were readily available from the Mediterranean coast during the Roman period, but at an earlier time the fish supply depended to a large extent upon whichever nation had control of the coastline. In the postexilic period the people of Tyre supplied the city of Jerusalem with fish, which were sold near the Fish Gate (<a href="?bref=Neh.3.3">Neh 3:3</a>). In the regulations concerning the types of fish suitable for food, only those that had fins and scales were acceptable (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.9-12">Lv 11:9-12</a>).</p>
<p>In NT times many of the distinctions concerning food were eliminated. In the Gospel of Mark, Jesus, challenging the Pharisees’ hypocrisy, upset the Jewish food laws by saying that evil thoughts, not certain foods, make a person unclean (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.19">Mk 7:19</a>). As Christianity spread into gentile areas, there was, however, a continuing concern about eating meat that had been offered to idols. The question came to a head in Corinth. The apostle Paul maintained that though the meat was acceptable, one should take care not to cause spiritual damage to another Christian with a more sensitive conscience.</p>
<p class="h2" id="InsectsandTheirFoodProducts">Insects and Their Food Products</p>
<p class="fl">Wild honey was found in Palestine, but there is no evidence of bee-keeping. Egyptians, however, did practice beekeeping at that time.</p>
<p>The honeycomb is mentioned specifically in <a href="?bref=1Sam.14.27">1 Samuel 14:27</a> and <a href="?bref=Song.5.1">Song of Songs 5:1</a>; liquid honey is referred to in <a href="?bref=1Kgs.14.3">1 Kings 14:3</a>. Honey was to be found in crevices of rocks and on trees (<a href="?bref=Deut.32.13">Dt 32:13</a>). It was the primary sweetener in cooking. Although it could not be used in a sacrifice to the Lord (<a href="?bref=Lev.2.11">Lv 2:11</a>), honey was prized as a delicacy. In the 15th century <span class="era">BC</span>, when Thutmose III was campaigning in Syria and Palestine, he brought back vast quantities of honey as tribute from his newly conquered lands.</p>
<p>Locusts were probably first eaten in desperation after they had devastated crops. They are one of the few insects mentioned as a permissible source of food (<a href="?bref=Lev.11.22">Lv 11:22</a>). Locusts were fried in flour or honey, or were preserved by being dried. Locusts and wild honey formed John the Baptist’s basic diet in the wilderness (<a href="?bref=Matt.3.4">Mt 3:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.1.6">Mk 1:6</a>). Although locusts contain little protein, they are rich in fat and have some mineral content.</p>
<p class="h2" id="VegetablesandSeasoning">Vegetables and Seasoning</p>
<p class="fl">The Hebrew people wandering in the Sinai wilderness bemoaned the loss of the flavorful vegetables they had become accustomed to during their Egyptian captivity. In particular, they expressed a longing for cucumbers, melons (possibly watermelons), leeks, onions, and garlic (<a href="?bref=Num.11.5">Nm 11:5</a>). Many of these vegetables were later grown in Palestine (particularly in the Gaza). When cucumbers were first cultivated, they were regarded as luxury items and had to be protected by guards who lived in shacks overlooking the gardens (<a href="?bref=Isa.1.8">Is 1:8</a>). Beans, lentils, and parched grain were among the items brought to David and his soldiers at Mahanaim (<a href="?bref=2Sam.17.28">2 Sm 17:28</a>). Lentils were known in Egypt from at least the 13th century <span class="era">BC</span> and were used extensively both then and in later times by the Israelites. Lentil soup is mentioned in <a href="?bref=Gen.25.34">Genesis 25:34</a>.</p>
<p>In times of hunger the husks of the carob tree, normally fed to cattle, could be used for food. These would have been most acceptable to the prodigal son (<a href="?bref=Luke.15.16">Lk 15:16</a>). There were many kinds of green herbs that could provide a meal for the poor in time of need (<a href="?bref=Pr.15.17">Prv 15:17</a>). In cases of extreme hunger, some kinds of mallow and juniper roots could also be used as food. In Elisha’s time a group of prophets at Gilgal prepared a stew of wild vegetables, to which they mistakenly added poisonous wild gourds. Elisha rectified the situation by adding meal to the pot (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.4.38-41">2 Kgs 4:38-41</a>). While there is no actual record of the kinds of bitter herbs used as part of the Passover offering (<a href="?bref=Exod.12.8">Ex 12:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.9.11">Nm 9:11</a>), mint and cummin were most probably included. Dill, cummin, rue, and mint were common garden herbs (<a href="?bref=Matt.23.23">Mt 23:23</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.11.42">Lk 11:42</a>).</p>
<p>Seasonings were welcome additives to the rather bland character of typical Israelite fare. Salt came mainly from the Dead Sea area and was essential as a seasoning and preserving agent. Salt was so important in the diet that it became part of the vocabulary of moral obligation. The sharing of salt with a person at a meal sealed a covenant or pact (<a href="?bref=Num.18.19">Nm 18:19</a>). In the Levitical sacrificial ritual, salt was part of meat and cereal offerings, since it signified the sealing of God’s covenant with Israel (<a href="?bref=Lev.2.13">Lv 2:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.43.24">Ez 43:24</a>).</p>
<p>The mustard tree, which was probably grown for its oil content, grew from a minute seed to the height of 15 feet (4.5 meters) (<a href="?bref=Matt.13.31-32">Mt 13:31-32</a>). Anise, coriander, and cinnamon were also available (<a href="?bref=Exod.16.31">Ex 16:31</a>; <a href="?bref=Num.11.7">Nm 11:7</a>). Perhaps the most popular and widely used spice, apart from salt, was garlic. Vinegar was also probably used as a flavoring agent and a preservative. From the number of seeds and plants found in Egyptian tombs from the 18th dynasty, it is obvious that the use of seasoning was widespread in antiquity.</p>
<p class="h2" id="FruitsNutsandWine">Fruits, Nuts, and Wine</p>
<p class="fl">Olive trees grew abundantly in Palestine and were an excellent source of food and oil. Even in poor soil, one tree could sufficiently supply a family for a whole year. Some green olives were pickled in brine and eaten with bread, but the olive was most important as a source of oil. Olive oil was used in baking bread and cakes and in frying foods. The best quality olive oil was used in the temple sacrifices.</p>
<p>Oil was extracted from olives by a simple process: for the finest quality oil, olives were picked before fully ripe and then crushed by hand with a stone mortar and pestle. Usually, however, pickers beat the olives from trees with long poles and collected them in baskets. The oil was then trodden out, probably in the same vat used for grapes (<a href="?bref=Mic.6.15">Mi 6:15</a>), which were harvested approximately four weeks later.</p>
<p>An oil mill was developed subsequently, and the heavy upper grinding stone was turned by two people. As the oil dripped through, it was collected in another stone vat and was allowed to settle and purify. When refined, the oil was stored in skins or jars.</p>
<p>Fig trees grew in all areas of Palestine. They required little attention and provided two or three crops per year. The most abundant of these was the second, which ripened in late summer. The first figs of the season were considered a great delicacy (<a href="?bref=Isa.28.4">Is 28:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Mic.7.1">Mi 7:1</a>). The prophet Hosea suggested that the Israelites were like the firstfruits of the fig tree (<a href="?bref=Hos.9.10">Hos 9:10</a>). Another prophet, Jeremiah, spoke of those who had gone into exile as being like the first figs, while those who were left behind were the bad figs, fit only for destruction (<a href="?bref=Jer.24.1-10">Jer 24:1-10</a>).</p>
<p>Figs were usually eaten fresh from the trees, but some were pressed into cakes to use when traveling (<a href="?bref=1Sam.25.18">1 Sm 25:18</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.30.12">30:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Chr.12.40">1 Chr 12:40</a>). Figs were also valuable for medicinal purposes, since effective poultices could be made from them (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.20.7">2 Kgs 20:7</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.38.21">Is 38:21</a>). Sycamore trees produced small, figlike fruit eaten primarily by the poor. A short time before harvest, the fruit was slightly incised, making it swell and ripen more quickly. The prophet Amos notched sycamore fruit before he was called by God (<a href="?bref=Amos.7.14">Am 7:14</a>).</p>
<p>Fruit from the date palm could also have been pressed into flat cakes for travelers, as figs were. The Bible, however, makes no specific reference to its fruit as food (see <a href="?bref=Judg.4.5">Jgs 4:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.92.12">Ps 92:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Joel.1.12">Jl 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=John.12.13">Jn 12:13</a>).</p>
<p>Another popular Near Eastern fruit was the red pomegranate. It was eaten whole, or the seeds were pressed to provide a refreshing drink. The pomegranate is mentioned in temple ritual as one of the fruits brought back from Canaan to Moses by his spies (<a href="?bref=Exod.28.33">Ex 28:33</a>) and as an exotic drink (<a href="?bref=Song.8.2">Sg 8:2</a>). The “apple” mentioned in Scripture (<a href="?bref=Pr.25.11">Prv 25:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.2.5">Sg 2:5</a>) was most likely a type of apricot or quince, not an apple as we know it today. Nuts were used for additional flavor in cooking. Almonds and pistachio nuts were among the gifts sent by Jacob to ransom his sons (<a href="?bref=Gen.43.11">Gn 43:11</a>).</p>
<p>Grapes were popular and plentiful from the early Bronze Age. In addition to being eaten fresh from the vine, grapes were dried as raisins (<a href="?bref=Num.6.3">Nm 6:3</a>; <a href="?bref=1Sam.25.18">1 Sm 25:18</a>) or pressed, their juice drunk either as new wine or fermented into an alcoholic drink. One of the duties of the cup-bearer in ancient royal courts was to provide grape juice or wine for the king, his family, and guests (<a href="?bref=Gen.40.9-13">Gn 40:9-13</a>).</p>
<p>The juice of grapes also provided vinegar when wine deteriorated. Vinegar was used as a flavoring agent in cooking and as a preservative. When diluted with water, it supplied a refreshing drink for workers in the fields. A type of jelly was made in the Near East by boiling grapes until they assumed the consistency of molasses. This syrup could also be used as a sweetening agent in cooking.</p>
<p>Wine was the universal drink in antiquity. It could be diluted with water or mixed with spices or honey to make a mulled wine (<a href="?bref=Song.8.2">Sg 8:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.5.22">Is 5:22</a>). The Hebrew word for “banquet” or “feast” literally means “drinking,” which reveals much of the character of such occasions. A certain amount of merriment was considered proper at a festival or banquet (<a href="?bref=Gen.43.34">Gn 43:34</a>; <a href="?bref=Judg.9.13">Jgs 9:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.34">Lk 5:34</a>).</p>
<p>Wine making was similar in many respects to the production of olive oil. Clusters of grapes were cut from the vine with a sickle, collected in baskets, and taken to the winepress, where they were trodden by men and women. The juice ran into a lower vat, where, under the hot sun, fermentation began almost immediately. The wine was left to settle so that any twigs or skins would form a sediment; after that the wine could be strained off. In about six weeks the wine was ready to drink or store in earthenware jars or wineskins.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=Animals_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Animals</a>; <a href="?item=Bread_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Bread</a>; <a href="?item=FamilyLifeandRelations_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Family Life and Relations</a>; <a href="?item=Leaven_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Leaven</a>; <a href="?item=MealsSignificanceof_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Meals, Significance of</a>; <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants</a>; <a href="?item=UnleavenedBread_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Unleavened Bread</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>