<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Frankincense">
  <title>Frankincense</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FRANKINCENSE</p>
<p class="fl">Fragrant gum resin that can be ground into powder and burned to produce a balsamlike odor. It was often associated with myrrh (<a href="?bref=Song.3.6">Sg 3:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Song.4.6">4:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Matt.2.11">Mt 2:11</a>). Frankincense is obtained from balsam trees of the genus <span class="ital">Boswellia,</span> specifically the species <span class="ital">B. carterii, B. papyrifera,</span> and <span class="ital">B. thurifera.</span> These trees, which are related to turpentine trees, have star-shaped flowers that are pure white or green, tipped with rose. To obtain the resin, a deep incision is cut into the trunk, yielding an amber-colored gum. Since these trees were native only to Saba (Sheba) in southern Arabia (<a href="?bref=Isa.60.6">Is 60:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.6.20">Jer 6:20</a>) and Somaliland, the resin was a costly item transported into Palestine by caravan. The so-called frankincense tree growing in Palestine (<a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Ecclus.50.8">Ecclus 50:8</a>) was probably <span class="ital">Commiphora opobalsamum</span> whose resin was used to produce perfume.</p>
<p>Frankincense was used alone or with other materials for incense. It was one of the ingredients of the holy incense used for worship in the tabernacle (<a href="?bref=Exod.30.34">Ex 30:34</a>). It was placed on the bread of the Presence (<a href="?bref=Lev.24.7">Lv 24:7</a>) and mixed with oil on the cereal offerings (<a href="?bref=Lev.2.1-2,14-16">Lv 2:1-2, 14-16</a>; <a href="?bref=Lev.6.15">6:15</a>), but it was excluded from the sin offering (<a href="?bref=Lev.5.11">5:11</a>). A supply of frankincense was maintained in the Jerusalem temple (<a href="?bref=Neh.13.5,9">Neh 13:5, 9</a>). It was later used in cosmetics and perfume (<a href="?bref=Song.3.6">Sg 3:6</a>). Both the costly value and its use for worship made the presentation of frankincense to the infant Jesus an appropriate gift (<a href="?bref=Matt.2.11">Mt 2:11</a>). <span class="ital">See</span> <a href="?item=Plants_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Plants</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>