<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="FuneralCustoms">
  <title>Funeral Customs</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FUNERAL CUSTOMS</p>
<p class="fl">Practices and rites that encompass the dying and death of human beings. Funerary rites have been practiced by all social groups from their very beginnings.</p>
<p>Most anthropologists believe that funeral customs fulfill certain important social functions for the living. However, the general meaning these customs provide for any given culture is a matter of longstanding dispute. On the one hand, some behavioral scientists believe that funeral rites alleviate the sudden anxiety that death brings for the grieving. On the other hand, some believe that the purpose of death customs is not to dispel anxiety but rather to foster the feelings of religious awe or group solidarity. In varying degrees both of these factors probably underlie most funeral rites. Funerary customs remind the participants that death must be taken seriously, while at the same time they provide a comforting interpretation of death.</p>
<include_items src="../Pictures/Pictures.xml" name="AncientJewishFuneralProcession"/>
<p>Belief patterns have profoundly influenced funeral customs. A conception of immortality is one of the more commonly held beliefs. The discovery of artifacts such as tools, ornaments, and even food in the oldest known human graves may be evidence of the pervasive conviction that human beings continue to exist in some form after death. Proper funeral rites were believed to assist the dead in reaching their final habitat, which usually included a journey fraught with various perils, such as crossing mythical rivers or wide chasms. The rites also assured the living that the spirits of the dead would not harm them.</p>
<p class="h2" id="DisposingoftheCorpse">Disposing of the Corpse</p>
<p class="fl">A common form of disposing of a corpse has been burial in the earth (inhumation). This practice may have emerged because of the belief that the abode of the dead was located under the ground. Often the grave was considered the entrance to the underworld, although some groups considered the habitation of the dead to be in the sky. Above-ground disposal has also been practiced by many. Some communities place the corpse on a rack to be devoured by birds or other animals. A few groups have been known to eat the corpse, believing that the good qualities of the deceased could be ingested. Many Asian societies have traditionally practiced cremation, or the burning of the corpse. In the past, it was not uncommon for the wife and slaves of a deceased man to throw themselves on the burning pyre. Cremation is becoming popular in the West and may become more widely practiced because of the increasing scarcity of land for grave sites.</p>
<p>Nearly every society observes special mourning customs during the disposal of the body. These include the wearing of special clothing, emotional outbursts, seclusion, and food taboos. Most societies mark the experience by a ceremony that may include purification rites and the sharing of special meals by the friends and relatives of the dead. In almost every cultural group, status symbols infiltrate the funeral customs and rituals. For instance, if the deceased were of a high social standing, then the funeral ceremonies would be more elaborate.</p>
<p class="h2" id="FuneralCustomsandtheBible">Funeral Customs and the Bible</p>
<p class="fl">While the Bible does not provide a detailed picture of burial procedures, it does allude to the common burial practices of the Hebrew people and contains some scattered prohibitions relating to death. Placing the corpse in the ground or in a cave was the principal method for disposing of the dead. One of the worst indignities was to be left unburied or become food for predators (<a href="?bref=Deut.28.26">Dt 28:26</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.11.15">1 Kgs 11:15</a>). If possible, the deceased were to be buried on the day of death (<a href="?bref=Deut.21.23">Dt 21:23</a>). While embalming was not practiced, the corpse was dressed in special burial clothes and sprinkled with various perfumes (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.46">Mk 15:46</a>; <a href="?bref=John.11.44">Jn 11:44</a>).</p>
<p>Intense weeping surrounded funerary rites during biblical times. This mourning did not simply result from spontaneous grief but was part of the funeral ritual (<a href="?bref=Matt.11.17">Mt 11:17</a>). In ancient Israel, groups of paid mourners emerged who could wail on ritual cue. Much of the funeral service centered on these professional mourners who sang psalms and delivered elaborate eulogies for the dead (<a href="?bref=2Chr.35.25">2 Chr 35:25</a>; <a href="?bref=Jer.9.17-22">Jer 9:17-22</a>). The emphasis upon mourning resulted from the Hebrew appreciation of human life and health, which was considered one of God’s greatest gifts (<a href="?bref=Ps.91.16">Ps 91:16</a>), and also from a view of human nature that affirmed embodied existence (<a href="?bref=Ps.16.9-11">16:9-11</a>). This latter belief may have contributed to the OT’s lack of a full-fledged doctrine of immortality, even though it implies that the dead partake in the “shadowy existence” of Sheol and will someday be resurrected (<a href="?bref=Job.14.13">Jb 14:13</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.37.1-28">Ez 37</a>).</p>
<p>The early Christian church affirmed the Jewish belief in embodied existence but highlighted a belief in existence after death. Unlike the Greek dualists, who asserted the immortality of only the soul, the NT writers, following the OT, emphasized a belief in eternal life that entailed not only the soul but also the body. This view became the fulcrum for the belief in the bodily resurrection, which undergirded Christian funeral customs. Nearly every practice symbolized a belief in the resurrection and eternal life. Thus, the emphasis upon lamentation gave way to joyful singing of psalms. The body was washed, anointed with perfumes and spices, wrapped in linen, and surrounded by candles, all of which represented eternal life. Friends and relatives usually held a vigil at the home of the deceased, and scriptural passages dealing with the resurrection and eternal life were read. Whenever possible, the Lord’s Supper was observed, symbolizing the sacrifice of Christ. At the church or the grave site, a funeral oration was delivered both to eulogize the dead and to comfort the living. Many of these practices are still observed by Christians today.</p>
<p><span class="ital">See also</span> <a href="?item=BurialBurialCustoms_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Burial, Burial Customs</a>; <a href="?item=Mourning_Article_TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary">Mourning</a>.</p>
  </body>
</item>