<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Furniture">
  <title>Furniture</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">FURNITURE</p>
<p class="fl">Items of material culture used in homes, palaces, and temples. Because of its close geographical proximity to other nations, Israel had extensive contact with neighboring cultures. Historical surveys document parallels between the furniture of Israel and that of other tribes and countries.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PalestineinOldTestamentTimes">Palestine in Old Testament Times</p>
<p class="fl">OT passages supply most of the information about furniture in ancient Palestine, although there are also significant archaeological data. There are many references to beds in the OT, using at least three Hebrew nouns. Jacob is pictured as sitting up in bed (<a href="?bref=Gen.48.2">Gn 48:2</a>) and as dying on his bed (<a href="?bref=Gen.49.33">49:33</a>). Moses threatened that frogs would invade the bedroom and bed of the Egyptian pharaoh (<a href="?bref=Exod.8.3">Ex 8:3</a>). Michal, Saul’s daughter, placed an effigy in David’s bed (<a href="?bref=1Sam.19.11-17">1 Sm 19:11-17</a>) when Saul sent messengers to capture him there. King David condemned the practice of killing a defenseless person sleeping in bed (<a href="?bref=2Sam.4.7,11">2 Sm 4:7, 11</a>). The prophet Elijah laid a dead boy on his bed and revived him (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.17.19">1 Kgs 17:19</a>).</p>
<p>King Ahab sulked on his bed (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.21.4">1 Kgs 21:4</a>), and King Ahaziah lay on his sick bed (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.1.4-6,16">2 Kgs 1:4-6, 16</a>). The prophet Amos criticized the rich who lay on beds of ivory and stretched out on their couches (<a href="?bref=Amos.6.4">Am 6:4</a>). The prophet Ezekiel spoke symbolically of disobedient Jerusalem as a prostitute sitting on a stately couch with the Lord’s incense and oil on a table nearby (<a href="?bref=Ezek.23.41">Ez 23:41</a>). Isaiah promised that the righteous would rest in their beds (<a href="?bref=Isa.57.2">Is 57:2</a>) and also spoke of the unrighteous setting their beds among false worshipers (vv <a href="?bref=Isa.57.7-8">7-8</a>). The psalmist flooded his bed with tears (<a href="?bref=Ps.6.6">Ps 6:6</a>), and Proverbs refers to a sluggard on his bed (<a href="?bref=Pr.26.14">Prv 26:14</a>).</p>
<p>“Table” in the OT refers both to the temple table for the bread of the Presence and to the table used in the palace or home for meals or banquets. King Adoni-bezek had his captives scrambling for scraps under his table (<a href="?bref=Judg.1.7">Jgs 1:7</a>). Jonathan’s disabled son Mephibosheth was allowed to sit at David’s table (<a href="?bref=2Sam.9.7,10-13">2 Sm 9:7, 10-13</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.19.28">19:28</a>). Solomon’s table is described several times (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.2.7">1 Kgs 2:7</a>; <a href="?bref=1Kgs.4.27">4:27</a>). The queen of Sheba was particularly impressed by the food and table service in Solomon’s palace (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.5">10:5</a>). The prophets frequently refer to tables (<a href="?bref=Isa.21.5">Is 21:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.28.8">28:8</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.65.11">65:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.40.39-43">Ez 40:39-43</a>). The few references to chairs describe people reclining at meals and indicate couches rather than actual chairs (<a href="?bref=Amos.6.4">Am 6:4</a>).</p>
<p>There are numerous mentions of thrones, including those of the pharaoh (<a href="?bref=Gen.41.40">Gn 41:40</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.11.5">Ex 11:5</a>), David (<a href="?bref=2Sam.3.10">2 Sm 3:10</a>; <a href="?bref=2Sam.7.13">7:13</a>), Solomon (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.18">1 Kgs 10:18</a>), the kings of Israel and Judah (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.10">1 Kgs 22:10</a>), and God (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.22.19">1 Kgs 22:19</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.9.4,7">Pss 9:4, 7</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.11.4">11:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.93.2">93:2</a>). The OT writers sometimes indicate thrones decorated with ivory (<a href="?bref=1Kgs.10.18">1 Kgs 10:18</a>).</p>
<p>The exact character of furniture in Palestine is difficult to determine. Bas-reliefs and wall paintings are more common among Israel’s neighbors. Excavations in Jericho, however, have unearthed some valuable archaeological clues. Tombs of the middle Bronze Age produced reasonably well-preserved tables, stools, and boxes, making possible a study of ancient joinery methods. A variety of small trinket boxes show evidence of bone inlay and incised decoration. Some large slabs of timber may have been beds. Although primarily Canaanite styles, the furniture reflects the household furniture used in Israel in the centuries to follow.</p>
<p class="h2" id="GreekandRoman">Greek and Roman</p>
<p class="fl">Historians are quite informed about Greek furniture because of the abundance of decorated vases, bas-reliefs, bronze and terra-cotta statuettes, and literary descriptions. That archaeological evidence indicates that Greek furniture was influenced by preceding civilizations. The picture is generally one of comparative simplicity, far removed from the cluttered and crowded rooms of later civilizations.</p>
<p>The Greeks made several types of seats: (1) the throne, often with a back, legs of various shapes, and armrests; (2) the lighter curved-back chair with arm supports; (3) the four-legged stool; (4) the folding stool with crossed legs traceable to Egyptian models; and (5) the bench. Representations that regularly appear on monuments dating from the eighth to the second century <span class="era">BC</span> link Greek chairs to Egyptian and Assyrian prototypes.</p>
<p>Greeks used couches for sleeping and for reclining at meals. Footstools were used to rest the feet or as a step up to higher couches. Like chair legs, couch legs varied in style. Some were carved in the shape of animal legs, some were turned, some were rectangular. From about the sixth century <span class="era">BC</span>, the legs projected above the frame. Such projections later became headboards and footboards. In Hellenistic times these headrests and footrests were carved and carried bronze medallions in high relief depicting children, satyrs, and animals. Turned legs replaced the rectangular ones. Couches were normally in wood, although bronze and marble couches are known.</p>
<p>Tables were used during meals to hold dishes and food and were removed after the meal. They were made of wood, bronze, and marble and normally had four legs, but three-legged tables were occasionally used. Chests, large and small, served to store clothes, jewelry, and other articles. They were normally of wood, although some were bronze.</p>
<p class="h2" id="Rome">Rome</p>
<p class="fl">Roman furniture continued many Greek patterns. The eruption of the volcano Vesuvius in <span class="era">AD</span> 79 preserved actual pieces of Roman furniture in its lava flow.</p>
<p>Chairs with backs were heavier than their Greek counterparts and widely used. There were several types of stools: the folding stool, mostly wooden, though sometimes metal; and a newly developed decorative stool, often of bronze, that was supported by four curved legs ornamented with scrolls.</p>
<p>A variety of couches were in use. Some followed Greek models, but others were of Roman invention. Excellent examples of bronze bed frames have been preserved. Presumably, interlaced strips of leather or cords were stretched crisscross on the frame. Gold, silver, tortoiseshell, bone, and ivory decoration were used along with veneer work in rare timber. Later, couches in Italy and in other lands had high backs and sides. The Romans seem to have used tables more widely than Greeks. They appear often as permanent supports for vases and other possessions. Tables were normally rectangular with four legs, but table makers also constructed some with three legs, or even resting on a single support. Round tabletops and legs of animals became popular from the fourth century <span class="era">BC</span> on. Plain, undecorated wooden tables and benches were used in kitchens and workshops. Outdoor tables were usually of marble with carved animal legs or decorative figures of animals and monsters.</p>
<p>There were various chests and boxes in daily use. Shelves and cupboards became much more popular than in Greek times.</p>
<p class="h2" id="PalestineinNewTestamentTimes">Palestine in New Testament Times</p>
<p class="fl">The nature of furniture in the NT is probably best understood in relation to contemporaneous Roman models. The NT refers to beds in several passages. People brought a paralytic lying on his bed to Jesus (<a href="?bref=Matt.9.2,6">Mt 9:2, 6</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.5.18">Lk 5:18</a>). When the apostles went into Solomon’s portico, people brought the sick to them on beds (<a href="?bref=Acts.5.15">Acts 5:15</a>). A Syro-Phoenician woman’s sick child lay on a bed (<a href="?bref=Mark.7.30">Mk 7:30</a>). Jesus spoke of setting a lamp on a stand and not placing it under a bed (<a href="?bref=Mark.4.21">Mk 4:21</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.8.16">Lk 8:16</a>), and described what would happen to people in bed when the Day of the Lord came (<a href="?bref=Luke.17.34">Lk 17:34</a>). In another parable Jesus spoke of a needy person begging for bread at midnight from a friend who was already in bed with his family (<a href="?bref=Luke.11.7">Lk 11:7</a>). Beds of the poor and sick were probably only pallets or mattresses (<a href="?bref=Mark.6.55">Mk 6:55</a>; <a href="?bref=John.5.8">Jn 5:8</a>). When people reclined at meals, they would have been lying on a couch (<a href="?bref=John.13.23">Jn 13:23</a>).</p>
<p>There are numerous NT references to tables. Jesus mentioned crumbs falling from a rich man’s table (<a href="?bref=Matt.15.27">Mt 15:27</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.7.28">Mk 7:28</a>; <a href="?bref=Luke.16.21">Lk 16:21</a>). Jesus overthrew the money changers’ tables in the temple (<a href="?bref=Matt.21.12">Mt 21:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.11.15">Mk 11:15</a>). Jesus sat with his disciples at a table for the Passover meal (<a href="?bref=Luke.22.21">Lk 22:21</a>) and promised his disciples that they would sit at his table in God’s kingdom. The apostles were relieved of serving tables in order to preach (<a href="?bref=Acts.6.2">Acts 6:2</a>).</p>
<p>The household lamp is referred to a number of times (<a href="?bref=Matt.25.1">Mt 25:1</a>; <a href="?bref=Mark.4.21">Mk 4:21</a>). Terra-cotta domestic lamps have been found in abundance in excavations.</p>
  </body>
</item>