<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Crete">
  <title>Crete</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CRETE</p>
<p class="fl">Fourth largest island in the Mediterranean, lying approximately <span class="translatorPutInYourMeasurementUnit">60 miles (97 kilometers)</span> southeast of Greece and <span class="translatorPutInYourMeasurementUnit">110 miles (177 kilometers)</span> southwest of Turkey. It is <span class="translatorPutInYourMeasurementUnit">160 miles (257.4 kilometers)</span> long from east to west, with a width of approximately <span class="translatorPutInYourMeasurementUnit">36 miles (58 kilometers),</span> an area of <span class="translatorPutInYourMeasurementUnit">3,200 square miles (5,149 square kilometers).</span> Through the island stretches a mountain range dominated in the center by the sacred Mt Ida <span class="translatorPutInYourMeasurementUnit">(altitude 9,000 feet or 2,742 meters).</span> These mountains slope down sharply to the southern coast, with the result that most of the inhabitants live on the more gradual northern slopes.</p>
<p>Crete is important in the history of the Christian church. When Paul went to Rome as a prisoner, the ship sought refuge from a storm at Fair Havens (<a href="?bref=Acts.27.8">Acts 27:8</a>). The ship tried in vain to reach the more commodious harbor at Phoenix (v <a href="?bref=Acts.27.12">12</a>) but was blown off course and sought refuge at an island off the southwest coast of Crete, called Cauda (v <a href="?bref=Acts.27.16">16</a>). Paul may have visited Crete after imprisonment in Rome, for in his Letter to Titus, he said, “I left you on the island of Crete” (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.5">Ti 1:5</a>, <span class="sc">nlt</span>). On the basis of this and other evidence, many scholars conclude that Paul was released and had an extended ministry before his second imprisonment and execution (<a href="?bref=2Tim.4.6">2 Tm 4:6</a>). Paul had little good to say about the people of Crete, quoting one of their own poets as saying they were “liars, cruel animals, and lazy gluttons” (<a href="?bref=Titus.1.12">Ti 1:12</a>). But the gospel must have made quite a difference there, for today the name of Titus is honored in many villages, churches, and monasteries.</p>
<p>Because of its location and its relative fertility, Crete has been a prize of war and of commerce. The island was conquered by Rome in 67 <span class="era">BC</span> and became a separate province. The inhabitants prospered under the Romans and later under the Greek Christians (Byzantines). The Saracens (Muslims) occupied the island for over a century (<span class="era">AD</span> 823–960). After centuries of Christian leadership, it was conquered by the Turkish sultan, and civilization languished (1669–1898). In the 20th century Crete has been a part of Greece, except for a period of German occupancy during World War II.</p>
<include_items src="../Maps/Maps.xml" name="CreteanIslandintheMediterranean"/>
</body>
</item>