<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><item typename="Article" product="TyndaleOpenBibleDictionary" name="Crown">
  <title>Crown</title>
  <body>
<p class="h1">CROWN</p>
<p class="fl">Headpiece symbolizing honor or high office. In addition to using the word metaphorically, the OT refers to three kinds of crowns. One type of crown was worn by the high priest and Hebrew kings. The high priest’s “holy crown” was a gold plate engraved with the words “Holy to the Lord” fastened to the front of a turban (<a href="?bref=Exod.29.6">Ex 29:6</a>; <a href="?bref=Exod.39.30">39:30</a>). It symbolized his consecration as the people’s representative before God. The Hebrew kings wore a crown light enough to be worn into battle (<a href="?bref=2Sam.1.10">2 Sm 1:10</a>)—perhaps a narrow band of silk covered with jewels. Like the high priest’s, the king’s crown also indicated a divinely appointed office (<a href="?bref=2Kgs.11.12">2 Kgs 11:12</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.89.39">Pss 89:39</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.132.18">132:18</a>). A second type of crown was a massive gold and jeweled symbol of office worn by pagan kings and idols (<a href="?bref=2Sam.12.30">2 Sm 12:30</a>; <a href="?bref=Esth.1.11">Est 1:11</a>). The prophet Zechariah placed such a crown on Joshua the high priest to indicate the union of royal and priestly functions (<a href="?bref=Zech.6.11,14">Zec 6:11, 14</a>). A third type of crown was a crown of flowers used at a banquet to symbolize joy and celebration (<a href="?bref=Song.3.11">Sg 3:11</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.28.1">Is 28:1</a>; <a class="apocrypha" href="?bref=Wisd.2.8">Wisd of Sol 2:8</a>).</p>
<p>The word “crown” is used metaphorically to indicate rule or royalty (<a href="?bref=Nah.3.17">Na 3:17</a>, <span class="sc">kjv</span>), glory or honor (<a href="?bref=Job.19.9">Jb 19:9</a>; <a href="?bref=Ps.8.5">Ps 8:5</a>; <a href="?bref=Ezek.16.12">Ez 16:12</a>), joy (<a href="?bref=Ezek.23.42">Ez 23:42</a>), or pride (<a href="?bref=Job.31.36">Jb 31:36</a>; <a href="?bref=Isa.28.3">Is 28:3</a>).</p>
<p>In the NT the most common word for “crown” means a laurel crown worn at banquets or a prize given as a civic or military honor. The apostle Paul makes reference to it as an athletic prize when he urged Christians to strive for a “crown” that would not wither (<a href="?bref=1Cor.9.25">1 Cor 9:25</a>; <a href="?bref=2Tim.2.5">2 Tm 2:5</a>). Paul regarded his converts as his “joy and crown” (<a href="?bref=Phil.4.1">Phil 4:1</a>; <a href="?bref=1Thes.2.19">1 Thes 2:19</a>).</p>
<p>A victor’s crown symbolizes the eternal life inherited by Christians who have persevered (<a href="?bref=Jas.1.12">Jas 1:12</a>; <a href="?bref=1Pet.5.4">1 Pt 5:4</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.2.10">Rv 2:10</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.3.11">3:11</a>). In the book of Revelation the victories of the locusts (<a href="?bref=Rev.9.7">9:7</a>), the woman (<a href="?bref=Rev.12.1">12:1</a>), and Christ (<a href="?bref=Rev.6.2">6:2</a>; <a href="?bref=Rev.14.14">14:14</a>) are symbolized by laurel crowns. A different Greek word, meaning a royal crown, is used for the diadems on the heads of the dragon (<a href="?bref=Rev.12.3">12:3</a>), the beast from the sea (<a href="?bref=Rev.13.1">13:1</a>), and Christ (<a href="?bref=Rev.19.12">19:12</a>).</p>
<p>Jesus’ crown of thorns was a small circle formed from a bush covered in prickles—an ironic parody of a victor’s crown (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.17-18">Mk 15:17-18</a>). Its combination with the robe, scepter (<a href="?bref=Matt.27.27-29">Mt 27:27-29</a>), and satirical inscription on the cross that Jesus was “the King of the Jews” (<a href="?bref=Mark.15.26">Mk 15:26</a>), were all meant to mock him as a defeated messianic aspirant.</p>
  </body>
</item>